<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT xml:lang="amis" source="Taiwan presidential apology to indigenous people">
    <S id="0">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">On this day 22 years ago, the term "shanbao" (mountain people) in the Additional Articles of our Constitution was replaced with the proper name: "indigenous people".</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="1">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">This correction not only did away with a discriminatory term, but also highlighted the status of indigenous peoples as Taiwan's "original owners".</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="2">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">From this basis, today, we are taking another step forward.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="3">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">To all indigenous peoples of Taiwan: On behalf of the government, I express to you our deepest apology.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="4">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">For the four centuries of pain and mistreatment you have endured, I apologize to you on behalf of the government.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="5">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I know that even now, there are some around us who see no need to apologize.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="6">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But that is the most important reason why I am representing the government to issue this apology today.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="7">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">To see what was unfair in the past as a matter of course, or to treat the pain of other ethnic peoples as an unavoidable part of human development, this is the first mindset that we, standing here today, resolve to change and overturn.                                        </TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="8">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Let me put in simple terms why we are apologizing to the indigenous peoples.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="9">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Four hundred years ago, there were already people living in Taiwan.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="10">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">These first inhabitants lived their lives and had their own languages, cultures, customs, and domains.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="11">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But then, without their consent, another group of people arrived on these shores, and in the course of history, took everything from the first inhabitants who, on the land they have known most intimately, became displaced, foreign, non-mainstream, and marginalized.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="12">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The success of one ethnic people can be built on the suffering of another.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="13">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Unless we deny that we are a country of justice, we must face up to this history.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="14">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">We must tell the truth.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="15">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And then, most importantly, the government must genuinely reflect on this past.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="16">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">This is why I stand here today.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="17">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">There is a book called "The General History of Taiwan" published in 1920.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="18">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">In its foreword are these words: "Taiwan had no history.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="19">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The Dutch pioneered it, the Koxinga Kingdom built it, and the Qing Empire managed it.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="20">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">This is a typical Han view of history.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="21">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The truth is that indigenous peoples have been here for thousands of years, with rich culture and wisdom that have been passed down through generations.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="22">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But we only know to write history from the perspective of the dominant.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="23">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">For this, I apologize to the indigenous peoples on behalf of the government.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="24">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The Dutch and the Koxinga Kingdom massacred and exploited the Pingpu ethnic group.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="25">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The Qing Empire presided over bloody confrontations and suppression.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="26">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Colonial Japan put in place comprehensive savage policies.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="27">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And the post- war ROC government undertook assimilation policies.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="28">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">For 400 years, every regime that has come to Taiwan has brutally violated the rights of indigenous peoples through armed invasion and land seizure.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="29">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">For this, I apologize to the indigenous peoples on behalf of the government.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="30">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Indigenous peoples maintain tribal order according to traditional customs, and ecological balance according to traditional wisdom.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="31">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But in the process of modern state-building, indigenous peoples lost the right to steer their own course and govern their own affairs.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="32">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The fabric of traditional societies was torn apart, and the collective rights of peoples were not recognized.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="33">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">For this, I apologize to the indigenous peoples on behalf of the government.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="34">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Indigenous peoples had their own languages.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="35">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">However, with Japanese rule aiming to assimilate and turn all into imperial subjects, and with the ROC government banning tribal languages after 1945, indigenous peoples' languages suffered great losses.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="36">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Most Pingpu languages have disappeared.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="37">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Successive governments have been negligent in the protection of indigenous cultures.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="38">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">For this, I apologize to the indigenous peoples on behalf of the government.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="39">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Without the knowledge of the Yami tribe, the government stored nuclear waste on Orchid Island.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="40">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Tribe members on the island had to suffer the negative consequences.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="41">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">For this, I apologize to the Yami people on behalf of the government.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="42">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Ever since outsiders began arriving in Taiwan, the Pingpu ethnic group on the western plains have born the brunt of the impact.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="43">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">One ruling power after another eroded the individual and collective identities of the Pingpu ethnic group.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="44">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">For this, I apologize to the Pingpu ethnic group on behalf of the government.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="45">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">After the democratic transition, the country began to respond to the appeals of indigenous movements.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="46">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The government made certain promises and efforts.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="47">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Today, we have an Indigenous Peoples Basic Law that is quite advanced.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="48">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">However, government agencies have not given sufficient weight to this law.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="49">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Our actions have not been fast enough, comprehensive enough or sound enough.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="50">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">For this, I apologize to the indigenous peoples on behalf of the government.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="51">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Taiwan is known as a culturally diverse society.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="52">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But even today, indicators on health, education, economic livelihood, political participation and more still show gaps between indigenous and non- indigenous peoples.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="53">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Meanwhile, stereotypes and even discrimination against indigenous peoples have not gone away.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="54">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The government has not done enough, so indigenous peoples have suffered pain and frustration unknown to other ethnic peoples.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="55">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">For this, I apologize to the indigenous peoples on behalf of the government.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="56">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Our efforts have fallen short, and succeeding generations have been blind to this inadequacy.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="57">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Because of this, your hardship has continued to this day.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="58">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">For this we are truly sorry.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="59">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Today's apology is long overdue, but it is a beginning.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="60">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I do not expect any one speech or phrase of apology to wipe away four centuries of pain and suffering by the indigenous peoples.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="61">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But I do hope with all my heart that today's apology will set this country and all its people on the path towards reconciliation.                                        </TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="62">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Please allow me to shed light on this occasion with a piece of indigenous wisdom.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="63">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">In the Atayal language, truth is called "Balay", and reconciliation is called "Sbalay", so you simply add an "S" sound to "Balay".</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="64">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Truth and reconciliation are in fact two related concepts.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="65">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">In other words, only by facing the truth sincerely can reconciliation be attained.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="66">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">In indigenous cultures, when a tribe member has offended another and intends to reconcile, an elder brings together the offender and the offended  not to produce a direct apology, but to allow each side to frankly share their inner journeys.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="67">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">When this truth-telling concludes, the elder calls for everyone to drink together, so that what is past is truly past.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="68">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">This is "Sbalay".</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="69">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I hope today's occasion can be a "Sbalay" between the government and the indigenous peoples.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="70">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I have spoken of past mistakes and truths the best I can, with nothing held back.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="71">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">In a moment, our indigenous friends will speak.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="72">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I do not dare ask you to forgive, here and now.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="73">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But I sincerely ask you to sustain the hope that past wrongs will not be repeated, and that one day, this country can see true reconciliation.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="74">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Today is only a beginning.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="75">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The duty for reconciliation lies not with the indigenous peoples and the Pingpu ethnic group, but with the government.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="76">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I know that words of apology alone are not enough.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="77">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">What we actually do for the indigenous peoples will decide whether reconciliation succeeds or stumbles.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="78">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Therefore, I am here to announce that we are setting up an Indigenous Historical Justice and Transitional Justice Commission under the Presidential Office.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="79">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">As the head of state, I will serve as convener and work hand in hand with tribal representatives to pursue historical justice.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="80">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">We will also discuss, on the basis of equality, the future policy direction of this country.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="81">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I want to stress that this commission places the greatest importance on equality between the country and the indigenous peoples.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="82">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The election of tribal representatives, including for the Pingpu ethnic group, will take as basis the consensus of peoples and tribes.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="83">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">This commission will serve as a mechanism for collective decision-making by indigenous peoples, and will ensure that the voices of tribe members find true expression.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="84">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">In addition, I will request that our Executive Yuan convene regularly the Indigenous Peoples Basic Law Promotion Committee, and use the Yuan's authority to coordinate and handle matters related to any consensus reached by the above-mentioned commission.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="85">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">These matters include the following: to retrieve historical memories, to promote indigenous self-government, to seek fair economic development, to ensure continuation of culture and education, to safeguard indigenous health, and to protect the rights of urban indigenous peoples, etc.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="86">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Where modern laws and indigenous traditional cultures are at odds, we will set up an Indigenous Legal Service Center with a high degree of cultural sensitivity, to reduce through institutional design the growing clashes between indigenous customs and modern laws.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="87">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I will ask the relevant agencies to immediately pull together cases in which indigenous community members have been indicted or sentenced for hunting, where the hunting was done in accordance with traditional customs, on traditional lands, and for non-transactional needs, and where the animals hunted were not protected by conservation laws.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="88">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">For such cases we will deliberate solutions.                                                 </TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="89">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I will also direct relevant agencies to present an investigative report on the decision-making process of nuclear waste storage on Orchid Island.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="90">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Before finding a permanent solution for the nuclear waste, we will provide the Yami tribe appropriate compensation.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="91">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">At the same time, under the principle of respecting the Pingpu ethnic group's self- identity, and recognizing their identity, we will examine relevant laws before September 30 of this year, so that Pingpu ethnic group identity will receive the rights and status it deserves.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="92">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">On November 1 of this year, we will begin to delineate and announce indigenous traditional territories and lands.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="93">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The system of tribal public corporation is already in place.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="94">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">In the future, the ideals of indigenous self-government will be realized step by step.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="95">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">We will step up the pace and submit for legislative deliberation three laws of great importance to indigenous peoples: the Indigenous Peoples Self-Government Law, the Indigenous Peoples Land and Sea Areas Law, and the Indigenous Languages Development Law.         </TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="96">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Later this afternoon, we will convene a national indigenous peoples administrative meeting.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="97">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">In that meeting, the government will elaborate on the policies.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="98">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">On every August 1 to come, the Executive Yuan will report to the indigenous peoples our progress on restoring historical justice and transitional justice.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="99">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">To implement the Indigenous Peoples Basic Law, to serve indigenous historical justice, and to lay the foundation for indigenous self- government – these are the three major goals for the government's policy towards indigenous peoples.         </TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="100">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">To all of our indigenous friends here and watching on TV and online: I invite you to stand witness.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="101">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I invite you not to endorse, but to oversee.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="102">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Please keep pressure on the government and right its course where necessary, so that it will realize its commitments and right historical wrongs.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="103">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I want to thank all of our indigenous friends.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="104">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">You remind everyone in this country that there is irreplaceable value in the land we tread on and the traditions we inherit.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="105">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">This value deserves dignity.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="106">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">In the future, we will push for policies to ensure that succeeding generations of indigenous tribes and all ethnic peoples in Taiwan never lose their languages and memories, that they are never separated from their cultural traditions, and that never again are they lost in a land of their own.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="107">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I call upon our entire society to come together and get to know our history, get to know our land, and get to know the cultures of our many ethnic peoples.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="108">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Let us work towards reconciliation, a shared existence and shared prosperity, and a new future for Taiwan.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="109">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I call upon all citizens to seize the opportunities offered by this day – to join together, work hard, and build a country of justice, a country of true diversity and equality.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="110">
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Thank you all</TRANSL>
    </S>
</TEXT>
