<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEXT id="Siraya_Dutch_Matthew_Chapter19" xml:lang="fos" source="Siraya Bible, Matthew gospel" copyright="public domain" citation="Gravius, Daniël. 1661. Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa. Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang. Amsterdam: Michiel Hartogh." BibTeX_citation="@book{Gravius1661,&#10;  author    = {Gravius, Daniël},&#10;  year      = {1661},&#10;  title     = {Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa},&#10;  note      = {Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang},&#10;  address   = {Amsterdam},&#10;  publisher = {Michiel Hartogh}&#10;}" dialect="Siraya">
    <S id="verse1">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> KA ni-k'mato-hynna, rou ni-mattæ'i-kaha mattæ'i-limou-limou ki sou k'atta ta ti Jesus, ka ni-d'marang thaboul tou Galilæä, ka ni-iroua mou-arogh ki Jordaan tou pææpt-ten ki Judæa.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> KA ni-k'mato-hynna, rou ni-mattæ'i-kaha mattæ'i-limou-limou ki sou k'atta ta ti Jesus, ka ni-d'marang thaboul tou Galilæä, ka ni-iroua mou-arogh ki Jordaan tou pææpt-ten ki Judæa.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ndehet geschiedde doe Jesus dese woorden ghe-eyndight hadde dat hy bertrock ban Gililea ende quam obe den Jordaen in de landtpalen ban Judea.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And it came to pass, that when Jesus had finished these sayings, he departed from Galilee, and came into the coasts of Judaea beyond Jordan;</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說完了這些話，就離開加利利，來到猶太的境界約旦河外。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse2">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-mææuugh tyni-æn ta mabatoung ki makoi-lalaulau, ka ni-pædærikæh tyn neini-æn to hynna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-mææuugh tyni-æn ta mabatoung ki makoi-lalaulau, ka ni-pædærikæh tyn neini-æn to hynna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende bele charen bolgden hem ende hy genas se aldaer.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And great multitudes followed him; and he healed them there.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">有許多人跟着他，他就在那裏把他們的病人治好了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse3">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-iroua tyni-æn ta Fa-riséen ki rih-pung-ah tyni-en, k'ma, Hahei-en kaua ta taou pæ-darang ki kæi-æn tyn alei ki ma mang</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-iroua tyni-æn ta Fa-riséen ki rih-pung-ah tyni-en, k'ma, Hahei-en kaua ta taou pæ-darang ki kæi-æn tyn alei ki ma mang</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende de Pharilten quamen tot hem bersoeckende hem ende seggende tot hem Js het cen mensche geoorloft fijn wyf te berlaten om allerley oorsake +</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">The Pharisees also came unto him, tempting him, and saying unto him, Is it lawful for a man to put away his wife for every cause?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">有法利賽人來試探耶穌，說：「人無論甚麼緣故都可以休妻嗎？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse4">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Nda ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta teni k'ma neini-æn, Assi-moumi lava ni-ktung, ka teni ka ni-men-ryngei [ki kaæuloung] tou naunamon, ka ni-pei-ryngei tyn neini-æn ta pæ-rah ta jna?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Nda ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta teni k'ma neini-æn, Assi-moumi lava ni-ktung, ka teni ka ni-men-ryngei [ki kaæuloung] tou naunamon, ka ni-pei-ryngei tyn neini-æn ta pæ-rah ta jna?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Dochhy antwoordende seyde tot haer En hebt ghy niet gelesen die ban den beginne [ den mensche] gemaeckt heeft dat hy'se gemaeckt heeft man ende wyfs</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And he answered and said unto them, Have ye not read, that he which made them at the beginning made them male and female,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌回答說：「那起初造人的，是造男造女，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse5">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-komm'appa, Alei ki anna d'marang-ah ta taqu ki Rama ki Reina, ka saul-lam-ah ki ki-en tyn, ka rarouha ka-anna saäsat-ah ki vaat.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-komm'appa, Alei ki anna d'marang-ah ta taqu ki Rama ki Reina, ka saul-lam-ah ki ki-en tyn, ka rarouha ka-anna saäsat-ah ki vaat.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Eit geseght heeft Daerom sal een mensche bady efi moede? berlaten eti sal shnen wijbe aenhangen efi die twee lullen tot een bleetch zijn.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And said, For this cause shall a man leave father and mother, and shall cleave to his wife: and they twain shall be one flesh?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">並且說：『因此，人要離開父母，與妻子連合，二人成為一體。』這經你們沒有念過嗎？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse6">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> K'ma-hynna ka assi rarouha ta neni, nda dyk saäsat ki vaät. Anna ka ni-papæ-sal ki Alid assi papahpiah-auh ki kaæuloung.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> K'ma-hynna ka assi rarouha ta neni, nda dyk saäsat ki vaät. Anna ka ni-papæ-sal ki Alid assi papahpiah-auh ki kaæuloung.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Alsoo dat p niet meer twee en zijn mae? ef bleesch. Het gene dan Godt te samen oheborgt heeft en schepdede menschemer,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Wherefore they are no more twain, but one flesh. What therefore God hath joined together, let not man put asunder.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">既然如此，夫妻不再是兩個人，乃是一體的了。所以，上帝配合的，人不可分開。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse7">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ni-k'ma [ta neni] tyni-æn, Kaoumang ka ni-pakou-sou-en ti Moses ka p'ha-en-eih ta soulat ki pad-ad-arad-arang, ka pad-arang-auh ta teini [ka kæi-en ki pæræh?]</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ni-k'ma [ta neni] tyni-æn, Kaoumang ka ni-pakou-sou-en ti Moses ka p'ha-en-eih ta soulat ki pad-ad-arad-arang, ka pad-arang-auh ta teini [ka kæi-en ki pæræh?]</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Sy leyden tot hem Waerom heeft dan Moles geboden eenen schepdt-brief te geben ende hae: te berlaten</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">They say unto him, Why did Moses then command to give a writing of divorcement, and to put her away?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">法利賽人說：「這樣，摩西為甚麼吩咐給妻子休書，就可以休她呢？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse8">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ni-k'ma [ta teni] neini-æn, Ni-hahei-en-kamou ti Moses alei ki 'thagh-oumi ki tintin ka pad-a-rang-ah-kamou ki kæi-'en-noumi: Rå assi ni-k'ma-hynna tou nauna-mou.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ni-k'ma [ta teni] neini-æn, Ni-hahei-en-kamou ti Moses alei ki 'thagh-oumi ki tintin ka pad-a-rang-ah-kamou ki kæi-'en-noumi: Rå assi ni-k'ma-hynna tou naunamou.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">hy leyde tot haer Moses heeft ban wegen de hardigheyt uwer hertenu toegelaten uwe wijben te berlaten: Mae ban den beginne en is het alsoo niet geweelt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">He saith unto them, Moses because of the hardness of your hearts suffered you to put away your wives: but from the beginning it was not so.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：「摩西因為你們的心硬，所以許你們休妻，但起初並不是這樣。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse9">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ koun-næu-kamou, Ti-mamang ta padarang ki ki-æn tyn, dou assi alei ki kavei-joung-an, ka maja ki pani, 'rbourbo atou-râ, ka timamang ta mæ'iä ki ni-pæd'arang, 'rbourbo-[appa-râ.]</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ koun-næu-kamou, Ti-mamang ta padarang ki ki-æn tyn, dou assi alei ki kavei-joung-an, ka maja ki pani, 'rbourbo atou-râ, ka timamang ta mæ'iä ki ni-pæd'arang, 'rbourbo-[appa-râ.]</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">MWaerickseggeu Dat foo wieshn wijf berlaet anders dan om hoererye ende een ander trouwt [die] doet obexspel eii die de berlatene trouwt doet [oock] obexspel,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And I say unto you, Whosoever shall put away his wife, except it be for fornication, and shall marry another, committeth adultery: and whoso marrieth her which is put away doth commit adultery.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我告訴你們，凡休妻另娶的，若不是為淫亂的緣故，就是犯姦淫了；有人娶那被休的婦人，也是犯姦淫了。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse10">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ni-k'ma tyni-æn ta Pahta-tæutæu-han tyn, Heirou komma-hynna ta kidi ki ka'æuloung ki kæ iän tyn, assi mariang ka mæ'iä-ah,</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ni-k'ma tyni-æn ta Pahtatæutæu-han tyn, Heirou komma-hynna ta kidi ki ka'æuloung ki kæ iän tyn, assi mariang ka mæ'iä-ah,</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Hijne Ditcipelen eyden tot hem Indien de sake des menschen met den wijbe alsoo staet soo en is het niet orbarr te trouwen,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">His disciples say unto him, If the case of the man be so with his wife, it is not good to marry.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">門徒對耶穌說：「人和妻子既是這樣，倒不如不娶。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse11">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Teni-râ ni-kma neini-æn, Assi pæh-ymmid pah-balei ki sou k'atta, dyk neinien ka ni-p'ha-æn-ato.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Teni-râ ni-kma neini-æn, Assi pæh-ymmid pah-balei ki sou k'atta, dyk neinien ka ni-p'ha-æn-ato.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Boch hy fepde tot haer Alle en batten dit woort | ret | mae? dien het gegeben s.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But he said unto them, All men cannot receive this saying, save they to whom it is given.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：「這話不是人都能領受的，惟獨賜給誰，誰才能領受。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse12">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka akoume-'ato ki ni-hæp, ka ni-pei-alak-kin komma-hynna ki vouil ki rena [nein]: ka akou-meä ki ni-ähæp ka ni-ähæp ki kaæuloung: ka akoume-'appa ki ni-ähæp ka ni-mæhæp neini-æn tei-mado alei ki Pei-sasou-an ki tounnoun ki vullu-vullum. Tima-mang ta pah-lpough pah-balei [ki atta] pæh-balei-auto.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka akoume-'ato ki ni-hæp, ka ni-pei-alak-kin komma-hynna ki vouil ki rena [nein]: ka akou-meä ki ni-ähæp ka ni-ähæp ki kaæuloung: ka akoume-'appa ki ni-ähæp ka ni-mæhæp neini-æn tei-mado alei ki Pei-sasou-an ki tounnoun ki vullu-vullum. Tima-mang ta pah-lpough pah-balei [ki atta] pæh-balei-auto.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Want daer zijn gesnedene die uyt moeders lijbe alsoo geboren zijn: ende dae zijn gesnedene die ban de mentchen gesneden zijn: ende daer 3yn gesnedene die haer felben gesneden hebben om Het Koninckryck der Hemeten. Die [dit] batten kan batte [het.]</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">For there are some eunuchs, which were so born from their mother's womb: and there are some eunuchs, which were made eunuchs of men: and there be eunuchs, which have made themselves eunuchs for the kingdom of heaven's sake. He that is able to receive it, let him receive it.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">因為有生來是閹人，也有被人閹的，並有為天國的緣故自閹的。這話誰能領受就可以領受。」 （可10‧13－16；路18‧15－17）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse13">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Tou kidi k'anna ni-âd' pa ou-koua tyni-æn ta rarauwei ka atta-halap-eih tyn ta rima neini-æn, tou pako-Alilid-den: nda ni-patymhga'n ta neini ki Pahtatæu-tæu-hæn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Tou kidi k'anna ni-âd' pa ou-koua tyni-æn ta rarauwei ka atta-halap-eih tyn ta rima neini-æn, tou pako-Alilid-den: nda ni-patymhga'n ta neini ki Pahtatæu-tæu-hæn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Boe | wicrden kinderkens tot hem gebracht op pers de handen haer sonde eggen ende bidden: ende De oem ie beft} aften deetbe</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then were there brought unto him little children, that he should put his hands on them, and pray: and the disciples rebuked them.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那時，有人帶着小孩子來見耶穌，要耶穌給他們按手禱告，門徒就責備那些人。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse14">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus, ou-roung-an-ei ta rarauwei, ynna ma-vagh neini-æn pa-ou-koua jau-an: alei ka â neini ta Pei-sasou-an ki tounnoun ki vullu-vullum.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus, ou-roung-an-ei ta rarauwei, ynna ma-vagh neini-æn pa-ou-koua jau-an: alei ka â neini ta Pei-sasou-an ki tounnoun ki vullu-vullum.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Maer Jesus sepde Laec af ban de kinderkens ende en berhinde:t hae: niet tot my te komen : want der</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But Jesus said, Suffer little children, and forbid them not, to come unto me: for of such is the kingdom of heaven.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：「讓小孩子到我這裏來，不要禁止他們；因為在天國的，正是這樣的人。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse15">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou ka ni-atta-halap-en tyn ta rima neini-æn, ni-thaboul ta teni d'marang hynna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou ka ni-atta-halap-en tyn ta rima neini-æn, ni-thaboul ta teni d'marang hynna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende als. hw hae: de handen opgheleght hadde berttock hy ban daer.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And he laid his hands on them, and departed thence.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌給他們按手，就離開那地方去了。 （可10‧17－31；路18‧18－30）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse16">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka kyttei, ka saät [ki vouel] ta ni-mou-koua ka ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Tama-mahtautuuh ka mariang, pam't-au-mau ta riang ki mang, tou akoumea-ei-mau ki kauæg-han ka myh-kakoua myd-darynnough?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka kyttei, ka saät [ki vouel] ta ni-mou-koua ka ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Tama-mahtautuuh ka mariang, pam't-au-mau ta riang ki mang, tou akoumea-ei-mau ki kauæg-han ka myh-kakoua myd-darynnough?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende fiet Datr quam ten tot Hem ende [eyde tor hem | Goede meester wat fal tck goedts doen op dat ick het eeuwige leben hebbe r $</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And, behold, one came and said unto him, Good Master, what good thing shall I do, that I may have eternal life?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">有一個人來見耶穌，說：「夫子，我該做甚麼善事才能得永生？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse17">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ni-k'ma ta teni tyni-æn, Ka mang ta pa-nænang-en-hou jau-an ka mariang? Aousi ta tima-mang ka mariang, dyk sâsat ki Alid. Heirou mamoei kow mou-rbo tou kæuæg-han, nda ah-koua-au ta na sou ki ni-pakou-sou-en [tou Tatoulko.]</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ni-k'ma ta teni tyni-æn, Ka mang ta pa-nænang-en-hou jau-an ka mariang? Aousi ta tima-mang ka mariang, dyk sâsat ki Alid. Heirou mamoei kow mou-rbo tou kæuæg-han, nda ah-koua-au ta na sou ki ni-pakou-sou-en [tou Tatoulko.]</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende hy sepde cot hem Wat noemt gy mp goedt + Niemandt en is goet Dan een [namelick] Godt, Doch wilt gp in het leben ingaen onderhout de gebo-</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And he said unto him, Why callest thou me good? there is none good but one, that is, God: but if thou wilt enter into life, keep the commandments.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌對他說：「你為甚麼以善事問我呢？只有一位是善的。你若要進入永生，就當遵守誡命。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse18">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ni-k'ma ta teni tyni-æn, Sou ka mang? Nda ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus [Atta:] Assi kow louhpough-ah: Assi kow mou-zouzoung-ah ni-makakyttil Assi kow haou-zoung-ah: Assi kow hmæ'il-ah si haharang.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ni-k'ma ta teni tyni-æn, Sou ka mang? Nda ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus [Atta:] Assi kow louhpough-ah: Assi kow mou-zouzoung-ah ni-makakyttil Assi kow haou-zoung-ah: Assi kow hmæ'il-ah si haharang.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">dat onmogelick maer by Godt zijn alle dingen mogelick.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">He saith unto him, Which? Jesus said, Thou shalt do no murder, Thou shalt not commit adultery, Thou shalt not steal, Thou shalt not bear false witness,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他說：「甚麼誡命？」耶穌說：「就是不可殺人；不可姦淫；不可偷盜；不可作假見證；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse19">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Milligh-a-kow ti Am-au-hou-en ti In-au-hou-en: ka, Ma-væ'æng-o-ah kow ki ta'u ka rarou-ma mama mamado ymhou-an</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Milligh-a-kow ti Am-au-hou-en ti In-au-hou-en: ka, Ma-væ'æng-o-ah kow ki ta'u ka rarou-ma mama mamado ymhou-an</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Gert uwen bader ende moeder:ende Ghp fult uwen Naesten lief Hebben als u . felben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Honour thy father and thy mother: and, Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">當孝敬父母；又當愛人如己。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse20">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ni-k'ma tyni-æn ta kæuh-paparah, Ymd-dennæu milligh ta mamang katta ki na kararauwei-au: Ka mang ta äou-si-appa jæu-an?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ni-k'ma tyni-æn ta kæuh-paparah, Ymd-dennæu milligh ta mamang katta ki na kararauwei-au: Ka mang ta äou-si-appa jæu-an?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">De Jonghelingh leyde tot hem Alle dese dingen hebbe ick onderhouden ban mijne jonckhept af; Wat gebreeckt my noch &gt;</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">The young man saith unto him, All these things have I kept from my youth up: what lack I yet?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那少年人說：「這一切我都遵守了，還缺少甚麼呢？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse21">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus tyni æn, Irou mamoei kow mænænæh mataraæuh, oukouâ, pa-zadum-m'a ki mamang oho, ka p'hæ-eito ki malimouk, ka akou-me'æh kow ki vangei tou tounnoun ki vullum: ka mou-kouâ hia, mæuuugh jau an-da.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus tyni æn, Irou mamoei kow mænænæh mataraæuh, oukouâ, pa-zadum-m'a ki mamang oho, ka p'hæ-eito ki malimouk, ka akou-me'æh kow ki vangei tou tounnoun ki vullum: ka mou-kouâ hia, mæuuugh jau an-da.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Jesus seyde tot hem Soo ghp wilt bolmaeckt 3yn gaet henen berkoopt wat ghy hebt ende geefthet den Armen ende ghy sult eenen schat hebben in den Hemel : ende komt herwaerts bolght mp.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus said unto him, If thou wilt be perfect, go and sell that thou hast, and give to the poor, and thou shalt have treasure in heaven: and come and follow me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：「你若願意作完全人，可去變賣你所有的，分給窮人，就必有財寶在天上；你還要來跟從我。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse22">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou ka millingigh ki sou katta ta Kauh-pæparah, ni-d'ma-rang ta teni mavoulas,alei ka akou-mea tyni-æn ki madagh ki hourup.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou ka millingigh ki sou katta ta Kauh-pæparah, ni-d'ma-rang ta teni mavoulas,alei ka akou-mea tyni-æn ki madagh ki hourup.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Alsnu de Jongeling dit woordt hoorde gingh Hp bedroeft wech : wane hy hadde bele goederen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But when the young man heard that saying, he went away sorrowful: for he had great possessions.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那少年人聽見這話，就憂憂愁愁地走了，因為他的產業很多。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse23">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Nda ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus ki Pahtatæutæu-han tyn, Missing koun-næu-kamou-ra, ka mag-ho-gpyt ta mavangei mou-rbo tou pei-sasou-an ki tounnoun ki vul. lum.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Nda ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus ki Pahtatæutæu-han tyn, Missing koun-næu-kamou-ra, ka mag-ho-gpyt ta mavangei mou-rbo tou pei-sasou-an ki tounnoun ki vul. lum.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende Jesus leyde tot lijne Dilcipelen Doorwaer ick segghe u dat een rijcke swaerlick in het honinckryck der Hemelen sal ingaen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then said Jesus unto his disciples, Verily I say unto you, That a rich man shall hardly enter into the kingdom of heaven.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌對門徒說：「我實在告訴你們，財主進天國是難的。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse24">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka he-la-en-au-kamou ma-sousou, Ka si-ourou-hmæh-ei ta louang ka makhgoun ki rikour tau-koua tou lbas ki simsin, ka: mou-rbo-ah ta mavangei tou pei-sasou-an ki Alid.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka he-la-en-au-kamou ma-sousou, Ka si-ourou-hmæh-ei ta louang ka makhgoun ki rikour tau-koua tou lbas ki simsin, ka: mou-rbo-ah ta mavangei tou pei-sasou-an ki Alid.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende wederom segge ick u Het is lichter dat een kemel gae door de ooge ban een naelde dan dat een rijcke ingae in het Koninckrijcke Godts. =</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And again I say unto you, It is easier for a camel to go through the eye of a needle, than for a rich man to enter into the kingdom of God.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我又告訴你們，駱駝穿過針的眼，比財主進上帝的國還容易呢！」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse25">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Tou illing-hen [ki atta] ki Pahtatæutæu-han tyn, ouhang ni-mouhkiap ta neni, ka ni-k'ma, Timang ta paka-lpoug-eih rou an-na paka-riang?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Tou illing-hen [ki atta] ki Pahtatæutæu-han tyn, ouhang ni-mouhkiap ta neni, ka ni-k'ma, Timang ta paka-lpoug-eih rou an-na paka-riang?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Sijne Discipelen nu {dir ] hoorende wierden seer berflaghen seggende Wie kan dan saligh wordens</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">When his disciples heard it, they were exceedingly amazed, saying, Who then can be saved?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">門徒聽見這話，就希奇得很，說：「這樣誰能得救呢？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse26">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka dou 'ararau ti Jesus ni-k'ma neini-æn, Assi pæi-lpoug-hen ta atta tou ka'æuloung-an, rå pæi Ipoug-hen ymmid ki mamang ki Alid.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka dou 'ararau ti Jesus ni-k'ma neini-æn, Assi pæi-lpoug-hen ta atta tou ka'æuloung-an, rå pæi Ipoug-hen ymmid ki mamang ki Alid.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende Jesus [haes] aensiende sepde tot haer By</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But Jesus beheld them, and said unto them, With men this is impossible; but with God all things are possible.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌看着他們，說：「在人這是不能的，在上帝凡事都能。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse27">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Tou kidi k'anna doumat tæ'i-v'lli ta ti Petrus ni-k'ma tyni-æn, K'ytt'ei, ni-saou-ymd-änian sau-tæuagh ki mamang, ka ni mæuuuuh-kame ymhou-an: ma-mang-al-ato ymian-æn?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Tou kidi k'anna doumat tæ'i-v'lli ta ti Petrus ni-k'ma tyni-æn, K'ytt'ei, ni-saou-ymd-änian sau-tæuagh ki mamang, ka ni mæuuuuh-kame ymhou-an: ma-mang-al-ato ymian-æn?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Boe antwoordde Petrus ende sepde tot hem Siet wp hebben alles berlaten ende zijn u gebolght : wat sal ons dan gewerden :</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then answered Peter and said unto him, Behold, we have forsaken all, and followed thee; what shall we have therefore?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">彼得就對他說：「看哪，我們已經撇下所有的跟從你，將來我們要得甚麼呢？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse28">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Nda ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus neini-æn, Missing koun-nau-ka-mou-râ, ka ymoumi ka ni-mæu-auug jau-an tou pei-likoug-hen mei-alak, rou mier-roung-al-ato ta Alak ki ka'æuloung tou iraroung-an ki tounnoun ki karæræmæg-hen ki kidi tyn, ka mieroung-al-appa-kamou tou såt kytti-æn 'æb ki rouha ki ierraroung-an ka toun-noun pæmæmæh ki sât kytti-æn 'æb ki rouha ki kavouy-vouyl-an ti Isræ'l.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Nda ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus neini-æn, Missing koun-nau-ka-mou-râ, ka ymoumi ka ni-mæu-auug jau-an tou pei-likoug-hen mei-alak, rou mier-roung-al-ato ta Alak ki ka'æuloung tou iraroung-an ki tounnoun ki karæræmæg-hen ki kidi tyn, ka mieroung-al-appa-kamou tou såt kytti-æn 'æb ki rouha ki ierraroung-an ka toun-noun pæmæmæh ki sât kytti-æn 'æb ki rouha ki kavouy-vouyl-an ti Isræ'l.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende Jesus lepde tot haer Doorwaer ick legge u dat ghy die my ghebolght rht in de weder geboorte wanneer de Sone des menschen sal geseten rijii op den Throon oon [lijner Heerlickhept [dat] ghy oock sult sitten op twaelf Throonen oordeelende de twaelf gheslachten Ifratls.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And Jesus said unto them, Verily I say unto you, That ye which have followed me, in the regeneration when the Son of man shall sit in the throne of his glory, ye also shall sit upon twelve thrones, judging the twelve tribes of Israel.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：「我實在告訴你們，你們這跟從我的人，到復興的時候，人子坐在他榮耀的寶座上，你們也要坐在十二個寶座上，審判以色列十二個支派。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse29">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka timamang ta sau-tauagh-al-ato ki tallagh, ki tæia-papara, ki niäha, ki rama, ki rena, ki kæi-æn, ki alalak, ki ouma-ouma lava alei ki Nanang-au, tenita A-bli-ah mara ki sât kæ ætong-han, ka ta-bli-al-appa ki kæuæg-han ka myhkakoua myddarynnough.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka timamang ta sau-tauagh-al-ato ki tallagh, ki tæia-papara, ki niäha, ki rama, ki rena, ki kæi-æn, ki alalak, ki ouma-ouma lava alei ki Nanang-au, tenita A-bli-ah mara ki sât kæ ætong-han, ka ta-bli-al-appa ki kæuæg-han ka myhkakoua myddarynnough.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende so wie [al berlaten hebben huysen of broeders of fulters of bade; of moeder of wyf of kinderen of ackers om mijns Naems wille die] sal hondert-bout ontfangen ende het eeuwige leben be-erben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And every one that hath forsaken houses, or brethren, or sisters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, or lands, for my name's sake, shall receive an hundredfold, and shall inherit everlasting life.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">凡為我的名撇下房屋，或是弟兄、姊妹、父親、母親、兒女、田地的，必要得着百倍，並且承受永生。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse30">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ mabatoung ki si-ouro. ouro ta si-augh-al-ato, ka maba. toung ki si-äæugh ta si-ouro-ou-ro-al-ato. Ka rarouha kytti-an kilbæh ki soulat.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ mabatoung ki si-ouro. ouro ta si-augh-al-ato, ka maba. toung ki si-äæugh ta si-ouro-ou-ro-al-ato. Ka rarouha kytti-an kilbæh ki soulat.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Watet bele cesfte fullen de laetite zijn ende[ ele]laetste de ecrlte,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But many that are first shall be last; and the last shall be first.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">然而，有許多在前的，將要在後；在後的，將要在前。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
</TEXT>