<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEXT id="Siraya_Dutch_Matthew_Chapter23" xml:lang="fos" source="Siraya Bible, Matthew gospel" copyright="public domain" citation="Gravius, Daniël. 1661. Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa. Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang. Amsterdam: Michiel Hartogh." BibTeX_citation="@book{Gravius1661,&#10;  author    = {Gravius, Daniël},&#10;  year      = {1661},&#10;  title     = {Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa},&#10;  note      = {Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang},&#10;  address   = {Amsterdam},&#10;  publisher = {Michiel Hartogh}&#10;}">
    <S id="verse1">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Tou kidi k'anna ni-masousou ta ti Jesus ki makoilalau-lau ki Pah-tatautau-han appa tyn,</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Tou kidi k'anna ni-masousou ta ti Jesus ki makoilalaulau ki Pah-tatautau-han appa tyn,</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">D Oe sprack Jesus tot de charen ende tot syne Discipelen</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then spake Jesus to the multitude, and to his disciples,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那時，耶穌對眾人和門徒講論，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse2">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> K'ma, Tou ni-ierrarong-en ti Moses, da mieroung-ato ta mako-sasoulat ki Fariséen ap pa:</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> K'ma, Tou ni-ierrarong-en ti Moses, da mieroung-ato ta mako-sasoulat ki Fariséen ap pa:</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Seggende De Schaiftgeleerde ende de Phariseen zijn gheseten op den [toel Mosts : =</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Saying The scribes and the Pharisees sit in Moses' seat:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">說：「文士和法利賽人坐在摩西的位上，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse3">
        <FORM kindOf="original">. Anna ta kamamang ka pæ-sousou-eih nein paahkoua ymou mi-an,ahkoua-au moumi-râ, âmt-auppa ta anna, râ na ryngei nein assi ahkoua auh: alei ka pasousou-en nein râ assi nein pamt'tin [k'an-na.]</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">. Anna ta kamamang ka pæ-sousou-eih nein paahkoua ymou mi-an,ahkoua-au moumi-râ, âmt-auppa ta anna, râ na ryngei nein assi ahkoua auh: alei ka pasousou-en nein râ assi nein pamt'tin [k'an-na.]</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Darerom al war sp.u feggen dat ghy houden sult houdt [dat] ende doer [het,] maer en doet niet na hare wercken : want fp seggen Het ende en doen het nier,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">All therefore whatsoever they bid you observe, that observe and do; but do not ye after their works: for they say, and do not.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">凡他們所吩咐你們的，你們都要謹守遵行。但不要效法他們的行為；因為他們能說，不能行。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse4">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Alei ka 'æustin nein ta ul ka makdung, ka assi a-lpoughin ma-val, ka pakah-taæu-in ki kaeu-loung, râ ynnang pa-ylikalika ta neni ki kæamos nein.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Alei ka 'æustin nein ta ul ka makdung, ka assi a-lpoughin ma-val, ka pakah-taæu-in ki kaeu-loung, râ ynnang pa-ylikalika ta neni ki kæamos nein.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Want sy binden lasten die (wat zijn ende qualick om dragen ende leggense op de schouderen der menschen mae? sy en willen die met haren binge niet berroeren.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">For they bind heavy burdens and grievous to be borne, and lay them on men's shoulders; but they themselves will not move them with one of their fingers.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們把難擔的重擔捆起來，擱在人的肩上，但自己一個指頭也不肯動。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse5">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka pamt-tin nein ta ymmid ki na ringaring-ei nein ka ararau-eih ki kaeuloung. Ka paka-irang ki lyci ki pahibalei-en, ka pahou-irang nein pahoupat ta na papitpit ki koulamough nein.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka pamt-tin nein ta ymmid ki na ringaring-ei nein ka ararau-eih ki kaeuloung. Ka paka-irang ki lyci ki pahibalei-en, ka pahou-irang nein pahoupat ta na papitpit ki koulamough nein.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende alle hare wercken doen sy om ban de menschen gesien te worden. Want sp maken hare gedenck-cedels breedt ende make de roomen ban hare kleederen groot.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But all their works they do for to be seen of men: they make broad their phylacteries, and enlarge the borders of their garments,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們一切所做的事都是要叫人看見，所以將佩戴的經文做寬了，衣裳的繸子做長了，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse6">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka kamau-en nein ta itou-gnada mieroungi tou pileileigh-en, ki taul-appa ki itou-ouro-en tou Pæuisasal-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka kamau-en nein ta itou-gnada mieroungi tou pileileigh-en, ki taul-appa ki itou-ouro-en tou Pæuisasal-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende sy beminnen de boor-aensittinge in de maeltijden ende de boor geftoelten in de Synagogen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And love the uppermost rooms at feasts, and the chief seats in the synagogues,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">喜愛筵席上的首座，會堂裏的高位，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse7">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ta pasirariou-en-appa tou pænæh ka pakoi-sal tyn, ta pana-nang-en-appa ki k'æ'euloung, Rabbi, Rabbi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ta pasirariou-en-appa tou pænæh ka pakoi-sal tyn, ta pana-nang-en-appa ki k'æ'euloung, Rabbi, Rabbi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Oock de begroetingen op de merckten ende ban de mentchen genaemt te worden Rabbi Kabbi.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And greetings in the markets, and to be called of men, Rabbi, Rabbi.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">又喜愛人在街市上問他安，稱呼他拉比 。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse8">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ymoumi-râ ynna pananang-eih Rabbi, râ saät ta Tama-mæh-tæutæuugh ymoumi-æn, ka ti vhristus: ka ymdei-au-kamou tæi-apapara ta ymoumi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ymoumi-râ ynna pananang-eih Rabbi, râ saät ta Tama-mæh-tæutæuugh ymoumi-æn, ka ti vhristus: ka ymdei-au-kamou tæi-apapara ta ymoumi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doch ghy en sule met dabbi ghenaemt worden want een is uwen Meelte? [namelick ] Chiiltus : ende ghy zijt alle broeders.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But be not ye called Rabbi: for one is your Master, even Christ; and all ye are brethren.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">但你們不要受拉比的稱呼，因為只有一位是你們的夫子；你們都是弟兄。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse9">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka assi moumi ratama-auh ta timamang tou Næi, alei ka saär ta Raraman-oumi ka ææia-toun-noun ki vullum.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka assi moumi ratama-auh ta timamang tou Næi, alei ka saär ta Raraman-oumi ka ææia-toun-noun ki vullum.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende en sult niemandt uwen uwen bader noemen op der atrden : want een is uw' baDer { namelick } die inde Hemelen is.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And call no man your father upon the earth: for one is your Father, which is in heaven.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">也不要稱呼地上的人為父，因為只有一位是你們的父，就是在天上的父。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse10">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka assi kamou pananang-eih Tama-mahtæutuugh: alei ka saät ta Tama-mahtautæuugh ymoumi-æn ka tip-æhristus:</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka assi kamou pananang-eih Tama-mahtæutuugh: alei ka saät ta Tama-mahtautæuugh ymoumi-æn ka tip-æhristus:</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Nochghn en fult met meelters ghenoemt worden : want een-is uw' meelter [oamelick] Chultus:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Neither be ye called masters: for one is your Master, even Christ.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">也不要受師尊的稱呼，因為只有一位是你們的師尊，就是基督。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse11">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ timamang ta siouro tou keirang-en ki kidi ymoumi-æn, teni ta pæiroung-au-moumi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ timamang ta siouro tou keirang-en ki kidi ymoumi-æn, teni ta pæiroung-au-moumi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Mae} de meefte ban u fal iny' dienaer zijn.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But he that is greatest among you shall be your servant.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們中間誰為大，誰就要作你們的用人。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse12">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka timamang ta poumado pou-keirang-en ki kidi tyni-æn, anna ta pourarim-eih-da: tima mang ta pourarimæh ki kidi tyni-æn pou-mædo, ama ta pou-kei-rang-eih-da.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka timamang ta poumado pou-keirang-en ki kidi tyni-æn, anna ta pourarim-eih-da: tima mang ta pourarimæh ki kidi tyni-æn pou-mædo, ama ta pou-kei-rang-eih-da.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende wie hemselben berhoogen sal [die] sal bernedert worden : ende wie hem-felben sal bemnederen [die] sal berhooght worden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And whosoever shall exalt himself shall be abased; and he that shall humble himself shall be exalted.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">凡自高的，必降為卑；自卑的，必升為高。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse13">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ ænnæi ymoumi ka Ma-koi-sasoulat ki Fariséen-appa, ka panini-en ki rygh [ki sou:] Ilb-an-noumi ki ka'eulong ta Peisasou-an ki tounnoun ki vullum, alei ka assi-kamou mourbo, timamang-appa ka ynna ou-rbo, assi-moumi hahei-en pa-ourbo ta neni.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ ænnæi ymoumi ka Ma-koi-sasoulat ki Fariséen-appa, ka panini-en ki rygh [ki sou:] Ilb-an-noumi ki ka'eulong ta Peisasou-an ki tounnoun ki vullum, alei ka assi-kamou mourbo, timamang-appa ka ynna ou-rbo, assi-moumi hahei-en pa-ourbo ta neni.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Matr wee u ghy Schaift-geleerde ende Phariseen ghy gebeynde: Want ghy fluyt het Koninckrijck der Hemelen boor be mentchen obermidts ghy[daer] niet in en gaet noch de gene die ingaen souden niet en laet ingaen;</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But woe unto you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! for ye shut up the kingdom of heaven against men: for ye neither go in yourselves, neither suffer ye them that are entering to go in.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">「你們這假冒為善的文士和法利賽人有禍了！因為你們正當人前，把天國的門關了，自己不進去，正要進去的人，你們也不容他們進去。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse14">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ennai ymoumi ka Mako-sasoulat ki Fariséen appa, ka pæ-vinien ki rÿh [ki sou: Alei ka ka-nin-noumi ta tatalagh ki jnejna ka vi-kapatei-æn ki tbung, tou hau-at-en ki hawei ki pako-daliadalli en makou Alilid. Alei ki ahna pæ-ki-valei-ei moumi ta siouro niak-dung ka ding-ding-en.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ennai ymoumi ka Mako-sasoulat ki Fariséen appa, ka pæ-vinien ki rÿh [ki sou: Alei ka ka-nin-noumi ta tatalagh ki jnejna ka vi-kapatei-æn ki tbung, tou hau-at-en ki hawei ki pako-daliadalli en makou Alilid. Alei ki ahna pæ-ki-valei-ei moumi ta siouro niak-dung ka ding-ding-en.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ween ghy Schaiftgeleerde ende Phariseen ghy gebeynsde : Want ghy eet de huyfen der weduwen op ende [dat] onder den schyn ban lange te bidden. Daerom sult ghy te [wacrder 00rdeel ontfangen. '</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Woe unto you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! for ye devour widows' houses, and for a pretence make long prayer: therefore ye shall receive the greater damnation.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse15">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ænnei ymoumi ka Makou-sasoulat ki Fariséen-appa, ka pæ-nini-en ki rÿh [ki sou:] Ka tau ryttoung-kamou ki vaoung ki pouro-pourough pou ta'u ki væ-au ka Joden: ka rou ni-pou-tæ'u-en, pou-alak-kamou tyni-æn ki alak ki kaleu'æuan pou-pohal pou-saoun ymoumi-æn-da.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ænnei ymoumi ka Makou-sasoulat ki Fariséen-appa, ka pæ-nini-en ki rÿh [ki sou:] Ka tau ryttoung-kamou ki vaoung ki pouro-pourough pou ta'u ki væ-au ka Joden: ka rou ni-pou-tæ'u-en, pou-alak-kamou tyni-æn ki alak ki kaleu'æuan pou-pohal pou-saoun ymoumi-æn-da.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Wee u ghy Schiittgeleerde ende Phariseen ghy gebeynide : Want ghy omreplt ree ende landt om een Jode-genoodt te maken : ende als hy het gheworden is foo maeckt ghy hem een kindt der hellen tweemael mee: dan ghp [zijt.]</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Woe unto you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! for ye compass sea and land to make one proselyte, and when he is made, ye make him twofold more the child of hell than yourselves.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">「你們這假冒為善的文士和法利賽人有禍了！因為你們走遍洋海陸地，勾引一個人入教，既入了教，卻使他作地獄之子，比你們還加倍。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse16">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ænnei ymoumi ka Tama-dyllough ka mavoutta, ka k'ma, Dou timamang ta saulkit-al-ato ki sou sau-Kouva ki tatamd-en ki Alid, ka nynno ta anna: rå tima-mang ta saulkit-al-ato sau-kim ka tou Kouva ki ta tamd-den ki Alid, nda kau itting-eih ta ti anna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ænnei ymoumi ka Tama-dyllough ka mavoutta, ka k'ma, Dou timamang ta saulkit-al-ato ki sou sau-Kouva ki tatamd-en ki Alid, ka nynno ta anna: rå tima-mang ta saulkit-al-ato sau-kim ka tou Kouva ki ta tamd-den ki Alid, nda kau itting-eih ta ti anna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Wee u ghy blinde lepdts-lieden die segget So wie ghesworen sal hebben bp den Tempel dat en is niet: maer fo wie gesworen fal hebben by het gout des Tempels die 1s schuldigh.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Woe unto you, ye blind guides, which say, Whosoever shall swear by the temple, it is nothing; but whosoever shall swear by the gold of the temple, he is a debtor!</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">「你們這瞎眼領路的有禍了！你們說：『凡指着殿起誓的，這算不得甚麼；只是凡指着殿中金子起誓的，他就該謹守。』</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse17">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ymoumi ka marynghau ka mavoutta kamang ta masaoun mangal ki kidi, kym kauwa, Kou-va kaua ka papa-nni ki kym tou tatamd-den ki Alid?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ymoumi ka marynghau ka mavoutta kamang ta masaoun mangal ki kidi, kym kauwa, Kou-va kaua ka papa-nni ki kym tou tatamd-den ki Alid?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ghpdwase ende blinde: want welck is meerder het gout ofte de Tempel die. het gout heplight +</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Ye fools and blind: for whether is greater, the gold, or the temple that sanctifieth the gold?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們這無知瞎眼的人哪，甚麼是大的？是金子呢？還是叫金子成聖的殿呢？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse18">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka rou Yaul-kit-al-ato ki sou ta timamang ki itou-koua nki p'hik-an, ka nynno ta anna:râ tima-mang ta saul-kit-al-ato ki na pæ-pæ ka ni-pou-halap-en, ka kau it-ting-eih ta teni.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka rou Yaul-kit-al-ato ki sou ta timamang ki itou-koua nki p'hik-an, ka nynno ta anna:râ tima-mang ta saul-kit-al-ato ki na pæ-pæ ka ni-pou-halap-en, ka kau it-ting-eih ta teni.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende So wie ghefworensal hebben by den Altaer dat en is niet: mae} soo wie gesworen sal hebben by de gabe die daer op is die is schuldigh. =</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And, Whosoever shall swear by the altar, it is nothing; but whosoever sweareth by the gift that is upon it, he is guilty.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們又說：『凡指着壇起誓的，這算不得甚麼；只是凡指着壇上禮物起誓的，他就該謹守。』</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse19">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ymoumi ka marynghau ka mavoutta nda kamang ma-saoun na keirang-en ki kidi, na papa kaua, ytto u-kouan kaua ki pap'hik an ka papa-nni ki na pæ-pa tou tatamd-en ki Alid?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ymoumi ka marynghau ka mavoutta nda kamang ma-saoun na keirang-en ki kidi, na papa kaua, ytto u-kouan kaua ki pap'hik an ka papa-nni ki na pæ-pa tou tatamd-en ki Alid?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ghy dwale ende blinde: want wat is meerder de gabe of den Altaer die de gabe heplight + .</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Ye fools and blind: for whether is greater, the gift, or the altar that sanctifieth the gift?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們這瞎眼的人哪，甚麼是大的？是禮物呢？還是叫禮物成聖的壇呢？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse20">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta timamang ta saul-kud ki sou ki yttou-koua'n ki pa-p'hik-an saul-lik'd-den tyn ki an-na, kamamang-appa ka atta-halap en-ato hynna,</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta timamang ta saul-kud ki sou ki yttou-koua'n ki pa-p'hik-an saul-lik'd-den tyn ki an-na, kamamang-appa ka atta-halap en-ato hynna,</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Datrom wie fweert by doen den Altaer die fiweert by den selben ende by al wat daeropis. —_</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Whoso therefore shall swear by the altar, sweareth by it, and by all things thereon.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">所以，人指着壇起誓，就是指着壇和壇上一切所有的起誓；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse21">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Katimamang ta saulkud ki sou sau-Kouva ki tatamd-den ki Alid, saul-li'kd-en tyn ki anna, tyni-æn-appa ka itou-kakoua hynna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Katimamang ta saulkud ki sou sau-Kouva ki tatamd-den ki Alid, saul-li'kd-en tyn ki anna, tyni-æn-appa ka itou-kakoua hynna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende wie sweert by den Tempel die sweert by den selben ende by dien die daer in woont.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And whoso shall swear by the temple, sweareth by it, and by him that dwelleth therein.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">人指着殿起誓，就是指着殿和那住在殿裏的起誓；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse22">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka timamang ta saulkud ki: tounoun ki vullum, saul-likd-en tyn ki ierra-raoung-en ki Alid, ty-ni-æn-appa ka ta'a raoung hynna</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka timamang ta saulkud ki: tounoun ki vullum, saul-likd-en tyn ki ierra-raoung-en ki Alid, ty-ni-æn-appa ka ta'a raoung hynna</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende wie sweert by den Hemel die sweert by den Throon Godts endebpdien Dit daer op fit, =</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And he that shall swear by heaven, sweareth by the throne of God, and by him that sitteth thereon.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">人指着天起誓，就是指着上帝的寶座和那坐在上面的起誓。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse23">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Annei ymoumi ka Makou-sasoulat ki Fariséen-appa, ka pan-ninni-en ki rÿh ki sou, pi'ä-kamou ki atagh ka sat kytti-æn ki Munte ki dille, ki komyn appa, ka assi moumi pamtin ta siouro irang tou Tatouhko, [atta] ta dungdung en, kaharuman ki kas'hut-an [ki ni-pataumsing-en.] Nda kidi ka pamtæuh ta atta, ka assi ynnangeih ta anna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Annei ymoumi ka Makou-sasoulat ki Fariséen-appa, ka pan-ninni-en ki rÿh ki sou, pi'ä-kamou ki atagh ka sat kytti-æn ki Munte ki dille, ki komyn appa, ka assi moumi pamtin ta siouro irang tou Tatouhko, [atta] ta dungdung en, kaharuman ki kas'hut-an [ki ni-pataumsing-en.] Nda kidi ka pamtæuh ta atta, ka assi ynnangeih ta anna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Wee ughy Schaiftgheleerde ende Pharileen ] ghy ghebepnsde want ghy ‚ btrtient de munte ende de dille ende Het Komyn ende ghy laet nae het swaerste der Wet [yamelick] het oordeel ende de barmhertighepdt ende het geloobe. Dese dingen moestmen doen ende de andere niet nalaten.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Woe unto you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! for ye pay tithe of mint and anise and cummin, and have omitted the weightier matters of the law, judgment, mercy, and faith: these ought ye to have done, and not to leave the other undone.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">「你們這假冒為善的文士和法利賽人有禍了！因為你們將薄荷、茴香、芹菜獻上十分之一，那律法上更重的事，就是公義、憐憫、信實，反倒不行了。這更重的是你們當行的；那也是不可不行的。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse24">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Tama-dyllough ka ma vouttâ, pasasakd-en-noumi ta ri-kuh, ka ryhal-in-noumi ta louang ka Kemel.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Tama-dyllough ka ma vouttâ, pasasakd-en-noumi ta ri-kuh, ka ryhal-in-noumi ta louang ka Kemel.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ghy blinde leydtslieden die ghy de mugge uptrijget ende den kemel doorswelget.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Ye blind guides, which strain at a gnat, and swallow a camel.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們這瞎眼領路的，蠓蟲你們就濾出來，駱駝你們倒吞下去。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse25">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ennei ymoumi ka mako-sasoulat ki Fariseen-appa, ka pan-nini-en ki rÿh ki sou: pakakou ptigh-'noumi ta heuugh ka yhtan ki tangia-appa touhalap, ratourbo matmoei ta anna ki turinough-an ki assi katiktik-an ki ryb.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ennei ymoumi ka mako-sasoulat ki Fariseen-appa, ka pan-nini-en ki rÿh ki sou: pakakou ptigh-'noumi ta heuugh ka yhtan ki tangia-appa touhalap, ratourbo matmoei ta anna ki turinough-an ki assi katiktik-an ki ryb.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Wee u ghy Schaiftgheleerde ende Phariseen ghy gebepnsde : want ghy ' reynight het buytenste des drinck-bekers ende des chotels maer ban binnen zijnle bol ban roof ende onmatig-</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Woe unto you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! for ye make clean the outside of the cup and of the platter, but within they are full of extortion and excess.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">「你們這假冒為善的文士和法利賽人有禍了！因為你們洗淨杯盤的外面，裏面卻盛滿了勒索和放蕩。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse26">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Fariseus ka mavoutta koh-pa siouro-au pakakouptigh ta a tourbo ki hæuugh ka yht-en ki tangi-'appa, alei ka paka kouptig-eil-appa ta atou-halap.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Fariseus ka mavoutta koh-pa siouro-au pakakouptigh ta a tourbo ki hæuugh ka yht-en ki tangi-'appa, alei ka paka kouptig-eil-appa ta atou-halap.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ghy blinde Phariseer sepnigght eesft dat binnen in den drinck-beke: efi de schotel 1s op dat oock het buytenlte der selbe repn worde.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Thou blind Pharisee, cleanse first that which is within the cup and platter, that the outside of them may be clean also.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你這瞎眼的法利賽人，先洗淨杯盤的裏面，好叫外面也乾淨了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse27">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ænnei ymoumi ka Mako-sasoulat ki Fariséen-appa, ka pani-ni-en ki rÿh ki sou: ka papihmæh-kaulaul'en-kamou ki ravaravak ka tæ'apoughin, ka mahauwei matta-bung tou halap, râ matmoei tou-rbo ki toural ki patei ki kama-mang ki kavossouk-kin.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ænnei ymoumi ka Mako-sasoulat ki Fariséen-appa, ka pani-ni-en ki rÿh ki sou: ka papihmæh-kaulaul'en-kamou ki ravaravak ka tæ'apoughin, ka mahauwei matta-bung tou halap, râ matmoei tou-rbo ki toural ki patei ki kama-mang ki kavossouk-kin.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Wee u ghy Schiifchelcerde ende Pharileen ghy ghebepnsde : want ghy 3yt de wit-geplaesterde graben ghelyck die ban bupten wel frhoon ichijnen maer ban binnen 3hnse bol doodtsbeenderen ende aller onreynigheer.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Woe unto you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! for ye are like unto whited sepulchres, which indeed appear beautiful outward, but are within full of dead men's bones, and of all uncleanness.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">「你們這假冒為善的文士和法利賽人有禍了！因為你們好像粉飾的墳墓，外面好看，裏面卻裝滿了死人的骨頭和一切的污穢。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse28">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Komnia-kamou hynna mahau-ei matiktik ki ka'euloung tou halap, râ mat moei-kamou tou-rbo ki poukakei-halap-pen ki ka-tou-koul-lan.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Komnia-kamou hynna mahau-ei matiktik ki ka'euloung tou halap, râ mat moei-kamou tou-rbo ki poukakei-halap-pen ki ka-tou-koul-lan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Aloo oock ichijnt ghy wel den menschen ban buyten rechtbeerdigh maer ban binnen zijt ghn bol ghebeynlthepde ende ongerechtigheyt. .</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Even so ye also outwardly appear righteous unto men, but within ye are full of hypocrisy and iniquity.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們也是如此，在人前，外面顯出公義來，裏面卻裝滿了假善和不法的事。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse29">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ænnei ymoumi ka Mako-sasoulat ki Fariséen-appa, ka pan-vini-en ki rÿh ki sou:ka pei-ryngei-noumi ta ravaravak ki na Tama-mattæ'i-tan, ka pei-tabung-noumi ta tih-halong-an ki pahibalei-en ki ta'u ka na matiktik.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ænnei ymoumi ka Mako-sasoulat ki Fariséen-appa, ka pan-vini-en ki rÿh ki sou:ka pei-ryngei-noumi ta ravaravak ki na Tama-mattæ'i-tan, ka pei-tabung-noumi ta tih-halong-an ki pahibalei-en ki ta'u ka na matiktik.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Wee u ghy Schaifcgeleerde ende Phariseen ghy gebepnsde: want ghy bouwt de graben der Propheren op ende berciert de graf-ceeckenen de: rechtbeerdige.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Woe unto you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! because ye build the tombs of the prophets, and garnish the sepulchres of the righteous,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">「你們這假冒為善的文士和法利賽人有禍了！因為你們建造先知的墳，修飾義人的墓，說：</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse30">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka k'na-kamou hynna, Heirou ynna-kame akou-me'ato tou kidi ki wæ'i ki Ramou-ian, ynna-kame akousi-ato ki sau-sâl-an tou æmægh ki na Tama-mat-tæ'i-tan.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka k'na-kamou hynna, Heirou ynna-kame akou-me'ato tou kidi ki wæ'i ki Ramou-ian, ynna-kame akousi-ato ki sau-sâl-an tou æmægh ki na Tama-mattæ'i-tan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende segget Indien wp ten tijden onser Daderen hadden geweelt wp en souden met haer geen gemeentSchap gehadt hebben aen het bloet der Propheten.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And say, If we had been in the days of our fathers, we would not have been partakers with them in the blood of the prophets.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">『若是我們在我們祖宗的時候，必不和他們同流先知的血。』</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse31">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Komma-hynna gmail-ka-mou mattæ'i-douma ymoumi-æn mamado, ka na alalak-kamou nein ka ni-pækapatei ki na Tama-mæt-. tæ'i-tan.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Komma-hynna gmail-ka-mou mattæ'i-douma ymoumi-æn mamado, ka na alalak-kamou nein ka ni-pækapatei ki na Tama-mæt-. tæ'i-tan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Aldus getuyght ghy tegen u selben dat ghy kinderen zijt Der ghene die de Propheten gedoodt heben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Wherefore ye be witnesses unto yourselves, that ye are the children of them which killed the prophets.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">這就是你們自己證明是殺害先知者的子孫了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse32">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ymoumi ta pouht'moei ki rarpung-an ki na mamoumou-an-noumi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ymoumi ta pouht'moei ki rarpung-an ki na mamoumou-an-noumi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ghy [dan] oock berbult de mate uwer Daderen,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Fill ye up then the measure of your fathers.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們去充滿你們祖宗的惡貫吧！</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse33">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ymoumi ka voelei ka ni-kubkub ki tpoung, illipt-ah-ka-mou mama ki mang ki pahko-ava-vægh-an ki kalau heu-an?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ymoumi ka voelei ka ni-kubkub ki tpoung, illipt-ah-ka-mou mama ki mang ki pahko-ava-vægh-an ki kalau heu-an?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Gbly flanghen ghy adderen gebroctsels hoe soudt ghy de helsche berdoemenille ontblieden +</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Ye serpents, ye generation of vipers, how can ye escape the damnation of hell?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們這些蛇類、毒蛇之種啊，怎能逃脫地獄的刑罰呢？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse34">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Alei ki anna, k'ytt'ei, pa-dadingi-en-au-kamou ta Tama mattæ i-tan, ta Makou sacyng, ki Makou-sasoulat-appa, ka pakapa-tei-ah-kamou ki rarouma pouna-væværægh-appa neini-æn, ka pæ-tæubæurigh-ah-kamou smaplat ki rarouma tou Pæuisasal noumi, ka kmou-dylloug-ah-kamou [neini-an] tou æuma-auma.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Alei ki anna, k'ytt'ei, pa-dadingi-en-au-kamou ta Tama mattæ i-tan, ta Makou sacyng, ki Makou-sasoulat-appa, ka pakapa-tei-ah-kamou ki rarouma pouna-væværægh-appa neini-æn, ka pæ-tæubæurigh-ah-kamou smaplat ki rarouma tou Pæuisasal noumi, ka kmou-dylloug-ah-kamou [neini-an] tou æuma-auma.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Daeromsieticksende tot u Propheten ende Wijse ende Schaift-geleerde ende upt den elben sulc ghy [ommige] dooden ende kruycighen ende [ sommige.] upt Den selben sult ghy getllelen in uwe Synagoghen ende sultse berbolghen pan ftadt tot ffabt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Wherefore, behold, I send unto you prophets, and wise men, and scribes: and some of them ye shall kill and crucify; and some of them shall ye scourge in your synagogues, and persecute them from city to city:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">所以我差遣先知和智慧人並文士到你們這裏來，有的你們要殺害，要釘十字架；有的你們要在會堂裏鞭打，從這城追逼到那城，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse35">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Alei ka mou-halap-ah ymoumi-æn ta ymmid ki na æ-magh ka matiktik, ka ni-oudoudo en tou Nai, na amagh ti Abel ka na matiktik tou kidi-appa ki na amagh tipa-gagharias ka na Alak ti Barachias, ka ni-lpoghnoumi tou toukad ki Kouva ki tatamd-den ki Alid ki yttou-kouan ki pap'hik-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Alei ka mou-halap-ah ymoumi-æn ta ymmid ki na æ-magh ka matiktik, ka ni-oudoudo en tou Nai, na amagh ti Abel ka na matiktik tou kidi-appa ki na amagh tipa-gagharias ka na Alak ti Barachias, ka ni-lpoghnoumi tou toukad ki Kouva ki tatamd-den ki Alid ki yttou-kouan ki pap'hik-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Opdatopu kome alle t rechtbeerdige bloet dat bergoten is op der aerden ban het bloet des rechtbeerDigen Abels af tot op het bloedt Zacharie des soons Barachie welcken ghy gedoodt hebt tuffchen den Temperl ende den Altaer,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">That upon you may come all the righteous blood shed upon the earth, from the blood of righteous Abel unto the blood of Zacharias son of Barachias, whom ye slew between the temple and the altar.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">叫世上所流義人的血都歸到你們身上，從義人亞伯的血起，直到你們在殿和壇中間所殺的巴拉加的兒子撒迦利亞的血為止。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse36">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Missing koun-nau-kamou, ka irou 'ah ta mamang katta mou-halap ki kavouyvouyl-lan kanna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Missing koun-nau-kamou, ka irou 'ah ta mamang katta mou-halap ki kavouyvouyl-lan kanna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Poorwaer segge ick u alle dese dingen sullen komen obe? dit geflachte.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Verily I say unto you, All these things shall come upon this generation.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我實在告訴你們，這一切的罪都要歸到這世代了。」 （路13‧34－35）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse37">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Jerusalem, Jerusalem, ka Ipogh-kow ki Tama-mattæi tan, ka taka-cycyt kow ki na vahto ki padadingi-en paou-koua ymhou an Ni-mæua-pynnan ta ni-ka-moei-en-au papaululud ki alalak oho mama ki taoukka ka papa-au-alud ki pyppiou tyn tou papæ-ryl [tyn, ]rà assi-ka mou ni-bmahei-ato.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Jerusalem, Jerusalem, ka Ipogh-kow ki Tama-mattæi tan, ka taka-cycyt kow ki na vahto ki padadingi-en paou-koua ymhou an Ni-mæua-pynnan ta ni-ka-moei-en-au papaululud ki alalak oho mama ki taoukka ka papa-au-alud ki pyppiou tyn tou papæ-ryl [tyn, ]rà assi-ka mou ni-bmahei-ato.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ferusalem Jerulalem ghp die de Propheten doodet ende steemight die tot u gesonden zijn : Hoe menigmael hebbe ick uwe kinderen willen bp een bergadert lickerwijs een hinne hare ieckenen by een bergadert onde; de bleugelen ende gylieden en hebt niet gewilt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">O Jerusalem, Jerusalem, thou that killest the prophets, and stonest them which are sent unto thee, how often would I have gathered thy children together, even as a hen gathereth her chickens under her wings, and ye would not!</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">「耶路撒冷啊，耶路撒冷啊，你常殺害先知，又用石頭打死那奉差遣到你這裏來的人。我多次願意聚集你的兒女，好像母雞把小雞聚集在翅膀底下，只是你們不願意。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse38">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> K'ytt'ei paitoukoua-auh ymoumi-au ta tallag-oumi ka ni-oubulbul-en.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> K'ytt'ei paitoukoua-auh ymoumi-au ta tallag-oumi ka ni-oubulbul-en.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Siet uw' huys wort u woelt gelaten.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Behold, your house is left unto you desolate.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">看哪，你們的家成為荒場留給你們。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse39">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka pasousou-en-au-kamou, Assi-kamou kmytta-ah jau-an si-augh ki kidi hnyn, tou kidi-appa k'anna ka pasousou-ei-moumi, Pa-ka-riang-eih loumoulugh ta teni k'anna ka irarouroua tou Nanang ki Meirang. Kararouha kytti-an'æb ki hpat ki Ibæh ki soulat.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka pasousou-en-au-kamou, Assi-kamou kmytta-ah jau-an si-augh ki kidi hnyn, tou kidi-appa k'anna ka pasousou-ei-moumi, Pa-ka-riang-eih loumoulugh ta teni k'anna ka irarouroua tou Nanang ki Meirang. Kararouha kytti-an'æb ki hpat ki Ibæh ki soulat.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Want ick segghe u Ghy en sult my ban nu aen niet sien tot dat ghy seggen sult Geregent is hy die komt in den Name des Heeren,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">For I say unto you, Ye shall not see me henceforth, till ye shall say, Blessed is he that cometh in the name of the Lord.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我告訴你們，從今以後，你們不得再見我，直等到你們說：『奉主名來的是應當稱頌的。』」</TRANSL>
    </S>
</TEXT>