<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEXT id="Siraya_Dutch_Matthew_Chapter16" xml:lang="fos" source="Siraya Bible, Matthew gospel" copyright="public domain" citation="Gravius, Daniël. 1661. Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa. Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang. Amsterdam: Michiel Hartogh." BibTeX_citation="@book{Gravius1661,&#10;  author    = {Gravius, Daniël},&#10;  year      = {1661},&#10;  title     = {Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa},&#10;  note      = {Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang},&#10;  address   = {Amsterdam},&#10;  publisher = {Michiel Hartogh}&#10;}">
    <S id="verse1">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka irou'ato tyni-an ta Fariseen lam ki Sadduceen rihpung, ni-tmoumimia tyni-æn ka pa-kytta-ah neini-æn ki pou-ki-di-en ka makka-vullum.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka irou'ato tyni-an ta Fariseen lam ki Sadduceen rihpung, ni-tmoumimia tyni-æn ka pa-kytta-ah neini-æn ki pou-kidi-en ka makka-vullum.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende de Phariseen ende Sadduceen tot Hem gegekomen zijnde nde [hem] bersoeckende degeerden ban hem dat hn hae een teecken upt den Hemel soude toonen,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The Pharisees also with the Sadducees came, and tempting desired him that he would shew them a sign from heaven.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">法利賽人和撒都該人來試探耶穌，請他從天上顯個神蹟給他們看。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse2">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ teni ta ni-mattæ'i-vli k'ma neini-æn, Irou ka madoung k'ma-kamou ki sounda, Matika-nagh-al-ato, alei ka meip-hang ta vullum.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ teni ta ni-mattæ'i-vli k'ma neini-æn, Irou ka madoung k'ma-kamou ki sounda, Matika-nagh-al-ato, alei ka meip-hang ta vullum.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> WMaer hy antwoordde ende seyde tot haer Als het abont gheworden is feght ghy Schoon weder want de Hemel is root.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">He answered and said unto them, When it is evening, ye say, It will be fair weather: for the sky is red.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌回答說：「晚上天發紅，你們就說：『天必要晴。』</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse3">
        <FORM kindOf="original">. Dou madama, Bajoug-hah, alei ka meip-hang kyvoulas-en ta vullum. Emoumi ka pa-nni-nni-en ki ryh ki sou,ou-mha-noumi mou-piri ki hauwei ki vullum, ka assi-moumi ou-mh'an [moupiri] ki pou-kidi-en ki kidi [ki tauwil?]</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">. Dou madama, Bajoug-hah, alei ka meip-hang kyvoulas-en ta vullum. Emoumi ka pa-nni-nni-en ki ryh ki sou,ou-mha-noumi mou-piri ki hauwei ki vullum, ka assi-moumi ou-mh'an [moupiri] ki pou-kidi-en ki kidi [ki tauwil?]</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende des morghens Heden onwede want den Hemelis droebig root . Ghy gebeynide het aenschyn des HÃžHemels weet ghy wel te onderschepden ende en kont ghy de teeckenen der tyden niet [onderscheyden ? ]</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And in the morning, It will be foul weather to day: for the sky is red and lowering. O ye hypocrites, ye can discern the face of the sky; but can ye not discern the signs of the times?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">早晨天發紅，又發黑，你們就說：『今日必有風雨。』你們知道分辨天上的氣色，倒不能分辨這時候的神蹟。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse4">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Kavouyvouyl-lan ka ma't'e ka tama-rarbourbo, tmoumimia ki pou-kidi-en: ka assi p'a-an-eih neini-æn ta pou-kidi-en dyk ki na poukakidi ki Tama-mattæ'i-tan ka ti Jonas. Irou ka pa-itoukaqua neini-æn, ni-darang-en tyn-râ.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Kavouyvouyl-lan ka ma't'e ka tama-rarbourbo, tmoumimia ki pou-kidi-en: ka assi p'a-an-eih neini-æn ta pou-kidi-en dyk ki na poukakidi ki Tama-mattæ'i-tan ka ti Jonas. Irou ka pa-itoukaqua neini-æn, ni-darang-en tyn-râ.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Het boos ende obesspeligh geflachte bersoeckt een teecken: ende [ haer] en sal gheen teecken gegeben worden dan het teecken Jone des Propheten. Ende haer berlatende gingh hy wech.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">A wicked and adulterous generation seeketh after a sign; and there shall no sign be given unto it, but the sign of the prophet Jonas. And he left them, and departed.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">一個邪惡淫亂的世代求神蹟，除了約拿的神蹟以外，再沒有神蹟給他看。」耶穌就離開他們去了。 （可8‧14－21）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse5">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou ka irou-ato ta Pahta. tutæu-han tyn tou sait ka tou arough, ni-hou-by-ngnarup-pen nein kei-ul ki paoul.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou ka irou-ato ta Pahta. tutæu-han tyn tou sait ka tou arough, ni-hou-by-ngnarup-pen nein kei-ul ki paoul.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende als lhne Difcipelenop d'ander rijde gekomen waren hadden p bergeten brooden [mede] te nemen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And when his disciples were come to the other side, they had forgotten to take bread.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">門徒渡到那邊去，忘了帶餅。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse6">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus neini-æn, Kmyttâ, saou-kavierrâ ki ni-pei-apyngit ki Fariseen ki Saddu-ceen-appa.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus neini-æn, Kmyttâ, saou-kavierrâ ki ni-pei-apyngit ki Fariseen ki Saddu-ceen-appa.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende Jesus leyde tor haer Siet toe ende wacht u ban den suer deefsem der Phariseen ende Sadduceen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then Jesus said unto them, Take heed and beware of the leaven of the Pharisees and of the Sadducees.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌對他們說：「你們要謹慎，防備法利賽人和撒都該人的酵。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse7">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Neni-râ ni-pæh-alalei pæh-dimdim pæh-madou neini-æn, koun, Alei ka assi-kytta ahkei-ul ki paoul [ta anna.]</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Neni-râ ni-pæh-alalei pæh-dimdim pæh-madou neini-æn, koun, Alei ka assi-kytta ahkei-ul ki paoul [ta anna.]</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende sy oberleyden by hae: selben seggende [is] om dat wn gheen brooden[mede] genomen en hebben,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And they reasoned among themselves, saying, It is because we have taken no bread.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">門徒彼此議論說：「這是因為我們沒有帶餅吧。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse8">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka rou oum-h'an ti Jesus [ta atta] ni-koun tyn neini-æn, Kamang ta pah-alalei 'noumi pah-raryh, ymoumi ka oussyng ki tna-msing-an, ka assi-moumi ah-kakei-ul ta paoul?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka rou oum-h'an ti Jesus [ta atta] ni-koun tyn neini-æn, Kamang ta pah-alalei 'noumi pah-raryh, ymoumi ka oussyng ki tna-msing-an, ka assi-moumi ah-kakei-ul ta paoul?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende Jesus [dat] wetende sepde tot haer Wat oberleght ghy by u selben ghy kleyn-gheloobige dat ghy geen brooden [mede]genomen en hebt</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Which when Jesus perceived, he said unto them, O ye of little faith, why reason ye among yourselves, because ye have brought no bread?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌看出來，就說：「你們這小信的人，為甚麼因為沒有餅彼此議論呢？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse9">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Assi-appa moumi oum-han, assi-moumi pæh-balei-en pah-dim-dim ta ryrymma ki paoul, ki rÿm-ma katounnoun-nan [ka papæ-ræh] ka pyppynna ka læ'i-an ka ni-a-likough-noumi illud?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Assi-appa moumi oum-han, assi-moumi pæh-balei-en pah-dim-dim ta ryrymma ki paoul, ki rÿm-ma katounnoun-nan [ka papæ-ræh] ka pyppynna ka læ'i-an ka ni-a-likough-noumi illud?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> En bestaet ghp noch niet # noch en gedenckt ghy niet aen de bijf brooden Der biif duysent [ mannen, ] ende Hoe beel korben ghy op naemt</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Do ye not yet understand, neither remember the five loaves of the five thousand, and how many baskets ye took up?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們還不明白嗎？不記得那五個餅分給五千人、又收拾了多少籃子的零碎嗎？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse10">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ta pyppytto-appa ki paoul, ki hpat katounoun-nan [ki pæpæ-rah, ka pyppynna ka læ'i-æn ta ni-a-likough-noumi illud?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ta pyppytto-appa ki paoul, ki hpat katounoun-nan [ki pæpæ-rah, ka pyppynna ka læ'i-æn ta ni-a-likough-noumi illud?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Noch aen de seben brooden der bier dupsent [mannen, Jende hoe beel manden ghy op-naemt</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Neither the seven loaves of the four thousand, and how many baskets ye took up?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">也不記得那七個餅分給四千人、又收拾了多少筐子的零碎嗎？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse11">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Mamamang ka assi-moumi oumhan, ka assi-mau-kamou ni-passousou-en ki paoul, [rou ni-koua-au-kamou] ka saou kavier-ah-kamou ki ni-pei-apyngit ki Fariseen ki Sadduceen-appa?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Mamamang ka assi-moumi oumhan, ka assi-mau-kamou ni-passousou-en ki paoul, [rou ni-koua-au-kamou] ka saou kavier-ah-kamou ki ni-pei-apyngit ki Fariseen ki Sadduceen-appa?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">How is it that ye do not understand that I spake it not to you concerning bread, that ye should beware of the leaven of the Pharisees and of the Sadducees?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我對你們說：『要防備法利賽人和撒都該人的酵』，這話不是指着餅說的，你們怎麼不明白呢？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse12">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta oumhan nein, ka assi ni-k'ma, ka saou-kavier-ah ki ni-pei-apyngit ki paoul-rå, ki pæh-tatautæu-en-appa ki Fariseen ki Sadduceen.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta oumhan nein, ka assi ni-k'ma, ka saou-kavier-ah ki ni-pei-apyngit ki paoul-rå, ki pæh-tatautæu-en-appa ki Fariseen ki Sadduceen.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Boe berftonden fp dat hy niet gesegt en hadde dat sy haer wachten fouden ban den suer-deessem des broods maer ban de leere der Phariseen ende Sadduceen</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then understood they how that he bade them not beware of the leaven of bread, but of the doctrine of the Pharisees and of the Sadducees.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">門徒這才曉得他說的不是叫他們防備餅的酵，乃是防備法利賽人和撒都該人的教訓。 （可8‧27－30；路9‧18－21）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse13">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka dou irou-'an ti Jesus tou kidi ki pourough kipassarea ka na ti Filippus, ni-tmaligh ki Pæh-tatæutæu-han tyn, koun, Timang koumma jau-an ta tau, ka Alak-koh ki ka'æuloung ti jau?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka dou irou-'an ti Jesus tou kidi ki pourough kipassarea ka na ti Filippus, ni-tmaligh ki Pæh-tatæutæu-han tyn, koun, Timang koumma jau-an ta tau, ka Alak-koh ki ka'æuloung ti jau?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Alsnn Jesus ghekomen was in de deelen Cesaree Philippi braeghde hy syne Difcipelen segghende Wie seggen demenschen dat ick de Zone des menschen ben :</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">When Jesus came into the coasts of Caesarea Philippi, he asked his disciples, saying, Whom do men say that I the Son of man am?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌到了凱撒利亞‧腓立比的境內，就問門徒說：「人說我－－人子是誰？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse14">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-k'ma ta neni, Ta rou-ma, ka ti Joannes [kow] ka na Tama-'eulough, ta rouma, ka ti Elias [kow], ta rouma-râ ka ti Je remias [kow], ki saät lava ki na Tama-mattæi-tan.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-k'ma ta neni, Ta rou-ma, ka ti Joannes [kow] ka na Tama-'eulough, ta rouma, ka ti Elias [kow], ta rouma-râ ka ti Je remias [kow], ki saät lava ki na Tama-mattæi-tan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende sy sepden Sommige Joannes de Doope ende andere Elias mde andere Jeremias ofte ten ban de Propheten.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And they said, Some say that thou art John the Baptist: some, Elias; and others, Jeremias, or one of the prophets.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們說：「有人說是施洗的約翰；有人說是以利亞；又有人說是耶利米或是先知裏的一位。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse15">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Nik'ma neini-æn, Ymou mi-râ, timang -k'ma-ka-mou jæu-an?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Nik'ma neini-æn, Ymou mi-râ, timang -k'ma-ka-mou jæu-an?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Hy eyde tot haer Maer ghy wie seght ghy dat ick bens</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">He saith unto them, But whom say ye that I am?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：「你們說我是誰？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse16">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ni-pattæi-bli-en ti Simon Petrus, ka k'ma, Ti ihristus kow, ka Alak ki Alid ka mæuagh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ni-pattæi-bli-en ti Simon Petrus, ka k'ma, Ti ihristus kow, ka Alak ki Alid ka mæuagh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende Simon Petrus antwoordende sepde Ghy zijt de Chiiltus de Sone des lebendigen Godts.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And Simon Peter answered and said, Thou art the Christ, the Son of the living God.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">西門‧彼得回答說：「你是基督，是永生上帝的兒子。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse17">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Karou mattæ'i-vli ta ti Je-sus ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Tama-tæi-riang kow Simon Bar-Jona: alei ka assi pa-ou-mha-ato ki atta ym-hou-an ta vaät ki amagh, râ Ra-man-appa mau ka itou-tounnoun ki vulluvullum.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Karou mattæ'i-vli ta ti Je-sus ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Tama-tæi-riang kow Simon Bar-Jona: alei ka assi pa-ou-mha-ato ki atta ym-hou-an ta vaät ki amagh, râ Ra-man-appa mau ka itou-tounnoun ki vulluvullum.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> EndeJesus antwoordende sepde tot hem Saligh Zyt ghy Simon Bar Jona: want bleefch ende bloedt en heeft u [dat]niet gheopenbaert maer mijn Dader die inde Hemelen is.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And Jesus answered and said unto him, Blessed art thou, Simon Barjona: for flesh and blood hath not revealed it unto thee, but my Father which is in heaven.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌對他說：「西門‧巴‧約拿，你是有福的！因為這不是屬血肉的指示你的，乃是我在天上的父指示的。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse18">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka koun-nappa kow ka ti Petrus kow, ka tou halap ki Pe-tra katta pei-s'hut-ei-mau mei-ryngei ki Pakoi-sasaal-lan-au, ka assitmounoun-nah ki atta ta ngatas ki kalæu-hæu-en.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka koun-nappa kow ka ti Petrus kow, ka tou halap ki Pe-tra katta pei-s'hut-ei-mau mei-ryngei ki Pakoi-sasaal-lan-au, ka assitmounoun-nah ki atta ta ngatas ki kalæu-hæu-en.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende ick segghe n oock dat ghy rije Petrus ende op dee Petra sal ick mijn Gemepnte bouwen esi de poorten der Helle en sullen deselbe niet oberweldigen, -</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And I say also unto thee, That thou art Peter, and upon this rock I will build my church; and the gates of hell shall not prevail against it.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我還告訴你，你是彼得，我要把我的教會建造在這磐石上；陰間的權柄不能勝過他。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse19">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka pha 'nei-mæu-kow ta a'au-alilib ki Pei-sasou-an ki toun-noun ki vulluvullum: ka kama-mang ka vauut-au-'mhou tou Næi, væuut-an-eil-ato tou toun-noun ki vulluvullum. Râ kama-mang. ka æ'au-vavæuut-ei-'mhou tou Næi, ææu-vavæu-ut-eih tou tounnoun ki vulluvullum.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka pha 'nei-mæu-kow ta a'au-alilib ki Pei-sasou-an ki toun-noun ki vulluvullum: ka kama-mang ka vauut-au-'mhou tou Næi, væuut-an-eil-ato tou toun-noun ki vulluvullum. Râ kama-mang. ka æ'au-vavæuut-ei-'mhou tou Næi, ææu-vavæu-ut-eih tou tounnoun ki vulluvullum.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende ick salu geben de flentelen ban het Koninckriick der Hemelen:ende foo wat ghy sult binden op der aeeden al in de Hemelen ghebonden zijn. Ende soo wat ghy ontbinden sult op der aerden sal in de Hemelen ontbonden zijn.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And I will give unto thee the keys of the kingdom of heaven: and whatsoever thou shalt bind on earth shall be bound in heaven: and whatsoever thou shalt loose on earth shall be loosed in heaven.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我要把天國的鑰匙給你，凡你在地上所捆綁的，在天上也要捆綁；凡你在地上所釋放的，在天上也要釋放。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse20">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Tou kidi k'anna ni-ma-vagh ki Pahtatautau-han tyn, kassi banavana-ah ty mamang-an ka ti Jesus ta teni ka ti ahristus.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Tou kidi k'anna ni-ma-vagh ki Pahtatautau-han tyn, kassi banavana-ah ty mamang-an ka ti Jesus ta teni ka ti ahristus.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Doe Boe berboodt hy shne. Discipelen dat sy niemant segghen en souden dat hy was Jesns de Ehriltus.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then charged he his disciples that they should tell no man that he was Jesus the Christ.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">當下，耶穌囑咐門徒，不可對人說他是基督。 （可8‧31－9‧1；路9‧22－27）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse21">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Tou kidi-appa k'anna ni-mæi-næunamou ta ti Jesus vanna-vanna ki Pahtatæutæu-han tyn,ka kidi-ato ki darang-eih tyn mou-koua tou Jerusalem, ka tub'-hah ki madagh neini-æn ka Mamou-mou [ki tau,]ka Si-bavau ka Ta-ma-p'hik, ka Makou-sasoulat, ka paka-patei-auh, ka pa-pætti-mau-aeil-appa tou katatouro ki wæ'i.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Tou kidi-appa k'anna ni-mæi-næunamou ta ti Jesus vanna-vanna ki Pahtatæutæu-han tyn,ka kidi-ato ki darang-eih tyn mou-koua tou Jerusalem, ka tub'-hah ki madagh neini-æn ka Mamou-mou [ki tau,]ka Si-bavau ka Ta-ma-p'hik, ka Makou-sasoulat, ka paka-patei-auh, ka pa-pætti-mau-aeil-appa tou katatouro ki wæ'i.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Pan doen aen begon Jesus sijne Dilciptlen te bertoonen dat hy moeste hemen gaen nae Jerulalem ende bele lijden ban de Ouderlingen ende Oberpiielteren ende Schiift-geleerden ende gedoode worden ende ten erden daghe opgheweckc worden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">From that time forth began Jesus to shew unto his disciples, how that he must go unto Jerusalem, and suffer many things of the elders and chief priests and scribes, and be killed, and be raised again the third day.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">從此，耶穌才指示門徒，他必須上耶路撒冷去，受長老、祭司長、文士許多的苦，並且被殺，第三日復活。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse22">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Trou ka ni-pa-toulam tyni-æn ta ti Petrus, ni-kmæ-i-nauna-mou matymha tyni-æn, koun, Mei-rang maharum-mâ ymhou-an, assi pavut-anh ta atta ymhou-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Trou ka ni-pa-toulam tyni-æn ta ti Petrus, ni-kmæ-i-nauna-mou matymha tyni-æn, koun, Mei-rang maharum-mâ ymhou-an, assi pavut-anh ta atta ymhou-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende Petrughem tot sich genome hebbende begon b te beli affen seggende eere [zijt] u genadigh : dit en sal n geenfins geschieden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then Peter took him, and began to rebuke him, saying, Be it far from thee, Lord: this shall not be unto thee.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">彼得就拉着他，勸他說：「主啊，萬不可如此！這事必不臨到你身上。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse23">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ teni rou ni-ma'æu-douma tyni-æn, ni-k'ma ti Petrus an, 'arang-â Tama-makou-dou-ma mourikour jæu-an, ka pa-ræu ræu kow jau-an: ka assi kow pæh-arpit pæh-dimdim ka à tou Alid: dyk ka à tou ka'æuloung-da,</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ teni rou ni-ma'æu-douma tyni-æn, ni-k'ma ti Petrus an, 'arang-â Tama-makou-dou-ma mourikour jæu-an, ka pa-ræu ræu kow jau-an: ka assi kow pæh-arpit pæh-dimdim ka à tou Alid: dyk ka à tou ka'æuloung-da,</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Maerhyhemomkeerende eyde cot Petrum Gaet wech achter my Satana: ghy rhjt my een aenftoot: want ghy en besfint niet DE dingen die Godts zijn mae? Die der menschen zijn.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But he turned, and said unto Peter, Get thee behind me, Satan: thou art an offence unto me: for thou savourest not the things that be of God, but those that be of men.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌轉過來，對彼得說：「撒但，退我後邊去吧！你是絆我腳的；因為你不體貼上帝的意思，只體貼人的意思。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse24">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Tou kidi k'anna ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus ki Pahtatæutau-han tyn, Timamang ta mamoei mææuugh mouqua jau-an-nda, rmau-à mad-dotyni-æn, mara-a ka navæværægh tyn, ka smala-dylloum-à jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Tou kidi k'anna ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus ki Pahtatæutau-han tyn, Timamang ta mamoei mææuugh mouqua jau-an-nda, rmau-à mad-dotyni-æn, mara-a ka navæværægh tyn, ka smala-dylloum-à jau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Doe sepde Jesus tot thne Discipelen Soo yemant achter my wil komen Die berloochene hem-sflben ende neeme fijn kmys op ende bolge my,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then said Jesus unto his disciples, If any man will come after me, let him deny himself, and take up his cross, and follow me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">於是耶穌對門徒說：「若有人要跟從我，就當捨己，背起他的十字架來跟從我。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse25">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka timamang ta mamoei 'hma ki kæuag-han tyn, ataurum-ma-æh ki anna: rå ti mamang ta pataurumia-al-ato ki kæuag-han tyn alei jau-an, smou-valei-ah ki anna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka timamang ta mamoei 'hma ki kæuag-han tyn, ataurum-ma-æh ki anna: rå ti mamang ta pataurumia-al-ato ki kæuag-han tyn alei jau-an, smou-valei-ah ki anna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Want soo wit sYi leben sal willen behouden die sal her selbeberliesen : mats ger foo wie fijn leben berliefen fal om mijnent wille die sal het selbe binden. |</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">For whosoever will save his life shall lose it: and whosoever will lose his life for my sake shall find it.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">因為，凡要救自己生命的，必喪掉生命；凡為我喪掉生命的，必得着生命。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse26">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka akou-than ki mang ta ka'æuloung, ka pa pouthan-nen tyn tyni-æn ta ymmid ki Næi, rou mahavoung ki vatte tyn? Kamang-alato lava ta papap-æ ki ta'u, ka pa-viri-eih ki vatte tyn?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka akou-than ki mang ta ka'æuloung, ka pa pouthan-nen tyn tyni-æn ta ymmid ki Næi, rou mahavoung ki vatte tyn? Kamang-alato lava ta papap-æ ki ta'u, ka pa-viri-eih ki vatte tyn?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Want wat batet een mensche soo hy de geheele werelt ghewint ende lydt fchade syner riele 4 Ofte wat sal een mensche geben tot lossinge ban sijne riele $</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">For what is a man profited, if he shall gain the whole world, and lose his own soul? or what shall a man give in exchange for his soul?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">人若賺得全世界，賠上自己的生命，有甚麼益處呢？人還能拿甚麼換生命呢？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse27">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka koumma-al-ato-hynna ka ierou-'æh ta Alak ki ka'æuloung tou keirang-en ki kidi ki Rama tyn lam ki Tama-gnau tyn, ka tou kidi k'anna pa'a-vli-ah ki Meig-bovoel ki na poungas tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka koumma-al-ato-hynna ka ierou-'æh ta Alak ki ka'æuloung tou keirang-en ki kidi ki Rama tyn lam ki Tama-gnau tyn, ka tou kidi k'anna pa'a-vli-ah ki Meig-bovoel ki na poungas tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Want de Sone des WMenschen sal komen in de heerlickhepdt cijns Daders met shne Engelen ende als dan sal hy cen pegelick bergelden na syn doen, _</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">For the Son of man shall come in the glory of his Father with his angels; and then he shall reward every man according to his works.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">人子要在他父的榮耀裏，同着眾使者降臨；那時候，他要照各人的行為報應各人。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse28">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> D'lligh koun-næu-kamou râ, akou-mea ta rarouma ki mi-touhko hia, ka assi kdiman-ah ki kapatei-an, tou kidi-appa k'anna ka kytta-eil-ato nein ta Alak ki ka'æuloung iroua tou Pei-sasou-an tyn. Kasasat kytti-an 'ab ki pyttou ki Ibæh ki soulat.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> D'lligh koun-næu-kamou râ, akou-mea ta rarouma ki mi-touhko hia, ka assi kdiman-ah ki kapatei-an, tou kidi-appa k'anna ka kytta-eil-ato nein ta Alak ki ka'æuloung iroua tou Pei-sasou-an tyn. Kasasat kytti-an 'ab ki pyttou ki Ibæh ki soulat.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Yoorwaer segge ick u Daer zijn sommighe ban die bier staen dewelcke den doodt niet imaken en cullen tot dat sy den Sone des Wenschen ullen hebben sien komt in syn Koninckrijcke.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Verily I say unto you, There be some standing here, which shall not taste of death, till they see the Son of man coming in his kingdom.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我實在告訴你們，站在這裏的，有人在沒嘗死味以前必看見人子降臨在他的國裏。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
</TEXT>