<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEXT id="Siraya_Dutch_Matthew_Chapter27" xml:lang="fos" source="Siraya Bible, Matthew gospel" copyright="public domain" citation="Gravius, Daniël. 1661. Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa. Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang. Amsterdam: Michiel Hartogh." BibTeX_citation="@book{Gravius1661,&#10;  author    = {Gravius, Daniël},&#10;  year      = {1661},&#10;  title     = {Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa},&#10;  note      = {Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang},&#10;  address   = {Amsterdam},&#10;  publisher = {Michiel Hartogh}&#10;}" dialect="Siraya">
    <S id="verse1">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> IRou ka madama ato, ni-kmi-ym ki sou ta Sibavau ka Ta-ma-P'hik ki Mamoumou-appa ki ta'u sadadoumma ti Jesus-an tou pakapatei-an-ei tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> IRou ka madama ato, ni-kmi-ym ki sou ta Sibavau ka Ta-ma-P'hik ki Mamoumou-appa ki ta'u sadadoumma ti Jesus-an tou pakapatei-an-ei tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">het nu morghenstont geworden was hebben alle de Obeypiielters ende de Onderlinghen des bolcx t'samen raet genomen tegen Jesum dat fp hem dooden souden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">When the morning was come, all the chief priests and elders of the people took counsel against Jesus to put him to death:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">到了早晨，眾祭司長和民間的長老大家商議要治死耶穌，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse2">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka rou ni-bæuut tyni-æn, ni-addneyn padarang ka ni-pæ æ tounnoun tyni-en ti Pontius Pili-tus ka Tæi-sou ki pourough.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka rou ni-bæuut tyni-æn, ni-addneyn padarang ka ni-pæ æ tounnoun tyni-en ti Pontius Pili-tus ka Tæi-sou ki pourough.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende hem gebonden hebbende leydden fp [hem] wech emde gaben hem ober aen Pontius Pilatus den Stadthouder.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And when they had bound him, they led him away, and delivered him to Pontius Pilate the governor.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">就把他捆綁，解去，交給巡撫彼拉多。 （徒1‧18－19）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse3">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta ni-kavoulas-sen ti Judas ka ni sivanavana-ato tyni. æn, æn, kytt'an tyn ka dung-dung-en-ato ta teni, ni-âli kough tyn mad ki toutourou kyttiæn ki ma-lyttouk ki Sibavau ka Tama-P'hik ki Mamoumou-appa-râ.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta ni-kavoulas-sen ti Judas ka ni sivanavana-ato tyni. æn, æn, kytt'an tyn ka dung-dung-en-ato ta teni, ni-âli kough tyn mad ki toutourou kyttiæn ki ma-lyttouk ki Sibavau ka Tama-P'hik ki Mamoumou-appa-râ.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doe heeft Judas die hem berraden hadde siende dat dat hy beroordeelddt was berouw ghehadt ende heekt de dertigh silbere{[penningen] den Oberpiielteren ende den Ouderlinge wede: gebracht.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then Judas, which had betrayed him, when he saw that he was condemned, repented himself, and brought again the thirty pieces of silver to the chief priests and elders,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">這時候，賣耶穌的猶大看見耶穌已經定了罪，就後悔，把那三十塊錢拿回來給祭司長和長老，說：</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse4">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Kma, Ni-mavarau-koh, ki sivanavan'an ta 'æmægh ka matik-tik. Râ ni-k'ma ta neni, Mangau-mi-æn? Ymhou ta kmytta-ah.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Kma, Ni-mavarau-koh, ki sivanavan'an ta 'æmægh ka matiktik. Râ ni-k'ma ta neni, Mangau-mi-æn? Ymhou ta kmytta-ah.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Seggende Ick hebbe gesondight . berradende het onfchuldigh bloet. Maer n sepden Wat gaet ons [dat] aen + Ghy meught toesien,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Saying, I have sinned in that I have betrayed the innocent blood. And they said, What is that to us? see thou to that.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">「我賣了無辜之人的血是有罪了。」他們說：「那與我們有甚麼相干？你自己承當吧！」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse5">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Jrou ka ni-aryng tyn ta ma-lyttouk smaki-koua tou Kouva ki tatamd-den ki Alid, ni-d'marang-atou-râ, irou ka ou-koun, ni-mau-sæid.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Jrou ka ni-aryng tyn ta ma-lyttouk smaki-koua tou Kouva ki tatamd-den ki Alid, ni-d'marang-atou-râ, irou ka ou-koun, ni-mau-sæid.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Endeals hy de filbere [penningen] in den Tempel geworpen hadde bertrock hy ende henen gaends berworghde [hem-felben.] |</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And he cast down the pieces of silver in the temple, and departed, and went and hanged himself.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">猶大就把那銀錢丟在殿裏，出去吊死了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse6">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Jrou ka æughin ki Si-bavæu ka Tama-P'hik ta malyttouk, ni-koun nein, Assi hahei-en ka sacyt eih ta anna tou poukakou'an ki ni-pap'hik-an, alei ka na kidi ki assa ki amagh ta anna-râ.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Jrou ka æughin ki Si-bavæu ka Tama-P'hik ta malyttouk, ni-koun nein, Assi hahei-en ka sacyt eih ta anna tou poukakou'an ki ni-pap'hik-an, alei ka na kidi ki assa ki amagh ta anna-râ.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">EndedeOber-paesters de silbere [ penninghen ] nemende sepden Het 1s met gheoorloft deselbe in de Offer kitte te leggen dewijle Het eenen prijs des bloets 1s,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And the chief priests took the silver pieces, and said, It is not lawful for to put them into the treasury, because it is the price of blood.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">祭司長拾起銀錢來，說：「這是血價，不可放在庫裏。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse7">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Jrou ka maki-kaha kmi'ym ki sou, nipeila nein ki anna ta ou ma ki Tama-toulou ki rangi, tou raravakeih ki ta'ækoua [neini-æn.]</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Jrou ka maki-kaha kmi'ym ki sou, nipeila nein ki anna ta ou ma ki Tama-toulou ki rangi, tou raravakeih ki ta'ækoua [neini-æn.]</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende t'samen raedt genomen hebbende kochten (p daer mede den acker des pot-backers tot eene begrabeniCle boor de breembelingen</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And they took counsel, and bought with them the potter's field, to bury strangers in.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們商議，就用那銀錢買了窯戶的一塊田，為要埋葬外鄉人。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse8">
        <FORM kindOf="original">. Ka alei ki anna na-pana-nang-en ta ouma k'anna, ouma ki amagh, tou kidi-appa ki wæ'i hnyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">. Ka alei ki anna na-pana-nang-en ta ouma k'anna, ouma ki amagh, tou kidi-appa ki wæ'i hnyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Baerom 18 diey acker ghenaemt den acker deg ior tot op den hupdigen</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Wherefore that field was called, The field of blood, unto this day.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">所以那塊田直到今日還叫做「血田」。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse9">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta ni-paste ta na sousou ki Tama-mattæ'i-tan ka ti Jere-mias, ka ni-koun tyn, Ka ni-æugh nein touro kyttien ki malyttouk, ta angal ka kidi ki na alalak ti Isræul, ki ni-sikidi-en nein.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta ni-paste ta na sousou ki Tama-mattæ'i-tan ka ti Jere-mias, ka ni-koun tyn, Ka ni-æugh nein touro kyttien ki malyttouk, ta angal ka kidi ki na alalak ti Isræul, ki ni-sikidi-en nein.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doe is beybult geworden Her gene gelproken 18 door den Prophheet JeremiAin feggende Ende sy heben ben de dertigh silbere [penninghen] genomen de weerde des geweerdeerden ban de kinderen Jsratls den welcKen sy geweerdecrt hebben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then was fulfilled that which was spoken by Jeremy the prophet, saying, And they took the thirty pieces of silver, the price of him that was valued, whom they of the children of Israel did value;</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">這就應了先知耶利米的話，說：「他們用那三十塊錢，就是被估定之人的價錢，是以色列人中所估定的，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse10">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-p'hæn nein ta anna alei ki ouma ki tmatoulou ki ran-gi, tou ahkoua-an ki ni-sikidi-en ti JEHOVA jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-p'hæn nein ta anna alei ki ouma ki tmatoulou ki ran-gi, tou ahkoua-an ki ni-sikidi-en ti JEHOVA jau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende hebben deselbe gegeben boor den acke: des pot-backes bolgens t gene my de Heere bebolen heefc.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And gave them for the potter's field, as the Lord appointed me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">買了窯戶的一塊田；這是照着主所吩咐我的。」 （可15‧2－5；路23‧3－5；約18‧33－38）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse11">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-jtou-douma mitouh ko ta ti Jesus ki Ta'isou ki pou-rough, ka ni-tmaligh ta Ta'isou, k'ma, Mei-sasou kow kaua ka Si-bavau ki Joden? Ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus tyni-en, Pattæ'irouk-en-hou.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-jtou-douma mitouh ko ta ti Jesus ki Ta'isou ki pou-rough, ka ni-tmaligh ta Ta'isou, k'ma, Mei-sasou kow kaua ka Si-bavau ki Joden? Ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus tyni-en, Pattæ'irouk-en-hou.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende Jesus ltondt boor den Stadthoude ende de Stadthouder braeghde hem segghende Zijt ghy De Koningh der Jodenr ende Jesus seyde hem Ghy feght</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And Jesus stood before the governor: and the governor asked him, saying, Art thou the King of the Jews? And Jesus said unto him, Thou sayest.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌站在巡撫面前；巡撫問他說：「你是猶太人的王嗎？」耶穌說：「你說的是。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse12">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka tou pat'barau-en tyni-æn ki Si-bavau ka Tama-Phik ki Mamoumou-appa, assi tyn-pattæ'i-v'lli-en ta mamang.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka tou pat'barau-en tyni-æn ki Si-bavau ka Tama-Phik ki Mamoumou-appa, assi tyn-pattæ'i-v'lli-en ta mamang.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende als hy ban de Ober-pitesters ende de Ouderlingen beschuldigt wiert en antwoordde hy niets.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And when he was accused of the chief priests and elders, he answered nothing.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他被祭司長和長老控告的時候，甚麼都不回答。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse13">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta ni-k'ma ta ti Pila-tus tyni-æn, Assi kow millingigh papynna ta pattæ'i-hail nein sada-douma ymhou-an?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta ni-k'ma ta ti Pilatus tyni-æn, Assi kow millingigh papynna ta pattæ'i-hail nein sada-douma ymhou-an?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doe seyde Pilatus tot hem En hoort ghy niethoe bele [faken}sp tegen u getuygen s</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then said Pilate unto him, Hearest thou not how many things they witness against thee?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">彼拉多就對他說：「他們作見證告你這麼多的事，你沒有聽見嗎？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse14">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ assi ni-pattæ'i-v'lli-en tyn ki sasasat ki sou tyni-æn, kom-ma-hynna ka ouhang ni-mourynh-gau ta Tæ'i-sou.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ assi ni-pattæ'i-v'lli-en tyn ki sasasat ki sou tyni-æn, kom-ma-hynna ka ouhang ni-mourynh-gau ta Tæ'i-sou.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Waer hy en antwoordde hem niet op een eenigh woordt alsoo dar de Stadt houder hem seer berwonderde.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And he answered him to never a word; insomuch that the governor marvelled greatly.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌仍不回答，連一句話也不說，以致巡撫甚覺希奇。 （可15‧6－15；路23‧13－25；約18‧39－19‧16）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse15">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka na kidi ki kadæ'æm-en tou Ouvavoutoug-han ka â-sâteih-mæ æumia ki Tæ'i-sou ta ni-pou sangat ki makoilalaulau, timamang lava ka kamoei-in nein-da.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka na kidi ki kadæ'æm-en tou Ouvavoutoug-han ka â-sâteih-mæ æumia ki Tæ'i-sou ta ni-pou sangat ki makoilalaulau, timamang lava ka kamoei-in nein-da.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende op het Feest was de Stadthoude: ghewoon den bolckeeenen ghebangenen los te laten welcken sy wilden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Now at that feast the governor was wont to release unto the people a prisoner, whom they would.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">巡撫有一個常例，每逢這節期，隨眾人所要的釋放一個囚犯給他們。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse16">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-akoumea nein tou kidi k'anna saat ki vænut-en-ato ka mæmægh ki varau, ka ni-saki-nanang-en ti Barabbæs.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-akoumea nein tou kidi k'anna saat ki vænut-en-ato ka mæmægh ki varau, ka ni-saki-nanang-en ti Barabbæs.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende ly hadden doen eenen emen wel-bekenden gebangenen ghenaemt Barabas.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And they had then a notable prisoner, called Barabbas.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">當時有一個出名的囚犯叫巴拉巴。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse17">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Jrou ka ni-papæui-sal ta neni, ni-k'ma ta ti Pilatus neini-æn, Timang ta kamoei-'noumi ka aumi-æu-mau-kamou, ti Barabbas kaua ti Jesus kaua, ka siouwa ti mhristus?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Jrou ka ni-papæui-sal ta neni, ni-k'ma ta ti Pilatus neini-æn, Timang ta kamoei-'noumi ka aumi-æu-mau-kamou, ti Barabbas kaua ti Jesus kaua, ka siouwa ti mhristus?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Adls sy dan bergadert waren sepde Pilatus tot hae Welcken wilt ghy dat ick u [al los laten Barabbam ofte Jelum die ghenaemt wordt Chiiftus t</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Therefore when they were gathered together, Pilate said unto them, Whom will ye that I release unto you? Barabbas, or Jesus which is called Christ?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">眾人聚集的時候，彼拉多就對他們說：「你們要我釋放哪一個給你們？是巴拉巴呢？是稱為基督的耶穌呢？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse18">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ kavanan tyn ka ni. paa-tounnoun ta neni tyni-æn. alei ki ni-'a'as-sen tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ kavanan tyn ka ni. paa-tounnoun ta neni tyni-æn. alei ki ni-'a'as-sen tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Want hy wist datsp hem doorr nijdigheyt obergelebert hadden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">For he knew that for envy they had delivered him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">巡撫原知道他們是因為嫉妒才把他解了來。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse19">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Jrou ka mierrong ta teni tou Jerrarong-an ki au-pæpæ-nah-hen, ni-madingi ta kei'an tyn pakavana tyni-æn, ka komma koua, Ynna oumamang ki Matik-tik k'anna nda madagh ta ni tub'bhen-nau hnyn ki euvan k'atta tou malling alei tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Jrou ka mierrong ta teni tou Jerrarong-an ki au-pæpæ-nah-hen, ni-madingi ta kei'an tyn pakavana tyni-æn, ka komma koua, Ynna oumamang ki Matiktik k'anna nda madagh ta ni tub'bhen-nau hnyn ki euvan k'atta tou malling alei tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">e als hy op den Kechterftoel sat soo heeft sjne huy[brouwe tot hem ghesonden eggende Hebt [doch] niet te doen met dien Kechtbeerdigen : want ick hebbe heden beel geleden in Den Dr00m om (ijnent wille.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">When he was set down on the judgment seat, his wife sent unto him, saying, Have thou nothing to do with that just man: for I have suffered many things this day in a dream because of him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">正坐堂的時候，他的夫人打發人來說：「這義人的事，你一點不可管，因為我今天在夢中為他受了許多的苦。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse20">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ ni-pa-tæumha ta Si-bavæu ka Tama-Phik ki Mamoumou-appa ki makoilalaulau, ka tou-mini-au nein ta ti Barabbas, papa-kapatei ti Jesus-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ ni-pa-tæumha ta Si-bavæu ka Tama-Phik ki Mamoumou-appa ki makoilalaulau, ka tou-mini-au nein ta ti Barabbas, papa-kapatei ti Jesus-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Maer de Ober-paieters ende de Ouderlinghen hebben de scharen aengeraden dat sy Barabbam souden begeeren ende Jesum dooden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But the chief priests and elders persuaded the multitude that they should ask Barabbas, and destroy Jesus.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">祭司長和長老挑唆眾人，求釋放巴拉巴，除滅耶穌。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse21">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-mattæ'i-vlli ta Tæ''-sou ki pourough, k'ma neini-æn, Timang ki rarouha katta ta ka-moei'noumi ka æumi-au-mau-ka-mou? Ka ni-k'ma ta neni, Ti Barab-bas.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-mattæ'i-vlli ta Tæ''-sou ki pourough, k'ma neini-æn, Timang ki rarouha katta ta ka-moei'noumi ka æumi-au-mau-ka-mou? Ka ni-k'ma ta neni, Ti Barab-bas.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende de StadthouDer antwoordende sepde tot haer Welckenbandese twee wilt ghy dat ick u sal los lawm? endesp sepden Barab-</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">The governor answered and said unto them, Whether of the twain will ye that I release unto you? They said, Barabbas.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">巡撫對眾人說：「這兩個人，你們要我釋放哪一個給你們呢？」他們說：「巴拉巴。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse22">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ni-k'ma ta ti Pilatus neini-an, Mang-aul-at'mau ta ti Jesus, ka siouwa ti Nhristus? Ni-kmæi-beiaveiah tyni-an, Ndà pouna-væ væræh-auh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ni-k'ma ta ti Pilatus neini-an, Mang-aul-at'mau ta ti Jesus, ka siouwa ti Nhristus? Ni-kmæi-beiaveiah tyni-an, Ndà pouna-væ væræh-auh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Pilatus sepde tot Haer Wat sal ick dan doen [ met] Jesu die ghenaemt wordt Chaisuss Sy eyden alletot hem Laet hem ghekyuwcight wordm.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Pilate saith unto them, What shall I do then with Jesus which is called Christ? They all say unto him, Let him be crucified.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">彼拉多說：「這樣，那稱為基督的耶穌我怎麼辦他呢？」他們都說：「把他釘十字架！」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse23">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ ni-k'ma ta Tæ'ï-sou ki pourough, Kamang ta na varau tyn? Ka pakosaoun-neyu mako-toun, k'ma, Papounævæværæh-auh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ ni-k'ma ta Tæ'ï-sou ki pourough, Kamang ta na varau tyn? Ka pakosaoun-neyu mako-toun, k'ma, Papounævæværæh-auh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doch de Stadthouder seyde Wat heeft hy dan quaets gedaent Ende sy rieen te meer seggende Laet hem gekruycight worden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And the governor said, Why, what evil hath he done? But they cried out the more, saying, Let him be crucified.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">巡撫說：「為甚麼呢？他做了甚麼惡事呢？」他們便極力地喊着說：「把他釘十字架！」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse24">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Jrou ka hmauat ta ti Pila-tus, ka assi tyn paka-saoun-nen mil-ligh, rå nipaka-saoun-nen appa ta karakkarak-an, ni-æugh tyn ta ra-loum, ka ni-madynnæu ki rima tou amæh ki makoisasal, ka ni-koun tyn, Aousi-koh ki varau ki papou tatiri-en ki æmagh ki matiktik kat-ta: Hmæuattâ ta ymoumi-râ.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Jrou ka hmauat ta ti Pilatus, ka assi tyn paka-saoun-nen mil-ligh, rå nipaka-saoun-nen appa ta karakkarak-an, ni-æugh tyn ta ra-loum, ka ni-madynnæu ki rima tou amæh ki makoisasal, ka ni-koun tyn, Aousi-koh ki varau ki papou tatiri-en ki æmagh ki matiktik katta: Hmæuattâ ta ymoumi-râ.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ails nu Pilatus Cagh dat hy niet en borderde maer beel meer '{datter} oproer wiert nam hy wate ende wiesch de handen boor de schare seggende Ick ben onchuldigh ban het bloedc deses Rechtbeerdigen: Ghyheden meught toefie.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">When Pilate saw that he could prevail nothing, but that rather a tumult was made, he took water, and washed his hands before the multitude, saying, I am innocent of the blood of this just person: see ye to it.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">彼拉多見說也無濟於事，反要生亂，就拿水在眾人面前洗手，說：「流這義人的血，罪不在我，你們承當吧。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse25">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-mattæ-vlli ta ma-koitatmouk ka ta'u, kmagh tyn ta mouhalap-a ymi-ænæn, ki alla-lak-appa-mian.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-mattæ-vlli ta ma-koitatmouk ka ta'u, kmagh tyn ta mouhalap-a ymi-ænæn, ki alla-lak-appa-mian.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende alle het bolck antwoordende seyde Sijn bloet [kome] ober ons ende obe: onse kinderen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then answered all the people, and said, His blood be on us, and on our children.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">眾人都回答說：「他的血歸到我們和我們的子孫身上。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse26">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta ni-æumi-en tyn pæ æ koua neini-æn ta ti Barabbæs, jrou ka ni-smaplat ti Jesus-an, ni-pa'a tounnoun tou pounavævæ ræh-eih tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta ni-æumi-en tyn pæ æ koua neini-æn ta ti Barabbæs, jrou ka ni-smaplat ti Jesus-an, ni-pa'a tounnoun tou pounavævæ ræh-eih tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doeliet hy hae: Barabbam los maer Fesum gegeesselt hebbende gaf hy hem ober om ghtkrupcight te worden. =</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then released he Barabbas unto them: and when he had scourged Jesus, he delivered him to be crucified.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">於是彼拉多釋放巴拉巴給他們，把耶穌鞭打了，交給人釘十字架。 （可15‧16－20；約19‧2－3）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse27">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta ni-patoulam ta Ta-ma-macytki Ta'i sou ki pourough ti Jesus-an, paoukoua teini-an tou keirang-en ki papa-mamaghan, ka ni-papæui-mouk nein papæu-isal tyni-æn ta makoitatmouk ki sat ka-ylyl-lan.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta ni-patoulam ta Ta-ma-macytki Ta'i sou ki pourough ti Jesus-an, paoukoua teini-an tou keirang-en ki papa-mamaghan, ka ni-papæui-mouk nein papæu-isal tyni-æn ta makoitatmouk ki sat ka-ylyl-lan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doe namen de Krijgsknechten des Stadt-houders Jelum met haer in het Kecht-hups ende bergaderden ober hem de gantsche bende, |</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then the soldiers of the governor took Jesus into the common hall, and gathered unto him the whole band of soldiers.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">巡撫的兵就把耶穌帶進衙門，叫全營的兵都聚集在他那裏。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse28">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Jrou ka ni-æumi-en nein ta pammi-'en tyn, ni-papæh-kouvar ta neni tyni-æn ki kouvar ka ma-ma ki apoei [ka patagh.]</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Jrou ka ni-æumi-en nein ta pammi-'en tyn, ni-papæh-kouvar ta neni tyni-æn ki kouvar ka ma-ma ki apoei [ka patagh.]</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende als sy hem ontkleedt hadden deden sy hem eenen tenen purpuren mantel om.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And they stripped him, and put on him a scarlet robe.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們給他脫了衣服，穿上一件朱紅色袍子，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse29">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Jrou ka ni-tynnoun nein ta saki-rou ka na adum, ni-paka-boungo-en nein tyni-æn ta atta, pou-koua ki angto-appa tou rima ka ouwal tyn, ka rou mata ly-kou-rog tou doumma tyni-æn, ni-bylla vylla tyni-æn, k'ma, Tabe mei-sasou ka Si-bavæu ki Joden.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Jrou ka ni-tynnoun nein ta saki-rou ka na adum, ni-paka-boungo-en nein tyni-æn ta atta, pou-koua ki angto-appa tou rima ka ouwal tyn, ka rou mata ly-kou-rog tou doumma tyni-æn, ni-bylla vylla tyni-æn, k'ma, Tabe mei-sasou ka Si-bavæu ki Joden.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Endeeen kroone ban doornen gheblochten hebbende setteden [die] op ijn Hooft ende cenen rietltock in fijne rechter baot;] ende ballendeop hare knyen boor Hem bespotteden sy hem segghende Weelt gegroet ghy koningh de: Joden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And when they had platted a crown of thorns, they put it upon his head, and a reed in his right hand: and they bowed the knee before him, and mocked him, saying, Hail, King of the Jews!</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">用荊棘編做冠冕，戴在他頭上，拿一根葦子放在他右手裏，跪在他面前，戲弄他，說：「恭喜，猶太人的王啊！」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse30">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka rou ni-madipægh tyni-æn, ni-ara nein ta angto, ka ni-v'llat tou voungo tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka rou ni-madipægh tyni-æn, ni-ara nein ta angto, ka ni-v'llat tou voungo tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Eft op hem gespogen bebbende namen ly den rietfiock efi floege op (ijn hooft.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And they spit upon him, and took the reed, and smote him on the head.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">又吐唾沫在他臉上，拿葦子打他的頭。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse31">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Jrou ka ni-bylla-vylla tyni-an, ni-æumi-en nein ta kouvar, ka ni-pæpæh koulamough nein ki nipammæmmien tyn, ka ni-æd-dnein tou pounavæværæh-eih ty-nien.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Jrou ka ni-bylla-vylla tyni-an, ni-æumi-en nein ta kouvar, ka ni-pæpæh koulamough nein ki nipammæmmien tyn, ka ni-æd-dnein tou pounavæværæh-eih ty-nien.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende doe sy hem besportet hadden dedensp hem den mantel af ende deden fijne kleederen aen ende eydden hem heenen om te krupcigen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And after that they had mocked him, they took the robe off from him, and put his own raiment on him, and led him away to crucify him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">戲弄完了，就給他脫了袍子，仍穿上他自己的衣服，帶他出去，要釘十字架。 （可15‧21－32；路23‧26－43；約19‧17－27）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse32">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Jrou ka tpæpænæh ni-kab-alei nein ta voual ka makkæ' ryre-nen, ka ti Simon ki nanang: ka ni yhgarei-en nein pa-aval ki-nava-væværæh tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Jrou ka tpæpænæh ni-kabalei nein ta voual ka makkæ' ryre-nen, ka ti Simon ki nanang: ka ni yhgarei-en nein pa-aval ki-nava-væværæh tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende uytgaende bonden sy eenen man ban Cyrenen met namen Simon : desen dwonghen n dat hy fyn Kyyyce droege. |</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And as they came out, they found a man of Cyrene, Simon by name: him they compelled to bear his cross.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們出來的時候，遇見一個古利奈人，名叫西門，就勉強他同去，好背着耶穌的十字架。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse33">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Jrou ka jerrou-'ato tou yttou-koua-an, ka pananang-en-ato Golgotha, ka siouwa jtou-koua-an ki toktok,</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Jrou ka jerrou-'ato tou yttou-koua-an, ka pananang-en-ato Golgotha, ka siouwa jtou-koua-an ki toktok,</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Endet gekomen zijnde tot deplaetse ghenaemt Golgotha welcke is geseght Hooft-scheel-partse </TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And when they were come unto a place called Golgotha, that is to say, a place of a skull,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">到了一個地方名叫各各他，意思就是「髑髏地」。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse34">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ni-pæyt tyni-æn ki mapyn-git ka ni hou-ræd ki parno: jrou ka ni kdiman-nen tyn, ni-ynnang myt.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ni-pæyt tyni-æn ki mapyn-git ka ni hou-ræd ki parno: jrou ka ni kdiman-nen tyn, ni-ynnang myt.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Gaben fp hem te drincken edick met galle gemenght : ende als hy [dien] gesmaeckt hadde en wilde hy niet drincken.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">They gave him vinegar to drink mingled with gall: and when he had tasted thereof, he would not drink.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">兵丁拿苦膽調和的酒給耶穌喝；他嘗了，就不肯喝。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse35">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Jrou ka ni-pounavævæ-ræh tyni-æn, ni-patatah nein ta ni-pæmmæmmien ki na pakkiau: alei ka pavut-auh ta na sou ki Tæ-ma-mattæi-tan, Ni-mæisal mata. tagh ta neni ki pammami-en-au, ka ni-pækk jau alei ki koula-mough-au.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Jrou ka ni-pounavævæ-ræh tyni-æn, ni-patatah nein ta ni-pæmmæmmien ki na pakkiau: alei ka pavut-auh ta na sou ki Tæ-ma-mattæi-tan, Ni-mæisal mata. tagh ta neni ki pammami-en-au, ka ni-pækk jau alei ki koula-mough-au.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doe sy nu hem gheRrupcight hadden berdeelden sy syne kleederen Het lot werpende : op dat berbult soude worden het gene gheleght is door den Propheet Sy hebben mijne kleederen onder haer berdeelt ende hebben het lot ober myne leedinge geworpen. .</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And they crucified him, and parted his garments, casting lots: that it might be fulfilled which was spoken by the prophet, They parted my garments among them, and upon my vesture did they cast lots.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們既將他釘在十字架上，就拈鬮分他的衣服，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse36">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka dou mieroung, ni-kmading tou hynna tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka dou mieroung, ni-kmading tou hynna tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende sy nede: sittende bewatrden hem aldaer.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And sitting down they watched him there;</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">又坐在那裏看守他。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse37">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-pou-koua-an nein pou-vavau ki voungo tyn ta na sa-soulat ki ni-alei-en patbarau tyni an, Ti atta ta ti Jejus ka Mei-sasou ka Sibavau ki soden.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-pou-koua-an nein pou-vavau ki voungo tyn ta na sa-soulat ki ni-alei-en patbarau tyni an, Ti atta ta ti Jejus ka Mei-sasou ka Sibavau ki soden.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Endespsteldenboben sijn hooft sijne beschuldin gesch:eben Dese is Jesus de ‚ Konmgh der Joden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And set up over his head his accusation written, THIS IS JESUS THE KING OF THE JEWS.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">在他頭以上安一個牌子，寫着他的罪狀，說：「這是猶太人的王耶穌。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse38">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Tou kidi k'anna ni-pou-lamen tyni-æn pou-navæværæh ta rarouha ki Tama-lpogh, tou ou wal ta sasat, tou u-'i ta sasat.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Tou kidi k'anna ni-pou-lamen tyni-æn pou-navæværæh ta rarouha ki Tama-lpogh, tou ou wal ta sasat, tou u-'i ta sasat.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Boe wierden met hem tweemoordenaers-ghekrmpcight cen ter rechter ende een ter flincker-[rijde.] _</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then were there two thieves crucified with him, one on the right hand, and another on the left.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">當時，有兩個強盜和他同釘十字架，一個在右邊，一個在左邊。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse39">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Rå neni ka hmarivat, ni-mako-avavagh tyni-æn bikbik ki voung  nein,</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Rå neni ka hmarivat, ni-mako-avavagh tyni-æn bikbik ki voung  nein,</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende die boorby ginghen lasterden hem schuddende hare hookden</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And they that passed by reviled him, wagging their heads,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">從那裏經過的人譏誚他，搖着頭，說：</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse40">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> K'ma, Ymhou ka kuhta-kow ki Kouva ki tatamd-den ki Alid, ka mei-ringei ki anna [mei-likough] tou toutourou ki wæi, nda ma'au-mado hmamia ym-hou-an. Heiro Alak kow ki Alid, mou-rarim-mâ ki navæværæh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> K'ma, Ymhou ka kuhta-kow ki Kouva ki tatamd-den ki Alid, ka mei-ringei ki anna [mei-likough] tou toutourou ki wæi, nda ma'au-mado hmamia ym-hou-an. Heiro Alak kow ki Alid, mou-rarim-mâ ki navæværæh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende segghende Ghy die den Tempel afbreeckt ende in dry daghen opbouwt berlolt u selben. Indien ghy de SoneGodts zijt soo komt af ban t kmys.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And saying, Thou that destroyest the temple, and buildest it in three days, save thyself. If thou be the Son of God, come down from the cross.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">「你這拆毀聖殿、三日又建造起來的，可以救自己吧！你如果是上帝的兒子，就從十字架上下來吧！」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse41">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Mahkaulaula k'ma-hynna ta Si-bavau ka Tama-P'hik ki Mæ-kou-sasoulat, ki Mamoumou, ki Fariseen-appa, dou bylla-vylla, ni-k'ma ta neni,</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Mahkaulaula k'ma-hynna ta Si-bavau ka Tama-P'hik ki Mæ-kou-sasoulat, ki Mamoumou, ki Fariseen-appa, dou bylla-vylla, ni-k'ma ta neni,</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende defsghelijcks oock de Oberprielters inet de Schuft-geleerde ende Ouderlinghen ende Phariseen {bem} bespottende seyden </TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Likewise also the chief priests mocking him, with the scribes and elders, said,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">祭司長和文士並長老也是這樣戲弄他，說：</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse42">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Pani ki voual ta ni-hami-'an tyn-ra, assi ma'au-lpough ma-au-mado hmamia tyni-æn. Hei-rou Mei-sasou ka Si-bavau ta teni ki Isaäl, ndâ mou-rarim-mâ hnyn ta teni ki navæværæh, ka tna-msing-ah-kame tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Pani ki voual ta ni-hami-'an tyn-ra, assi ma'au-lpough ma-au-mado hmamia tyni-æn. Hei-rou Mei-sasou ka Si-bavau ta teni ki Isaäl, ndâ mou-rarim-mâ hnyn ta teni ki navæværæh, ka tna-msing-ah-kame tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Andere heeft hy berlost hy en kan hem-elben niet berlossen, Fndien hy de Koningh Jsraels is dat hy nu af-kome ban het kruys ende wp sullen hem gelooben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">He saved others; himself he cannot save. If he be the King of Israel, let him now come down from the cross, and we will believe him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">「他救了別人，不能救自己。他是以色列的王，現在可以從十字架上下來，我們就信他。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse43">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ni-mashut ki rÿh ki Alid: nda hamiauh tyn hnyn tyni-æn, heirou akou-moei tyni-æn ta teni. Kou ni-k'ma ta teni, Alak koh ki Alid ti jæu.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ni-mashut ki rÿh ki Alid: nda hamiauh tyn hnyn tyni-æn, heirou akou-moei tyni-æn ta teni. Kou ni-k'ma ta teni, Alak koh ki Alid ti jæu.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Hy heeftop Godt betrouwt : dat hy hem nu berlofe indien hy hem [wel] wil. Want hy heeft geseght Ack ben Godts Sone. -</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">He trusted in God; let him deliver him now, if he will have him: for he said, I am the Son of God.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他倚靠上帝，上帝若喜悅他，現在可以救他；因為他曾說：『我是上帝的兒子。』」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse44">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka teni ki atta ni-pau-na-ni tyni-æn ta Tamalpogh, ka ni-pou-lam-en-ato pounavæværæh tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka teni ki atta ni-pau-na-ni tyni-æn ta Tamalpogh, ka ni-pou-lam-en-ato pounavæværæh tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende t selbe berweten hem oock de moordenaers die met hem ghekrupcight waren.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">The thieves also, which were crucified with him, cast the same in his teeth.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那和他同釘的強盜也是這樣地譏誚他。 （可15‧33－41；路23‧44－49；約19‧28－30）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse45">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka na kidi ki ka annum ki tæ'lei ni-jerroua ta karimdum-man tou myhta tmouk ki Næi, tou kidi-appa ki kamamatouda ki tæ'lei.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka na kidi ki ka annum ki tæ'lei ni-jerroua ta karimdum-man tou myhta tmouk ki Næi, tou kidi-appa ki kamamatouda ki tæ'lei.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende ban de: sester upre aen wiert er duyfternise ober de geheele aerde tot de negende uyre toe.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Now from the sixth hour there was darkness over all the land unto the ninth hour.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">從午正到申初，遍地都黑暗了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse46">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka mahivat-ato ki kama-matouda ki tæ'lei, ni-makou-lang-ah ta ti Jesus ki yngau ka irang, k'ma, Eli, Eli, Lama-Sabaghthani, ka ynna-ahkoua-an-ei, Alid-au, Alid-au, kaumang ka ni-d'marang-kow pa-itou-sât jau-an?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka mahivat-ato ki kama-matouda ki tæ'lei, ni-makou-lang-ah ta ti Jesus ki yngau ka irang, k'ma, Eli, Eli, Lama-Sabaghthani, ka ynna-ahkoua-an-ei, Alid-au, Alid-au, kaumang ka ni-d'marang-kow pa-itou-sât jau-an?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende ontrent de negende upre riep Jesus met een moote ttemme feggende Eli, Eli, Lama Sabachthani,dat is Mijn Godt Mijn Godt waerom hebt ghy my berlaren,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And about the ninth hour Jesus cried with a loud voice, saying, Eli, Eli, lama sabachthani? that is to say, My God, my God, why hast thou forsaken me?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">約在申初，耶穌大聲喊着說：「以利！以利！拉馬撒巴各大尼？」就是說：「我的上帝！我的上帝！為甚麼離棄我？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse47">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka rarouma ka mitouhko hynna, rou illingh-en nein[ta atta,] ta ni-k'ma, Tmatæäm ti Elias-an ta ti atta.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka rarouma ka mitouhko hynna, rou illingh-en nein[ta atta,] ta ni-k'ma, Tmatæäm ti Elias-an ta ti atta.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende sommigheban die daer ftonden [sulcks)] hoorende leyden Dese roept Eliam,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Some of them that stood there, when they heard that, said, This man calleth for Elias.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">站在那裏的人，有的聽見就說：「這個人呼叫以利亞呢！」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse48">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka madys saat neini-æn ta ni-sioum mara ki na vadiou, ka mama ki pourout, ka rou ni-pou-t'moei-en tyn ki mapyngit, ti-mali-ryttoung mali-vyt ki na angto, ka ni-pæyt tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka madys saat neini-æn ta ni-sioum mara ki na vadiou, ka mama ki pourout, ka rou ni-pou-t'moei-en tyn ki mapyngit, ti-mali-ryttoung mali-vyt ki na angto, ka ni-pæyt tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende tesstondt een banhaerstoe-Jloopendenam een spongie ende [dic] met edick ghebult Hebbende tackstackse op eenen tietltock ende gaf hem te drincken.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And straightway one of them ran, and took a spunge, and filled it with vinegar, and put it on a reed, and gave him to drink.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">內中有一個人趕緊跑去，拿海絨蘸滿了醋，綁在葦子上，送給他喝。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse49">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ra ni-k'ma ta rarouma, Os'eito, k'ytt'ei-mytta, ma lava ka irou'ah ta ti Elias hmamia tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ra ni-k'ma ta rarouma, Os'eito, k'ytt'ei-mytta, ma lava ka irou'ah ta ti Elias hmamia tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Boch de andere sepden Houdt op laet ons sien of Elias komt om hem te berlossen,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">The rest said, Let be, let us see whether Elias will come to save him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">其餘的人說：「且等着，看以利亞來救他不來。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse50">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka dou mila mako-ligh ki yngau ka irang ta ti Jesus, ni myh-taraæuh ki hynnaua.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka dou mila mako-ligh ki yngau ka irang ta ti Jesus, ni myh-taraæuh ki hynnaua.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende Jesus wederom met een groote stemme roepende gaf den geeft.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus, when he had cried again with a loud voice, yielded up the ghost.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌又大聲喊叫，氣就斷了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse51">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka kyttei, ni-papouhdou-ha ta varit ka kouvar ki Kouva ki tatamd-den ki Alid, makka vavau tou kidi-appa ka tou rarim: kani-ninugh ta Nai, ka ni-muasas ta vahto.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka kyttei, ni-papouhdou-ha ta varit ka kouvar ki Kouva ki tatamd-den ki Alid, makka vavau tou kidi-appa ka tou rarim: kani-ninugh ta Nai, ka ni-muasas ta vahto.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende siet het Doorhanghfel des @Tempels scheurde in tween ban boben tot beneden: ende de aerde beefde ende de steenrotsen scheurden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And, behold, the veil of the temple was rent in twain from the top to the bottom; and the earth did quake, and the rocks rent;</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">忽然，殿裏的幔子從上到下裂為兩半，地也震動，磐石也崩裂，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse52">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-mouhtlægh ta rava-ravak, ka madagh ki vouel ki ma-d'lligh matiktik, ka ni-mei-rip, ta ni-pæ'æhpit-en-ato.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-mouhtlægh ta rava-ravak, ka madagh ki vouel ki ma-d'lligh matiktik, ka ni-mei-rip, ta ni-pæ'æhpit-en-ato.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende de graben wierden geopent ende bele lichamen der Heplighe dieontsiapen waren wierden opgheweckt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And the graves were opened; and many bodies of the saints which slept arose,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">墳墓也開了，已睡聖徒的身體多有起來的。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse53">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka rou ni-'tpæpænæh-hen nein makka-rbo ki ravaravak si äugh ki ni-patimææ'-æn [pa'æh-pit tyni-æn, ni-ierroua ta neni tou auma ka ni-pa-itou-nni tou ta-tamd-den ki Alid, ka ni-moupa-nah tou æmæh ki mabatoung [ki voual.]</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka rou ni-'tpæpænæh-hen nein makka-rbo ki ravaravak si äugh ki ni-patimææ'-æn [pa'æh-pit tyni-æn, ni-ierroua ta neni tou auma ka ni-pa-itou-nni tou ta-tamd-den ki Alid, ka ni-moupa-nah tou æmæh ki mabatoung [ki voual.]</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende uyt de graben uptgegaen zijnde nae [ijne opstandinghe quamen sy in de heplighe stadt ende zijn belen berschenen,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And came out of the graves after his resurrection, and went into the holy city, and appeared unto many.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">到耶穌復活以後，他們從墳墓裏出來，進了聖城，向許多人顯現。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse54">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ Meisasou ki sat ka'æu-toughan, neni-appa ka kmasal ty-ni-æn kmading ti Jesus-an, rou kyttan nein ta nynnugh, kama-mang-appa ka ni-pâmt-en, ouhang ni-mæhtakout, k'ma, Missing Alak ki Alid ta ti anna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ Meisasou ki sat ka'æu-toughan, neni-appa ka kmasal ty-ni-æn kmading ti Jesus-an, rou kyttan nein ta nynnugh, kama-mang-appa ka ni-pâmt-en, ouhang ni-mæhtakout, k'ma, Missing Alak ki Alid ta ti anna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende de Hooft-man ober hondert ende die mec hem Jelum bewaerden fiende de aerdtbebinghe ende de dingen die geschiet waren wierden seer bebreest seggende 1Vaerlick dese was Gods &amp;ont,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Now when the centurion, and they that were with him, watching Jesus, saw the earthquake, and those things that were done, they feared greatly, saying, Truly this was the Son of God.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">百夫長和一同看守耶穌的人看見地震並所經歷的事，就極其害怕，說：「這真是上帝的兒子了！」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse55">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-æ'ia-koua-hynna ta jnejna ka mabatoung, matau-tau-agh mararau, ka ni-siäugh ti Jesus-an makka Galileä, alei ka pileilei-eih nein tyni-cn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-æ'ia-koua-hynna ta jnejna ka mabatoung, matau-tau-agh mararau, ka ni-siäugh ti Jesus-an makka Galileä, alei ka pileilei-eih nein tyni-cn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende AlVae? waren bele. bronwen ban berre aenfchouwende die Jelum gebolght waren ban Galilea om hem te dienen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And many women were there beholding afar off, which followed Jesus from Galilee, ministering unto him:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">有好些婦女在那裏，遠遠地觀看；她們是從加利利跟隨耶穌來服事他的。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse56">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka æ'ia-tamæuh neini-æn ta ti Maria Magdalena, ta ti Maria ka raren'an ti Jakobus, ti Joses-appa, ki raren'an-appa ki alalak ka papæræh tipa-bebedeus.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka æ'ia-tamæuh neini-æn ta ti Maria Magdalena, ta ti Maria ka raren'an ti Jakobus, ti Joses-appa, ki raren'an-appa ki alalak ka papæræh tipa-bebedeus.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Onder dewelcke was Maria Magdalena ende Maria de Moeder Jacobi nide Jole ende de Moeder der onen Sebedei.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Among which was Mary Magdalene, and Mary the mother of James and Joses, and the mother of Zebedees children.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">內中有抹大拉的馬利亞，又有雅各和約西的母親馬利亞，並有西庇太兩個兒子的母親。 （可15‧42－47；路23‧50－56；約19‧38－42）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse57">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Jrou ka madoung-ato ni-iroua ta voual ka mavangei ka makka Arimathea, ka ti Joses ki nanang, ka Pahtatæutauughan-appa ti Jesus.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Jrou ka madoung-ato ni-iroua ta voual ka mavangei ka makka Arimathea, ka ti Joses ki nanang, ka Pahtatæutauughan-appa ti Jesus.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende als het abondr, ibe Dep Jesu was.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">When the even was come, there came a rich man of Arimathaea, named Joseph, who also himself was Jesus' disciple:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">到了晚上，有一個財主，名叫約瑟，是亞利馬太來的，他也是耶穌的門徒。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse58">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Teni ta ni-mou-koua ti Pilatus-an, ka ni-toumimi-en tyn ta vouel ti Jesus. Anna ta ni-ma-dingi ta ti Pilatus ka pa ä-likoug-hei ta voual.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Teni ta ni-mou-koua ti Pilatus-an, ka ni-toumimi-en tyn ta vouel ti Jesus. Anna ta ni-ma-dingi ta ti Pilatus ka pa ä-likoug-hei ta voual.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Dese quam tot Pilamn. ende brgeerde he het liJesu. Doe bebal Pitatus dat [hem] het lichaem gegeben soude worden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">He went to Pilate, and begged the body of Jesus. Then Pilate commanded the body to be delivered.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">這人去見彼拉多，求耶穌的身體；彼拉多就吩咐給他。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse59">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Jrou ka aran ti Joses ta vouel, ni-toupou tyn ta anna ki äit ka makouptigh ka palyhpigh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Jrou ka aran ti Joses ta vouel, ni-toupou tyn ta anna ki äit ka makouptigh ka palyhpigh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende Joseph het lichaemnemende wandt het felbe in een upber fijn lijnwaet.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And when Joseph had taken the body, he wrapped it in a clean linen cloth,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">約瑟取了身體，用乾淨細麻布裹好，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse60">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-atta-koua-an tyn ta anna tou ravak tyn ka va'æu, ka ni-kou-tæ-an tyn tou vahto: jrou ka ni-ryhkyllen tyn ta vahto ka irang tou ngatas ki ravak, ni-d'ma-rang ta teni.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-atta-koua-an tyn ta anna tou ravak tyn ka va'æu, ka ni-kou-tæ-an tyn tou vahto: jrou ka ni-ryhkyllen tyn ta vahto ka irang tou ngatas ki ravak, ni-d'ma-rang ta teni.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende leyde dat in sijn nieuw graf t welck hy in een steenrotre uptgehouwen adde: ende eenen grooten een [tegen] de deure deg grafs ghewentelt hebbende gingh hy wech.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And laid it in his own new tomb, which he had hewn out in the rock: and he rolled a great stone to the door of the sepulchre, and departed.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">安放在自己的新墳墓裏，就是他鑿在磐石裏的。他又把大石頭滾到墓門口，就去了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse61">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-æ'ia-koua-hynna ta ti Maria Magdalena, ti Maria-appa ka saät, ka mieroung ta neni tou dimit ki ravak.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-æ'ia-koua-hynna ta ti Maria Magdalena, ti Maria-appa ka saät, ka mieroung ta neni tou dimit ki ravak.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende aldaer was Maria Magdalena ende de andere Maria sierende tegen ober het graf.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And there was Mary Magdalene, and the other Mary, sitting over against the sepulchre.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">有抹大拉的馬利亞和那個馬利亞在那裏，對着墳墓坐着。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse62">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ tou sasat-appa kiwa'i, ka siäugh ki sitatanang-en, ni mæuisal ta Sibavau ka Tama-Phik ki Fariseen-appa ti Pilatus-an, sou ta</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ tou sasat-appa kiwa'i, ka siäugh ki sitatanang-en, ni mæuisal ta Sibavau ka Tama-Phik ki Fariseen-appa ti Pilatus-an, sou ta</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Des anderen daeghs nu welcke is nae de boorbereydinghe bergaderden de Oberpiielters ende de Phariseen tot Pitatum </TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Now the next day, that followed the day of the preparation, the chief priests and Pharisees came together unto Pilate,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">次日，就是預備日的第二天，祭司長和法利賽人聚集來見彼拉多，說：</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse63">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Kma, Meirang, hibalei 'nian ka ni-mattæ'i-k'ma hynna ki Tama-patau-rahei ki anna ka mauagh-appa ta teni, æhpit-aumau siäugh ki toutouro ki wæ'i.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Kma, Meirang, hibalei 'nian ka ni-mattæ'i-k'ma hynna ki Tama-patau-rahei ki anna ka mauagh-appa ta teni, æhpit-aumau siäugh ki toutouro ki wæ'i.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Segghende Heere wp 3yn indachtigh dat dese Derleyde noch lebende gheseght heeft Nae drie dagen falick opstaen,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Saying, Sir, we remember that that deceiver said, while he was yet alive, After three days I will rise again.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">「大人，我們記得那誘惑人的還活着的時候曾說：『三日後我要復活。』</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse64">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Padingi-au hnyn papææu saoun kmading ta ravak tou kidi ki katatouro ki wæ'i, alei ka assi lava ierrou-'æh ta Pahtatæutaung-han tyn dou euvanan haouzoung tyni-æn, ka mattæ'i-k'ma-ah-hyn-na ki ta'u, Nipatimææ-æn [pa æhpit] ki ni-kapateian: ka kom ma-hynna masaoun-al-ato mate ta taurahei-en ka siæugh ki ni-sion ro-ato.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Padingi-au hnyn papææu saoun kmading ta ravak tou kidi ki katatouro ki wæ'i, alei ka assi lava ierrou-'æh ta Pahtatæutaung-han tyn dou euvanan haouzoung tyni-æn, ka mattæ'i-k'ma-ah-hyn-na ki ta'u, Nipatimææ-æn [pa æhpit] ki ni-kapateian: ka kom ma-hynna masaoun-al-ato mate ta taurahei-en ka siæugh ki ni-sion ro-ato.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Bebeelt dan dat het graf berickere worde tor op den derden dagh toe op dat sjne Dilcipelen misschien niet en komen bp nachte ende ftelen hem ende eggeri tot den bolcke hy is opgestaenban den dooden : ende [foo] sal de laette dwalinge ergher zijn als de cerlte.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Command therefore that the sepulchre be made sure until the third day, lest his disciples come by night, and steal him away, and say unto the people, He is risen from the dead: so the last error shall be worse than the first.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">因此，請吩咐人將墳墓把守妥當，直到第三日，恐怕他的門徒來，把他偷了去，就告訴百姓說：『他從死裏復活了。』這樣，那後來的迷惑比先前的更利害了！」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse65">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ ni-k'ma neini-en ta ti Pilatus, Akou-mea-kamou ki kma kading, ou-koua-au, papau-saoun-auto ki anna mama ki kava-næ-noumi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ ni-k'ma neini-en ta ti Pilatus, Akou-mea-kamou ki kma kading, ou-koua-au, papau-saoun-auto ki anna mama ki kava-næ-noumi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende Pilatus sepde tot hen-lieden Ghp hebt eene wacht gaet henen bersekert het gheliick ghy het besstaet.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Pilate said unto them, Ye have a watch: go your way, make it as sure as ye can.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">彼拉多說：「你們有看守的兵，去吧！盡你們所能的把守妥當。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse66">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Jrou ka d'marang ta neni, ni-papæu-saoun-nen nein ki kma kading ta ravak, rou ni-pou-ka-ha'n nein pou-tapoei-ou pou-kidi ta vahto. Kararouha kytti-an 'ab ki koyghpa kilbæb ki soulat.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Jrou ka d'marang ta neni, ni-papæu-saoun-nen nein ki kma kading ta ravak, rou ni-pou-ka-ha'n nein pou-tapoei-ou pou-kidi ta vahto. Kararouha kytti-an 'ab ki koyghpa kilbæb ki soulat.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende sphenen gaende bessckeyden t graf met de wacht den fteen ber3egett hebbende,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">So they went, and made the sepulchre sure, sealing the stone, and setting a watch.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們就帶着看守的兵同去，封了石頭，將墳墓把守妥當。</TRANSL>
    </S>
</TEXT>