<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEXT id="Siraya_Dutch_Matthew_Chapter26" xml:lang="fos" source="Siraya Bible, Matthew gospel" copyright="public domain" citation="Gravius, Daniël. 1661. Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa. Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang. Amsterdam: Michiel Hartogh." BibTeX_citation="@book{Gravius1661,&#10;  author    = {Gravius, Daniël},&#10;  year      = {1661},&#10;  title     = {Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa},&#10;  note      = {Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang},&#10;  address   = {Amsterdam},&#10;  publisher = {Michiel Hartogh}&#10;}" dialect="Siraya">
    <S id="verse1">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> KA ni-pæmting, dou ni-pat-tæi-kahan ti Jesus mattæ'i-simoulymmou ki sou k'atta, ka ni-k'ma ki Pahtatæutæuughan tyn,</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> KA ni-pæmting, dou ni-pat-tæi-kahan ti Jesus mattæ'i-simoulymmou ki sou k'atta, ka ni-k'ma ki Pahtatæutæuughan tyn,</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende het is geschiet als Jesus alle dese woorden ghe-eyndight hadde dat hy tot lijne Ditcipelen sepde </TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And it came to pass, when Jesus had finished all these sayings, he said unto his disciples,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說完了這一切的話，就對門徒說：</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse2">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Kavana'noumi ka rorouha-appa ki wæ'i mou-vatoug-ah ki halida'æu-an, ka pæ'ǣ-tounnoun eih ta Alak ki ka'æuloung tou pouna-væværæh-eih tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Kavana'noumi ka rorouha-appa ki wæ'i mou-vatoug-ah ki halida'æu-an, ka pæ'ǣ-tounnoun eih ta Alak ki ka'æuloung tou pouna-væværæh-eih tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ghy weet dat nae twee</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Ye know that after two days is the feast of the passover, and the Son of man is betrayed to be crucified.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">「你們知道，過兩天是逾越節，人子將要被交給人，釘在十字架上。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse3">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta ni-mæu'isal ta Si. bavau ka Tama-phik, ta makou-sasoulat, ki mamoumou-appa ki taou, tou las ki Dadyllo-ka Siba-vau, ka ti Kajasas ta nanang tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta ni-mæu'isal ta Si. bavau ka Tama-phik, ta makou-sasoulat, ki mamoumou-appa ki taou, tou las ki Dadyllo-ka Sibavau, ka ti Kajasas ta nanang tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doe bergaderden de Ober Piiesters eei de Schaiftgegeleerde ende de Ouderlingen des Volcks inde sale des Hoogen-Piielters die genaemt was Cajaphas.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then assembled together the chief priests, and the scribes, and the elders of the people, unto the palace of the high priest, who was called Caiaphas,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那時，祭司長和民間的長老聚集在大祭司稱為該亞法的院裏。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse4">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-kmi-ym ki sou, ka touroung-auh nein ki sivanavan'an ta ti Jesus, ka paka-pætei-aul-appa ta teni.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-kmi-ym ki sou, ka touroung-auh nein ki sivanavan'an ta ti Jesus, ka paka-pætei-aul-appa ta teni.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende beraedtslaeghden c samen dat sy Jefum met liftigheydt bangen ende dooden ouden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And consulted that they might take Jesus by subtilty, and kill him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">大家商議要用詭計拿住耶穌，殺他，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse5">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-k'ma ta neni: Assi tou ou-vavatoug-an, alei ka aousi-ah ki kavaroutti-vut'tan ki ta'u.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-k'ma ta neni: Assi tou ou-vavatoug-an, alei ka aousi-ah ki kavaroutti-vut'tan ki ta'u.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doch iy leyden : Niet in het. Feelt op datter geen oprotr en worde onde? het</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But they said, Not on the feast day, lest there be an uproar among the people.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">只是說：「當節的日子不可，恐怕民間生亂。」 （可14‧3－9；約12‧1－8）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse6">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka rou æia-koua ta ti Jesus tou Bethanien tou tallagh ti Simon ka outæum-in-ato [ki Leproos:]</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka rou æia-koua ta ti Jesus tou Bethanien tou tallagh ti Simon ka outæum-in-ato [ki Leproos:]</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Als nu Jesus te Bethanien was ten huyse Simonis des Melaetschen:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Now when Jesus was in Bethany, in the house of Simon the leper,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌在伯大尼長大痲瘋的西門家裏，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse7">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ni-ierroua tyni-æn ta jna ka mei-koua ki vahto ka poule ka roukoul, ka akou-rapol ka ouhang ki angal, ka ni-roudo tyn ta anna massi-halap ki voungo tyn tou ira-rong-en tyn tou avokkan.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ni-ierroua tyni-æn ta jna ka mei-koua ki vahto ka poule ka roukoul, ka akou-rapol ka ouhang ki angal, ka ni-roudo tyn ta anna massi-halap ki voungo tyn tou ira-rong-en tyn tou avokkan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Quam tot Hem een brouwe hebbende een alabaste:-flefsche mec seer kostelicke salbe ende gootse upt op lijn hooft daer hy aen [rafel} sat. _</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">There came unto him a woman having an alabaster box of very precious ointment, and poured it on his head, as he sat at meat.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">有一個女人拿着一玉瓶極貴的香膏來，趁耶穌坐席的時候，澆在他的頭上。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse8">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Jrou ka kak'ytt'an ta anna ki Pahtatæutæuughan tyn, ouhang vi-mæiddingit ta neni, koun, Kæu-mang ta atta-ænno-an k'atta?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Jrou ka kak'ytt'an ta anna ki Pahtatæutæuughan tyn, ouhang vi-mæiddingit ta neni, koun, Kæu-mang ta atta-ænno-an k'atta?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende shne Discipelen [dat] fiende namen het seer qualick seggende Waer toe dit belies 4</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But when his disciples saw it, they had indignation, saying, To what purpose is this waste?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">門徒看見就很不喜悅，說：「何用這樣的枉費呢！</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse9">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ynna patou-ilpough pæ-peila tou ouhang ki angal ta rah-poul katta, papha-an-ei ta than tyn ki tæ'u ka malymmouk.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ynna patou-ilpough pæ-peila tou ouhang ki angal ta rah-poul katta, papha-an-ei ta than tyn ki tæ'u ka malymmouk.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Wantdese salbe hadde konnen dier berkocht ende depenningen den Armen gegeben worden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">For this ointment might have been sold for much, and given to the poor.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">這香膏可以賣許多錢，賙濟窮人。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse10">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ra tou oumhgan ti Jesus [ta atta] ni-k'ma neini-æn, Ka'u-mang ka paka-himkou-'noumi ta jna k'atta? Ka mariang ta na ryng-ei tyn jau-an-da.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ra tou oumhgan ti Jesus [ta atta] ni-k'ma neini-æn, Ka'u-mang ka paka-himkou-'noumi ta jna k'atta? Ka mariang ta na ryng-ei tyn jau-an-da.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Maer Jesus [yolor] besstaende seyde tot haer Waerom dott ghy dese brouwe moeyte aen + Want n heefc een goet werck aen mp gewrocht.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">When Jesus understood it, he said unto them, Why trouble ye the woman? for she hath wrought a good work upon me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌看出他們的意思，就說：「為甚麼難為這女人呢？她在我身上做的是一件美事。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse11">
        <FORM kindOf="original">11 Ka myhkakona akou meæ'h-kamou ki ma-lymmouk aiakous ymoumi-æn, râ aou-si-ah-kamou myhkakoua jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">11 Ka myhkakona akou meæ'h-kamou ki ma-lymmouk aiakous ymoumi-æn, râ aou-si-ah-kamou myhkakoua jau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Want de Nrme hebt ghp altijdt metu matr mp en hebt ghy niet altijdt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">For ye have the poor always with you; but me ye have not always.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">因為常有窮人和你們同在；只是你們不常有我。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse12">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Nda irou ka ni-roudo tyn ta rahpoul k'atta tou vouelau, ni-pamt-en tyn ta anna [tou sitan-in] ki ravak-ei jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Nda irou ka ni-roudo tyn ta rahpoul k'atta tou vouelau, ni-pamt-en tyn ta anna [tou sitan-in] ki ravak-ei jau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">want a sy dese salbe op myn lichaem gegoten heefc soo heeft sy Het gedaen tot [een boorbereydinge ban] myne begrabenisse</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">For in that she hath poured this ointment on my body, she did it for my burial.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">她將這香膏澆在我身上是為我安葬做的。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse13">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Missing koun-nau-kamon, Toumang ka pattasasou-eih ta Ha gnau katta ka mariang tou ymmid ki Næi, pasousou-eil-appa hynna ta mamang ka na ryngei tyn tou hibava-lei-en tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Missing koun-nau-kamon, Toumang ka pattasasou-eih ta Ha gnau katta ka mariang tou ymmid ki Næi, pasousou-eil-appa hynna ta mamang ka na ryngei tyn tou hibava-lei-en tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doorwaer segge ick u Alwaer dit Euangelinm gepredickt sal worden in de geheele werelt [ daer ] sal oock tot harer gedachtenisse gesp:oken worden ban t gene sy gedaen heeft.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Verily I say unto you, Wheresoever this gospel shall be preached in the whole world, there shall also this, that this woman hath done, be told for a memorial of her.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我實在告訴你們，普天之下，無論在甚麼地方傳這福音，也要述說這女人所行的，作個紀念。」 （可14‧10－11；路22‧3－6）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse14">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Tou kidi k'anna ni-d'ma-rang ta saät ki sat kytti-æn 'æb ki rouha k'anna, ka ti Judas Iska-rioth ta nanang tyn, ka ni-mou-koua ki Si-bavau ka Tama-p'hik,</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Tou kidi k'anna ni-d'ma-rang ta saät ki sat kytti-æn 'æb ki rouha k'anna, ka ti Judas Iska-rioth ta nanang tyn, ka ni-mou-koua ki Si-bavau ka Tama-p'hik,</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doe gingheen ban de twaelbe genaemt Judas Atcarioth tot de Oberpirieliess </TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then one of the twelve, called Judas Iscariot, went unto the chief priests,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">當下，十二門徒裏有一個稱為加略人猶大的，去見祭司長，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse15">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> K'ma, Mang ta p'hei-anei-moumi jæu-an, ka pa æ-tounnoun-eimau tyni-æn ymoumi-æn ka ni-si-kidi-en nein tyni-æn tourou kytti-æn ki malyttouk.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> K'ma, Mang ta p'hei-anei-moumi jæu-an, ka pa æ-tounnoun-eimau tyni-æn ymoumi-æn ka ni-si-kidi-en nein tyni-æn tourou kytti-æn ki malyttouk.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Endesepde Wat wilt ghy my geben ende ick sal hemu oberleberen + Ende sp hebben Hem toegeleght Der: tigh silbere [ penningen. ]</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And said unto them, What will ye give me, and I will deliver him unto you? And they covenanted with him for thirty pieces of silver.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">說： 「我把他交給你們，你們願意給我多少錢？」他們就給了他三十塊錢。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse16">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka na kidi k'anna ni-han en tyn ta kidi ka mariang, ka mannono ka pa ä-tounnoun-an-eih tyn tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka na kidi k'anna ni-han en tyn ta kidi ka mariang, ka mannono ka pa ä-tounnoun-an-eih tyn tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende ban doen af focht hy gelegentheyt op dat hy hem oberleberen mochte.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And from that time he sought opportunity to betray him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">從那時候，他就找機會要把耶穌交給他們。 （可14‧12－21；路22‧7－14，21－23；約13‧21－30）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse17">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka tou naunamou ki wæ'i ka assi ni-pei-apyng-it [ta pæul] ni-iroua ta Pahtatautauughan ti Jesus, ka ni-koun nein teni-æn, Toumang ta kamoei-en-hou kata-nang-au-mian ymhouan pa-kan ki joukko ki Hæli-da'æu-en?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka tou naunamou ki wæ'i ka assi ni-pei-apyng-it [ta pæul] ni-iroua ta Pahtatautauughan ti Jesus, ka ni-koun nein teni-æn, Toumang ta kamoei-en-hou kata-nang-au-mian ymhouan pa-kan ki joukko ki Hæli-da'æu-en?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende op den certen [dagh] der onghehebelde f brooden, } quamen de Dittipclen tot Jelum seggende tot hem Waer wilt ghy dat — wy wy u thereyden het Pascha te eten</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Now the first day of the feast of unleavened bread the disciples came to Jesus, saying unto him, Where wilt thou that we prepare for thee to eat the passover?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">除酵節的第一天，門徒來問耶穌說：「你吃逾越節的筵席，要我們在哪裏給你預備？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse18">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-k'ma ta teni, Ou-koua-au tou æuma k'anna ti anno-an, ka bana tyni-æn, Na sou ki Mahtatæutæuuh, tou touk ta ki di-au, k-koua-ah-koh kman ym-hou-an [ki joukko] ki Hali-da-au-en lam ki Pahtatæutzuugh en-au.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-k'ma ta teni, Ou-koua-au tou æuma k'anna ti anno-an, ka bana tyni-æn, Na sou ki Mahtatæutæuuh, tou touk ta ki di-au, k-koua-ah-koh kman ym-hou-an [ki joukko] ki Hali-da-au-en lam ki Pahtatæutzuugh en-au.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende p sepde Gaet henen in de adt tot sulck tenen ende segget hem Be Meefter leght mijnen tijdt is naby ick sal bp u het Pascha houden met mijne Dilcipelen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And he said, Go into the city to such a man, and say unto him, The Master saith, My time is at hand; I will keep the passover at thy house with my disciples.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：「你們進城去，到某人那裏，對他說：『夫子說：我的時候快到了，我與門徒要在你家裏守逾越節。』」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse19">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-mei-amut ta Pahta-tæutæuugh-an, mama ki na si-a. tæutæuugh ti Jesus neini-æn, ka ni-patæu-tan nein [ta joukko] ki Hali-daæu-en.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-mei-amut ta Pahta-tæutæuugh-an, mama ki na si-a. tæutæuugh ti Jesus neini-æn, ka ni-patæu-tan nein [ta joukko] ki Hali-daæu-en.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende de Discipelen deden gheliick Jesus haer bebolen hadde ende berepdden het Pascha.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And the disciples did as Jesus had appointed them; and they made ready the passover.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">門徒遵着耶穌所吩咐的就去預備了逾越節的筵席。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse20">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Jrou ka mad-oung-ato ni-k-lam meirrong ki sat kytti-æn 'æb ki rouha.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Jrou ka mad-oung-ato ni-k-lam meirrong ki sat kytti-æn 'æb ki rouha.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende als het abondt geworden was fat hy am met de twaelbe.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Now when the even was come, he sat down with the twelve.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">到了晚上，耶穌和十二個門徒坐席。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse21">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Jrou ka kannin nein, anna ta ni k'ma ta teni, Missing koun-nau-kamou, ka saät ymoumi-æn ta si-vanavana-ah jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Jrou ka kannin nein, anna ta ni k'ma ta teni, Missing koun-nau-kamou, ka saät ymoumi-æn ta si-vanavana-ah jau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende doe sy aten [eyde hy Doorwaer ick seggeu Dat een ban u my sal berraen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And as they did eat, he said, Verily I say unto you, that one of you shall betray me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">正吃的時候，耶穌說：「我實在告訴你們，你們中間有一個人要賣我了。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse22">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka rou ou-hang ta neni mivavoulas, ni-mattæi-naunamou ta meihbouavou-al neini-æn mat-tæ'i-kmahynna tyni-æn, Ti jau kaua Meirang?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka rou ou-hang ta neni mivavoulas, ni-mattæi-naunamou ta meihbouavou-al neini-æn mat-tæ'i-kmahynna tyni-æn, Ti jau kaua Meirang?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende sy seer bedroeft geworden zijnde begonnen een pegelick ban hae: tot em re seggen Ben ick het</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And they were exceeding sorrowful, and began every one of them to say unto him, Lord, is it I?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們就甚憂愁，一個一個地問他說：「主，是我嗎？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse23">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta teni, kma, Teni ka smilam jau-an dmæuk ki rima tyn tou tangia, teni ta si-vanavana-ah jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta teni, kma, Teni ka smilam jau-an dmæuk ki rima tyn tou tangia, teni ta si-vanavana-ah jau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende hy antwoordende sepde Die de hantmetmp mn de sthotel m doopt die sal mp berraden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And he answered and said, He that dippeth his hand with me in the dish, the same shall betray me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌回答說：「同我蘸手在盤子裏的，就是他要賣我。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse24">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ouma-ato ka d'marang ta Alak ki ka'æuloung mama ki nisoulat-en-ato tyni-æn, râ ænnaih ki ta'u k'anna ka sivanavana-ah ki Alak ki ka'æuloung, ynna ma-riang tyni-æn, rou assi ni-pei-alak-kin ta ka auloung kanna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ouma-ato ka d'marang ta Alak ki ka'æuloung mama ki nisoulat-en-ato tyni-æn, râ ænnaih ki ta'u k'anna ka sivanavana-ah ki Alak ki ka'æuloung, ynna ma-riang tyni-æn, rou assi ni-pei-alak-kin ta ka auloung kanna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">De Sone des Menfchen gaet wel henen gelijck ban hem gelchreben is maer wee dien mentche door wileKen be Sone des Menschen berraden wort het ware hem ott so die mensche niet geborenen hadde geweest, |</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">The Son of man goeth as it is written of him: but woe unto that man by whom the Son of man is betrayed! it had been good for that man if he had not been born.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">人子必要去世，正如經上指着他所寫的；但賣人子的人有禍了！那人不生在世上倒好。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse25">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Katou Judas ka si-vanavana tyni-æn ta ni-mattæ'i-v'lli, k'ma, Ti jau kana Rabbi? Ni-k'ma ta teni tyni-æn, Pattæ'i-rouk-en-ato-'mhou.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Katou Judas ka si-vanavana tyni-æn ta ni-mattæ'i-v'lli, k'ma, Ti jau kana Rabbi? Ni-k'ma ta teni tyni-æn, Pattæ'i-rouk-en-ato-'mhou.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende Judas die hem berriedt antwoordde ende lepde Ben ick t Kabbis Hy leyde tot hem Ghy hebt het gifegh.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then Judas, which betrayed him, answered and said, Master, is it I? He said unto him, Thou hast said.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">賣耶穌的猶大問他說：「拉比，是我嗎？」耶穌說：「你說的是。」 （可14‧22－26；路22‧15－20；林前11‧23－25）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse26">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Jrou ka mei-kakan ta neni, ni-mmeugh ta ti Jesus ki paoul, ka rou ni-makou-v'lli makou Alildd, ni-pihpi tyn, ka ni-phan tyn ki Pahtateuteung-han tyn ta atta, ka ni-kma, Arau, kan-nau, atta ta voual-au.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Jrou ka mei-kakan ta neni, ni-mmeugh ta ti Jesus ki paoul, ka rou ni-makou-v'lli makou Alildd, ni-pihpi tyn, ka ni-phan tyn ki Pahtateuteung-han tyn ta atta, ka ni-kma, Arau, kan-nau, atta ta voual-au.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende als sy aten nam Jesus het broodt ende gheregent hebbende brack hy het ende gaf het den Disc1pelen ende sepde Nemet etet dat is mijn Lichaem.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And as they were eating, Jesus took bread, and blessed it, and brake it, and gave it to the disciples, and said, Take, eat; this is my body.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們吃的時候，耶穌拿起餅來，祝福，就擘開，遞給門徒，說：「你們拿着吃，這是我的身體」；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse27">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka rou ni-eugh tyn ta hæu-ugh ka äyht-en, ka rou ni-pako. vili-tyn mako-Alilid, ni-p'hen tyn neini-æn ta atta, k'ma, Houh-tmouk-au moumi tou [hæuugh ki] atta.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka rou ni-eugh tyn ta hæu-ugh ka äyht-en, ka rou ni-pako. vili-tyn mako-Alilid, ni-p'hen tyn neini-æn ta atta, k'ma, Houh-tmouk-au moumi tou [hæuugh ki] atta.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende hy nam den Dtiinckbeker ende ghedanckt hebbende gaf hae: [dien,] segghende Drinckt alle daer uyt. _</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And he took the cup, and gave thanks, and gave it to them, saying, Drink ye all of it;</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">又拿起杯來，祝謝了，遞給他們，說：「你們都喝這個；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse28">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka atta ta 'æmægh-au, [ta amagh] ki Si-kavag-hen ka va'æu, ka tiri-auh alei ki mabatoung tou atta-nynno-an ki varau.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka atta ta 'æmægh-au, [ta amagh] ki Si-kavag-hen ka va'æu, ka tiri-auh alei ki mabatoung tou atta-nynno-an ki varau.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Want dat is mjn bloedt het[bloedt] des Nieuwen Teltaments het welck boor bele bergoten wordt tot bergebinge der sonden,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">For this is my blood of the new testament, which is shed for many for the remission of sins.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">因為這是我立約的血，為多人流出來，使罪得赦。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse29">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka pasousou-en-au-kamou, ka assimau yht-auh na kidi hnyn ki na voua k'atta ki ngara ki ka-ræumætæh, tou kidi-appa ki wa'i kanna, rou hou-baau-au-mau myt ta atta hmou-lam ymou-mi-en tou pei-sasou-an ki Rara-man-au.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka pasousou-en-au-kamou, ka assimau yht-auh na kidi hnyn ki na voua k'atta ki ngara ki ka-ræumætæh, tou kidi-appa ki wa'i kanna, rou hou-baau-au-mau myt ta atta hmou-lam ymou-mi-en tou pei-sasou-an ki Rara-man-au.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Endeickseggeu dat ick ban nu aen niet en sal drincken ban dese beucht des wijnltocks rot op dien dagh wanneer ick met u deselbe nieuw sal drincken n t honinckriick mijus</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But I say unto you, I will not drink henceforth of this fruit of the vine, until that day when I drink it new with you in my Father's kingdom.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">但我告訴你們，從今以後，我不再喝這葡萄汁，直到我在我父的國裏同你們喝新的那日子。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse30">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Jrou ka taka-kahan nein ta taka-loulough-an, ni-t'papanah ta neni moukoua tou voukkyn ka makka-vavoua ki akou-imagh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Jrou ka taka-kahan nein ta taka-loulough-an, ni-t'papanah ta neni moukoua tou voukkyn ka makka-vavoua ki akou-imagh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Endeals sy den Loffangh gesongen hadden ging sy uyt na den Olyfbergh.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And when they had sung an hymn, they went out into the mount of Olives.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們唱了詩，就出來往橄欖山去。 （可14‧27－31；路22‧31－34；約13‧36－38）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse31">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus neini-æn, Paka-ymdau-kamou paka-varau ki euvan k'atta: Alei ka ni-sasoulat-in, Ep'yd-aumau ta Souajam, ka papæiävoak-auh ta joukko ki jouagh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus neini-æn, Paka-ymdau-kamou paka-varau ki euvan k'atta: Alei ka ni-sasoulat-in, Ep'yd-aumau ta Souajam, ka papæiävoak-auh ta joukko ki jouagh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Boe sepde Jesus tot Haer Ghy sult alle am mp ge-ergert worden in desen nacht: Want dae? is geschreben Ick (al de Herde: llaen ende de schapen de: kudde fullen berstropt worden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then saith Jesus unto them, All ye shall be offended because of me this night: for it is written, I will smite the shepherd, and the sheep of the flock shall be scattered abroad.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那時，耶穌對他們說：「今夜，你們為我的緣故都要跌倒。因為經上記着說：</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse32">
        <FORM kindOf="original">. Jrou ka hkaha-al-ato-koh hpit, tourourou-ah-koh ymou mi-æn mou-koua tou Galileen.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">. Jrou ka hkaha-al-ato-koh hpit, tourourou-ah-koh ymou mi-æn mou-koua tou Galileen.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Waet nae dat ick sal opgheltaen zijn sal ick u boorgaen na Galiler</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But after I am risen again, I will go before you into Galilee.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">但我復活以後，要在你們以先往加利利去。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse33">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta ti Pe-trus k'ma tyni-æn, Meita rou paka ymd-auh ta neni paka-varau alei ymhou-an, myh-kakoua koh assi pakavarau-auh ta ti jæu.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta ti Pe-trus k'ma tyni-æn, Meita rou paka ymd-auh ta neni paka-varau alei ymhou-an, myh-kakoua koh assi pakavarau-auh ta ti jæu.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doch Petrus antwoordende sepde tot hem Al wierden sy oock atle aen u ghe-ergert ick en sal nimmermer: ge-rrgert worden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Peter answered and said unto him, Though all men shall be offended because of thee, yet will I never be offended.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">彼得說：「眾人雖然為你的緣故跌倒，我卻永不跌倒。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse34">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus tyni æn, Missing kounnau kow, ka tou euvan katta dou assi-appa mouni ta taoukka, ka t' touroul-ei-mhourmau jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus tyni æn, Missing kounnau kow, ka tou euvan katta dou assi-appa mouni ta taoukka, ka t' touroul-ei-mhourmau jau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Jesus leyde tot ham Doorwaer ick segge u dat ghy in desen-selben nacht eer be haen gekraeyt sal hebben my driemael sult berTr &amp; sepde tothem </TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus said unto him, Verily I say unto thee, That this night, before the cock crow, thou shalt deny me thrice.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：「我實在告訴你，今夜雞叫以先，你要三次不認我。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse35">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ni-k'ma ta ti Petrus tyni. an, Meita-rou pis-lalam-appa mau-kow mapatei, assi-koh rmau-ah ymhou-an. Ka komm'appa hynna ki sou ta ymmid ki Pahta tæutæuughan.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ni-k'ma ta ti Petrus tyni. an, Meita-rou pis-lalam-appa mau-kow mapatei, assi-koh rmau-ah ymhou-an. Ka komm'appa hynna ki sou ta ymmid ki Pahta tæutæuughan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">r0S lepde tot Al migelte ick oock met u fterben so en sal ick u geenfins berloochenen. Delghelijcks feyden oock alle de Biscipelen, m</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Peter said unto him, Though I should die with thee, yet will I not deny thee. Likewise also said all the disciples.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">彼得說：「我就是必須和你同死，也總不能不認你。」眾門徒都是這樣說。 （可14‧32－42；路22‧39－46）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse36">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta ni-toulam neini-an ta ti Jesus mou-koua tou jtou-kakoua-an ka pananang-en Geth-semane, ka ni-k'ma ki Pahtatæu-tæuughan, Mierrong-hia tou ki-di ki ou-koua-eimau hynna mako-Alilid.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta ni-toulam neini-an ta ti Jesus mou-koua tou jtou-kakoua-an ka pananang-en Geth-semane, ka ni-k'ma ki Pahtatæu-tæuughan, Mierrong-hia tou ki-di ki ou-koua-eimau hynna mako-Alilid.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doe ty Hae: in een plaetse genaemt Gethsemane ende seyde tot de Dilcipelen Sit hier ne| er der tot dat ick henen gae enDe aldaer sal ghebeden heb-</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then cometh Jesus with them unto a place called Gethsemane, and saith unto the disciples, Sit ye here, while I go and pray yonder.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌同門徒來到一個地方，名叫客西馬尼，就對他們說：「你們坐在這裏，等我到那邊去禱告。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse37">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Jrou ka patou-para tyni, æn ti Petrus-an, ki rarouha-appa ka na alalak tipaebedeus, ni-ma-naunamou mavoulas malouas-ap-pa mahymko ta teni.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Jrou ka patou-para tyni, æn ti Petrus-an, ki rarouha-appa ka na alalak tipaebedeus, ni-ma-naunamou mavoulas malouas-ap-pa mahymko ta teni.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende met hem nemende Petrum ende de twee sonen Zebedet begon hy droebigh ende setr beangst te worden, : '</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And he took with him Peter and the two sons of Zebedee, and began to be sorrowful and very heavy.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">於是帶着彼得和西庇太的兩個兒子同去，就憂愁起來，極其難過，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse38">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta ni-k'ma ta teni neini-æn, Mataraæugh mavoulas ta vatti-au tou kidi ki kapatei-an jtou-koua hia mahamæuæ'-æ itou-lam jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta ni-k'ma ta teni neini-æn, Mataraæugh mavoulas ta vatti-au tou kidi ki kapatei-an jtou-koua hia mahamæuæ'-æ itou-lam jau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doe seyde hy tot haer Mijne riele is gheheel bedroeft totter doodt toe: blyft Hier ende waeckt met mp.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then saith he unto them, My soul is exceeding sorrowful, even unto death: tarry ye here, and watch with me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">便對他們說：「我心裏甚是憂傷，幾乎要死；你們在這裏等候，和我一同警醒。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse39">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Jrou ka ni-oukakoukoua tyn, ni-mahgakup ki vlung tyn, ka ni-mako-Alilid, k'ma, Rama au, heirou ka ilpoug-hin, pahali-auragha jau-an ki hæuugh k'atta ka äyht-tan: Nda assi mama ki ka-moei-en-au, râ mam'æppa ki ka-moei-en-hou.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Jrou ka ni-oukakoukoua tyn, ni-mahgakup ki vlung tyn, ka ni-mako-Alilid, k'ma, Rama au, heirou ka ilpoug-hin, pahali-auragha jau-an ki hæuugh k'atta ka äyht-tan: Nda assi mama ki ka-moei-en-au, râ mam'æppa ki kamoei-en-hou.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende een weynigh boort gegaen zijnde biel hp op stjn aengelicht biddende seggende Myn Dader indien het mogelick is laet dese Diinck-beke; ban my boorby gat:Doch niet geliick ick wil maer geliick ghy [wilt.]</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And he went a little farther, and fell on his face, and prayed, saying, O my Father, if it be possible, let this cup pass from me: nevertheless not as I will, but as thou wilt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他就稍往前走，俯伏在地，禱告說：「我父啊，倘若可行，求你叫這杯離開我。然而，不要照我的意思，只要照你的意思。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse40">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-mou-kona ta teni ki Pahtatautæuughan, ka ni-kmaba lei neini-æn ka meirip, ka ni-k'ma ti Petrus-an, Maurou-kamou kaua mahamauä toulam, jau-an sasat kita lei?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-mou-kona ta teni ki Pahtatautæuughan, ka ni-kmaba lei neini-æn ka meirip, ka ni-k'ma ti Petrus-an, Maurou-kamou kaua mahamauä toulam, jau-an sasat kita lei?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende hy quam tot ds Disciptlen ende bondse flapende ende sepde tot Petrum En kondt ghp dan niet ren upre met my waecken # w mm_</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And he cometh unto the disciples, and findeth them asleep, and saith unto Peter, What, could ye not watch with me one hour?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">來到門徒那裏，見他們睡着了，就對彼得說：「怎麼樣？你們不能同我警醒片時嗎？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse41">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Nda mahanaua-Alilid-a, ki assi-moumi ou-koua-eih tou rpung-an: Massorol ta Joepan, rå assi masaukit ta vaat.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Nda mahanaua-Alilid-a, ki assi-moumi ou-koua-eih tou rpung-an: Massorol ta Joepan, rå assi masaukit ta vaat.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Waeckt ende bidt op dat ghy niet in bersoeckinge en komt: de geelt is wel gewilligh | maer het bleesch 1s ac w</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Watch and pray, that ye enter not into temptation: the spirit indeed is willing, but the flesh is weak.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">總要警醒禱告，免得入了迷惑。你們心靈固然願意，肉體卻軟弱了。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse42">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Mila tou kararouha dou ou-koun tyn, ni-æma-ou-Rama-au, heirou assi mali-phough mali-æuragh iauan ta hæuuh katta ka ayht-ten, dou assi-mau hou-ouro-en myt, nda paanit-auto ta kamoei-en-hou.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Mila tou kararouha dou ou-koun tyn, ni-æma-ou-Rama-au, heirou assi mali-phough mali-æuragh iauan ta hæuuh katta ka ayht-ten, dou assi-mau hou-ouro-en myt, nda paanit-auto ta kamoei-en-hou.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Wedtrom ten tweeden-mael henen gaende badt hy feggende Mijn Dade? indien dee Drinckbeke; ban mpmetboorbp en kan gaen ten ry dat ick hem drincke uwen wille gefchiede.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">He went away again the second time, and prayed, saying, O my Father, if this cup may not pass away from me, except I drink it, thy will be done.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">第二次又去禱告說：「我父啊，這杯若不能離開我，必要我喝，就願你的意旨成全。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse43">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka dou mou-koua ta teni, mila kmabalei neini-æn ka meirip: alei ka ouhang marisigh ta matta nein.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka dou mou-koua ta teni, mila kmabalei neini-æn ka meirip: alei ka ouhang marisigh ta matta nein.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende komende [ by haer J bondt Hy'se wederom Napende : want hare oogen waren beswaerr,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And he came and found them asleep again: for their eyes were heavy.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">又來，見他們睡着了，因為他們的眼睛困倦。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse44">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka dou payhkakoua neini-an, ni-ou-koun tyn mila, ka ni-mako-Alilid tou katatourou, mat-tæ'i-la teni ki sou-rà.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka dou payhkakoua neini-an, ni-ou-koun tyn mila, ka ni-mako-Alilid tou katatourou, mat-tæ'i-la teni ki sou-rà.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende haer latende gingh hy wederom henen ende badt ten derden-mael feggende deelbe woorden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And he left them, and went away again, and prayed the third time, saying the same words.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌又離開他們去了。第三次禱告，說的話還是與先前一樣。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse45">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta ni-mou-koua ta teni ki Pahtatæutæuughan tyn, k'ma neini-æn, masinipp-à smaki-likough ki mangahar pæ'i-hababa: K'ytt'ei matouk-ato ta kidi ki ta'-lei, ka pa'a-tounnoun-auh ta Alak ki ka'æuloung tou rima ki tama-kavarau.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta ni-mou-koua ta teni ki Pahtatæutæuughan tyn, k'ma neini-æn, masinipp-à smaki-likough ki mangahar pæ'i-hababa: K'ytt'ei matouk-ato ta kidi ki ta'-lei, ka pa'a-tounnoun-auh ta Alak ki ka'æuloung tou rima ki tama-kavarau.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doe quam hy tot lijne Dilcipelen ende eyde tot haer Slaept[nu] boort ende rultet: Siet de upre ig na by gekomen ende de Sone des menlchen wordt ober gelebert in de handen der condaren.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then cometh he to his disciples, and saith unto them, Sleep on now, and take your rest: behold, the hour is at hand, and the Son of man is betrayed into the hands of sinners.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">於是來到門徒那裏，對他們說：「現在你們仍然睡覺安歇吧！時候到了，人子被賣在罪人手裏了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse46">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Matti-mæu-æhpit, ou koua-ei-mytta, k'ytt'ei, mou-touk-ato ta sim'hamha iau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Matti-mæu-æhpit, ou koua-ei-mytta, k'ytt'ei, mou-touk-ato ta sim'hamha iau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Start op laet ons gaen liet hy is na by die mp berraedt. | '</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Rise, let us be going: behold, he is at hand that doth betray me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">起來！我們走吧。看哪，賣我的人近了！」 （可14‧43－50；路22‧47－53；約18‧3－12）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse47">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Jrou ka masousou-appa ta teni, k'ytt'ei, Ni-iroua ta ti Judas ka saät ki sat kytti-æn 'æb ki rou-ha, ka toulam tyni-æn ta kalauan ka irang ka mei-koua ki tyrrau ki vavouvoukbouk, ka ni-padingien ki Tama-p'hik ka Sibavau, ki Ma moumou-appa ki ta'u.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Jrou ka masousou-appa ta teni, k'ytt'ei, Ni-iroua ta ti Judas ka saät ki sat kytti-æn 'æb ki rouha, ka toulam tyni-æn ta kalauan ka irang ka mei-koua ki tyrrau ki vavouvoukbouk, ka ni-padingien ki Tama-p'hik ka Sibavau, ki Ma moumou-appa ki ta'u.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende als hy noch fprack liet Judas een ban de twaelbe quam ende met hem een groote ichare met sweerdenende ftocken [ghefonden] ban de Ober piriefteren ende Ouderlingen des Dolcks.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And while he yet spake, lo, Judas, one of the twelve, came, and with him a great multitude with swords and staves, from the chief priests and elders of the people.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">說話之間，那十二個門徒裏的猶大來了，並有許多人帶着刀棒，從祭司長和民間的長老那裏與他同來。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse48">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka teni ka si-vanavana ty-ni-æn, ni-pou-kidi neini-æn, k'ma, Teni ka bæigh-au-mau, teni ta ti anna, tmouroung-å tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka teni ka si-vanavana ty-ni-æn, ni-pou-kidi neini-æn, k'ma, Teni ka bæigh-au-mau, teni ta ti anna, tmouroung-å tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende die hem berriedt hadde haer een teecKen gegheben segghende Dien ick sal kussen deselbe is het grijpt hem.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Now he that betrayed him gave them a sign, saying, Whomsoever I shall kiss, that same is he: hold him fast.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那賣耶穌的給了他們一個暗號，說：「我與誰親嘴，誰就是他。你們可以拿住他。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse49">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka madys dou mou-koua ti Jesus-an, ni-koun tyn, Tabe Rabbi, kani-bæigh tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka madys dou mou-koua ti Jesus-an, ni-koun tyn, Tabe Rabbi, kani-bæigh tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende tegstondt komende tot Jelum eyde hy weelt ghegroet Kabbi ; ende Hp kuste hem.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And forthwith he came to Jesus, and said, Hail, master; and kissed him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">猶大隨即到耶穌跟前，說：「請拉比安」，就與他親嘴。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse50">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Diou, oua-mang kow hia? Anna ta dou ni-moutouk ta neni, ni-pæ-tkoua ki rima ti Jesus-an, ka ni-tmouroung-appa tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Diou, oua-mang kow hia? Anna ta dou ni-moutouk ta neni, ni-pæ-tkoua ki rima ti Jesus-an, ka ni-tmouroung-appa tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Mae Jesus lepde tot Hem Driendt waer toe 3Ht ghy hier + Doe quamen fp toe ende loeghen de handen gen Jesum ende grepen hem.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And Jesus said unto him, Friend, wherefore art thou come? Then came they, and laid hands on Jesus and took him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌對他說：「朋友，你來要做的事，就做吧。」於是那些人上前，下手拿住耶穌。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse51">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka k'ytt'ei, sasat neini-æn ka tou-læm ti Jesus-an, dou ni-sikkigh ki rima, ni-lmouhgout ki tyrræu tyn, ka ni-rmad ki kouncia ki Dadyllo, tubbo ki tang-ira tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka k'ytt'ei, sasat neini-æn ka tou-læm ti Jesus-an, dou ni-sikkigh ki rima, ni-lmouhgout ki tyrræu tyn, ka ni-rmad ki kouncia ki Dadyllo, tubbo ki tang-ira tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Endesiet een ban de ghene die met Jesu waren dehandt untsteeckendetrock syn sweerdt uyt ende laende den dienstknecht des Hoogen-piiefters hieuw syne oore af.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And, behold, one of them which were with Jesus stretched out his hand, and drew his sword, and struck a servant of the high priest's, and smote off his ear.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">有跟隨耶穌的一個人伸手拔出刀來，將大祭司的僕人砍了一刀，削掉了他一個耳朵。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse52">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Pou-likoug-au pou-ka-rouloung ta tyrræu-ouho: alei ka na mamang ta mara ki tyrrau, sid-ad-au pakapatei ta neni ki tyrræu.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Pou-likoug-au pou-ka-rouloung ta tyrræu-ouho: alei ka na mamang ta mara ki tyrrau, sid-ad-au pakapatei ta neni ki tyrræu.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Boe seyde Jesus tot Hem Keert uw' sweerde in fijne plactse : want alle die Het sweert nemen sullen doo? het sweert beygaen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then said Jesus unto him, Put up again thy sword into his place: for all they that take the sword shall perish with the sword.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌對他說：「收刀入鞘吧！凡動刀的，必死在刀下。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse53">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Pah-dimdim-en-hou lava, ka assi-koh makou-lpough ma-kou-Alilid hnyn ki Raraman-au, ka pa-tou-læm-ah ta teni jau-an masaoun madagh ki sat kytti-æn 'æb ki rouha ki Legioenen, ki Tama-Gnæu.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Pah-dimdim-en-hou lava, ka assi-koh makou-lpough ma-kou-Alilid hnyn ki Raraman-au, ka pa-tou-læm-ah ta teni jau-an masaoun madagh ki sat kytti-æn 'æb ki rouha ki Legioenen, ki Tama-Gnæu.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ofmeynt ghy dat ick mijnen Vadernu niet en kan bidden ende hy sal my mee als twaelf legioenen Engelen by setten</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Thinkest thou that I cannot now pray to my Father, and he shall presently give me more than twelve legions of angels?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你想，我不能求我父現在為我差遣十二營多天使來嗎？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse54">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Nda pavut-auh mama ki mang ta na sasoulat, [ka k'ma] ka pam't-an-eih komma-hynna ta ma-mang k'atta.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Nda pavut-auh mama ki mang ta na sasoulat, [ka k'ma] ka pam't-an-eih komma-hynna ta ma-mang k'atta.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Hoe souden dan de Schaiften berbult worden fdie feggen] dat het alsoo geschieden moet + .</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But how then shall the scriptures be fulfilled, that thus it must be?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">若是這樣，經上所說，事情必須如此的話怎麼應驗呢？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse55">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Tou kidi ki tæ'lei katta ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus ki kalau-an, Ni-t'papænæh-kamou mama ki mou-kouah ki Tama-lpogh, ki tyrrau ki vavouvouk-bouk, alei ki tou roung-au-monmi jauian : wa'i ni-mi-sal-koh mierrong ymoumi-æn mahtatæutæuugh tou Kouva ki tatamd-den ki Alid, ka assikamou ni-tmouroung jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Tou kidi ki tæ'lei katta ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus ki kalau-an, Ni-t'papænæh-kamou mama ki mou-kouah ki Tama-lpogh, ki tyrrau ki vavouvouk-bouk, alei ki tou roung-au-monmi jauian : wa'i ni-mi-sal-koh mierrong ymoumi-æn mahtatæutæuugh tou Kouva ki tatamd-den ki Alid, ka assikamou ni-tmouroung jau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ter selber upre sprack Jesus tot de scharen Ghy 3yt zijt uytghegaen als teghen eenen moorden aer met sweerden ende [tocken om my te bangen: dagelicks (at ick by u leerende in den Tempel ende ghy en hebt my met gegeepen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">In that same hour said Jesus to the multitudes, Are ye come out as against a thief with swords and staves for to take me? I sat daily with you teaching in the temple, and ye laid no hold on me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">當時，耶穌對眾人說：「你們帶着刀棒出來拿我，如同拿強盜嗎？我天天坐在殿裏教訓人，你們並沒有拿我。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse56">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ ni-pamt-en ta-mamang k'atta alei ka pavut-aul-ato ta na sasoulat ki Tama Mattæ'i-tan-da. Tou kidi k'anna ni-pou-ymmid ilpout ta Pahtatæutæuug-han tyn, pa-itou-koua tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ ni-pamt-en ta-mamang k'atta alei ka pavut-aul-ato ta na sasoulat ki Tama Mattæ'i-tan-da. Tou kidi k'anna ni-pou-ymmid ilpout ta Pahtatæutæuug-han tyn, pa-itou-koua tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doch dit alles is gheschiedt op dat de Schrifcen det: Propheten souden berbult worden. Doe bluchteden alle de Discipelen hem berlatende.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But all this was done, that the scriptures of the prophets might be fulfilled. Then all the disciples forsook him, and fled.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">但這一切的事成就了，為要應驗先知書上的話。」當下，門徒都離開他，逃走了。 （可14‧53－65；路22‧54－55，63－71；約18‧13－14，19－24）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse57">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Neni ka ni-tmouroung ti Jesus-an, ni-mad [tyni-en] pa-ou-koua ti Kaisas-an ka Dadyllo ka Si-bavau, ni-mæu'i-sâl-hynna ta Makou-sasoulat ki Mamou-mou-appa.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Neni ka ni-tmouroung ti Jesus-an, ni-mad [tyni-en] pa-ou-koua ti Kaisas-an ka Dadyllo ka Si-bavau, ni-mæu'i-sâl-hynna ta Makou-sasoulat ki Mamou-mou-appa.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Die nn Jelum gebangen hadden lepdden [hem]. henen tot Cajapham den Hooghen piielter alwaer de Schaift-gheleerde ende Ouderlingen bergadert waren.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And they that had laid hold on Jesus led him away to Caiaphas the high priest, where the scribes and the elders were assembled.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">拿耶穌的人把他帶到大祭司該亞法那裏去；文士和長老已經在那裏聚會。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse58">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-itou-dallia itou-äugh tyni-æn ta ti Petrus tou kidi-appa ki las ki Dadyllo, ka rou mou-rbo-ato, ni-mi-lam mierrong ki Makoua, ka kakytta-auh tyn ta lymmou-lymmou.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-itou-dallia itou-äugh tyni-æn ta ti Petrus tou kidi-appa ki las ki Dadyllo, ka rou mou-rbo-ato, ni-mi-lam mierrong ki Makoua, ka kakytta-auh tyn ta lymmou-lymmou.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende Petrus bolgde hem ban berre tot aen de sale des Hoogen piielters ende binnen gegaen zijnde sat hy by de dienaren om het epnde te lien.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But Peter followed him afar off unto the high priest's palace, and went in, and sat with the servants, to see the end.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">彼得遠遠地跟着耶穌，直到大祭司的院子，進到裏面，就和差役同坐，要看這事到底怎樣。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse59">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ Tama-P'hik ka Si-bæ-vau, Mamoumou, ki na-pæui-sasal-appa ta ni-kmi'ym ki sou ka pattæ ihail-in si-haharang tou doummati Jesus-an, alei ki paka-patei-au nein tyni-æn, ka assi nein ni-pæki-valei-en-dâ.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ Tama-P'hik ka Si-bæ-vau, Mamoumou, ki na-pæui-sasal-appa ta ni-kmi'ym ki sou ka pattæ ihail-in si-haharang tou doummati Jesus-an, alei ki paka-patei-au nein tyni-æn, ka assi nein ni-pæki-valei-en-dâ.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende de Ober piiefters ende de Ouderlinghen ende dengheheelen GrootenKaedt ochten balsche getuygenisse tegen Jelum op dat sp hem dooden mochten ende en bonden niet.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Now the chief priests, and elders, and all the council, sought false witness against Jesus, to put him to death;</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">祭司長和全公會尋找假見證控告耶穌，要治死他。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse60">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Mou-kounna ka maba toung ta Gmail ka si-haharang ka ni-iroua-hynna, assi nein ni-paki-valei-en ki mamang.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Mou-kounna ka maba toung ta Gmail ka si-haharang ka ni-iroua-hynna, assi nein ni-paki-valei-en ki mamang.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende hoewel daer bele balsche getupgen toe ghekomen men waren soo en bonden fp {doch} met.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But found none: yea, though many false witnesses came, yet found they none. At the last came two false witnesses,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">雖有好些人來作假見證，總得不着實據。末後有兩個人前來，說：</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse61">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Tou äugh-dâ ni-iroua ta rarouha ki Gmail ka sihaharang, ka ni-k ma, Teni katta ta ni-k'ma-k'ma, Kou-lpoughen-au kuhta ta Kouva ki tatamd-den ki'Alid, ka mei-likough mei-ryngei ki anna tou toutourou ki wæ'i.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Tou äugh-dâ ni-iroua ta rarouha ki Gmail ka sihaharang, ka ni-k ma, Teni katta ta ni-k'ma-k'ma, Kou-lpoughen-au kuhta ta Kouva ki tatamd-den ki'Alid, ka mei-likough mei-ryngei ki anna tou toutourou ki wæ'i.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Mar; ten laetften quamen twee balsche ghetupghen ende sepden Dele heeft gheseght Ick kan den Tempel Godts af-breken ende in drie dagen den selben opbouwen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And said, This fellow said, I am able to destroy the temple of God, and to build it in three days.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">「這個人曾說：『我能拆毀上帝的殿，三日內又建造起來。』」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse62">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Jrou ka ahpit ta Dadyllo, ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Assi-kow mat-tæ'i-vlli ki mamang? Mang ta hail-len nein mattæ'i-doumma ym-hou-an?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Jrou ka ahpit ta Dadyllo, ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Assi-kow mat-tæ'i-vlli ki mamang? Mang ta hail-len nein mattæ'i-doumma ym-hou-an?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende de Hooge-prieGer opltaende sepdetot hem En antwoordt ghy niets ? Wat ghetupghen dese tegenu ? |</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And the high priest arose, and said unto him, Answerest thou nothing? what is it which these witness against thee?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">大祭司就站起來，對耶穌說：「你甚麼都不回答嗎？這些人作見證告你的是甚麼呢？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse63">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ ti Jesus ta ni-meipat, ka mattæ i-v'lli ta Dadyllo ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Paka-rihe-rihe-koh [mat-ta sou] ymhou-an ki Alid ka mæuagh, ka banna-ah-kow ymi-æn-an, ma lava ka tip-hhristus kow, ka Alak ki Alid?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ ti Jesus ta ni-meipat, ka mattæ i-v'lli ta Dadyllo ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Paka-rihe-rihe-koh [matta sou] ymhou-an ki Alid ka mæuagh, ka banna-ah-kow ymi-æn-an, ma lava ka tip-hhristus kow, ka Alak ki Alid?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doch Jesus iweegh ftille ende de Hooge-priester antwoordede eyde tot hem Ack besweere u by den leben dighen Godt dat ghy ons Tseght of ghy rije de Chiiftus de Sone Godts *</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But Jesus held his peace, And the high priest answered and said unto him, I adjure thee by the living God, that thou tell us whether thou be the Christ, the Son of God.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌卻不言語。大祭司對他說：「我指着永生上帝叫你起誓告訴我們，你是上帝的兒子基督不是？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse64">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ni-k'ma tati Jesus tyni-een, Ni-mattæ i-rouk kow. Ra k'ma-koh ymoumi-æn, na hnnnan k'atta k'ytt'ei-moumi ta Alak ki ka'æuloung tou ierrong-eih tyn tou ouwal ki kailhgen [ki Alid] rou ierroua-ah tou pourarei ki vullum.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ni-k'ma tati Jesus tyni-een, Ni-mattæ i-rouk kow. Ra k'ma-koh ymoumi-æn, na hnnnan k'atta k'ytt'ei-moumi ta Alak ki ka'æuloung tou ierrong-eih tyn tou ouwal ki kailhgen [ki Alid] rou ierroua-ah tou pourarei ki vullum.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Jesus sepde tot hem Ghy hebt het ghesegt.Doch ick segge u-lieden ban nu aen sult ghy sien den Sone des menschen sittende ter rechter-shandt ] der Kracht [Godts] ende komende op de Wolcken des hemels ;7</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus saith unto him, Thou hast said: nevertheless I say unto you, Hereafter shall ye see the Son of man sitting on the right hand of power, and coming in the clouds of heaven.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌對他說：「你說的是。然而，我告訴你們，後來你們要看見人子坐在那權能者的右邊，駕着天上的雲降臨。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse65">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta ni-ki it ta Dadyllo ki pammammien tyn, k'ma, Ni-barigh ta teni makou talum [ki Alid,] mangau-mi-an ta Mattæ'i-hail ka rouma? K'ytt'ei, ni-illing-igh'noumi hnyn ta bavarugh tyn [ki Alid.]</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta ni-ki it ta Dadyllo ki pammammien tyn, k'ma, Ni-barigh ta teni makou talum [ki Alid,] mangau-mi-an ta Mattæ'i-hail ka rouma? K'ytt'ei, ni-illing-igh'noumi hnyn ta bavarugh tyn [ki Alid.]</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doe besscheurde de Hooght-puielter fijne kleederen segghende Hy heeft [Godt] gelaltert wat hebbeti wp noch getuygen ban noode? Hitt nu hebt gy sijne Godts-" [Godts-Jlafteringe ghehoort.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then the high priest rent his clothes, saying, He hath spoken blasphemy; what further need have we of witnesses? behold, now ye have heard his blasphemy.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">大祭司就撕開衣服，說：「他說了僭妄的話，我們何必再用見證人呢？這僭妄的話，現在你們都聽見了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse66">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Pah-mang ta ryh-oumi? Rå neni ta ni-naattæi-vlli kima, [Oohoh] mamsing ki pakapapa-tapatei.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Pah-mang ta ryh-oumi? Rå neni ta ni-naattæi-vlli kima, [Oohoh] mamsing ki pakapapa-tapatei.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Wat dunckt u-liedens Ende sy antwoordende [eyden Hy is des doodts schuldigh.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">What think ye? They answered and said, He is guilty of death.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們的意見如何？」他們回答說：「他是該死的。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse67">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta ni-padipaghan nein tou vlung tyn, ka ni-bouk-bouk en nein kina kmud tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta ni-padipaghan nein tou vlung tyn, ka ni-bouk-bouk en nein kina kmud tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doe lpoghen lp in shn. aengesichte mde floegen hem met bupften, -</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then did they spit in his face, and buffeted him; and others smote him with the palms of their hands,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們就吐唾沫在他臉上，用拳頭打他，也有用手掌打他的，說：</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse68">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka pæni ki voual ta ni-tmaplægh tyni-en tou timi, kma, Kæi-dmir-ou-kame kmæih-tan 'hristus, ti taplægh kow ti mang?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka pæni ki voual ta ni-tmaplægh tyni-en tou timi, kma, Kæi-dmir-ou-kame kmæih-tan 'hristus, ti taplægh kow ti mang?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">: Ende andere gaben hem Kinnebacks-flaghen eggende Propheteert ons Thiilte wieis't die u ghe-</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Saying, Prophesy unto us, thou Christ, Who is he that smote thee?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">「基督啊！你是先知，告訴我們打你的是誰？」 （可14‧66－72；路22‧56－62；約18‧15－18，25－27）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse69">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Kani-mi-mala miraoung ta ti Petrus tou ta-tallæghin, ka saat ka kæuh-jna ka pairoung-in ta ni-iroua tyni-æn, k'ma, Ni-makoi lam-appa kow ta ymhou ti Jesus-an ka makka Galileä.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Kani-mi-mala miraoung ta ti Petrus tou ta-tallæghin, ka saat ka kæuh-jna ka pairoung-in ta ni-iroua tyni-æn, k'ma, Ni-makoi lam-appa kow ta ymhou ti Jesus-an ka makka Galileä.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende g sat buyten in de sale ende een dienstmaeght quam tot hem segde Ghy waert oock met Sesu ben Galilerr, —</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Now Peter sat without in the palace: and a damsel came unto him, saying, Thou also wast with Jesus of Galilee.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">彼得在外面院子裏坐着，有一個使女前來，說：「你素來也是同那加利利人耶穌一夥的。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse70">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ æmah dmau ki taou ka ymmid, k'ma, Assi-mau ou mhgan kamang ta sou ouho.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ æmah dmau ki taou ka ymmid, k'ma, Assi-mau ou mhgan kamang ta sou ouho.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Mat? Hy loochende Het boor allen segghende Ak en weet mef wat gn legt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But he denied before them all, saying, I know not what thou sayest.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">彼得在眾人面前卻不承認，說：「我不知道你說的是甚麼！」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse71">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Jrou ka mou-mæla ta teni tou tangagh, ni-kmytta-appa ty-ni-an ta pani[ka jna ka pæiroung-in ka k'ma neini-æn ka ä'ia-koua hynna, Teni-appa ta na lam ti Jesus ka tæi-Nazareth.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Jrou ka mou-mæla ta teni tou tangagh, ni-kmytta-appa ty-ni-an ta pani[ka jna ka pæiroung-in ka k'ma neini-æn ka ä'ia-koua hynna, Teni-appa ta na lam ti Jesus ka tæi-Nazareth.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende als hy nae de boor poorte uptgingh lagh een andere [ dieastmaeght, ] mde sepde tot de gene die aldaer [waren,] Dele was oock met Jelu den Nararener.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And when he was gone out into the porch, another maid saw him, and said unto them that were there, This fellow was also with Jesus of Nazareth.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">既出去，到了門口，又有一個使女看見他，就對那裏的人說：「這個人也是同拿撒勒人耶穌一夥的。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse72">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-lala rmau ki sou ka na papakakariherihe, Assi-man kalang-en ta ta'u.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-lala rmau ki sou ka na papakakariherihe, Assi-man kalang-en ta ta'u.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Endehylochende het .wederom met eenen eedt [scgghende,] Ick en kenne den mensche met.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And again he denied with an oath, I do not know the man.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">彼得又不承認，並且起誓說：「我不認得那個人。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse73">
        <FORM kindOf="original">. Nda matouk ki kidi k'an-ni-mou-koua ta mirouh-ko-hynna, ka ni-k'ma ti Petrus-an, Missing ymhou ta na lam-appa nein, nda pakalang-kow ki yng-au ouho.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">. Nda matouk ki kidi k'an-ni-mou-koua ta mirouh-ko-hynna, ka ni-k'ma ti Petrus-an, Missing ymhou ta na lam-appa nein, nda pakalang-kow ki yngau ouho.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende cen weymigh daer nae dieder ondem y komende seyden tot Petjum Waer lick ghy zijt oock ban die want oock uwe sprake maeckt u openbaer. |</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And after a while came unto him they that stood by, and said to Peter, Surely thou also art one of them; for thy speech bewrayeth thee.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">過了不多的時候，旁邊站着的人前來，對彼得說：「你真是他們一黨的，你的口音把你露出來了。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse74">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta ni-manæunamou mahko avavagh tyni-een pakarihe-rihe-appa ki sou, Assi-mau kalang-en ta ta'u..</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta ni-manæunamou mahko avavagh tyni-een pakarihe-rihe-appa ki sou, Assi-mau kalang-en ta ta'u..</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doe begon hy [kch] te berbloecken ende te sweeren Ick en kenne den mensche niet.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then began he to curse and to swear, saying, I know not the man. And immediately the cock crew.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">彼得就發咒起誓地說：「我不認得那個人。」立時，雞就叫了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse75">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-tma-touk mouni ta taoukka: ka ni-hmi-balei ta ti Pe-trus ki na sou ti Jesus ka ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Tou-ouro ki oum-eih ki taoukka, sau-touroul-ah-kow rmau jau-an. Karou ni-samamala, ni-ænum [ki ryhtyn] ni-tmangi-tangi-ato. Kararouha kytti.ænæb ki pytto ki lbæb ki soulat.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-tma-touk mouni ta taoukka: ka ni-hmi-balei ta ti Pe-trus ki na sou ti Jesus ka ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Tou-ouro ki oum-eih ki taoukka, sau-touroul-ah-kow rmau jau-an. Karou ni-samamala, ni-ænum [ki ryhtyn] ni-tmangi-tangi-ato. Kararouha kytti.ænæb ki pytto ki lbæb ki soulat.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende terstondt kraeyde de ham : ende Petyus wiert indachtig des woorts Fesu die tot hem gheseght hadde Eer de hane gekraept sal hebben sult ghy my driemael berlocheneu. Ende nae buyten gaende weende hy bitterlick.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And Peter remembered the word of Jesus, which said unto him, Before the cock crow, thou shalt deny me thrice. And he went out, and wept bitterly.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">彼得想起耶穌所說的話：「雞叫以先，你要三次不認我。」他就出去痛哭。</TRANSL>
    </S>
</TEXT>