<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEXT id="Siraya_Dutch_Matthew_Chapter20" xml:lang="fos" source="Siraya Bible, Matthew gospel" copyright="public domain" citation="Gravius, Daniël. 1661. Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa. Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang. Amsterdam: Michiel Hartogh." BibTeX_citation="@book{Gravius1661,&#10;  author    = {Gravius, Daniël},&#10;  year      = {1661},&#10;  title     = {Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa},&#10;  note      = {Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang},&#10;  address   = {Amsterdam},&#10;  publisher = {Michiel Hartogh}&#10;}">
    <S id="verse1">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> KA mahkaula ta Pei-sasou-an ki tounnoun ki vullu-vullum ki Meirang ki sât-katallah-an, ka ni-t'pæpænæh dou madama ki pæ-pakalalam-eih tyn pa-ouvavarauh tou atto-kakaræumætæg-han tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> KA mahkaula ta Pei-sasou-an ki tounnoun ki vullu-vullum ki Meirang ki sât-katallah-an, ka ni-t'pæpænæh dou madama ki pæ-pakalalam-eih tyn pa-ouvavarauh tou atto-kakaræumætæg-han tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ant het Koninckrijck der Hemelen is gelijck een heere des huys die met den morgen-ltondt uytging om arbepders te hueren in synen wijngaert.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">For the kingdom of heaven is like unto a man that is an householder, which went out early in the morning to hire labourers into his vineyard.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">「因為天國好像家主清早去雇人進他的葡萄園做工，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse2">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou ka ni-mææu-amsing mææu-kla ta sou tyn ki sou ki makka-lam-ah dou sasat ki wæ'ï nda, sasat-ah ki malytouk, ni-pæ-ou-koua ta teni neni-æn tou atto-kakaræumætæg-han tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou ka ni-mææu-amsing mææu-kla ta sou tyn ki sou ki makka-lam-ah dou sasat ki wæ'ï nda, sasat-ah ki malytouk, ni-pæ-ou-koua ta teni neni-æn tou atto-kakaræumætæg-han tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende als hy met de arbeyders eens gheworden was boor eenen penningh des daeghs sand hy'se henen in sijnen wyngaert.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And when he had agreed with the labourers for a penny a day, he sent them into his vineyard.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">和工人講定一天一錢銀子，就打發他們進葡萄園去。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse3">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou ka ni-t'pæpænæh tou hivat ki kidi ki katatouro ki tæ'lei, ni-k'ytt'an tyn ta pani ki vouäl ka my-haoung mitouko tou pænæh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou ka ni-t'pæpænæh tou hivat ki kidi ki katatouro ki tæ'lei, ni-k'ytt'an tyn ta pani ki vouäl ka my-haoung mitouko tou pænæh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende uyt-gegaen 3inde ontrent de dede uyre sag hp andere ledigh staende op de mexckt, y</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And he went out about the third hour, and saw others standing idle in the marketplace,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">約在巳初出去，看見市上還有閒站的人，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse4">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-k'ma neini-æn, Nda ou-koua-au'ppa ymoumi tou atto kakaræumætæg-han: râ kama-mang ki pattæi-tiktik-eih, pha-ei-mau-kamou-ra. Ka ni-mou-koua ta neni.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-k'ma neini-æn, Nda ou-koua-au'ppa ymoumi tou atto kakaræumætæg-han: râ kama-mang ki pattæi-tiktik-eih, pha-ei-mau-kamou-ra. Ka ni-mou-koua ta neni.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende hy leyde tot deselbe Gaet ghy oock henen in den whngaert : ende soo wat recht 1s sal ick u geben. Ende ly gingen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And said unto them; Go ye also into the vineyard, and whatsoever is right I will give you. And they went their way.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">就對他們說：『你們也進葡萄園去，所當給的，我必給你們。』他們也進去了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse5">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou ka ni-mila t'papænæl tou hivat ki kaanum ki kamama-toudda-appa ki talei, mah-kaula ni-paou-koua tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou ka ni-mila t'papænæl tou hivat ki kaanum ki kamama-toudda-appa ki talei, mah-kaula ni-paou-koua tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Of is uwe ooghe hoos om dat ick goedt ben + j</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Again he went out about the sixth and ninth hour, and did likewise.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">約在午正和申初又出去，也是這樣行。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse6">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou rå ni-t'pæpænæh tou hivat ki ka fafat kytti-æn 'æb' ki fat ki tæ'lei, ni-kabalei tyn ta ra-rouma ka pani ka my-haoung mi-touko, ka ni-k'ma neini-æn, Ka-mang ta myhaoung-kamou mitou-ko hia makka fat ki wæ'i?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou rå ni-t'pæpænæh tou hivat ki ka fafat kytti-æn 'æb' ki fat ki tæ'lei, ni-kabalei tyn ta ra-rouma ka pani ka my-haoung mi-touko, ka ni-k'ma neini-æn, Ka-mang ta myhaoung-kamou mitou-ko hia makka fat ki wæ'i?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende nyt-gegaen rhnde ontrent de elfde uyre bondt hy andere ledig [taende ende seyde tot haer Wat. ltaet ghy hier den gheheclen dagh ledighs</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And about the eleventh hour he went out, and found others standing idle, and saith unto them, Why stand ye here all the day idle?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">約在酉初出去，看見還有人站在那裏，就問他們說：『你們為甚麼整天在這裏閒站呢？』</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse7">
        <FORM kindOf="original">. Ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Alei ka affi kame ni-uddam ki faäät. Ni-k'ma ta teni neini-æn, Ou-koua-auppa ymoumi tou atto-kakarau-mætæg-han, kamamang ka pat-tæ i-tiktik-eih, arau-moumi-râ.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">. Ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Alei ka affi kame ni-uddam ki faäät. Ni-k'ma ta teni neini-æn, Ou-koua-auppa ymoumi tou atto-kakarau-mætæg-han, kamamang ka pat-tæ i-tiktik-eih, arau-moumi-râ.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Sy feyds tot hem Om dat ons niemandt gehuert en heeft. Hy sepde tot haer Gaet oock ghy henen in den wijngaert ende so wat recht is sult ghy ontfangen:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">They say unto him, Because no man hath hired us. He saith unto them, Go ye also into the vineyard; and whatsoever is right, that shall ye receive.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們說：『因為沒有人雇我們。』他說：『你們也進葡萄園去。』</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse8">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou ka madoung-ato, ni-k'ma ta Meirang ki atto-kakaræu-mætæg-han ki Sih-koua tyn pou-da-auh, Tætæm-au ki makka-la-lam, nda pha-eito ki than-an nein ki ni-ou-varg-han, pa'ä-ourou neini-æn ka ni-fi-äuh pæ'ä-kidi-appa ki ni-fi-ourou.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou ka madoung-ato, ni-k'ma ta Meirang ki atto-kakaræu-mætæg-han ki Sih-koua tyn pou-da-auh, Tætæm-au ki makka-la-lam, nda pha-eito ki than-an nein ki ni-ou-varg-han, pa'ä-ourou neini-æn ka ni-fi-äuh pæ'ä-kidi-appa ki ni-fi-ourou.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ais het nu abondt geworden was sepde de Heere des wijngaerts tot shnen Kentmeelter Riorpt de arbepders ende gheeft hae den loon beginnende ban de laetste tot de eelte.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">So when even was come, the lord of the vineyard saith unto his steward, Call the labourers, and give them their hire, beginning from the last unto the first.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">到了晚上，園主對管事的說：『叫工人都來，給他們工錢，從後來的起，到先來的為止。』</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse9">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Nda jrou ka ni-mou-koua ta ni-papakalalam paou-varæuh tou hivat ki kasasat kytti-æn 'æb ki sat ki tæ lei, ni-à-sasat mara ki malyt-touk ta saäat ki voual,</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Nda jrou ka ni-mou-koua ta ni-papakalalam paou-varæuh tou hivat ki kasasat kytti-æn 'æb ki sat ki tæ lei, ni-à-sasat mara ki malyttouk ta saäat ki voual,</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende als se quamen die ter ter elfder uyre [gehuert waren,] ontfingen sy een peder eenen penningh.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And when they came that were hired about the eleventh hour, they received every man a penny.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">約在酉初雇的人來了，各人得了一錢銀子。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse10">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou ka mou-koua ta ni-si-ourou, ni-pou-rÿh ki à-saoun-eih nein mara, ka neni-appa ta saäat ni-mara ki sasat ki malyt. touk.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou ka mou-koua ta ni-si-ourou, ni-pou-rÿh ki à-saoun-eih nein mara, ka neni-appa ta saäat ni-mara ki sasat ki malyt. touk.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende de cerfte komende meynden dat sy meer ontfanghen ouden ende sy selbe ontfinghen oock elck eenen penningh.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But when the first came, they supposed that they should have received more; and they likewise received every man a penny.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">及至那先雇的來了，他們以為必要多得；誰知也是各得一錢。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse11">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka rou ah-kaha mmara [ki anna,]ni-mææurmour-ato' ki Ta'i-tallagh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka rou ah-kaha mmara [ki anna,]ni-mææurmour-ato' ki Ta'i-tallagh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Gú [dien] ontfangen hebbende mu;murcerden \p tegen den heere des huys.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And when they had received it, they murmured against the goodman of the house,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們得了，就埋怨家主說：</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse12">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Koun, Ni-si-äugh k'atta ni-mou-dyk mou-varæuh ki saat ki ta lei, ka ni-papa-myh-kaulau la-en-hou ta neni ymi-an-an ka ni-tubhga-ni-æn ta mahimko ki maal-ting ka wæ'i.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Koun, Ni-si-äugh k'atta ni-mou-dyk mou-varæuh ki saat ki ta lei, ka ni-papa-myh-kaulau la-en-hou ta neni ymi-an-an ka ni-tubhga-ni-æn ta mahimko ki maal-ting ka wæ'i.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Seggende Dese laetfte en hebben [maer] een uyre gearbept ende ghy hebtse ons gelyck ghemaeckt die wp den last des daeghs ende de hitte gedragen hebben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Saying, These last have wrought but one hour, and thou hast made them equal unto us, which have borne the burden and heat of the day.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">『我們整天勞苦受熱，那後來的只做了一小時，你竟叫他們和我們一樣嗎？』</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse13">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Teni-rå ni-mattæ'i-vlli k'ma kisaat neini-æn, Diou, assi koh pæ æ-toukol ymhou-an. Assi kaua ni-mæuakla kow jau-an ki sou ki sasat ki malyttouk?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Teni-rå ni-mattæ'i-vlli k'ma kisaat neini-æn, Diou, assi koh pæ æ-toukol ymhou-an. Assi kaua ni-mæuakla kow jau-an ki sou ki sasat ki malyttouk?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doch hy antwoordende sepde tot eenen ban haer Patent ick en doe u geen on recht. En 3yt ghy niet met mp eens gheworden boor eenen penningh s</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But he answered one of them, and said, Friend, I do thee no wrong: didst not thou agree with me for a penny?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">家主回答其中的一人說：『朋友，我不虧負你，你與我講定的不是一錢銀子嗎？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse14">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Arau ta â-mhou-ah, nda d'marang-ato. Mamoei-koh ki ni-si-äugh katta pää-mahkaulaula pi'a ymhou-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Arau ta â-mhou-ah, nda d'marang-ato. Mamoei-koh ki ni-si-äugh katta pää-mahkaulaula pi'a ymhou-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Neemt het uwt ende gaer henen. Ick wil desen laetsten oock geben gelyck als u.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Take that thine is, and go thy way: I will give unto this last, even as unto thee.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">拿你的走吧！我給那後來的和給你一樣，這是我願意的。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse15">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Assi koh kaua hahei-en ka sykkounoung-ah-koh ki âjau? Assi lava mariang ta matta-uhou, alei ka mariang-koh?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Assi koh kaua hahei-en ka sykkounoung-ah-koh ki âjau? Assi lava mariang ta matta-uhou, alei ka mariang-koh?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Öf enis het my niet pheoorloft te doen met het</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Is it not lawful for me to do what I will with mine own? Is thine eye evil, because I am good?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我的東西難道不可隨我的意思用嗎？因為我作好人，你就紅了眼嗎？』</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse16">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Kma hynna si-ourou-ah ta si-äugh, ka si-äæugh-ah ta si-ou-rou. Ka madagh ta ni-tætæäm, rå matityng ta ni-peri.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Kma hynna si-ourou-ah ta si-äugh, ka si-äæugh-ah ta si-ou-rou. Ka madagh ta ni-tætæäm, rå matityng ta ni-peri.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Also sullen de laetste de eerlte 3yn eri de eerlte de lactste. Want bele zijn geroepen maer weynige uytberkoren.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">So the last shall be first, and the first last: for many be called, but few chosen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">這樣，那在後的，將要在前；在前的，將要在後了。 」 （可10‧32－34；路18‧31－34）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse17">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Karou mi-vavau ta ti Jesus mou-Jerusalem, ni-patou-lalam tyn ta sat kytti-æn 'æb ki douha ki Pahtatæutau-han tyn patou-sinnæh tou darang, ka ni-k'ma neini-æn,</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Karou mi-vavau ta ti Jesus mou-Jerusalem, ni-patou-lalam tyn ta sat kytti-æn 'æb ki douha ki Pahtatæutau-han tyn patou-sinnæh tou darang, ka ni-k'ma neini-æn,</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende Jesus opgarnde nae Jerulalem nam tot hem de twaelf Discipelen alleen op den wegh ende sepde tot hatr | .</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And Jesus going up to Jerusalem took the twelve disciples apart in the way, and said unto them,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌上耶路撒冷去的時候，在路上把十二個門徒帶到一邊，對他們說：</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse18">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Kytt'ei mou-vavau-kytta mou-Jerusalem, ka pa'a-toun-- noun-an-eih ta Alak ki kaæuloung ki Sil-bavau ka Tania-p'higik ki Mahkou-sasoulat-appa, ka dmung-ding-ah tyni-æn ki pakapatei-eih.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Kytt'ei mou-vavau-kytta mou-Jerusalem, ka pa'a-toun-- noun-an-eih ta Alak ki kaæuloung ki Sil-bavau ka Tania-p'higik ki Mahkou-sasoulat-appa, ka dmung-ding-ah tyni-æn ki pakapatei-eih.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Siet wp gaen op nae Jerusalem ende de Sone des menschen sal den Oberprtesteren ende Schuft-gheleerden ober-ghelebert worden ende sy sullen Hem te: doodt beroordeelen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Behold, we go up to Jerusalem; and the Son of man shall be betrayed unto the chief priests and unto the scribes, and they shall condemn him to death,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">「看哪，我們上耶路撒冷去，人子要被交給祭司長和文士。他們要定他死罪，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse19">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka pa'ä-tounnoun-ah ty-ni-æn ki Heidang tou ouroung-eih, tou angat-eih, tou pou-na-væ væræ-eih-da, tou katatouro ki wa'i 'llikough-ah ta teni æhpit.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka pa'ä-tounnoun-ah ty-ni-æn ki Heidang tou ouroung-eih, tou angat-eih, tou pou-na-væ væræ-eih-da, tou katatouro ki wa'i 'llikough-ah ta teni æhpit.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende fn sullen hem den Hepdenen oberleberen om hem te bespotten ende te geesselen mde tekrupcigen ende ten derden daghe sal hp wede: opstaen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And shall deliver him to the Gentiles to mock, and to scourge, and to crucify him: and the third day he shall rise again.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">又交給外邦人，將他戲弄，鞭打，釘在十字架上；第三日他要復活。」 （可10‧35－45）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse20">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Tou kidi k'anna irou-ato tyni-æn ta Raren'an ki alalak ti Zebedeus lam ki alalak tyn, tou pako-Alilid-en tou toumimi-en-appa ki mamang tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Tou kidi k'anna irou-ato tyni-æn ta Raren'an ki alalak ti Zebedeus lam ki alalak tyn, tou pako-Alilid-en tou toumimi-en-appa ki mamang tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doe guam de moede der sonen Zebedei tot hem 'met hare sonen [bem] aenbiddende ende begeerende wat ban hem.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then came to him the mother of Zebedees children with her sons, worshipping him, and desiring a certain thing of him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那時，西庇太兒子的母親同她兩個兒子上前來拜耶穌，求他一件事。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse21">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Teni-râ ni-k'ma tyni-æn, mang ta kamoei-en-hou? Ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Pasonsou-ei ka mier-roung-ah ta rarouha ka alalak-au k'atta, ka saät-ah tou ouwal-ohou, ka saät-ah tou u-ï-ohou tou Pei-sasou-an-ohou.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Teni-râ ni-k'ma tyni-æn, mang ta kamoei-en-hou? Ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Pasonsou-ei ka mier-roung-ah ta rarouha ka alalak-au k'atta, ka saät-ah tou ouwal-ohou, ka saät-ah tou u-ï-ohou tou Pei-sasou-an-ohou.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Enihpsepde tot haer Wat wilt ghy? Sy sepde tot hem Seght dat dese myne twee sonen sitten moghen de een tot uwer rechter ende de ander tot uwer flincker[handr]inuw' Koninckrijck.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And he said unto her, What wilt thou? She saith unto him, Grant that these my two sons may sit, the one on thy right hand, and the other on the left, in thy kingdom.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：「你要甚麼呢？」她說：「願你叫我這兩個兒子在你國裏，一個坐在你右邊，一個坐在你左邊。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse22">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Rå ni-mattai-v'lli ta ti Jesus, ni-k'ma, Assi-kamou mavana ka mang ta tou-mimi-'an-noumi: Moulpough-kamou kana myt ki hæuugh ka yht-au-mau? ta'au-Ipough-en-kamou kaua mæu-lough ki Euloug-han ka æuloug-eih-koh? Ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Mou-Ipough-kame, ta'au-lpough-en kame.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Rå ni-mattai-v'lli ta ti Jesus, ni-k'ma, Assi-kamou mavana ka mang ta tou-mimi-'an-noumi: Moulpough-kamou kana myt ki hæuugh ka yht-au-mau? ta'au-Ipough-en-kamou kaua mæu-lough ki Euloug-han ka æuloug-eih-koh? Ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Mou-Ipough-kame, ta'au-lpough-en kame.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Mater Jesug antwoordde ende sepde Ghylieden en weet niet wat ghy begeert : Kondt ghy den D1inckbeker drincken die ick drincken sal : ende-met den Doop gedoopt worden daer mede ick gedoopt wordes Sy sepden tot hem Wy konnen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But Jesus answered and said, Ye know not what ye ask. Are ye able to drink of the cup that I shall drink of, and to be baptized with the baptism that I am baptized with? They say unto him, We are able.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌回答說：「你們不知道所求的是甚麼；我將要喝的杯，你們能喝嗎？」他們說：「我們能。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse23">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-k'ma ta teni neini-an, Nda-hâh myt-ah-kamou ki hæuugh-au, æulough-eih-kamou ki æuloug-han ka æuloug-eih koh, rå pa-ierroung-in tou ouwal au tou ui-appa-mau assi-mau si-kakou-an ta phan, râ [p'heih] neini-æn ka ni-si-tan-nin ti Rama-au.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-k'ma ta teni neini-an, Nda-hâh myt-ah-kamou ki hæuugh-au, æulough-eih-kamou ki æuloug-han ka æuloug-eih koh, rå pa-ierroung-in tou ouwal au tou ui-appa-mau assi-mau si-kakou-an ta phan, râ [p'heih] neini-æn ka ni-si-tan-nin ti Rama-au.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende hy seyde tot -Haer Mijnen Duinckbeke: s\ult ghp wel drincken ende met den Doop daer ick mede gedoopt worde lult ghy gedoopt wordt maee het sitten tot mijner rechter efi totmyne: flincker-[handr, J en staet by my niet te gebe mae} [het fal gegeben worden] dien het berept is ban mynen Dader.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And he saith unto them, Ye shall drink indeed of my cup, and be baptized with the baptism that I am baptized with: but to sit on my right hand, and on my left, is not mine to give, but it shall be given to them for whom it is prepared of my Father.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：「我所喝的杯，你們必要喝；只是坐在我的左右，不是我可以賜的，乃是我父為誰預備的，就賜給誰。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse24">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou ka millingígh ta sat kytti-æn [ka rarouma ki atta] ou-hang ni-tna-væingbing ki rarou ha ka mahtate'i-apara.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou ka millingígh ta sat kytti-æn [ka rarouma ki atta] ou-hang ni-tna-væingbing ki rarou ha ka mahtate'i-apara.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende als de [andere] tien [dat] hoorden namen sp het seer qualick ban de twee broeders; |</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And when the ten heard it, they were moved with indignation against the two brethren.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那十個門徒聽見，就惱怒他們弟兄二人。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse25">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka rou ni-tmætææm ta ti Jesus neini-æn pa-ou-koua tyni-æn, ni-k'ma, Kavan'an-noumi ka Si-bavau ki tautaou ta mei-sasou neini-æn, ka Meireirang ta sihka-koua ki kailhgen neini-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka rou ni-tmætææm ta ti Jesus neini-æn pa-ou-koua tyni-æn, ni-k'ma, Kavan'an-noumi ka Si-bavau ki tautaou ta mei-sasou neini-æn, ka Meireirang ta sihka-koua ki kailhgen neini-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende als haer Jesus tot hem gheroepen hadde seyde hy Ghy weer dat de Owertte der bolckeren heerschappye boeren ober hae? ende de Groote gebrupcken macht ober haer.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But Jesus called them unto him, and said, Ye know that the princes of the Gentiles exercise dominion over them, and they that are great exercise authority upon them.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌叫了他們來，說：「你們知道外邦人有君王為主治理他們，有大臣操權管束他們。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse26">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Rå assi k'ma-ah-hynna y-moumi-æn: râ timamang ymou mi-en ta mamoei-ah kauh-irang-en ki kidi, teni ta pa-iroung-au-moumi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Rå assi k'ma-ah-hynna y-moumi-æn: râ timamang ymou mi-en ta mamoei-ah kauh-irang-en ki kidi, teni ta pa-iroung-au-moumi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Dochalsooen sal het onder y niet zijn ; mae} soo wie onde: u sal willen groot worden {die} 3p uwe dienae?.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But it shall not be so among you: but whosoever will be great among you, let him be your minister;</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">只是在你們中間，不可這樣；你們中間誰願為大，就必作你們的用人；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse27">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka timamang ta mamoei-ah siouro ymoumi-æn, teni ta kouncia 'to moumi-ra.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka timamang ta mamoei-ah siouro ymoumi-æn, teni ta kouncia 'to moumi-ra.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende so wie onder u sal. fal willen de errste zijn die 3p uwe dienltknecht.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And whosoever will be chief among you, let him be your servant:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">誰願為首，就必作你們的僕人。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse28">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Mama ka assi ierrou-ato ta Alak ki ka'æuloung tou ierroung-eih tyni-æn, rå tou sau-mado-eih tyn mierroung, ka p'hæ-eil-appa ta vatti tyn tou t'aili-en mi-v'lli ki mabatoung.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Mama ka assi ierrou-ato ta Alak ki ka'æuloung tou ierroung-eih tyni-æn, rå tou sau-mado-eih tyn mierroung, ka p'hæ-eil-appa ta vatti tyn tou t'aili-en mi-v'lli ki mabatoung.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Gheliick de Sone des menschen niet en is gekomen om ghedient te worden maer om te dienen ende sijne riele te geben [ tot] een rantsoen boor bele.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Even as the Son of man came not to be ministered unto, but to minister, and to give his life a ransom for many.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">正如人子來，不是要受人的服事，乃是要服事人，並且要捨命，作多人的贖價。」 （可10‧46－52；路18‧35－43）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse29">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Nda jrou ka 't pæрæpæ nah ta neni tou Jerihgo, ni-ma-auugh tyni-æn ta makoilalaulau ka mabatoung.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Nda jrou ka 't pæрæpæ nah ta neni tou Jerihgo, ni-ma-auugh tyni-æn ta makoilalaulau ka mabatoung.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende als fp ban Jericho uyt-gingen is hem een gr00te schare gebolght.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And as they departed from Jericho, a great multitude followed him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們出耶利哥的時候，有極多的人跟隨他。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse30">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka kyttei ta rarouha ki mavouta ka mieroung tou said ki darang, jrou ka millingigh ka hmarivat ta ti Jesus, ni-mako-lang-æh tmætæäm kommo-koua, Mei-rang ka na Alak ti David, maha-rumm-ato ymian-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka kyttei ta rarouha ki mavouta ka mieroung tou said ki darang, jrou ka millingigh ka hmarivat ta ti Jesus, ni-mako-lang-æh tmætæäm kommo-koua, Mei-rang ka na Alak ti David, maha-rumm-ato ymian-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Endesiet twee blinde fittende aen den wegh als sp hoorden dat Jesus boorby ging riepen seggende Heere ghy fone Dibids ontfeymt u onler.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And, behold, two blind men sitting by the way side, when they heard that Jesus passed by, cried out, saying, Have mercy on us, O Lord, thou son of David.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">有兩個瞎子坐在路旁，聽說是耶穌經過，就喊着說：「主啊，大衛的子孫，可憐我們吧！」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse31">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Rå ni-matymha ta makoi-lalaulau neini-æn, ka maipat-ah ta neni, râ ni-makou-saoun-appa ma-ko-ton mako-lang-ah ta neni, matte'i-k'ma-hynna, Maharum-ma ymian-æn, Meirang ka na Alak ti David.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Rå ni-matymha ta makoi-lalaulau neini-æn, ka maipat-ah ta neni, râ ni-makou-saoun-appa ma-ko-ton mako-lang-ah ta neni, matte'i-k'ma-hynna, Maharum-ma ymian-æn, Meirang ka na Alak ti David.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende de schare befitafte hae op dat sy iwijgen souden mae? sy riepen te meer seggende Ontfermt n onsts] Heere ghy fone Da-</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And the multitude rebuked them, because they should hold their peace: but they cried the more, saying, Have mercy on us, O Lord, thou son of David.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">眾人責備他們，不許他們作聲；他們卻越發喊着說：「主啊，大衛的子孫，可憐我們吧！」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse32">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka rou rihkau mitouhko ta ti Jesus, ni-tmætæäm neini-æn, k'ma, Mang ta kamoei-'noumi ka pei-ringei-an-ei-mau-kamou?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka rou rihkau mitouhko ta ti Jesus, ni-tmætæäm neini-æn, k'ma, Mang ta kamoei-'noumi ka pei-ringei-an-ei-mau-kamou?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende Jesns tills] fachde riep'se ende eyde Wat wilt ghy dat ick u doe $</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And Jesus stood still, and called them, and said, What will ye that I shall do unto you?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌就站住，叫他們來，說：「要我為你們做甚麼？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse33">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ni-k'ma ta neni tyni-æn, Meirang, ka pa-rkyllat-auh ta mat-ta-jan.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ni-k'ma ta neni tyni-æn, Meirang, ka pa-rkyllat-auh ta mat-ta-jan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Sy senden tot hem Heere dat onse oogen gheopent werden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">They say unto him, Lord, that our eyes may be opened.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們說：「主啊，要我們的眼睛能看見！」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse34">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou ka ma-ymmid maha-rashas ki na mayavohak ta ti Jesus [alei ki kaharum-man,] ni-smou-kla ki matta nein, ka madis ni-kmytta ta matta nein, ka ni-ma-auugh ta neni tyui-æn. Kararouha kytti-æn'æb ki såt ki Ibah ki soulat.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou ka ma-ymmid maha-rashas ki na mayavohak ta ti Jesus [alei ki kaharum-man,] ni-smou-kla ki matta nein, ka madis ni-kmytta ta matta nein, ka ni-ma-auugh ta neni tyui-æn. Kararouha kytti-æn'æb ki såt ki Ibah ki soulat.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende Jesus innerlick bewergt 3ynde met Bam: r erhertigheydt raeckte hare ooghen am ende testont wierden hare oogen fiende ende sy bolgden hem. |</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">So Jesus had compassion on them, and touched their eyes: and immediately their eyes received sight, and they followed him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌就動了慈心，把他們的眼睛一摸，他們立刻看見，就跟從了耶穌。</TRANSL>
    </S>
</TEXT>