<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEXT id="Siraya_Dutch_Matthew_Chapter12" xml:lang="fos" source="Siraya Bible, Matthew gospel" copyright="public domain" citation="Gravius, Daniël. 1661. Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa. Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang. Amsterdam: Michiel Hartogh." BibTeX_citation="@book{Gravius1661,&#10;  author    = {Gravius, Daniël},&#10;  year      = {1661},&#10;  title     = {Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa},&#10;  note      = {Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang},&#10;  address   = {Amsterdam},&#10;  publisher = {Michiel Hartogh}&#10;}">
    <S id="verse1">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Tou kidi k'anna ni-tauqua ta ti Jesus ki na dadiri tou wæ'i ki pæ'i-hababan. ka mag-'hangei ta Pæhtatæutæu-en tyn, mabys moutout-appa ki nanagh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Tou kidi k'anna ni-tauqua ta ti Jesus ki na dadiri tou wæ'i ki pæ'i-hababan. ka mag-'hangei ta Pæhtatæutæu-en tyn, mabys moutout-appa ki nanagh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> In dien tijdt gingh Jesus op eenen Sabbathdagh door her gheraeyde endesyne Discipelen hadden hongher ende begonden ayren te plucken ende te eten.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">At that time Jesus went on the sabbath day through the corn; and his disciples were an hungred, and began to pluck the ears of corn and to eat.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那時，耶穌在安息日從麥地經過。他的門徒餓了，就掐起麥穗來吃。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse2">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka rou kytt'an [ta atta] ki Farizéen ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Kytt'ei pamut ta Pæhtatæutæu-en oho ki assi hahei-en paamut tou wæ'i ki pæ'i-hababan.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka rou kytt'an [ta atta] ki Farizéen ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Kytt'ei pamut ta Pæhtatæutæu-en oho ki assi hahei-en paamut tou wæ'i ki pæ'i-hababan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende de Pharireen[dac] fiende seyden tot hem Siet uweDiscipelen doen dat niet m is geoorlofc te doen } op den Sabbath. _</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But when the Pharisees saw it, they said unto him, Behold, thy disciples do that which is not lawful to do upon the sabbath day.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">法利賽人看見，就對耶穌說：「看哪，你的門徒做安息日不可做的事了！」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse3">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ra ni-k'ma ta teni neini-æn. Assi-kamou kaua ni-kuhting ka-mang ta ni-pei-ringei-en ti David, dou mah-gangei, neni-appa ka na lam tyn?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ra ni-k'ma ta teni neini-æn. Assi-kamou kaua ni-kuhting ka-mang ta ni-pei-ringei-en ti David, dou mah-gangei, neni-appa ka na lam tyn?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Maer hy seyde tot hae: En hebt ghy mit ghelesen wat Dabid ghedaen heeft doe hem hongerde ende haer die met Hem [waren?]</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But he said unto them, Have ye not read what David did, when he was an hungred, and they that were with him;</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌對他們說：「經上記着大衛和跟從他的人飢餓之時所做的事，你們沒有念過嗎？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse4">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Mama ki mang ka ni-mou-rbo ki tallagh ki Alid, ka ni-kman ki paoul ki pou-æmæh-in, ka assi hahei-en pakan tyni-æn ki lam-appa tyn-da: râ dyk. ki Dadyllo?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Mama ki mang ka ni-mou-rbo ki tallagh ki Alid, ka ni-kman ki paoul ki pou-æmæh-in, ka assi hahei-en pakan tyni-æn ki lam-appa tyn-da: râ dyk. ki Dadyllo?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> hoe dat hy ghegaen . in het huys Godts ende de Toon-brooden ghegheten Heeft die hem niet geoorloft waren te ecen noch oock Hae: die met hem { waren, | maer den Piielteren alleen * </TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">How he entered into the house of God, and did eat the shewbread, which was not lawful for him to eat, neither for them which were with him, but only for the priests?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他怎麼進了上帝的殿，吃了陳設餅，這餅不是他和跟從他的人可以吃得，惟獨祭司才可以吃。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse5">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Assei-kamou lava ni-kmut kut tou Tatouhko ka ni-pa-sa-sa-ram fam ta Dadyllo ki wæ'i ki pæ'i-hababan, tou ni-pa-sa-nni-en ka Kouva rou na wæ'i ki pæ'i-haba-bau, ka assi ni-mavarau ta neni?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Assei-kamou lava ni-kmut kut tou Tatouhko ka ni-pa-sa-sa-ram fam ta Dadyllo ki wæ'i ki pæ'i-hababan, tou ni-pa-sa-nni-en ka Kouva rou na wæ'i ki pæ'i-haba-bau, ka assi ni-mavarau ta neni?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ofenhebtghyniet gelesen in de Wet dat de Priefters den Sabbath ontheyligen in den Tempel op de abbath dagen ende [nochans] onschuldigh zijn</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Or have ye not read in the law, how that on the sabbath days the priests in the temple profane the sabbath, and are blameless?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">再者，律法上所記的，當安息日，祭司在殿裏犯了安息日還是沒有罪，你們沒有念過嗎？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse6">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka pasousou-en-au-kamou, Ka attaoun ta ma-saoun Meirang ki kidi ki Kouva.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka pasousou-en-au-kamou, Ka attaoun ta ma-saoun Meirang ki kidi ki Kouva.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende ick segge u Dat een meerder dan de Tempel hier is. </TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But I say unto you, That in this place is one greater than the temple.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">但我告訴你們，在這裏有一人比殿更大。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse7">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou-râ oumha'n oumi lava, ka mang k'anna, Kamoei-en-au ta kaharum-en assi ki pap hik-an, ynna-kamou assi ni-dmung-dung kmeih-kahier ki assi ni-mavarau.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou-râ oumha'n oumi lava, ka mang k'anna, Kamoei-en-au ta kaharum-en assi ki pap hik-an, ynna-kamou assi ni-dmung-dung kmeih-kahier ki assi ni-mavarau.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Doch loo ghy geweten haddet wat het ry Ick wil armhertigheyt ende niet offerande ghy en soudt de onschuldighe niet beroordeelt hebben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But if ye had known what this meaneth, I will have mercy, and not sacrifice, ye would not have condemned the guiltless.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">『我喜愛憐恤，不喜愛祭祀。』你們若明白這話的意思，就不將無罪的當作有罪的了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse8">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Kou Meirang-appa ki wæ'i ki pæ'i-habab'an ta Alak ki kaæu-loung.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Kou Meirang-appa ki wæ'i ki pæ'i-habab'an ta Alak ki kaæu-loung.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Want de Sone des menlchen is een Heereoock ban den Sabbath. --</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">For the Son of man is Lord even of the sabbath day.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">因為人子是安息日的主。」 （可3‧1－6；路6‧6－11）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse9">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka rou mali-daæua hynna, ni-iroua tou Pæu'i-sasâl-an nein.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka rou mali-daæua hynna, ni-iroua tou Pæu'i-sasâl-an nein.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende ban daer boortgaende quam hy in hare Synagoge. =</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And when he was departed thence, he went into their synagogue:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌離開那地方，進了一個會堂。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse10">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka k'ytt'ei ni-akou-kaæn-loung ka ni-ilaklak-en ki rima, ka ni-tmaligh ta neni tyni-æn, k'ma, Hahei-en kaua paka-dari-kægh tou wæ'i ki pæ'i-habab'an? (alei ka paka-vavarau-ah tyni-æn.)</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka k'ytt'ei ni-akou-kaæn-loung ka ni-ilaklak-en ki rima, ka ni-tmaligh ta neni tyni-æn, k'ma, Hahei-en kaua paka-dari-kægh tou wæ'i ki pæ'i-habab'an? (alei ka paka-vavarau-ah tyni-æn.)</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende liet daer was een mensche. die een dorre handt hadde eii sy braegden hem eggende Fs het oock gheoorloft op de Sabbathdagen te genesens (op dat sp hem mochten beschuldigen.)</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And, behold, there was a man which had his hand withered. And they asked him, saying, Is it lawful to heal on the sabbath days? that they might accuse him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那裏有一個人枯乾了一隻手。有人問耶穌說：「安息日治病可以不可以？」意思是要控告他。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse11">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-k'ma ta teni neini-æn, Toumang ta kaæuloung ymoumi-æn, ka akou-sasat ki joeko, ka rou mou-pouhto lava ta anna tou wæ'i ki pæ'i-habab'an, ka assi mæ-uh-ah pou bavau ki anna?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-k'ma ta teni neini-æn, Toumang ta kaæuloung ymoumi-æn, ka akou-sasat ki joeko, ka rou mou-pouhto lava ta anna tou wæ'i ki pæ'i-habab'an, ka assi mæ-uh-ah pou bavau ki anna?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Efihpseyde tot haer Wat mensche salder zijn onder u die cen schaep heefc efi soo dat selbe op eenen Sabbath-dagh in de gracht balt die het selbe niet en sal aenNrypen ende uptheffen +</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And he said unto them, What man shall there be among you, that shall have one sheep, and if it fall into a pit on the sabbath day, will he not lay hold on it, and lift it out?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：「你們中間誰有一隻羊，當安息日掉在坑裏，不把牠抓住、拉上來呢？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse12">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Sih-pynna-nan ki masaoun si-bavau ta kaæuloung ki joeko? Anna ta hahei-en-appa pamut ki mariang tou wæ'i ki pæ'i-habab'an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Sih-pynna-nan ki masaoun si-bavau ta kaæuloung ki joeko? Anna ta hahei-en-appa pamut ki mariang tou wæ'i ki pæ'i-habab'an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Hoe Hoe beel gaet nu een mensche een schaep te bobens Soo ilt dan op de Sabbath dagen geoorloft wel te doen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">How much then is a man better than a sheep? Wherefore it is lawful to do well on the sabbath days.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">人比羊何等貴重呢！所以，在安息日做善事是可以的。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse13">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta ni-k'ma ki vouel k'anna, Siksik-au ta rima-oho: ka ni-sik-ken tyn, ka ni-kæuh-likough kæuh-riang mama ki idi [tyn].</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta ni-k'ma ki vouel k'anna, Siksik-au ta rima-oho: ka ni-sik-ken tyn, ka ni-kæuh-likough kæuh-riang mama ki idi [tyn].</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Doe leyde hy tot dien mensche Strecktuwehandt uyt : ende hy fireckcele uyt ende sy weedt herstelt gesont geliick de andere,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then saith he to the man, Stretch forth thine hand. And he stretched it forth; and it was restored whole, like as the other.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">於是對那人說：「伸出手來！」他把手一伸，手就復了原，和那隻手一樣。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse14">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou ka ni-mou-mala ta Farizéen, ni-maki-sâl ki sou maki-doumma tyni-æn, mameimang ka pa-rmarma-ah tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou ka ni-mou-mala ta Farizéen, ni-maki-sâl ki sou maki-doumma tyni-æn, mameimang ka pa-rmarma-ah tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende de Pharireen uytghegaen zijnde hielden t samen raedt tegen hem hoe sy hem dooden mochten,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then the Pharisees went out, and held a council against him, how they might destroy him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">法利賽人出去，商議怎樣可以除滅耶穌。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse15">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ tou oumh-an ti Jesus [ta atta] ni-d'marang hynna, ka mara-rap ta makoi-lalaulau ka ni-mæu-æuugh tyni-æn, ka ni-paka-ymd-en tyn paka-darikægh neini-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ tou oumh-an ti Jesus [ta atta] ni-d'marang hynna, ka mara-rap ta makoi-lalaulau ka ni-mæu-æuugh tyni-æn, ka ni-paka-ymd-en tyn paka-darikægh neini-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> MWae Jesus [dat]wetende bertrock ban daer ende bele charen bolgden hem ende hy genas fe alle.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But when Jesus knew it, he withdrew himself from thence: and great multitudes followed him, and he healed them all;</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌知道了，就離開那裏，有許多人跟着他。他把其中有病的人都治好了；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse16">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-singigh mavagh nei-ni-æn, ka assi paka-æmæh-ah tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-singigh mavagh nei-ni-æn, ka assi paka-æmæh-ah tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende gheboodt hae; Trhepelick dat ly hem niet openbaer maken en sonden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And charged them that they should not make him known:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">又囑咐他們，不要給他傳名。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse17">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Alei ka pa-uft-aul-ato ta na sou ki na Tama-mattæi-tan ka ti Esajas, koun,</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Alei ka pa-uft-aul-ato ta na sou ki na Tama-mattæi-tan ka ti Esajas, koun,</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Opdatberbult soude worden het gene ghelproken 1s doo? Jelaiam den Pr0pheet leggende </TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">That it might be fulfilled which was spoken by Esaias the prophet, saying,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">這是要應驗先知以賽亞的話，說：</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse18">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> K'ytt'ei ta rarauwei-au, ka ni-peri-au, ka kævæ-ango-en au, ka kam-au-in ki vatti-au. Pou-halap-au-mau tyni-æn ta Joep-an-au, ka gnau-eih tyn ta dungdung-an ki Heidang.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> K'ytt'ei ta rarauwei-au, ka ni-peri-au, ka kævæ-ango-en au, ka kam-au-in ki vatti-au. Pou-halap-au-mau tyni-æn ta Joep-an-au, ka gnau-eih tyn ta dungdung-an ki Heidang.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Siet mijnen Knecht welcken ick berkoren hebbe mynen Beminden in welcKen myn riele een wel-behagen heefc, Ick sal mijnen Geeft op hem leggen ende Hy sal het oordeel den Heydenen berkondigen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Behold my servant, whom I have chosen; my beloved, in whom my soul is well pleased: I will put my spirit upon him, and he shall shew judgment to the Gentiles.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">看哪！我的僕人，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse19">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Assi marangi-rangil-ah, assi hmouwauwau-ah, assi millingig-ah ta ta timamang tou dara-darang ki jngau tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Assi marangi-rangil-ah, assi hmouwauwau-ah, assi millingig-ah ta ta timamang tou dara-darang ki jngau tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Hy ensal niet twitten noch rotpen noch daer en sal nieniemant sijne fttemme op de ftraten hooren.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">He shall not strive, nor cry; neither shall any man hear his voice in the streets.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他不爭競，不喧嚷；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse20">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Assi pa-'ou-nḡi-touagh ki htigh ka ni-mou-pto, assi pa-i-oup-auh tyn ta pourut ka maahto, tou kidi-al-appa ka pou-daæua-ah pou-pænæh ki dingding-en tou tatou-noun-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Assi pa-'ou-nḡi-touagh ki htigh ka ni-mou-pto, assi pa-i-oup-auh tyn ta pourut ka maahto, tou kidi-al-appa ka pou-daæua-ah pou-pænæh ki dingding-en tou tatou-noun-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Het gekroockte riet en fal hy niet berbrcken ende het roockende lemmet en sal hy metupt-blusschen tor dat hy het oordeel sal uptbrengen tot oberwinninge.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">A bruised reed shall he not break, and smoking flax shall he not quench, till he send forth judgment unto victory.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">壓傷的蘆葦，他不折斷；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse21">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka mitaddug-ah ta Hei-dang tou Nanang tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka mitaddug-ah ta Heidang tou Nanang tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende in shnen Name sullen de Hepdenen hopen,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And in his name shall the Gentiles trust.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">外邦人都要仰望他的名。 （可3‧20－30；路11‧14－23）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse22">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Tou kidi k'anna ni-addan päouqua tyni-æn ta saät-ka ni-ou-Lyttou, ka mavouta, ka mangou-pou, ka ni-paka-darikah-en tyn tyni-æn, tou kidi ka k'ma-hynna ka masousou-ato kmytta ta nimavou-ta k'anna ka ni-mangoupou-appa.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Tou kidi k'anna ni-addan päouqua tyni-æn ta saät-ka ni-ou-Lyttou, ka mavouta, ka mangou-pou, ka ni-paka-darikah-en tyn tyni-æn, tou kidi ka k'ma-hynna ka masousou-ato kmytta ta nimavou-ta k'anna ka ni-mangoupou-appa.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Doe wiert tot hem gebrachteen ban den Dupbel beseten [die] blindt ende ftom [was,] ende hy ghenas hem alsoo dat de blinde ende stonune beyde sprack ende sagh. </TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then was brought unto him one possessed with a devil, blind, and dumb: and he healed him, insomuch that the blind and dumb both spake and saw.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">當下，有人將一個被鬼附着、又瞎又啞的人帶到耶穌那裏，耶穌就醫治他，甚至那啞巴又能說話，又能看見。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse23">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka 'ni-ennagh ta ymmid ki makoilalaulau, ka ni-k'ma, Assi kaua na Alak ti David ta ti atta?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka 'ni-ennagh ta ymmid ki makoilalaulau, ka ni-k'ma, Assi kaua na Alak ti David ta ti atta?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Efialledescharenontsetteden haer ende sepd? Js niet dese de Sone Dabids +</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And all the people were amazed, and said, Is not this the son of David?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">眾人都驚奇，說：「這不是大衛的子孫嗎？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse24">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka rou illing-hen [ta atta] ki Farizéen, ni-k'ma, Assi pada-rang ta ti atta ki Lyttou, dyk ki Beelzebul, ka Si-bavau ki Lyttou-Lyttou.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka rou illing-hen [ta atta] ki Farizéen, ni-k'ma, Assi pada-rang ta ti atta ki Lyttou, dyk ki Beelzebul, ka Si-bavau ki Lyttou-Lyttou.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Maer de Pharireen [dit]gchoort Hebbende leydt Dese en werpt de Duybclen niet uyt dan door Beelrebul den Obersten der Duybelen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But when the Pharisees heard it, they said, This fellow doth not cast out devils, but by Beelzebub the prince of the devils.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">但法利賽人聽見，就說：「這個人趕鬼，無非是靠着鬼王別西卜啊。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse25">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou ka moumha ta ti Je-sus ki na-ddarimdim nein, ni-ma-sousou neini-æn, Ymmid ki Pei-sasou-an ka pæ'i-pa pouropouroh neini-æn mamado, paka pæpæu-læg-auh paka soupok: ymd-appa ki æuma ki tallagh-lava ka pæ'i-æumaæuma, pæ'i-tallatallagh nei-ni-æn mamado, assi itou kaqua'h ta anna-râ</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou ka moumha ta ti Je-sus ki na-ddarimdim nein, ni-ma-sousou neini-æn, Ymmid ki Pei-sasou-an ka pæ'i-pa pouropouroh neini-æn mamado, paka pæpæu-læg-auh paka soupok: ymd-appa ki æuma ki tallagh-lava ka pæ'i-æumaæuma, pæ'i-tallatallagh nei-ni-æn mamado, assi itou kaqua'h ta anna-râ</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Doch Jesus kennende hare gedachten sepde tot hatr Een yeder Koninckryck dat tegen hem-selben berdeelt 1s wort berwoelt : ende een peder stadt ofte huys dat teghen hem-elben perdeele is en sal niet beaen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And Jesus knew their thoughts, and said unto them, Every kingdom divided against itself is brought to desolation; and every city or house divided against itself shall not stand:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌知道他們的意念，就對他們說：「凡一國自相紛爭，就成為荒場；一城一家自相紛爭，必站立不住；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse26">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka rou padarang ta Lyttou ki Lyttou-an, pa-pah-piah-auh ty-ni-æn mamado ka itou kaqua'h mama ki mang ta pei-sasou-an tyn?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka rou padarang ta Lyttou ki Lyttou-an, pa-pah-piah-auh ty-ni-æn mamado ka itou kaqua'h mama ki mang ta pei-sasou-an tyn?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> EnEnde indien de Satan den Satan uptwerpt soo is hy tege hem-selben berdeelt: hoe sal dan [ijn riick bestae $</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And if Satan cast out Satan, he is divided against himself; how shall then his kingdom stand?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">若撒但趕逐撒但，就是自相紛爭，他的國怎能站得住呢？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse27">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou ka padarang-en-au ta Lyttou ki Beelzebul, padarang-en ta neni timang-an ki alalak-oumi? Alei ki anna Tama-dmung-dung-ah ta neni ymoumi-æn</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou ka padarang-en-au ta Lyttou ki Beelzebul, padarang-en ta neni timang-an ki alalak-oumi? Alei ki anna Tama-dmung-dung-ah ta neni ymoumi-æn</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende indien ick doo? Beelrebul de Bupbelen uptweype door wien werpense dan uwe sonen yyt-Daerom fullen die uwe rechters zijn.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And if I by Beelzebub cast out devils, by whom do your children cast them out? therefore they shall be your judges.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我若靠着別西卜趕鬼，你們的子弟趕鬼又靠着誰呢？這樣，他們就要斷定你們的是非。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse28">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou râ padarang-en-au ta Lyttou ki Joepan ki Alid, anna ta jrou-'ato ymoumi-æn ta Pei-sasou-an ki Alid.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou râ padarang-en-au ta Lyttou ki Joepan ki Alid, anna ta jrou-'ato ymoumi-æn ta Pei-sasou-an ki Alid.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Maer indien ick door den Geelt Godts de Duybelen uptwerpe lo is dan het Honinckryck Godts tot u gekomen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But if I cast out devils by the Spirit of God, then the kingdom of God is come unto you.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我若靠着上帝的靈趕鬼，這就是上帝的國臨到你們了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse29">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka mou-lpough-ah mama ki mang mourbo ta timamang ki tallagh ki siouro maligh pa-sau-ara ki satô tyn, rou assi tyn ali-ouro-en bæuut ta siouro maligh, anna ta pasau-ara-ah ki tallagh tyn?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka mou-lpough-ah mama ki mang mourbo ta timamang ki tallagh ki siouro maligh pa-sau-ara ki satô tyn, rou assi tyn ali-ouro-en bæuut ta siouro maligh, anna ta pasau-ara-ah ki tallagh tyn?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Oftehoekanpyemant in het huys eens stercken in komen ende sijne baten ontrooben het en 3p dat hy ee:st den stercken ghebonden hebbe ende als dan sal hy syn huys berooben +</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Or else how can one enter into a strong man's house, and spoil his goods, except he first bind the strong man? and then he will spoil his house.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">人怎能進壯士家裏，搶奪他的家具呢？除非先捆住那壯士，才可以搶奪他的家財。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse30">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Timamang ta assi tou-lam jau-an, teni ta makou-doumma jau-an: timamang-appa ta assi pæ-pah-kipou pæ-pæ'i-sâl tou-lam jau-an, pa-pæh-piæh ta teni.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Timamang ta assi tou-lam jau-an, teni ta makou-doumma jau-an: timamang-appa ta assi pæ-pah-kipou pæ-pæ'i-sâl tou-lam jau-an, pa-pæh-piæh ta teni.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Wie met my niet en is die is tegen my : ende wie met my niet en bergadert die besstopt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">He that is not with me is against me; and he that gathereth not with me scattereth abroad.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">不與我相合的，就是敵我的；不同我收聚的，就是分散的。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse31">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Alei ki atta pa-sousou-en-au-kamou, Ymmid ki varau ki barg-han-appa makou-talum atta-ral-eih ki kaæuloung: râ barg-han makou-talum ka makou-doumma ki Joep-an, assi atta-ral-eih ki ka-æuloung.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Alei ki atta pa-sousou-en-au-kamou, Ymmid ki varau ki barg-han-appa makou-talum atta-ral-eih ki kaæuloung: râ barg-han makou-talum ka makou-doumma ki Joep-an, assi atta-ral-eih ki ka-æuloung.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Daeyom legge ick u Alle sonde ende lasteringhe sal den menschen bergheben worden : mae: de lasteringhe teghen den Geest en sal den menschen niet bergeben woren,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Wherefore I say unto you, All manner of sin and blasphemy shall be forgiven unto men: but the blasphemy against the Holy Ghost shall not be forgiven unto men.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">所以我告訴你們：「人一切的罪和褻瀆的話都可得赦免，惟獨褻瀆聖靈，總不得赦免。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse32">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka timamang ta masousou-al-ato ki mamang ka sou mattæi-doumma ki Alak ki kaæuloung, atta-ral-eih tyni-æn [ta atta]: rå ti-mamang ta mattæ'i-douma-doum-'al-ato ki Joep-an ka D'lligh Ma-tiktik, assi atta-ral-eih tyni-æn ta atta, assi tou jdari-noug-han k'atta ka hnyn, assi tou atta-appa ka irou-ah dou rouman.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka timamang ta masousou-al-ato ki mamang ka sou mattæi-doumma ki Alak ki kaæuloung, atta-ral-eih tyni-æn [ta atta]: rå ti-mamang ta mattæ'i-douma-doum-'al-ato ki Joep-an ka D'lligh Ma-tiktik, assi atta-ral-eih tyni-æn ta atta, assi tou jdari-noug-han k'atta ka hnyn, assi tou atta-appa ka irou-ah dou rouman.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende soo wie [eenig ] woort gesproken sal hebben teteghen den Sone des mensche het sal hem bergeben worden : maer soo wie tegen den Heyligen Geelt sal ghesproken hebben her en sal hem niet bergeben worden noch in dese eeuwe noch in de torckomende.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And whosoever speaketh a word against the Son of man, it shall be forgiven him: but whosoever speaketh against the Holy Ghost, it shall not be forgiven him, neither in this world, neither in the world to come.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">凡說話干犯人子的，還可得赦免；惟獨說話干犯聖靈的，今世來世總不得赦免。」 （路6‧43－45）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse33">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Da pou-kidi-â matta-rÿh, ka mariang lava ta pærænnæh, mariang-appa ta voua tyn: ka assi mariang lava ta pærænnæh, ki voua-appa tyn. Ka kalangin ki voua ta pærænnæh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Da pou-kidi-â matta-rÿh, ka mariang lava ta pærænnæh, mariang-appa ta voua tyn: ka assi mariang lava ta pærænnæh, ki voua-appa tyn. Ka kalangin ki voua ta pærænnæh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ofce maeckt den boom goet ende syne byucht goet : ofte marckt den boom quaet ende lijne buchr quaet. Want uyt de brucht wordt de boom gekent.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Either make the tree good, and his fruit good; or else make the tree corrupt, and his fruit corrupt: for the tree is known by his fruit.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">「你們或以為樹好，果子也好；樹壞，果子也壞；因為看果子就可以知道樹。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse34">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Na kubkub ki tpoung, pou-lpough-kamou mama ki mang pou-sou ki mariang rou matt-'e-kamou-ra, ka tou pattau-louaf-en ki tintin masousou ta mou-tous.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Na kubkub ki tpoung, pou-lpough-kamou mama ki mang pou-sou ki mariang rou matt-'e-kamou-ra, ka tou pattau-louaf-en ki tintin masousou ta moutous.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Op adderen gebroedfels hoe kondt ghp goede dinghen spreecken daer ghy boos rhjt want nyt den oberbloedt des herten spreeckt de mondt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">O generation of vipers, how can ye, being evil, speak good things? for out of the abundance of the heart the mouth speaketh.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">毒蛇的種類！你們既是惡人，怎能說出好話來呢？因為心裏所充滿的，口裏就說出來。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse35">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ta'u ka mariang pou-pæ-næh ki mariang ki ka-vang-el-an ka mariang ki tintin, ta'u-appa ka matt-'e pou-pænæh ki assi mariang ki kavang-ei-an ka matt-'e.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ta'u ka mariang pou-pæ-næh ki mariang ki ka-vang-el-an ka mariang ki tintin, ta'u-appa ka matt-'e pou-pænæh ki assi mariang ki kavang-ei-an ka matt-'e.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Be goede mensche brenght gorde dingen boort upt den goeden schat des herten ende de boose mensche brenght boofe dingen boott uyt den boosen schat,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">A good man out of the good treasure of the heart bringeth forth good things: and an evil man out of the evil treasure bringeth forth evil things.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">善人從他心裏所存的善就發出善來；惡人從他心裏所存的惡就發出惡來。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse36">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ pafoufou-en-au-kamou Ka na sasasat ki nino ka sou ka pasousou-eil-ato ki kææuloung, ka mei-vli-ah ta neni kuhting ki anna tou wæ'i ki papæmæmæh-en.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ pafoufou-en-au-kamou Ka na sasasat ki nino ka sou ka pasousou-eil-ato ki kææuloung, ka mei-vli-ah ta neni kuhting ki anna tou wæ'i ki papæmæmæh-en.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Maet ick segghe u Dat ban elck ydel woort het welck de menschen sullen gesproken hebben sy ban het selbe sullen rekenschap geben in den daghe des oordeels.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But I say unto you, That every idle word that men shall speak, they shall give account thereof in the day of judgment.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我又告訴你們，凡人所說的閒話，當審判的日子，必要句句供出來；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse37">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka pou-tiktik-eih-kamon ki na sou-oumi, ka ding-ding-eih-kamou ki na sou-oumi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka pou-tiktik-eih-kamon ki na sou-oumi, ka ding-ding-eih-kamou ki na sou-oumi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Want uyt uwe woorden sult gy gerechtbeerdight worrden efi uyt uwe woorden fult gp beroordeelt worden. </TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">For by thy words thou shalt be justified, and by thy words thou shalt be condemned.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">因為要憑你的話定你為義，也要憑你的話定你有罪。」 （可8‧11－12；路11‧29－32）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse38">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta ni-mattæi-vli ta rarouma ki Mako-sasoulat ki Fari-zéen-appa ka ni-k'ma, Mahtatæu-tæuh kamoei-'nian kmytta ka pa-amt-ei-'m-hou ta pou-kidi-en.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta ni-mattæi-vli ta rarouma ki Mako-sasoulat ki Fari-zéen-appa ka ni-k'ma, Mahtatæu-tæuh kamoei-'nian kmytta ka pa-amt-ei-'m-hou ta pou-kidi-en.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Boe antwoordden fommige der Schrifrgeleerde ende Pharireen seggende Meefter wp wilden ban u [wel] een teecken sien,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then certain of the scribes and of the Pharisees answered, saying, Master, we would see a sign from thee.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">當時，有幾個文士和法利賽人對耶穌說：「夫子，我們願意你顯個神蹟給我們看。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse39">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ teni ta mattæi-vli ni-k'ma neini-æn, Kavouyl-an ka matt'-e ka rarbourbo tmoumimia ki pou-kidi-en, ka assi phæ-an-eil-ato neini-æn, dyk ki na pou-kaki-di ki na Tama-mattæi-tan ka ti Jonas.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ teni ta mattæi-vli ni-k'ma neini-æn, Kavouyl-an ka matt'-e ka rarbourbo tmoumimia ki pou-kidi-en, ka assi phæ-an-eil-ato neini-æn, dyk ki na pou-kaki-di ki na Tama-mattæi-tan ka ti Jonas.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Maet hy antwoordde ende sepde cot haer Det boos ende oberspeligh gheslachte bessoeckt een teecken ende hae? en sal geen teecken gegeben worden dan het teecen Jone des Propheten.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But he answered and said unto them, An evil and adulterous generation seeketh after a sign; and there shall no sign be given to it, but the sign of the prophet Jonas:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌回答說：「一個邪惡淫亂的世代求看神蹟，除了先知約拿的神蹟以外，再沒有神蹟給他們看。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse40">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka mama ka ni-makka-touro ki wæ'i, makka-touro-appa ki æuvan ta ti Jonas tou vouyl ki mæuæu, makka-touro-ah k'ma-hynna ki wæ'i ki æuvan ta Alak ki kaæuloung tou tintin [ka raroun] ki Næi-râ.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka mama ka ni-makka-touro ki wæ'i, makka-touro-appa ki æuvan ta ti Jonas tou vouyl ki mæuæu, makka-touro-ah k'ma-hynna ki wæ'i ki æuvan ta Alak ki kaæuloung tou tintin [ka raroun] ki Næi-râ.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Want gelyck Jonas die dagen ende drie nachten was in den bupck des walbisch alfoo sal be Sone des menschen drie daghen ende diie nachten wesen in het Herte der aerden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">For as Jonas was three days and three nights in the whale's belly; so shall the Son of man be three days and three nights in the heart of the earth.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">約拿三日三夜在大魚肚腹中，人子也要這樣三日三夜在地裏頭。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse41">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Æhpit-ah ta pæpæræh ka makka Ninive tou papæmæmæh-en lam ki kavavouyl-an k'atta, dmung-dung neini-æn: ka ni-si-lala nipa-sa-likough ki vana nein ki rÿh tou ni-patta-sasou-an ti Jo-nas. Ka kytt'ei masaoun tou vavau ki kidi ti Jonas-an, attaoun hia.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Æhpit-ah ta pæpæræh ka makka Ninive tou papæmæmæh-en lam ki kavavouyl-an k'atta, dmung-dung neini-æn: ka ni-si-lala nipa-sa-likough ki vana nein ki rÿh tou ni-patta-sasou-an ti Jo-nas. Ka kytt'ei masaoun tou vavau ki kidi ti Jonas-an, attaoun hia.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> De mannen ban Ninebe sullen opstaen in het dordeel met dit geflachte ende sullen Het selbe bero0rdeelen : want sy hebben haer bekeert op de predikinghe Jone. Ende siet meer dan Jonas 1s hier,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The men of Nineveh shall rise in judgment with this generation, and shall condemn it: because they repented at the preaching of Jonas; and, behold, a greater than Jonas is here.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">當審判的時候，尼尼微人要起來定這世代的罪，因為尼尼微人聽了約拿所傳的就悔改了。看哪，在這裏有一人比約拿更大！</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse42">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Æhpit-ah ta Si-bavau ka Mei-sasou ka jna ka makka-ti-mæuh tou papæmæmæh-in lam ki kavouyl-an k'atta, dmung-dung neini-æn: alei ka ni-iroua makka kidi ki Næi millingigh ki na kaka-koussa-cyng ti Salomon. Ka k'yt-t'ei, masaoun tou vavau ki kidi ti Salomon-an, attaoun hia.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Æhpit-ah ta Si-bavau ka Mei-sasou ka jna ka makka-ti-mæuh tou papæmæmæh-in lam ki kavouyl-an k'atta, dmung-dung neini-æn: alei ka ni-iroua makka kidi ki Næi millingigh ki na kaka-koussa-cyng ti Salomon. Ka k'yt-t'ei, masaoun tou vavau ki kidi ti Salomon-an, attaoun hia.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> De honinginne ban Het Zuyden sal opftaen in Het oordeel met dit geflachte ende het selbe beroordeelen:want sy is gekomen ban de eynden der acrde om te. hooren de whshende Salomons. Ende liet merrpan Salomon is hier.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The queen of the south shall rise up in the judgment with this generation, and shall condemn it: for she came from the uttermost parts of the earth to hear the wisdom of Solomon; and, behold, a greater than Solomon is here.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">當審判的時候，南方的女王要起來定這世代的罪； 因為她從地極而來，要聽所羅門的智慧話。看哪，在這裏有一人比所羅門更大！」 （路11‧24－26）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse43">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka rou d'marang-al-ato makka-rbo ki kæuloung ta Joep-an ka assi matikanagh, damiaka sahka-quan tyn mou-naunang tou itouquan ka markæh kma-ki-ym ki pæ'i-habab'-eih tyn, râ assi tyn paki-valei-in.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka rou d'marang-al-ato makka-rbo ki kæuloung ta Joep-an ka assi matikanagh, damiaka sahka-quan tyn mou-naunang tou itouquan ka markæh kma-ki-ym ki pæ'i-habab'-eih tyn, râ assi tyn paki-valei-in.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende wannee? de onrepne geelt bau den mensche uptgegaen 1s soo gaet hy door dorrs plaetsen loeckende rulte maer en bindtle niet.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">When the unclean spirit is gone out of a man, he walketh through dry places, seeking rest, and findeth none.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">「污鬼離了人身，就在無水之地過來過去，尋求安歇之處，卻尋不着。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse44">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta pa-sousou-en tyn, Sa-likough-ah-koh mou-qua tou tallagh-au, ka ni-darang-en-au: ka rou iroua, paki-valei-en tyn ka kouhko ka ni-ouwap-pan ki ou-wap tmoura paka-tabung ta anna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta pa-sousou-en tyn, Sa-likough-ah-koh mou-qua tou tallagh-au, ka ni-darang-en-au: ka rou iroua, paki-valei-en tyn ka kouhko ka ni-ouwap-pan ki ou-wap tmoura paka-tabung ta anna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Dan leght hy Ack sal weder keeren in myn huys ban waer ick uptghegaen ben : ende komende bindt hy het ledigh met besemen gekeert ende berciert.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then he saith, I will return into my house from whence I came out; and when he is come, he findeth it empty, swept, and garnished.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">於是說：『我要回到我所出來的屋裏去。』到了，就看見裏面空閒，打掃乾淨，修飾好了，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse45">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta 'ou-koun tyn mara pa-toulam tyni-æn pipito ki Joep-an ka pani ka masaoun matt-'e ty-ni-æn mamado, ka rou ni-sararbo itouqua ta neni hynna, ka æ'æuh ki kaæuloung k'anna paka-saoun-en pakatt'e ki na ouro tyn. K'ma-al-appa hynna ki kavouyl-an k'atta ka matt-'e.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta 'ou-koun tyn mara pa-toulam tyni-æn pipito ki Joep-an ka pani ka masaoun matt-'e ty-ni-æn mamado, ka rou ni-sararbo itouqua ta neni hynna, ka æ'æuh ki kaæuloung k'anna paka-saoun-en pakatt'e ki na ouro tyn. K'ma-al-appa hynna ki kavouyl-an k'atta ka matt-'e.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Dangaet hy henen ende neemt met hem seben andere geesten booser dan hy selbe ende in-ghegaen zijnde woonense aldaer nde het lartlte des selben mensches wordt erger dan het eerste. Aloo sal het oock met dit boos geslachte zijn.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then goeth he, and taketh with himself seven other spirits more wicked than himself, and they enter in and dwell there: and the last state of that man is worse than the first. Even so shall it be also unto this wicked generation.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">便去另帶了七個比自己更惡的鬼來，都進去住在那裏。那人末後的景況比先前更不好了。這邪惡的世代也要如此。」 （可3‧31－35；路8‧19－21）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse46">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka rou pasousou-en-appa tyn ki makoi-lalaulau, kytt-'ei ta ti rena ki tæ'i-apapa-r-appa tyn ta ni-mitoukko itou-mala, kmi-ym ki pasousou-ei nein tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka rou pasousou-en-appa tyn ki makoi-lalaulau, kytt'ei ta ti rena ki tæ'i-apapa-r-appa tyn ta ni-mitoukko itou-mala, kmi-ym ki pasousou-ei nein tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende als hy noch tot de scharen sprack siet stjne moeder ende boeders stonden buyten soeckende hem te spreken.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">While he yet talked to the people, behold, his mother and his brethren stood without, desiring to speak with him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌還對眾人說話的時候，不料他母親和他弟兄站在外邊，要與他說話。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse47">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-k'ma ta ti ano tyni-æn, Kytt'ei, itou-ma-'la hynna mi-toukko ta ti rena ki tæ'i-appa-rapp-amhou, kmi-ym kipasousou-ei nein ym-hou-an,</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-k'ma ta ti ano tyni-æn, Kytt'ei, itou-ma-'la hynna mi-toukko ta ti rena ki tæ'i-appa-rapp-amhou, kmi-ym kipasousou-ei nein ym-hou-an,</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende yemant [eyde tot hem Siet uwe moeder ende uwe broeders fkaen [daer] buyten soeckende u te spreken. :</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then one said unto him, Behold, thy mother and thy brethren stand without, desiring to speak with thee.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">有人告訴他說：「看哪，你母親和你弟兄站在外邊，要與你說話。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse48">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ ni-mattæi-vli ta teni k'ma tyni-æn ka bana [ki atta], Timang ta Rarenan-au? timang-ta tæ'i-appa para-au?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ ni-mattæi-vli ta teni k'ma tyni-æn ka bana [ki atta], Timang ta Rarenan-au? timang-ta tæ'i-appa para-au?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Mac Hy antwoordende sepde tot den gener die em hem dar] sepde Wie is myne moede? ende wie zijn myne broedyus</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But he answered and said unto him that told him, Who is my mother? and who are my brethren?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他卻回答那人說：「誰是我的母親？誰是我的弟兄？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse49">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka rou sikkiskigh ki rima tyn mei-vavau ki Patatæutæu-en tyn, ni-k'ma, K'ytt'ei ta Rarenan-au, ki tæi-appara-appa-mau.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka rou sikkiskigh ki rima tyn mei-vavau ki Patatæutæu-en tyn, ni-k'ma, K'ytt'ei ta Rarenan-au, ki tæi-appara-appa-mau.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende ijne handt uytlteckende obe: lijne Dilcipelen lepde Siet mijne moeder ende mijne broedees.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And he stretched forth his hand toward his disciples, and said, Behold my mother and my brethren!</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">就伸手指着門徒，說：「看哪，我的母親，我的弟兄。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse50">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka timamang ta paamt-al-ato ki kamoei-in ki Rama-au ka tou tounnoun ki vullu-vullum, teni ta tæ'i-appara-au, ki Niæhæ, ki Re-na-appa-mau. Ka sasat kytti-æn'æb' ki touro ki lbægh ki soulat.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka timamang ta paamt-al-ato ki kamoei-in ki Rama-au ka tou tounnoun ki vullu-vullum, teni ta tæ'i-appara-au, ki Niæhæ, ki Re-na-appa-mau. Ka sasat kytti-æn'æb' ki touro ki lbægh ki soulat.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Want so wie den wille mijns Daders doer die mde Hemelen is defclbe 18 mijn broeder ende sulker ende moeder.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">For whosoever shall do the will of my Father which is in heaven, the same is my brother, and sister, and mother.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">凡遵行我天父旨意的人，就是我的弟兄姊妹和母親了。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
</TEXT>