<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEXT id="Siraya_Dutch_Matthew_Chapter10" xml:lang="fos" source="Siraya Bible, Matthew gospel" copyright="public domain" citation="Gravius, Daniël. 1661. Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa. Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang. Amsterdam: Michiel Hartogh." BibTeX_citation="@book{Gravius1661,&#10;  author    = {Gravius, Daniël},&#10;  year      = {1661},&#10;  title     = {Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa},&#10;  note      = {Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang},&#10;  address   = {Amsterdam},&#10;  publisher = {Michiel Hartogh}&#10;}" dialect="Siraya">
    <S id="verse1">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka ni-tætææm tyn (paouqua) tyni-æn ki Pæhtatæu-tæu-en tyn ka sasat kyttien æb ki rouha, niphæn tyn neini-æn ki kailhg-en ki padarang-auh ta joep-an ka assi matikanagh (ki rÿh) ki padari-kag-eil-appa ta ka'æu-hayng-en.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka nitætææm tyn (paouqua) tyniæn ki Pæhtatæutæuen tyn ka sasat kyttien æb ki rouha, niphæn tyn neiniæn ki kailhgen ki padarangauh ta joepan ka assi matikanagh (ki rÿh) ki padarikageilappa ta ka'æuhayngen.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende sijne twaelf Ditcipelen tot hem gheroepen hebbende heeft haer macht gegheben ober de onrepne gheelten om deselbe uyt te werpen ende om alle ieckfieckte ende quale te ghenen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And when he had called unto him his twelve disciples, he gave them power against unclean spirits, to cast them out, and to heal all manner of sickness and all manner of disease.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌叫了十二個門徒來，給他們權柄，能趕逐污鬼，並醫治各樣的病症。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse2">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Atta hnyn ta nanang ki Padadingi-an ka sasat kytti-en æb ki rouha: Siouro ta ti Simon ka si-ouwa Petrus, ti Andreas-appa ka tæi-appara tyn: ti Jakobus (ka alak) ti Zebedeus, ti Joannes-appa ka tæi-appara tyn,</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Atta hnyn ta nanang ki Padadingian ka sasat kyttien æb ki rouha: Siouro ta ti Simon ka siouwa Petrus, ti Andreasappa ka tæiappara tyn: ti Jakobus (ka alak) ti Zebedeus, ti Joannesappa ka tæiappara tyn,</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">De naemen nu der twaelf Apostelen zijn dese : De eerlte Simon gheseght Petrus ende Andreas syn broeder : Jacobus de (fone) Zebedei ende Joannes fiji broeder</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Now the names of the twelve apostles are these; The first, Simon, who is called Peter, and Andrew his brother; James the son of Zebedee, and John his brother;</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">這十二使徒的名：頭一個叫西門（又稱彼得），還有他兄弟安得烈，西庇太的兒子雅各和雅各的兄弟約翰，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse3">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ti Filippus ti Bartholomæus-appa: ti Thomas ti Matthæus-appa ka na tama-imigh: ti Jakobus (ka alak) ti Alfeus, ti Lebbeus-appa ka pa-si-ou-an Thaddeus.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ti Filippus ti Bartholomæusappa: ti Thomas ti Matthæusappa ka na tamaimigh: ti Jakobus (ka alak) ti Alfeus, ti Lebbeusappa ka pasiouan Thaddeus.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Philippus ende Bartholomeus; Thomas ende Matthens de Tollenaer : Jacobus de {fone} Alphet ende Lebbeus toeghenaemt Thaddeus,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Philip, and Bartholomew; Thomas, and Matthew the publican; James the son of Alphaeus, and Lebbaeus, whose surname was Thaddaeus;</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">腓力和巴多羅買，多馬和稅吏馬太，亞勒腓的兒子雅各，和達太，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse4">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ti Simon Kananites, ti Judas Iskariotes-appa ka ni-si-tounnoun (si hm'amha) tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ti Simon Kananites, ti Judas Iskariotesappa ka nisitounnoun (si hm'amha) tyniæn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Simon Cananites ende Judas Jleartotes die hem oock berraden heefc.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Simon the Canaanite, and Judas Iscariot, who also betrayed him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">奮銳黨的西門，還有賣耶穌的加略人猶大。 （可6‧7－13；路9‧1－6）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse5">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Sasat kyttien æb ki rouha k'anna ta ni-padadingi-en ti Jesus, ka ni-makou sou neini-æn, koun, Asi-kamou mou qua-ah tou darang ki Heidang, ka assi-kamou mou-rbo-ah tou æuma-æuma ki Samaritanen.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Sasat kyttien æb ki rouha k'anna ta nipadadingien ti Jesus, ka nimakou sou neiniæn, koun, Asikamou mou quaah tou darang ki Heidang, ka assikamou mourboah tou æumaæuma ki Samaritanen.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Dese twaelbe heeft Jeus uytgesonden efi haer bebel gegeben feggende Ghy en sult niet henen gaen op DE wegh der Heydenen noch gy en fuit niet in gaen in(eenige) fladt der Samaritant.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">These twelve Jesus sent forth, and commanded them, saying, Go not into the way of the Gentiles, and into any city of the Samaritans enter ye not:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌差這十二個人去，吩咐他們說：＂外邦人的路，你們不要走；撒馬利亞人的城，你們不要進；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse6">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ra si-ouro-â sahkaqua tou hmi-taraæuh ka jouko ki tallagh ki Israel.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ra siouroâ sahkaqua tou hmitaraæuh ka jouko ki tallagh ki Israel.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Mae gaet beel meer heenen tot de berlorene schapen des huys Itcatls.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But go rather to the lost sheep of the house of Israel.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">寧可往以色列家迷失的羊那裏去。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse7">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka tou sahkaqua-noumi matta-sasou-â, koun, Mou-toukato ta Pei-sasou-an ki tounnoun ki vullu-vullum.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka tou sahkaquanoumi mattasasouâ, koun, Moutoukato ta Peisasouan ki tounnoun ki vulluvullum.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende henen gaende predickt sfeggende Het Roninckriick der Hemelen is na-by ghekomen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And as ye go, preach, saying, The kingdom of heaven is at hand.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">隨走隨傳，說＂天國近了！＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse8">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Pakadarikæ-'ǣ ki mangouri, paka-koupti-'ǣ ki (Leproos ka) ou-tataum-min, papatti-mæu-â ki patei, padarang-â ki Lyttou. Ni-paki-nynno-'noumi maki-valei-da, pæ'ǣ-nynno, âppa pihga ki atta.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Pakadarikæ'ǣ ki mangouri, pakakoupti'ǣ ki (Leproos ka) outataummin, papattimæuâ ki patei, padarangâ ki Lyttou. Nipakinynno'noumi makivaleida, pæ'ǣnynno, âppa pihga ki atta.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Genmeeltde krancke reynigt de melaetfehe weckt de doode op werpt de Diyworelen belen upt. Ghy hebt het om niet ontfangen geeft het om niet.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Heal the sick, cleanse the lepers, raise the dead, cast out devils: freely ye have received, freely give.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">醫治病人，叫死人復活，叫長大痲瘋的潔淨，把鬼趕出去。你們白白地得來，也要白白地捨去。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse9">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ynna taammia ki kym, ki malitouk, ki æu'a lava tou 'æitoumi ka rypiryp.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ynna taammia ki kym, ki malitouk, ki æu'a lava tou 'æitoumi ka rypiryp.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">En berkryght u noch goudt noch lilber noch koper(gelt) in uwe gordels. 10 Noch male tot den wegh noch twee rocken noch schoenen noch itaf. Want de arbeyder 18 syn boedtsel weerdigh. -</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Provide neither gold, nor silver, nor brass in your purses,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">腰袋裏不要帶金銀銅錢；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse10">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ynna (ammia) ki lavat tou darang, ki rourouha ki pou-louvo-en, ki tatapil, ki houkar lava. Ka mangal-ah ta tama-iroung ki ka-kannin tyn-da.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ynna (ammia) ki lavat tou darang, ki rourouha ki poulouvoen, ki tatapil, ki houkar lava. Ka mangalah ta tamairoung ki kakannin tynda.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Nor scrip for your journey, neither two coats, neither shoes, nor yet staves: for the workman is worthy of his meat.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">行路不要帶口袋；不要帶兩件褂子，也不要帶鞋和柺杖。因為工人得飲食是應當的。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse11">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Tou æuma toumamang ka tou keirang-en tou koussing-an-lava ka sa-rarbo-ei-moumi, tmeita-lighâ ti mang ta mangal tou hynna: ka itou-qua-hynna, tou kidi ki darang-ei-moumi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Tou æuma toumamang ka tou keirangen tou koussinganlava ka sararboeimoumi, tmeitalighâ ti mang ta mangal tou hynna: ka itouquahynna, tou kidi ki darangeimoumi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende Mm wat ftadt ofce blecke ghy sult in komen ondersoeckt wie dae&gt; in weerdigh is : ende blijfc aldaer tot dat ghy (daer) upt aet.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And into whatsoever city or town ye shall enter, enquire who in it is worthy; and there abide till ye go thence.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們無論進哪一城，哪一村，要打聽那裏誰是好人，就住在他家，直住到走的時候。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse12">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Dou sa-rarbo-kamou tou tallagh, mamau-â tah-kapis ki anna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Dou sararbokamou tou tallagh, mamauâ tahkapis ki anna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende als ghy in het huys gaet lo groet het lelbe.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And when ye come into an house, salute it.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">進他家裏去，要請他的安。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse13">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka rou mäângal ta tallagh nda, mou-qua-al-ato ta reia-oumi hynna: ka rou assi mångal, doumiaka sa-likough-al-ato ymoumi æn ta reia-oumi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka rou mäângal ta tallagh nda, mouquaalato ta reiaoumi hynna: ka rou assi mångal, doumiaka salikoughalato ymoumi æn ta reiaoumi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende indien dat huys werrdigh is soo kome uwen brede ober dat selbe: maer indit het niet weerdig en is so keere uwt brede weder tot u.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And if the house be worthy, let your peace come upon it: but if it be not worthy, let your peace return to you.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那家若配得平安，你們所求的平安就必臨到那家；若不配得，你們所求的平安仍歸你們。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse14">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka rou timamang ta assi makou-ta tallagh ymou-mi-æn, ta assi-appa millingigh-ah ki sou-oumi, rou d'marang-kamou tou tallagh tou æuma lava k'anna, t'aptapei ta rapoul ki rahpal-oumi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka rou timamang ta assi makouta tallagh ymoumiæn, ta assiappa millingighah ki sououmi, rou d'marangkamou tou tallagh tou æuma lava k'anna, t'aptapei ta rapoul ki rahpaloumi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende soo pemantu met en sal ontfatigen noch uwe woorden hooren uptgaende uyt dat huys ofte uyt deselbe ftadt schuddet Het stof uwer boeten af.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And whosoever shall not receive you, nor hear your words, when ye depart out of that house or city, shake off the dust of your feet.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">凡不接待你們、不聽你們話的人，你們離開那家，或是那城的時候，就把腳上的塵土跺下去。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse15">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Dilligh koun-nau-kamou râ, kafaoun-eih Imaua ki pahahavouvoung ta pourough ki Sodoma ki Gomorra tou wæ'i ki pæpæmæmæ'en ki 'æuma k'anna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Dilligh kounnaukamou râ, kafaouneih Imaua ki pahahavouvoung ta pourough ki Sodoma ki Gomorra tou wæ'i ki pæpæmæmæ'en ki 'æuma k'anna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Yoorwae? fegge ick u Her sal den lande ban Sodoma ende Gomorra berdraeghlicker 3tjn in den dag des oordeels dan deselb adr.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Verily I say unto you, It shall be more tolerable for the land of Sodom and Gomorrha in the day of judgment, than for that city.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我實在告訴你們，當審判的日子，所多瑪和蛾摩拉所受的，比那城還容易受呢！＂ （可13‧9－13；路21‧12－17）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse16">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Kytt'ei pa dingi-ennau-kamou mama ki joeko tou tamæuh ki louang ka mihakub: Anna ta matallahkau-â mama ki voelei, paka-saat-â (ki rÿh) mama ki dæuh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Kytt'ei pa dingiennaukamou mama ki joeko tou tamæuh ki louang ka mihakub: Anna ta matallahkauâ mama ki voelei, pakasaatâ (ki rÿh) mama ki dæuh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Siet ick sende u als fchapen in het midden der wolben : Zyt dan boorsichtigh geliick de Slangen enDe oprecht gelyck de Duyen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Behold, I send you forth as sheep in the midst of wolves: be ye therefore wise as serpents, and harmless as doves.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">＂我差你們去，如同羊進入狼群；所以你們要靈巧像蛇，馴良像鴿子。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse17">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Saou-kavier râ ki ka'æuloung: alei ka pæ'ǣ-tounnoun-ah ymoumi-æn tou paæuklaklan maki-sâl ki sou, ka pa-ængat-ah ymoumi-æn tou paæui-sasâllan nein-da.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Saoukavier râ ki ka'æuloung: alei ka pæ'ǣtounnounah ymoumiæn tou paæuklaklan makisâl ki sou, ka paængatah ymoumiæn tou paæuisasâllan neinda.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Mae: wacht u boor de menschen : want sy sullen u oberleberen in de Kaedtsbergaderinghen ende in hare Synagogen sullen sy u geesselen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But beware of men: for they will deliver you up to the councils, and they will scourge you in their synagogues;</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們要防備人；因為他們要把你們交給公會 ，也要在會堂裏鞭打你們，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse18">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka'ad-auh-kamou tou Tæi-sou ki pourough tou Mei-sasou-appa ka Si-bavau alei jau-an, alei ki hgeil-in tiktik neini-æn ki Heidang-appa-râ</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka'adauhkamou tou Tæisou ki pourough tou Meisasouappa ka Sibavau alei jauan, alei ki hgeilin tiktik neiniæn ki Heidangapparâ</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Efi gysult oock boor Stad-houders ende Koningen ghelepdet worden om mijnent wille haer ende den Hepdenen tot getuygeniffe.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And ye shall be brought before governors and kings for my sake, for a testimony against them and the Gentiles.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">並且你們要為我的緣故被送到諸侯君王面前，對他們和外邦人作見證。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse19">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou-râ pæ'ǣ-tounnou-ah ymoumi-æn, ynna ma-vouskar ki rÿh, mamang lavà, kamang lavà ta pasousou-ei-moumi. Ka pourarÿh-an-eil-ato pi-'æ tou kidi ki tælei k'anna ymoumi-æn, ka kamang ta pasousou-ei-moumi-râ.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irourâ pæ'ǣtounnouah ymoumiæn, ynna mavouskar ki rÿh, mamang lavà, kamang lavà ta pasousoueimoumi. Ka pourarÿhaneilato pi'æ tou kidi ki tælei k'anna ymoumiæn, ka kamang ta pasousoueimoumirâ.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Boch wannee: sy u oberleberen soo en sult ghy niet besorght 3tjn hoe of war ghy spreken sult. Want het alu in deselbe upre gegeben Worden wat ghy spreken ult.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But when they deliver you up, take no thought how or what ye shall speak: for it shall be given you in that same hour what ye shall speak.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們被交的時候，不要思慮怎樣說話，或說甚麼話。到那時候，必賜給你們當說的話；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse20">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka assi ta ymoumi ka masousou, râ Joep-an-appa ki Raraman-oumi, ka mattæi-rarÿh ki sou ymoumi-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka assi ta ymoumi ka masousou, râ Joepanappa ki Raramanoumi, ka mattæirarÿh ki sou ymoumiæn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Wantghyenrhit niet die spreket maer (het is) de Geelt uwes Yaders die in u spreeckt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">For it is not ye that speak, but the Spirit of your Father which speaketh in you.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">因為不是你們自己說的，乃是你們父的靈在你們裏頭說的。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse21">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka pæ'ǣ-tounnoun-ah ta (saät) ki tæ'i-appara ki tæ'i-appara tyn tou kapatei-an, ta Raraman ki Alak tyn, ka makou-douma-ah ta alalak ki tæi-alalak (neini-æn,) ka luhpouh-ah neini-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka pæ'ǣtounnounah ta (saät) ki tæ'iappara ki tæ'iappara tyn tou kapateian, ta Raraman ki Alak tyn, ka makoudoumaah ta alalak ki tæialalak (neiniæn,) ka luhpouhah neiniæn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende de (eene) broeder sal den (anderen) broede oberleberen tot de doodt ende de bader het kindt ende de kinderen sullen opstaen tegen de ouders ende sullenfe dooden,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And the brother shall deliver up the brother to death, and the father the child: and the children shall rise up against their parents, and cause them to be put to death.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">弟兄要把弟兄，父親要把兒子，送到死地；兒女要與父母為敵，害死他們；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse22">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka kavahyr-an-ei-kamou ki ymmid ki tau alei ki Nanangau, râ teni ka paha-limough tou jlalimough-an, ta paka-riang-eihda.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka kavahyraneikamou ki ymmid ki tau alei ki Nanangau, râ teni ka pahalimough tou jlalimoughan, ta pakariangeihda.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">EnEnde ghy fult ban allen gehatet worden om mijnen Name mae die bolstandigh sal blijben tot den eynde die sal saligh worden,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And ye shall be hated of all men for my name's sake: but he that endureth to the end shall be saved.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">並且你們要為我的名被眾人恨惡。惟有忍耐到底的必然得救。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse23">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka kmou-dyllough-ah ymoumi-æn tou æuma k'anna, yl-pout tâ mou-koua tou pani: Ka d'lligh-koun-nau-kamou-râ, assi-kamou hmæveiæ-æh tou limou-limou ki mæi-æuma-æuma ki Israël, ka hmah-kaha-al-ato iroua ta Alak ki ka'æuloung.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka kmoudylloughah ymoumiæn tou æuma k'anna, ylpout tâ moukoua tou pani: Ka d'llighkounnaukamourâ, assikamou hmæveiææh tou limoulimou ki mæiæumaæuma ki Israël, ka hmahkahaalato iroua ta Alak ki ka'æuloung.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Wannee: spu dan in dese ctadt berbolghen bliedt in de andere: Want boorwaer segge icku Ghy en o (ane reyse doos de He ratls niet ghe-eyndig hebben of de Sone des menfchen sal gekomen zijn.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But when they persecute you in this city, flee ye into another: for verily I say unto you, Ye shall not have gone over the cities of Israel, till the Son of man be come.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">有人在這城裏逼迫你們，就逃到那城裏去。我實在告訴你們，以色列的城邑，你們還沒有走遍，人子就到了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse24">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Assi masaoun tou vavau ki kidi ta Pahtatæutæu-en ki Mahtatæutæuuh tyni-æn, ta koungcia-appa ki Meirang tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Assi masaoun tou vavau ki kidi ta Pahtatæutæuen ki Mahtatæutæuuh tyniæn, ta koungciaappa ki Meirang tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">De Ditcipel en is niet boben den Meelter noch de dienltknecht boben ijnen</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">The disciple is not above his master, nor the servant above his lord.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">學生不能高過先生；僕人不能高過主人。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse25">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Mamsing ki Pahtatæutæu-en, rou myh-kaula-ah ki kidi mama ki Mahtatæutæuuh tyni-æn, ki koungcia, rou mama-ah ki Meirang tyn-da. Heirou ni-pa-nanang-en nein Beelzebul ta tæi-tallagh, pæh-pyn-nan-neih ki masaoun (mah-k'ma-hynna mananang) ta lalam tyn tou tallagh?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Mamsing ki Pahtatæutæuen, rou myhkaulaah ki kidi mama ki Mahtatæutæuuh tyniæn, ki koungcia, rou mamaah ki Meirang tynda. Heirou nipananangen nein Beelzebul ta tæitallagh, pæhpynnanneih ki masaoun (mahk'mahynna mananang) ta lalam tyn tou tallagh?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">het (ry) den Difcipel genoegh dat hy werde ghetiick yn Meefter ende de dienltknecht gelyk syn Heere. Indien ly den Heere des huys Beelrebul hebben gheteten hoe beel te meer lijne s phenooten 5</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">It is enough for the disciple that he be as his master, and the servant as his lord. If they have called the master of the house Beelzebub, how much more shall they call them of his household?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">學生和先生一樣，僕人和主人一樣，也就罷了。人既罵家主是別西卜，何況他的家人呢？＂ （路12‧2－7）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse26">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Anna ta, ynna mahtakout neini-æn: ka assi 'a'æu-tataæuf-eih, ka assi ni-h'a-in ki mamang, k'assi kavan'-eil-ato.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Anna ta, ynna mahtakout neiniæn: ka assi 'a'æutataæufeih, ka assi nih'ain ki mamang, k'assi kavan'eilato.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">En wreeft dan hae niet: want daer en 1s niet bedeckt t welck niet en sal ontdeckt worden ende bcrborgen het welck niet en sal geweten worden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Fear them not therefore: for there is nothing covered, that shall not be revealed; and hid, that shall not be known.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">＂所以，不要怕他們；因為掩蓋的事沒有不露出來的，隱藏的事沒有不被人知道的。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse27">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Kamamang ka vana-vanaen-nau-kamou tou karum-duman, pasousou-eito pou-ræmæh: ka mamang-appa ka illingigh-'noumi tou tangyrra, patta-sasou-eito tou apang.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Kamamang ka vanavanaennaukamou tou karumduman, pasousoueito pouræmæh: ka mamangappa ka illingigh'noumi tou tangyrra, pattasasoueito tou apang.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">het gene ick usegghe in de duysternille regget in Het licht: ende t gene ghy hoort hoott in de oore predickt dat op de daken.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">What I tell you in darkness, that speak ye in light: and what ye hear in the ear, that preach ye upon the housetops.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我在暗中告訴你們的，你們要在明處說出來；你們耳中所聽的，要在房上宣揚出來。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse28">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ynna mahtakout ki lmalpough ki voual, ka assi pis-ilpough paka-patei ki vatti: Râ masaoun-â mahtakout ki maligh smidada ki voual ki vatti tou kalæu'æu-en.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ynna mahtakout ki lmalpough ki voual, ka assi pisilpough pakapatei ki vatti: Râ masaounâ mahtakout ki maligh smidada ki voual ki vatti tou kalæu'æuen.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Eii en byeelt u niet boor de gene die t lichaem dood? ende de riele niet en konnen doode: Maer brcelst beel meer hem die beyde riele ende licha kan berderbt inde helle.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And fear not them which kill the body, but are not able to kill the soul: but rather fear him which is able to destroy both soul and body in hell.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那殺身體、不能殺靈魂的，不要怕他們；惟有能把身體和靈魂都滅在地獄裏的，正要怕他。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse29">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Assi kaua papeila'n ki laumari ka saäsat ta 'kyrri ka rourouha? Ka assi 't-næi ta saäsat ki anna dou ynnang-en ki Raramanoumi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Assi kaua papeila'n ki laumari ka saäsat ta 'kyrri ka rourouha? Ka assi 'tnæi ta saäsat ki anna dou ynnangen ki Raramanoumi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">En worden niet twee muschkensomeenpenningsken berkocht + Ende niet een ban desen en sal op de aerde ballen sonder uwen Dader.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Are not two sparrows sold for a farthing? and one of them shall not fall on the ground without your Father.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">兩個麻雀不是賣一分銀子嗎？若是你們的父不許，一個也不能掉在地上；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse30">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-tauki-ymd-in kuhting ta voukugh tou vongo-oumi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka nitaukiymdin kuhting ta voukugh tou vongooumi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Eindoock uwe hayren des hoofts zijn alle getelt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But the very hairs of your head are all numbered.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">就是你們的頭髮也都被數過了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse31">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Anna ta, ynna mahtakout, ka siouro-kamou tou vavau ki kidi ki 'kyrri ka madadagh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Anna ta, ynna mahtakout, ka siourokamou tou vavau ki kidi ki 'kyrri ka madadagh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">En byeest dan niet ghy gaet bele muschkens te boben, |</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Fear ye not therefore, ye are of more value than many sparrows.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">所以，不要懼怕，你們比許多麻雀還貴重！＂ （路12‧8－9）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse32">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Anna ta, timamang ta pouh-tatourou-tourough-ah pou-pænæh jau-an tou æmæh ki kaæu-loung, pouh-tatourou-tourouh-au-mau tyni-æn tou æmæh ki Raraman-an ka tou tounnoun ki vullu-vullum.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Anna ta, timamang ta pouhtatouroutouroughah poupænæh jauan tou æmæh ki kaæuloung, pouhtatouroutourouhaumau tyniæn tou æmæh ki Raramanan ka tou tounnoun ki vulluvullum.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Een yegelick dan die my belijden sal boor de menCchen dien sal ick oock belyden boor mynen Dader die inde Demelen (is.)</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Whosoever therefore shall confess me before men, him will I confess also before my Father which is in heaven.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">＂凡在人面前認我的，我在我天上的父面前也必認他；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse33">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Râ timamang ta rmau-ah jau-antou æmæh ki ka'æuloung, teni ta r'au-an-ei-mau tou æmæh ki Raraman-au ka tou tounnoun ki vullu-vullum.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Râ timamang ta rmauah jauantou æmæh ki ka'æuloung, teni ta r'auaneimau tou æmæh ki Raramanau ka tou tounnoun ki vulluvullum.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Wat; so wie my berloochent sal hebben boor de mensrhen dien (al ick oock berloochenen boor mjjnen Pader diein de Demelenfis.)</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But whosoever shall deny me before men, him will I also deny before my Father which is in heaven.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">凡在人面前不認我的，我在我天上的父面前也必不認他。＂ （路12‧51－53；14‧26－27）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse34">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ynna pou-kidi pou-rÿh ka irou'ato-koh ki ad-au-mau ta reia tou Næi: Assi-koh irou-'ato ki adau-mau ta reia, râ tyrrau-appa.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ynna poukidi pourÿh ka irou'atokoh ki adaumau ta reia tou Næi: Assikoh irou'ato ki adaumau ta reia, râ tyrrauappa.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Enmeynt niet dat ick ghekomen ben om brede te brengen op de aerde: Ick en ben niet gekomen om brede te brengen mae? het sweerr.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Think not that I am come to send peace on earth: I came not to send peace, but a sword.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">＂你們不要想我來是叫地上太平；我來並不是叫地上太平，乃是叫地上動刀兵。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse35">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka irou-ato-koh papatok-dangi-rangil ki ta-'u tou doumma ki Rarama-'n tyn, ki alak-appa ka ina tou doumma ki Raren-'an tyn, ki alak-appa ka ina ka äæukahin tou doumma ki Raren-'an ka ni mææukkagh tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka irouatokoh papatokdangirangil ki ta'u tou doumma ki Rarama'n tyn, ki alakappa ka ina tou doumma ki Raren'an tyn, ki alakappa ka ina ka äæukahin tou doumma ki Raren'an ka ni mææukkagh tyniæn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Want Wantick ben ghekomenom den mensche tweedrachtigh te maken teghen fijnen bader nde de dochter tegen hare moeder ende de fchoon-dochte teghen Hare fchoon-moeder. i</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">For I am come to set a man at variance against his father, and the daughter against her mother, and the daughter in law against her mother in law.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">因為我來是叫</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse36">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka mæyæuuh-ah ki tæ'æ-sâl tou sat katallagh-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka mæyæuuhah ki tæ'æsâl tou sat katallaghan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende sy (fullen) deg menschen byanden( worden, ) die fijne huys-genoott(rijo. )</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And a man's foes shall be they of his own household.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">人的仇敵就是自己家裏的人。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse37">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Timamang ta mævæ'ango ti Ama tyn-en ti Ina-tyn-enpa-siou-ro jau-an, assi mangal ki kidijau-an-da: ti-mamang-appa ta mæ-væan-go ki alak ka pa-ræh ki alak ina pasi-ouro jau-an, assi mangal ki kidijau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Timamang ta mævæ'ango ti Ama tynen ti Inatynenpasiouro jauan, assi mangal ki kidijauanda: timamangappa ta mævæango ki alak ka paræh ki alak ina pasiouro jauan, assi mangal ki kidijauan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Die Yader of Moede: lief heeft boben my en is mijns met weerdigh : ende die sone ofte dochter lief heeft boben my enis myns niet weerdigh.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">He that loveth father or mother more than me is not worthy of me: and he that loveth son or daughter more than me is not worthy of me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">＂愛父母過於愛我的，不配作我的門徒；愛兒女過於愛我的，不配作我的門徒；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse38">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Timamang-appa ta assi mara ki na væværæh tyn (pou-halap tyni-æn) mææuugh jau-an, assi mangal ki kidi jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Timamangappa ta assi mara ki na væværæh tyn (pouhalap tyniæn) mææuugh jauan, assi mangal ki kidi jauan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende die sijn kyyyce niet (op hem) en neemc ende mp nat en bolgt en is mijns nierweeddigh. â€¦ 39. Die fijne riele bindr sal{de}selbe berliefen : ende die sijne riele sal berlooren hebben om mijnent wille sal deselbe binden,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And he that taketh not his cross, and followeth after me, is not worthy of me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">不背着他的十字架跟從我的，也不配作我的門徒。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse39">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Timamang ta maki-valei (matta-ha) ki vatti tyn, pa-taurum-ma-auh tyn ta anna: ti mamang-appa ta pa-taurumma-al-ato ki vatti tyn alei jau-an, paki-valei-auh tyn (matta-ha) ta anna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Timamang ta makivalei (mattaha) ki vatti tyn, pataurummaauh tyn ta anna: ti mamangappa ta pataurummaalato ki vatti tyn alei jauan, pakivaleiauh tyn (mattaha) ta anna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Dieu ontfangt ontfangt my : ende die my ontfanght ontfanght hem die</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">He that findeth his life shall lose it: and he that loseth his life for my sake shall find it.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">得着生命的，將要失喪生命；為我失喪生命的，將要得着生命。＂ （可9‧41）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse40">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Timamang ta makou-ta-tallagh ymoumi-æn, makoutatal-lagh-ato jau-an: timamang-appa ta makou-tatallagh jau-an, makou-ta-tallagh-ato ki ni-madingi jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Timamang ta makoutatallagh ymoumiæn, makoutatallaghato jauan: timamangappa ta makoutatallagh jauan, makoutatallaghato ki nimadingi jauan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Die tm Propheer ontfangt m den naem eens Propheten sal den toon gns iwu Propheten ontlangen : ende die eenen rechtbeerdigen ontfangt in dt naem eens rechtbeerdigen sal den loon eens rechtbeerdigen ontfangen,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">He that receiveth you receiveth me, and he that receiveth me receiveth him that sent me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">＂人接待你們就是接待我；接待我就是接待那差我來的。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse41">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Timamang ta makou-ta-tallagh ki Tama-mattæi-tan tou nanang ki Tama-mattæi-tan, paki-valei-auh tyn ta 'ou-vavarg-han ki Tama-mattæi-tan: tima-mang ta makou-tatallagh ki matiktik tou nanang ki matiktik, paki-valei-auh tyn ta 'ou-vavarg-han ki matiktik.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Timamang ta makoutatallagh ki Tamamattæitan tou nanang ki Tamamattæitan, pakivaleiauh tyn ta 'ouvavarghan ki Tamamattæitan: timamang ta makoutatallagh ki matiktik tou nanang ki matiktik, pakivaleiauh tyn ta 'ouvavarghan ki matiktik.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">He that receiveth a prophet in the name of a prophet shall receive a prophet's reward; and he that receiveth a righteous man in the name of a righteous man shall receive a righteous man's reward.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">人因為先知的名接待先知，必得先知所得的賞賜；人因為義人的名接待義人，必得義人所得的賞賜。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse42">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka timamang ta pa-ÿt-ah dyk ki sât ka rou koul-an (ki ra-loum) ka mahanglou ki sasat ki oussising k'atta ki kidi, tou nanang ki Pahtatæutæu-en, d'liigh koun-nau-kamou râ, assi taurumma-ah ki 'ou-vavarg-han tyn. Ka sasat-kyttiæn 'æb ki sat ki lbæh ki soulat.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka timamang ta paÿtah dyk ki sât ka rou koulan (ki raloum) ka mahanglou ki sasat ki oussising k'atta ki kidi, tou nanang ki Pahtatæutæuen, d'liigh kounnaukamou râ, assi taurummaah ki 'ouvavarghan tyn. Ka sasatkyttiæn 'æb ki sat ki lbæh ki soulat.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende so wie een ban dese klepne te drincken geeft alleenlick eenen beker kout (waters,) im den name eens Discipels boorwaer segge icku hy en sal siinen loon geensins berliesen,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And whosoever shall give to drink unto one of these little ones a cup of cold water only in the name of a disciple, verily I say unto you, he shall in no wise lose his reward.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">無論何人，因為門徒的名，只把一杯涼水給這小子裏的一個喝，我實在告訴你們，這人不能不得賞賜。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
</TEXT>
