<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEXT id="Siraya_Dutch_Matthew_Chapter15" xml:lang="fos" source="Siraya Bible, Matthew gospel" copyright="public domain" citation="Gravius, Daniël. 1661. Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa. Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang. Amsterdam: Michiel Hartogh." BibTeX_citation="@book{Gravius1661,&#10;  author    = {Gravius, Daniël},&#10;  year      = {1661},&#10;  title     = {Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa},&#10;  note      = {Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang},&#10;  address   = {Amsterdam},&#10;  publisher = {Michiel Hartogh}&#10;}">
    <S id="verse1">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Tou kidi k'anna ni-iroua ti Jesus-an ta Mako-sasoulat ki Fariséen-appa ka ni-makka-Je-rusalem, ka k'ma,</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Tou kidi k'anna ni-iroua ti Jesus-an ta Mako-sasoulat ki Fariséen-appa ka ni-makka-Je-rusalem, ka k'ma,</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doe quamen tot Jesum fum Leenige] Schaftgeleerde efi Pharireen die ba Jerusalem{waren,seggende </TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then came to Jesus scribes and Pharisees, which were of Jerusalem, saying,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那時，有法利賽人和文士從耶路撒冷來見耶穌，說：</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse2">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka'umang ka kmaarough ta Pahtatæutæu-en-ohou ki na pæǣ-tatounnoun ki mamoumou, ka assi madinau ki rima nein, dou kman-ah ki paoul?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka'umang ka kmaarough ta Pahtatæutæu-en-ohou ki na pæǣ-tatounnoun ki mamoumou, ka assi madinau ki rima nein, dou kman-ah ki paoul?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Waoaetom obertreden nwe Dilcipelen de insettinghe der Oudens want sy en walfchen hare hande niet wannee: sy broodt sullen eten.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Why do thy disciples transgress the tradition of the elders? for they wash not their hands when they eat bread.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">「你的門徒為甚麼犯古人的遺傳呢？因為吃飯的時候，他們不洗手。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse3">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ teni ta ni-mattæ'i-vli k'ma neini-æn, Ka'umang ka kma-arough-appa-kamou ki pakou-sou-en ki Alid ki na pæ'ǣ-tatou-noun-oumi?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ teni ta ni-mattæ'i-vli k'ma neini-æn, Ka'umang ka kma-arough-appa-kamou ki pakou-sou-en ki Alid ki na pæ'ǣ-tatou-noun-oumi?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Maet hy antwoordende seydetot haer Waerom obertreedt oock ghy het ghebodt Godts door uwe inlettinge</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But he answered and said unto them, Why do ye also transgress the commandment of God by your tradition?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌回答說：「你們為甚麼因着你們的遺傳犯上帝的誡命呢？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse4">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-makou-sou ta Alid, kma, Milligh-ah kow ti Amau-hou-en ti Jnau-hou-en: ka, Timamang ta mahkou-avavagh ki Raraman ki Rarenan [tyn] pakapatei-eih ta teni.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-makou-sou ta Alid, kma, Milligh-ah kow ti Amau-hou-en ti Jnau-hou-en: ka, Timamang ta mahkou-avavagh ki Raraman ki Rarenan [tyn] pakapatei-eih ta teni.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Want Godt heeft gheboden segghende Eextuwen bader ende moeder:ende Wie bade: ofte moeder bloeckt die sal den doodt sterben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">For God commanded, saying, Honour thy father and mother: and, He that curseth father or mother, let him die the death.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">上帝說：『當孝敬父母』；又說：『咒罵父母的，必治死他。』</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse5">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ k'ma-kamou ta ymoumi, Timamang ta k'ma-ah hynna ki sou ti Ama [tyn-nen lava] ti jna [tyn-nen lava] pæpæpa [ta anna] kamamang ka papou-than-ei-mau kow, ka assi milligh-ah ki Rara-man tyn lava ki Rarenan tyn lava, [teni ta imsing-milligh.]</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ k'ma-kamou ta ymoumi, Timamang ta k'ma-ah hynna ki sou ti Ama [tyn-nen lava] ti jna [tyn-nen lava] pæpæpa [ta anna] kamamang ka papou-than-ei-mau kow, ka assi milligh-ah ki Raraman tyn lava ki Rarenan tyn lava, [teni ta imsing-milligh.]</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Mae: ghy seght Soo wie tot bader ofte moeder sal seggen: {Hetis] een gabe foo wat u ban my soude konnen te nutte komen ende shnen bader ofte shne moeder gheensins en sal eeren [die boldoet.]</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But ye say, Whosoever shall say to his father or his mother, It is a gift, by whatsoever thou mightest be profited by me;</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們倒說：『無論何人對父母說：我所當奉給你的已經作了供獻，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse6">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-paha-hnynno-kamou [kma hynna ki sou] ki ni-pakou-sou-en ki Alid ki na pæ'ǣ-tatou-noun-oumi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-paha-hnynno-kamou [kma hynna ki sou] ki ni-pakou-sou-en ki Alid ki na pæ'ǣ-tatou-noun-oumi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende ghy hebt [alfoo] Godts gebodt krachteloos ghemacckt door uwt insettinge.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And honour not his father or his mother, he shall be free. Thus have ye made the commandment of God of none effect by your tradition.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他就可以不孝敬父母。』這就是你們藉着遺傳，廢了上帝的誡命。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse7">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ymoumi ka panni-nni-en ki rÿh ki sou, mariang ta ni-pattæ'i-ta-nang-en ti Esajas ymoumi-æn, rou koun tyn,</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ymoumi ka panni-nni-en ki rÿh ki sou, mariang ta ni-pattæ'i-ta-nang-en ti Esajas ymoumi-æn, rou koun tyn,</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ghy Ghy gebeynsde wel heeft Jesaias banu ghepropheteert leggende </TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Ye hypocrites, well did Esaias prophesy of you, saying,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">假冒為善的人哪，以賽亞指着你們說的預言是不錯的。他說：</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse8">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Mou-hylli jau-an ta ta'u k'atta ki moutous nein, ka lou-moulugh jau-an ki bibygh nein, râ tintin nein ta irou-tauagh jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Mou-hylli jau-an ta ta'u k'atta ki moutous nein, ka lou-moulugh jau-an ki bibygh nein, râ tintin nein ta irou-tauagh jau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Bit bolck ghenaeckt mp met haren monde ende eert my met de lippen maer haer herte houdt hem berre ban mp.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">This people draweth nigh unto me with their mouth, and honoureth me with their lips; but their heart is far from me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">這百姓用嘴唇尊敬我，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse9">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ sauki-na-nynno tmamud hau-an, dou mah-tæutæuuh ki pah-tatæutæu-en ka na sikakidi ki ka-'æuloung.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ sauki-na-nynno tmamud hau-an, dou mah-tæutæuuh ki pah-tatæutæu-en ka na sikakidi ki ka-'æuloung.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Doch te bergeets eeren sy my leerende leeringen [die] geboden ban menichen [ rijo. ]</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But in vain they do worship me, teaching for doctrines the commandments of men.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們將人的吩咐當作道理教導人，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse10">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou ka ni-tætææm-en tyn paouqua tyni-æn ta makoi-lalau-lau, ni-k'ma neini-æn, Illing-hgau, ou-mha-au'ppa.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou ka ni-tætææm-en tyn paouqua tyni-æn ta makoi-lalaulau, ni-k'ma neini-æn, Illing-hgau, ou-mha-au'ppa.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende als hy de ichare y ogy royy abde sepot har; t en</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And he called the multitude, and said unto them, Hear, and understand:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌就叫了眾人來，對他們說：「你們要聽，也要明白。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse11">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka sararbo ki moutous, assi paka-voussouk mahyd ki ka-'æuloung, râ dyk ta atta ka sah-pæpænæh tou moutous, anna ta pa-ka-vossouk mahyd ki ka'æuloung.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka sararbo ki moutous, assi paka-voussouk mahyd ki ka-'æuloung, râ dyk ta atta ka sah-pæpænæh tou moutous, anna ta pa-ka-vossouk mahyd ki ka'æuloung.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Hetghene ten monde in gaet en ontrepnight den mentche niet maer het ghene ren monde uyt gaet dat ontreynight den mensche.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Not that which goeth into the mouth defileth a man; but that which cometh out of the mouth, this defileth a man.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">入口的不能污穢人，出口的乃能污穢人。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse12">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Tou kidi k'anna ni-iroua tyni-æn ta Pahtatæutæu-en tyn, ka ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Ou-mha-en-hou kaua, ka sou millingigh ta Fa-riseen ki sou k'anna, ka ni-fai-fala-kouap ta neni-paka-t'e neini-æn?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Tou kidi k'anna ni-iroua tyni-æn ta Pahtatæutæu-en tyn, ka ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Ou-mha-en-hou kaua, ka sou millingigh ta Fariseen ki sou k'anna, ka ni-fai-fala-kouap ta neni-paka-t'e neini-æn?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Doe quamen fine Discipelen tot hem ende leyden tot hem Weet ghp [wel] dat de Phariseen dese reden hoorende ge-trgert 3hn geweelt 4</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then came his disciples, and said unto him, Knowest thou that the Pharisees were offended, after they heard this saying?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">當時，門徒進前來對他說：「法利賽人聽見這話，不服，你知道嗎？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse13">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ ni-mattæi-vli ta teni, k'ma, Ymmid ki na talutalud ka assi ni-tallum ki Rama-au ka tou vullum, ptoul-aul-ato ta anna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ ni-mattæi-vli ta teni, k'ma, Ymmid ki na talutalud ka assi ni-tallum ki Rama-au ka tou vullum, ptoul-aul-ato ta anna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Maer hy antwoor dende sepde Alle plante die mijn Hemelsche Dader niet geplant en heeft sal upt-geroept worden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But he answered and said, Every plant, which my heavenly Father hath not planted, shall be rooted up.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌回答說：「凡栽種的物，若不是我天父栽種的，必要拔出來。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse14">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Nda a-moumo-au, Tama-dyllough ka mavoutta ta neni ki tau ka mavonta. Heirou mada.. dilough ta mavouta ki mavouta, tou dourouha-ah mou-aryng tou pouhtou-râ.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Nda a-moumo-au, Tama-dyllough ka mavoutta ta neni ki tau ka mavonta. Heirou mada.. dilough ta mavouta ki mavouta, tou dourouha-ah mou-aryng tou pouhtou-râ.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Kaetfe baren sy zijn blinde lepdts lieden der blin-den, Indien nit de blinde den blinden lepdt soo sullen sy bepde in de gracht balen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Let them alone: they be blind leaders of the blind. And if the blind lead the blind, both shall fall into the ditch.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">任憑他們吧！他們是瞎眼領路的；若是瞎子領瞎子，兩個人都要掉在坑裏。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse15">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-mattæ'i-vli ta ti Pe-trus k'ma tyni-æn, Pattæ'i-msing-i-kame ki pæmyh kaulaul'an k'anna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-mattæ'i-vli ta ti Pe-trus k'ma tyni-æn, Pattæ'i-msing-i-kame ki pæmyh kaulaul'an k'anna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Efi Petrus antwoordende sepde tot hem Derklaert ons dese gelyckenisse.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then answered Peter and said unto him, Declare unto us this parable.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">彼得對耶穌說：「請將這比喻講給我們聽。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse16">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus, Maurou-appa-kamou kaua ta y-moumi?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus, Maurou-appa-kamou kaua ta ymoumi?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Mater Jesus sepde Zijt oock ghy-lieden als noch onwetende 4</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And Jesus said, Are ye also yet without understanding?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：「你們到如今還不明白嗎？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse17">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Assi-appa-moumi ou-mhan, kamamang ka mou-moutous, ka mou-vouyl ka aryng tou 'au-va-væu-oung-en [ta anna?]</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Assi-appa-moumi ou-mhan, kamamang ka mou-moutous, ka mou-vouyl ka aryng tou 'au-va-væu-oung-en [ta anna?]</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Enberltaet ghy noch niet dat al wat ten monde in gaet in den bupck komt ende in de heymelickheydc wordt upt-geworpens |</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Do not ye yet understand, that whatsoever entereth in at the mouth goeth into the belly, and is cast out into the draught?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">豈不知凡入口的，是運到肚子裏，又落在茅廁裏嗎？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse18">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ kamamang ka makka moutous, sahpa-pænæh makka tintin', ka anna-appa ta paka-vous-souk mæhyd ki kaæuloung.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ kamamang ka makka moutous, sahpa-pænæh makka tintin', ka anna-appa ta paka-vous-souk mæhyd ki kaæuloung.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Maer die dinghen die ten monde uyt gaen komen boort uyt het herte eii deselbe ontrepnigen den mensche.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But those things which proceed out of the mouth come forth from the heart; and they defile the man.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">惟獨出口的，是從心裏發出來的，這才污穢人。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse19">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka makka tintin mou-pæ-nah ta naddarim-dim ka assi ina-riang, lalpoulpough, ou-zouzoung ki mi-makakyttil, ki assi ni-maka-kyttil, haheil-heil, sihaharang, ki vavarbærg-appa.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka makka tintin mou-pæ-nah ta naddarim-dim ka assi ina-riang, lalpoulpough, ou-zouzoung ki mi-makakyttil, ki assi ni-maka-kyttil, haheil-heil, sihaharang, ki vavarbærg-appa.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Want uyt het herte Komen boort boosfe bedenckingen doodtslaghen oberkpelen hoererhen dieberijen balsche getupgenissen lasteringen. </TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">For out of the heart proceed evil thoughts, murders, adulteries, fornications, thefts, false witness, blasphemies:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">因為從心裏發出來的，有惡念、凶殺、姦淫、苟合、偷盜、妄證、謗讟。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse20">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ann-appa paka-voussouk mahyd ki ka'æuloung: râ ta avo-vok ki rima ka assi ni-padinau, assi paka-boussouk mæhyd ki ka'æu soung.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ann-appa paka-voussouk mahyd ki ka'æuloung: râ ta avo-vok ki rima ka assi ni-padinau, assi paka-boussouk mæhyd ki ka'æu soung.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Dele dingen zijn het die den menfche ontrepnigen:maer het eten mer ongewasschen handen en ontreynight den menschemier.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">These are the things which defile a man: but to eat with unwashen hands defileth not a man.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">這都是污穢人的；至於不洗手吃飯，那卻不污穢人。」 （可7‧24－30）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse21">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou ka d'marang hynna ta ti Jesus ni-sah-kaqua tou ou-'nni-en ki lbæh ki næi ki Tyrus ki Sidon.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou ka d'marang hynna ta ti Jesus ni-sah-kaqua tou ou-'nni-en ki lbæh ki næi ki Tyrus ki Sidon.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende Jesus ban daer gaende bertrock nae de deelen ban Tyrus ende Zidon.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then Jesus went thence, and departed into the coasts of Tyre and Sidon.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌離開那裏，退到泰爾、西頓的境內去。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse22">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka kyttei sat ki jna ka tæu-æuma tou Kanaan ta ni-tma-tæäm mako-lang-ah tyni-æn, k'ma, Meirang ka na Alak ti Dæ-vid, kaharum-ou koh: ou-louas ato mou-Lyttou ta alak-au ka. jna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka kyttei sat ki jna ka tæu-æuma tou Kanaan ta ni-tma-tæäm mako-lang-ah tyni-æn, k'ma, Meirang ka na Alak ti Dæ-vid, kaharum-ou koh: ou-louas ato mou-Lyttou ta alak-au ka. jna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Endesiet een Chananeesche brouwe uyt die lantpalen palen komende riep tot hem seggende Heere [gby] sone Dabids ontfermtu mijnder: mijn dochter is deerlick ban den duphel beseten.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And, behold, a woman of Canaan came out of the same coasts, and cried unto him, saying, Have mercy on me, O Lord, thou son of David; my daughter is grievously vexed with a devil.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">有一個迦南婦人，從那地方出來，喊着說：「主啊，大衛的子孫，可憐我！我女兒被鬼附得甚苦。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse23">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Teni râ assi ni-mattæ'i-vli tyni-æn ki sasasat ka sou. Ka rou irou-'ato tyni-en ta Pahtatæutau-han tyn, ni-tmoumimia tyni-æn, koun, Padarang-au ta teni, ka ma-ko-dyllugh tmætæäm ymyttæn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Teni râ assi ni-mattæ'i-vli tyni-æn ki sasasat ka sou. Ka rou irou-'ato tyni-en ta Pahtatæutau-han tyn, ni-tmoumimia tyni-æn, koun, Padarang-au ta teni, ka ma-ko-dyllugh tmætæäm ymyttæn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Doch hy en antwoordde hae: niet een woore. Ende ijne Discipelen tot ho komende baden hem ende Laetse ban u wane sy roept ons nae.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But he answered her not a word. And his disciples came and besought him, saying, Send her away; for she crieth after us.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌卻一言不答。門徒進前來，求他說：「這婦人在我們後頭喊叫，請打發她走吧。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse24">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ra teni ta ni-mattæi-vli k'ma, Assi-koh ni-pada-dingi-en, dyk ka joeko k'anna ka patau rumma-an ki tallægh ki Israul.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ra teni ta ni-mattæi-vli k'ma, Assi-koh ni-pada-dingi-en, dyk ka joeko k'anna ka patau rumma-an ki tallægh ki Israul.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Mae hy antwoordende seyde Ick en ben niet gefonden dan tot de berlorenechayer des huys Itcatls.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But he answered and said, I am not sent but unto the lost sheep of the house of Israel.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：「我奉差遣不過是到以色列家迷失的羊那裏去。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse25">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-mou-qua ta teni tmamud tyni-æn, k'ma, Meirang, sah-kou-i-koh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-mou-qua ta teni tmamud tyni-æn, k'ma, Meirang, sah-kou-i-koh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende fp. quam ende arndant hem segghende Heere helpt</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then came she and worshipped him, saying, Lord, help me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那婦人來拜他，說：「主啊，幫助我！」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse26">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-mattæ'i-vli [ta teni] ni-k'ma, Assi mariang ka ä'au-mi-eih ta paoul ki Alalak, 'aryng-an-ei piä ki atta tou assou-assou-an ka poupou.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-mattæ'i-vli [ta teni] ni-k'ma, Assi mariang ka ä'au-mi-eih ta paoul ki Alalak, 'aryng-an-ei piä ki atta tou assou-assou-an ka poupou.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Doch bp antwoordde ende seyde Het en 1s niet betamelick het broodt der Kinderen te nemen ende den hondekens [boor] te werpen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But he answered and said, It is not meet to take the children's bread, and to cast it to dogs.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他回答說：「不好拿兒女的餅丟給狗吃。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse27">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-k'ma ta teni, Hahet Meirang ka kman-appa ta assour na pakipak ka mouaryng tou avok-kan ki Meireirang nein.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-k'ma ta teni, Hahet Meirang ka kman-appa ta assour na pakipak ka mouaryng tou avok-kan ki Meireirang nein.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende sy sepde Jae. Heere : doch de hondekens eten oock ban de brocckens Die daer ballen ban de tafel hare: heeren, </TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And she said, Truth, Lord: yet the dogs eat of the crumbs which fall from their masters' table.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">婦人說：「主啊，不錯；但是狗也吃牠主人桌子上掉下來的碎渣兒。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse28">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta ni-mattæ'i-vli ta ti Jesus, k'ma tyni-æn, Ano jna, irang ta tna-msing-an ohio, pa-vut-auh ymhou-an mama ki kamoei-en-hou. Ka ni-kæuh-darikah ta alak tyn ka jna tou kidi ki tælei k'anna,</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta ni-mattæ'i-vli ta ti Jesus, k'ma tyni-æn, Ano jna, irang ta tna-msing-an ohio, pa-vut-auh ymhou-an mama ki kamoei-en-hou. Ka ni-kæuh-darikah ta alak tyn ka jna tou kidi ki tælei k'anna,</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Boe odreet har 7H fus ende seyde tot haer O brouwe groot is uw' geloobe u geschiede geliick ghy wilt, Ende haer dochter wierdt gesont ban dier selber uyre.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then Jesus answered and said unto her, O woman, great is thy faith: be it unto thee even as thou wilt. And her daughter was made whole from that very hour.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：「婦人，你的信心是大的！照你所要的，給你成全了吧。」從那時候，她女兒就好了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse29">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou ka ni-mæli-daæua hynna ta ti Jesus, ni-iroua tou ta-mang ki vaoung ki Galilea, ka rou ni-maddakkin mou-voukin, mier-roung-ato hynna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou ka ni-mæli-daæua hynna ta ti Jesus, ni-iroua tou tamang ki vaoung ki Galilea, ka rou ni-maddakkin mou-voukin, mier-roung-ato hynna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> EnEnde Jesus ban daer bertreckende quam aen de See ban Galileen endeklam op den bergh ende sat daer neder.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And Jesus departed from thence, and came nigh unto the sea of Galilee; and went up into a mountain, and sat down there.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌離開那地方，來到靠近加利利的海邊，就上山坐下。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse30">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka mabatoung ta makoi-lalaulau ka ni-iroua tyni-æn, ka ni-pa-toulam neini-æn ki mapilei, ki mavoutta, ki mangoupou, ki ma-pykka, ki pani-appa ka mararap [ki vouel,] ka ni-maki qua neini-an matta-douma tou rahpal ti Je sus, ka ni-padarikah-en ta neni.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka mabatoung ta makoi-lalaulau ka ni-iroua tyni-æn, ka ni-pa-toulam neini-æn ki mapilei, ki mavoutta, ki mangoupou, ki ma-pykka, ki pani-appa ka mararap [ki vouel,] ka ni-maki qua neini-an matta-douma tou rahpal ti Je sus, ka ni-padarikah-en ta neni.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende bele scharen zijn tot hem gekomen hebbende bp haer kreupele blinde stomme lamme ende bele andere ende wierpense boor de boeten Jesu ende hy genas deselbe.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And great multitudes came unto him, having with them those that were lame, blind, dumb, maimed, and many others, and cast them down at Jesus' feet; and he healed them:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">有許多人到他那裏，帶着瘸子、瞎子、啞巴、有殘疾的，和好些別的病人，都放在他腳前；他就治好了他們。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse31">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Koumm'appa hynna, ka ni-mouh-kiap ta makoi-lalaulau dou kakytt'an nein, ka massousou-ta mangoupou, ka madarikagh ta mapykka, ka mou-næunang ta ma-pilei, ka kmyttâ ta mavoutta, ka ni-pou-vavau ta neni pou-keirang-en ki kidi ki Alid ki Isræul.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Koumm'appa hynna, ka ni-mouh-kiap ta makoi-lalaulau dou kakytt'an nein, ka massousou-ta mangoupou, ka madarikagh ta mapykka, ka mou-næunang ta ma-pilei, ka kmyttâ ta mavoutta, ka ni-pou-vavau ta neni pou-keirang-en ki kidi ki Alid ki Isræul.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Also dat de scharen haer berwonderden siende destomme sprekende de lamme gesont de kreupele wandelende ende de blinde siende:ende sy berheerlickten den Godt Iscatls.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Insomuch that the multitude wondered, when they saw the dumb to speak, the maimed to be whole, the lame to walk, and the blind to see: and they glorified the God of Israel.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">甚至眾人都希奇；因為看見啞巴說話，殘疾的痊癒，瘸子行走，瞎子看見，他們就歸榮耀給以色列的上帝。 （可8‧1－10）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse32">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou ka ni-tætææm ti Je-sus ta Pahtatæutæu-han tyn, ni k'ma, Mararyh-koh maharas has ki kaharum-en ki makoi-lalaulau, alei ka makka touro ki wæ'i itou-lam jæu-an, ka aousi ki mamang ka kan-nau nein: ka ynnang-koh pa-darang neini-æn ka assi-appa mavok, ka assi-a dou matub tou darang-da.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou ka ni-tætææm ti Je-sus ta Pahtatæutæu-han tyn, ni k'ma, Mararyh-koh maharas has ki kaharum-en ki makoi-lalaulau, alei ka makka touro ki wæ'i itou-lam jæu-an, ka aousi ki mamang ka kan-nau nein: ka ynnang-koh pa-darang neini-æn ka assi-appa mavok, ka assi-a dou matub tou darang-da.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende Jesus lijne Dittipelen tot hem gheroepen hebbende eyde Ick worde innerlick met ontferminge beweeght obe de schare om dat sy nu drie daghen by my gebleben zijn ende en hebben niet dat sy eten fouden : ende ick en wilfe niet nuchteren ban my laten op dat sy op DE wegh niet en beswycken,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then Jesus called his disciples unto him, and said, I have compassion on the multitude, because they continue with me now three days, and have nothing to eat: and I will not send them away fasting, lest they faint in the way.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌叫門徒來，說：「我憐憫這眾人；因為他們同我在這裏已經三天，也沒有吃的了。我不願意叫他們餓着回去，恐怕在路上困乏。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse33">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-k'ma ta Pahtatæu-tæu-han tyn tyni-æn, Toumang ta k'malynna ki dægh ki paoul tou poulægh tou pakavantau-au-myt-ta ta makoi-lalaulatu ka k'ma hyn-na ki vatoung?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-k'ma ta Pahtatæutæu-han tyn tyni-æn, Toumang ta k'malynna ki dægh ki paoul tou poulægh tou pakavantau-au-myt-ta ta makoi-lalaulatu ka k'ma hyn-na ki vatoung?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> EndeshneDiscipelen feyden tot hem Van waer [fullen] wp soo bele brooden in m de woeltiine [bekomen, ] dat wy sulck een groote schare souden bersadigen r</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And his disciples say unto him, Whence should we have so much bread in the wilderness, as to fill so great a multitude?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">門徒說：「我們在這野地，哪裏有這麼多的餅叫這許多人吃飽呢？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse34">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus neini-æn, Pyppyn-'ato ta paoul youmi-æn? Ka ni-k'ma ta neni, Pyppito, matiting-appa ki thing ka ousisyng.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus neini-æn, Pyppyn-'ato ta paoul youmi-æn? Ka ni-k'ma ta neni, Pyppito, matiting-appa ki thing ka ousisyng.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende Jesus leyde tot Haer Hoe beel brooden hebt ghy 4 Sy feyden Seben ende weynige bischkens.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And Jesus saith unto them, How many loaves have ye? And they said, Seven, and a few little fishes.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：「你們有多少餅？」他們說：「有七個，還有幾條小魚。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse35">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-pa-ierroung-en tyn tou næita makoi-lalaulau.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-pa-ierroung-en tyn tou næita makoi-lalaulau.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende hy geboodt de scharen neder te sitten op de aerde.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And he commanded the multitude to sit down on the ground.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他就吩咐眾人坐在地上，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse36">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka rou ni-ara tyn ta pyp pyttou ki paoul ki t'hing-appa, ka rou ni-patbli-en tyn ki laloulou-lugh, ni-pih-pi, ka ni-ph'an tyn ki Pahtatæutæu-han, rå neni-appa ka Pahtatautæu-han [ni-pa'a-toun-noun] ki makoi-lalaulau.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka rou ni-ara tyn ta pyp pyttou ki paoul ki t'hing-appa, ka rou ni-patbli-en tyn ki laloulou-lugh, ni-pih-pi, ka ni-ph'an tyn ki Pahtatæutæu-han, rå neni-appa ka Pahtatautæu-han [ni-pa'a-toun-noun] ki makoi-lalaulau.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Endehpnam de seben brooden ende de bisschen ende als hy gedanckt hadde brack hyse ende gaffe syne Distcipelen ende de Difcipelen [gabense] de schare,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And he took the seven loaves and the fishes, and gave thanks, and brake them, and gave to his disciples, and the disciples to the multitude.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">拿着這七個餅和幾條魚，祝謝了，擘開，遞給門徒；門徒又遞給眾人。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse37">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-mi-ymmid mavok, ka mibangtæu-ato, ka ni-ara nein illid ki ni-k'da ki na pih-pi pyttou ka læ'i-an ka matmoei-ra.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-mi-ymmid mavok, ka mibangtæu-ato, ka ni-ara nein illid ki ni-k'da ki na pih-pi pyttou ka læ'i-an ka matmoei-ra.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Endesp aten alle ende wierden bersadight ende sy namen op het oberschot der brocken seben bolle mande.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And they did all eat, and were filled: and they took up of the broken meat that was left seven baskets full.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">眾人都吃，並且吃飽了，收拾剩下的零碎，裝滿了七個筐子。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse38">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka neni ka ni-mavok na hpæt-ato katounnoun-nan ki pæ parah, dou assi eikakoun ta jnæ-jna ki alalak-appa.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka neni ka ni-mavok na hpæt-ato katounnoun-nan ki pæ parah, dou assi eikakoun ta jnæ-jna ki alalak-appa.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende die daer gegeten Hadden waren bie dupsent mannen sonder brouwen ende kinderen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And they that did eat were four thousand men, beside women and children.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">吃的人，除了婦女孩子，共有四千。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse39">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka rou ni-padarang-en tyn ta makoi-lalaulau, ni-mæddakkun mou-avang ta teni, ka ni-iroua tou paæpt'æn ki pourough ki Magda-Ka sasat kyttian' ab ki nnum ki lbægh ki soulat.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka rou ni-padarang-en tyn ta makoi-lalaulau, ni-mæddakkun mou-avang ta teni, ka ni-iroua tou paæpt'æn ki pourough ki Magda-Ka sasat kyttian' ab ki nnum ki lbægh ki soulat.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende de fchare ban Hem gelaten hebbende ging . Hy in het schip endequam m de lantpalen ban MagdaA.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And he sent away the multitude, and took ship, and came into the coasts of Magdala.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌叫眾人散去，就上船，來到馬加丹的境界。</TRANSL>
    </S>
</TEXT>