<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEXT id="Siraya_Dutch_Matthew_Chapter25" xml:lang="fos" source="Siraya Bible, Matthew gospel" copyright="public domain" citation="Gravius, Daniël. 1661. Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa. Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang. Amsterdam: Michiel Hartogh." BibTeX_citation="@book{Gravius1661,&#10;  author    = {Gravius, Daniël},&#10;  year      = {1661},&#10;  title     = {Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa},&#10;  note      = {Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang},&#10;  address   = {Amsterdam},&#10;  publisher = {Michiel Hartogh}&#10;}">
    <S id="verse1">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Tou kidi k'anna mama-ah ta Pei-sasou-an ki tounnoun ki vulluvullum ki sat kytti-æn ki kauh-jnejna, ka rou ni-ara nein ta poua-euingan nein, ni-tpapa-næh dmoumadoumma ki parah ka va'æu.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Tou kidi k'anna mama-ah ta Pei-sasou-an ki tounnoun ki vulluvullum ki sat kytti-æn ki kauh-jnejna, ka rou ni-ara nein ta poua-euingan nein, ni-tpapa-næh dmoumadoumma ki parah ka va'æu.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Esdan falc koninckEA riick der hemelen ghehiick zijn tien maregden welct hare lampen namen ende gingen uyt den Bjuydegom te gemoet.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then shall the kingdom of heaven be likened unto ten virgins, which took their lamps, and went forth to meet the bridegroom.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">「那時，天國好比十個童女拿着燈出去迎接新郎。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse2">
        <FORM kindOf="original">. Ka rarymma ta neni ka ma-tallahkau, rarymma-appa ta ma-rynhgæu.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">. Ka rarymma ta neni ka ma-tallahkau, rarymma-appa ta ma-rynhgæu.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende bijf ban haer waren whse ende de. bije waren dwase,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And five of them were wise, and five were foolish.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">其中有五個是愚拙的，五個是聰明的。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse3">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Neni ka marynhgau dou ni-ara nein ki pou-æuing-an nein, assi nein ni-ah-para ki jmagh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Neni ka marynhgau dou ni-ara nein ki pou-æuing-an nein, assi nein ni-ah-para ki jmagh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Die dwaes [wareo]Jhare lampen nemende en namen geen olye met haer.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">They that were foolish took their lamps, and took no oil with them:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">愚拙的拿着燈，卻不預備油；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse4">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ neni ka matallahkau ta ni-mara ki jmagh tou sato nein ahpara ki poutaeuing-an nein.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ neni ka matallahkau ta ni-mara ki jmagh tou sato nein ahpara ki poutaeuing-an nein.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">DMaye de wise namen odipe in hare baten met hare</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But the wise took oil in their vessels with their lamps.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">聰明的拿着燈，又預備油在器皿裏。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse5">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Jrou ka malanga ta Paræh, ka va'æu, nimy-ymmid misorugh, ka meirip-ato.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Jrou ka malanga ta Paræh, ka va'æu, nimy-ymmid misorugh, ka meirip-ato.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Als nt de Bruydegom bertoefde wierdt sy alle flupmerigh ende bielen in laep.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">While the bridegroom tarried, they all slumbered and slept.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">新郎遲延的時候，她們都打盹，睡着了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse6">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Jrou ka tonkad ta euvan ni-pako-langah-en', K'ytt'ei, irarou-roua ta parah ka va'æu, t'papa-næh-ei, doumadouma-au tyni-n.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Jrou ka tonkad ta euvan ni-pako-langah-en', K'ytt'ei, irarou-roua ta parah ka va'æu, t'papa-næh-ei, doumadouma-au tyni-n.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende ter midder-nacht gelchiedde een geroep Stet de Buiydegom komt gaet upt hem te gemoet.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And at midnight there was a cry made, Behold, the bridegroom cometh; go ye out to meet him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">半夜有人喊着說：『新郎來了，你們出來迎接他！』</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse7">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta ni-ælpit ta ymmid ki kæuh-jnejna k'anna, ka ni-siriang simimia ki pouæ-æugin an nein.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta ni-ælpit ta ymmid ki kæuh-jnejna k'anna, ka ni-siriang simimia ki pouæ-æugin an nein.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doe ftonden alle die marghden op ende bereyden hare lampen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then all those virgins arose, and trimmed their lamps.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那些童女就都起來收拾燈。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse8">
        <FORM kindOf="original">. Ka marynhgau ta ni-k'ma ki matallahkau, P'heikame ki imagh-ouni, ka mioup ta pata æuing'nian.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">. Ka marynhgau ta ni-k'ma ki matallahkau, P'heikame ki imagh-ouni, ka mioup ta pata æuing'nian.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende de dwale sepden tot de wijle Geeft ons ban uwe olye want onse lampen gaen upt. </TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And the foolish said unto the wise, Give us of your oil; for our lamps are gone out.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">愚拙的對聰明的說：『請分點油給我們， 因為我們的燈要滅了。』</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse9">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta matæl, lahkau, k'ma, [Aassi,] alei lava ka assi mamsing-ah ymian-æn, ymoumi-en-appa ta rouma: mou-auro-à mou-koua tou papeil-lan, ka peil-ato ki âmoumi-ab.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta matæl, lahkau, k'ma, [Aassi,] alei lava ka assi mamsing-ah ymian-æn, ymoumi-en-appa ta rouma: mou-auro-à mou-koua tou papeil-lan, ka peil-ato ki âmoumi-ab.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Boch de wijte antwoordden seggende [Geenfios ] op datter mitichien boor ons ende boor y niet ghenoegh en 3H: many gaet ieber tot de berkoopers ende koopt boor uselben,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But the wise answered, saying, Not so; lest there be not enough for us and you: but go ye rather to them that sell, and buy for yourselves.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">聰明的回答說：『恐怕不夠你我用的；不如你們自己到賣油的那裏去買吧。』</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse10">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou ka darang-en nein peila, ni-iroua ta Parah ka va-au, ka neni ka ni-patæu-tan, ni-toulam tyni-æn mourbo tou ibavauva-toug-han mavok, ka ni-ilben ta ngatass.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou ka darang-en nein peila, ni-iroua ta Parah ka va-au, ka neni ka ni-patæu-tan, ni-toulam tyni-æn mourbo tou ibavauva-toug-han mavok, ka ni-ilben ta ngatass.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Alsspnu henen ginghen om te koopen quam de Brupdegom ende die ghereedt{waren)gingen met hem in tot de Bruylotc ende de deure wiert gefioren.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And while they went to buy, the bridegroom came; and they that were ready went in with him to the marriage: and the door was shut.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">她們去買的時候，新郎到了。那預備好了的，同他進去坐席，門就關了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse11">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Si-æugh ni-irou'-appa ta kæuh-jnæ̈jna ka ra-rouma, k'ma, Meirang, Meirang, æu-lbei-ka-me.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Si-æugh ni-irou'-appa ta kæuh-jnæ̈jna ka ra-rouma, k'ma, Meirang, Meirang, æu-lbei-ka-me.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Daet na quamen oock de andere Maeghden segghende Heere Heere doet ons open.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Afterward came also the other virgins, saying, Lord, Lord, open to us.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">其餘的童女隨後也來了，說：『主啊，主啊，給我們開門！』</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse12">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka dou mattæ'i-v'lli ta teni vi-k'ma, issing koun-nau-kamou-râ, assi koh kmalang ymoumi-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka dou mattæ'i-v'lli ta teni vi-k'ma, issing koun-nau-kamou-râ, assi koh kmalang ymoumi-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende hy antwoordende sepde Doorwaer segge ick u ick en kenne u niet.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But he answered and said, Verily I say unto you, I know you not.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他卻回答說：『我實在告訴你們，我不認識你們。』</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse13">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta mahamæuæ-ä, ka assi-moumi oumhgan ta wæ'i ki kidi-appa ki te lei ka irouah ta Alak ki ka'æuloung.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta mahamæuæ-ä, ka assi-moumi oumhgan ta wæ'i ki kidi-appa ki te lei ka irouah ta Alak ki ka'æuloung.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Soo waeckt dan want ghy en weet den dagh niet noch de upre in de welcke de Sone des Menfchen komen fal.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Watch therefore, for ye know neither the day nor the hour wherein the Son of man cometh.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">所以，你們要警醒；因為那日子，那時辰，你們不知道。」 （路19‧11－27）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse14">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ mama [k'annæ] ki ka-æuloung, ka dou thabul-ah mou-koua tou pani ki pourough, ni-tmætæäm ki kouncia tyn, ka ni-pæ '-tounnoun-en tyn neini-æn ki hourup tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ mama [k'annæ] ki ka-æuloung, ka dou thabul-ah mou-koua tou pani ki pourough, ni-tmætæäm ki kouncia tyn, ka ni-pæ '-tounnoun-en tyn neini-æn ki hourup tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Want [ het is] ghelyck een mensche die buyten 'Slants reysende [ijne dienstRnechtenriep ende gaf haer syne goederen ober, .</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">For the kingdom of heaven is as a man travelling into a far country, who called his own servants, and delivered unto them his goods.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">「天國又好比一個人要往外國去，就叫了僕人來，把他的家業交給他們，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse15">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Kani-pää-rymma-en tyn ki talenten ki naunamou, ni-pa'ä-roua-en tyn ta kararouha, ni-pa sat-en tyn ta katatourou, ta meih-boua-voual na kidi ki pasiriang-eih tyn pasipyppyou, ka ni-madys tha boul.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Kani-pää-rymma-en tyn ki talenten ki naunamou, ni-pa'ä-roua-en tyn ta kararouha, ni-pa sat-en tyn ta katatourou, ta meih-boua-voual na kidi ki pasiriang-eih tyn pasipyppyou, ka ni-madys tha boul.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende den eenen gaf hy byf talenten ende den anderen twee ende den derden en een pegelick nae syn bermogen ende berreysde te;Ront.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And unto one he gave five talents, to another two, and to another one; to every man according to his several ability; and straightway took his journey.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">按着各人的才幹給他們銀子：一個給了五千，一個給了二千，一個給了一千，就往外國去了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse16">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka teni ka ni-a-rymma ki talenten, ni-d'marang p'a'i-assa ki anna, ka ni-pou-than ki ryryma ka pani.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka teni ka ni-a-rymma ki talenten, ni-d'marang p'a'i-assa ki anna, ka ni-pou-than ki ryryma ka pani.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Bien de bijf talenten sntkanghm hadde gin henen ende pandeids'd daer mede ende wan andere bijf talenten.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then he that had received the five talents went and traded with the same, and made them other five talents.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那領五千的隨即拿去做買賣，另外賺了五千。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse17">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Komm'æppa-hynna ta teni ka ni-a-douha, ni-pouthan ki ro-rouha ka pani.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Komm'æppa-hynna ta teni ka ni-a-douha, ni-pouthan ki ro-rouha ka pani.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">De sqrljcke oo oock die de twee[ont hadde,]die wan oock andere! twee.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And likewise he that had received two, he also gained other two.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那領二千的也照樣另賺了二千。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse18">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ra teni kani-a-sat mara, ni-d marang kmari tou næi, ka ni-ha tyn ta malyttouk ki Meirang tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ra teni kani-a-sat mara, ni-d marang kmari tou næi, ka ni-ha tyn ta malyttouk ki Meirang tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Maet die het een ontfangen hayde gingh henen ende groef in de aerde efi bergde het geldt ns hrem.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But he that had received one went and digged in the earth, and hid his lord's money.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">但那領一千的去掘開地，把主人的銀子埋藏了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse19">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka siäugh ki madallia ki kidi, ni-iroua ta Meirang ki koun cia kanna, ka ni-kting tyn mei-sal neini-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka siäugh ki madallia ki kidi, ni-iroua ta Meirang ki koun cia kanna, ka ni-kting tyn mei-sal neini-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende na eenen langen e quam de heere ban deFelbe-: dienstknechten ende hieldt reeckenirige met haer.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">After a long time the lord of those servants cometh, and reckoneth with them.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">過了許久，那些僕人的主人來了，和他們算帳。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse20">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Kateni ka ni-a-rymma ki talenten, ni-mou-koua maad ki ry-rymma-appa ka pa-nni ki talenten, ka ni-koua tyn, Meirang ryrymma ki talenten ka ni-pha-en-hou jaus an, k'yttei, ryrymma-appa ka pa nni ki talenten, ka ni-pou-saoun-koh pou-than ki anna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Kateni ka ni-a-rymma ki talenten, ni-mou-koua maad ki ry-rymma-appa ka pa-nni ki talenten, ka ni-koua tyn, Meirang ryrymma ki talenten ka ni-pha-en-hou jaus an, k'yttei, ryrymma-appa ka pa nni ki talenten, ka ni-pou-saoun-koh pou-than ki anna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende die de bijf talenten ontfangen hadde guam ende bracht tot hem andere ijf talenten segghende talenten hebt ghy my gegeben fiet andere byf ralenten hebbe ick boben deseibe gewonnen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And so he that had received five talents came and brought other five talents, saying, Lord, thou deliveredst unto me five talents: behold, I have gained beside them five talents more.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那領五千銀子的又帶着那另外的五千來，說：『主啊，你交給我五千銀子。請看，我又賺了五千。』</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse21">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-k'ma tyni-æn ta Meirang tyn, Mamsing, kouncia ka mariang ka makidkid, ni-ma kidkid kow tou katiting-an, ka pasi-bavau-aumau kow ki ma-dagh: Mou-rbo-à tou karei-en ki Meirang oho.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-k'ma tyni-æn ta Meirang tyn, Mamsing, kouncia ka mariang ka makidkid, ni-ma kidkid kow tou katiting-an, ka pasi-bavau-aumau kow ki ma-dagh: Mou-rbo-à tou karei-en ki Meirang oho.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende shn heere sepde tot them Wel ghy goedeende getrouwe dienftknecht ober weynigh 3ht 0, ghetronw' gheweelt ober bele fsal ick u setten: Gaet in inde breughde uwes heeren.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">His lord said unto him, Well done, thou good and faithful servant: thou hast been faithful over a few things, I will make thee ruler over many things: enter thou into the joy of thy lord.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">主人說：『好，你這又良善又忠心的僕人，你在不多的事上有忠心，我要把許多事派你管理；可以進來享受你主人的快樂。』</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse22">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka dou moukoua ta teni, ka ni-à-douba ki talenten, ni-koua tyn, Meirang, dourouha ki talen-ten ta ni-p'ha-en-hou jau-an, k'yt-t'ei, rourouha-appa ki pa-nni ki talenten ka ni-pou-saoun-koh pou than.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka dou moukoua ta teni, ka ni-à-douba ki talenten, ni-koua tyn, Meirang, dourouha ki talenten ta ni-p'ha-en-hou jau-an, k'yt-t'ei, rourouha-appa ki pa-nni ki talenten ka ni-pou-saoun-koh pou than.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Qnde die de twee talenten ontfangen hadde uam oock tot hem ende seyde Heere twee talenten hebt ghy my gegeben siet twee andere talenten hebbe ick boden deselbe gewonnen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">He also that had received two talents came and said, Lord, thou deliveredst unto me two talents: behold, I have gained two other talents beside them.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那領二千的也來，說：『主啊，你交給我二千銀子。請看，我又賺了二千。』</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse23">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-kma tyni-æn ta Mei-rang tyn, Mamsing kouncia ka mariang ka makidkid, Ni-makid-kid kow katiting-an, pæsi-bavau au-mau kow ki madagh: Mou-rbo-tou karæi-en ki Meirang oho.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-kma tyni-æn ta Mei-rang tyn, Mamsing kouncia ka mariang ka makidkid, Ni-makid-kid kow katiting-an, pæsi-bavau au-mau kow ki madagh: Mou-rbo-tou karæi-en ki Meirang oho.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Syn heere sepde tot hem Wel ghy goede ende getrouwe diensiknecht ober weynigh zijt ghy getrouw' geweelt ober bele sal ick u eetten: Gaet m in de breughde uwes heeren.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">His lord said unto him, Well done, good and faithful servant; thou hast been faithful over a few things, I will make thee ruler over many things: enter thou into the joy of thy lord.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">主人說：『好，你這又良善又忠心的僕人，你在不多的事上有忠心，我要把許多事派你管理；可以進來享受你主人的快樂。』</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse24">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka dou mou-koua ta teni ka ni-æ-sat ki talent, ni-koua tyn, Meirang, k'alang-en-au kow ka ka'æuloung kow ka maplægh, ka majam kow ki assi'mhou na da diri, ka pa-lud kow ki assi'mhou na sasasbugh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka dou mou-koua ta teni ka ni-æ-sat ki talent, ni-koua tyn, Meirang, k'alang-en-au kow ka ka'æuloung kow ka maplægh, ka majam kow ki assi'mhou na da diri, ka pa-lud kow ki assi'mhou na sasasbugh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Mae! die het een talent ontfangé hadde quam oock ende leyde Heere ick kende u dat ghy een hardt mensche 5yt maepende daer ghy niec geraeyt en hebt ende bergaderende ban daer [waer] ghy met gelthoyt en hebc.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then he which had received the one talent came and said, Lord, I knew thee that thou art an hard man, reaping where thou hast not sown, and gathering where thou hast not strawed:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那領一千的也來，說：『主啊，我知道你是忍心的人，沒有種的地方要收割，沒有散的地方要聚斂，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse25">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka alei ki tahkout-au ni-d'marang-koh hmaa ki talent oho tourbo ki næi: k'ytt'ei, akoumea kow-ki â'mhou.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka alei ki tahkout-au ni-d'marang-koh hmaa ki talent oho tourbo ki næi: k'ytt'ei, akoumea kow-ki â'mhou.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Eii bebyreett zijnde ben ick henen gegaen ende hebbe uw' talent berborghen inde aerde: siet ghy hebt het uwe.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And I was afraid, and went and hid thy talent in the earth: lo, there thou hast that is thine.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我就害怕，去把你的一千銀子埋藏在地裏。請看，你的原銀子在這裏。』</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse26">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ràni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta Mei-rang tyn, k'ma tyni-æn, Kouncia ka mate, ka manhgad, kavanna-en-hou, ka majam koh tou assi mau nad-adiri, ka palud-koh ki assi-mæu-na sasasbugh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ràni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta Mei-rang tyn, k'ma tyni-æn, Kouncia ka mate, ka manhgad, kavanna-en-hou, ka majam koh tou assi mau nad-adiri, ka palud-koh ki assi-mæu-na sasasbugh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Maer syn heere antwoordefi sepde tot hem Gy boole ende luye dienstknecht ghy wilt dat ick maeye daer ick niet geraept en hebbe ende ban daer bergadere waer ick niet geftropt en hebbe.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">His lord answered and said unto him, Thou wicked and slothful servant, thou knewest that I reap where I sowed not, and gather where I have not strawed:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">主人回答說：『你這又惡又懶的僕人，你既知道我沒有種的地方要收割，沒有散的地方要聚斂，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse27">
        <FORM kindOf="original">. Anna ta ynna'mhou p'hei ta malitouk-au ki Tama-viri, ka dou irouato-koh, ni-alikough-au ta à jau lam ki than.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">. Anna ta ynna'mhou p'hei ta malitouk-au ki Tama-viri, ka dou irouato-koh, ni-alikough-au ta à jau lam ki than.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">So moelt ghy dan mijn geldt den willelaren gedaen hebben efi ick komende foude het mijne weder genomen hebben met woecker.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Thou oughtest therefore to have put my money to the exchangers, and then at my coming I should have received mine own with usury.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">就當把我的銀子放給兌換銀錢的人，到我來的時候，可以連本帶利收回。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse28">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta hami-au ta talent k'anna, ka pha-an-eito tyni-æn ka akoumea ki sât kyttian ki ta-lenten.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta hami-au ta talent k'anna, ka pha-an-eito tyni-æn ka akoumea ki sât kyttian ki talenten.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Neemt dan ban hem her talent wech ende geeft et den-genen die de tien taten heeft. "' ,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Take therefore the talent from him, and give it unto him which hath ten talents.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">奪過他這一千來，給那有一萬的。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse29">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka veiagh ka akoumea, teni ta p'heih, ka poudimm'eil appa: râ teni ka aou-si, ara-eil appa ta akoumea tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka veiagh ka akoumea, teni ta p'heih, ka poudimm'eil appa: râ teni ka aou-si, ara-eil appa ta akoumea tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Want een pegelick die heeft [dien]sal gegeben worden ende hy sal oberbloedig hebben: mae ban degene die niet en heeft ban dien sal genomen worden oock dat hy</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">For unto every one that hath shall be given, and he shall have abundance: but from him that hath not shall be taken away even that which he hath.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">因為凡有的，還要加給他，叫他有餘；沒有的，連他所有的也要奪過來。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse30">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka aryng-an-ei ta kouncia k'anna ka saramsam smaki-tæuagh tyni-æn tou siouro itou-tæuagh ka karimdim-man, tou hynna-al-ato ta tangi-tangi-an ki pæ-it-ing-en-appa ki waligh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka aryng-an-ei ta kouncia k'anna ka saramsam smaki-tæuagh tyni-æn tou siouro itou-tæuagh ka karimdim-man, tou hynna-al-ato ta tangi-tangi-an ki pæ-it-ing-en-appa ki waligh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende den onnutten dienstknecht werpt uyt in de buptenste dupsternisse daer sal weeninge riji ende kner singe der tand.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And cast ye the unprofitable servant into outer darkness: there shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">把這無用的僕人丟在外面黑暗裏；在那裏必要哀哭切齒了。』」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse31">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka rou irou-'al-ato ta Alak ki ka'æuloung tou keirang-en k-kidi tyn, md-appa ki Tama-Gnau ka dlligh matiktik tou-lam tyni-æn, anna ta ierrong-eih tyn tou iirrarong-an ki keirang-en ki kidi tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka rou irou-'al-ato ta Alak ki ka'æuloung tou keirang-en k-kidi tyn, md-appa ki Tama-Gnau ka dlligh matiktik tou-lam tyni-æn, anna ta ierrong-eih tyn tou iirrarong-an ki keirang-en ki kidi tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Endewanneer de Sone des menschen komen sal in ijae heerlickheydt ende alle de Heplige Engelen met hem dan sal hy sitten op den Thyooon ijner heerlick-</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">When the Son of man shall come in his glory, and all the holy angels with him, then shall he sit upon the throne of his glory:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">「當人子在他榮耀裏、同着眾天使降臨的時候，要坐在他榮耀的寶座上。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse32">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka pæpa-al-eih tou æmah tyni-æn ta ymmid ki ta'utaou, ka papah-piah-eih tyn ta neni k'anna mæi tou-tavætævæh mama ki sou-ajam ka papahpiæh ki jouko ki jou.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka pæpa-al-eih tou æmah tyni-æn ta ymmid ki ta'utaou, ka papah-piah-eih tyn ta neni k'anna mæi tou-tavætævæh mama ki sou-ajam ka papahpiæh ki jouko ki jou.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Endeboorhemsullen atle de bolckeren bergadert worden ende hy salse ban malkanderen scheyden geliick de herde; deschapenban de bocken schepdet. .</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And before him shall be gathered all nations: and he shall separate them one from another, as a shepherd divideth his sheep from the goats:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">萬民都要聚集在他面前。他要把他們分別出來，好像牧羊的分別綿羊山羊一般，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse33">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka pa-itou-oual-eih tyn ta joukko, râ pa-itou-'u'i-eih tn ta jou.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka pa-itou-oual-eih tyn ta joukko, râ pa-itou-'u'i-eih tn ta jou.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende hy saldeschapen tot stjner rechter-[haodr] fetten maer de bocken tot [fjner] fliincker [bandr.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And he shall set the sheep on his right hand, but the goats on the left.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">把綿羊安置在右邊，山羊在左邊。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse34">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta mattæ'i-komm.al-appa-hynna ki sou ta Mei-sasou ka Si-bavau neini-æn ka itou-koua tou ouwal tyn, Mou-koua hia ta ymoumi ka ni-paka-riang-en-ka-mou ki sou ki Rama-au, tabli-ato ki Pei-sasouan ka ni tanang-in y-mouni-æn na kidi ki ni-pæitou-samding-en ta raroun ki Næi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta mattæ'i-komm.al-appa-hynna ki sou ta Mei-sasou ka Si-bavau neini-æn ka itou-koua tou ouwal tyn, Mou-koua hia ta ymoumi ka ni-paka-riang-en-ka-mou ki sou ki Rama-au, tabli-ato ki Pei-sasouan ka ni tanang-in y-mouni-æn na kidi ki ni-pæitou-samding-en ta raroun ki Næi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Alsdan sal de honing feggen tot de gene die totshw eee zijn,] Home ghy gheregende myns Dades be-erft dac Koninckrijck het welck u bereydt is ban de gront-legginge der</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then shall the King say unto them on his right hand, Come, ye blessed of my Father, inherit the kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the world:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">於是王要向那右邊的說：『你們這蒙我父賜福的，可來承受那創世以來為你們所預備的國；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse35">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-mahgang-ei-koh, ka ni-pakan-noumi jauan: Ni-myt-okoh, ka ni-pæ-yt-noumi jæu-an: Ni-tæ ækoua-en-at-'mau, ka ni-pæ-ih-tatallagh-'noumi jæu-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-mahgang-ei-koh, ka ni-pakan-noumi jauan: Ni-myt-okoh, ka ni-pæ-yt-noumi jæu-an: Ni-tæ ækoua-en-at-'mau, ka ni-pæ-ih-tatallagh-'noumi jæu-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Want ick ben hongerigh geweelt ende ghy hebt mp te eten gegeben: Ick ben dorltigh geweelt ende ghy hebt my te drincken gegebe : Ack was een breemdelingh efl ohy hebt my gehe:berght.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">For I was an hungred, and ye gave me meat: I was thirsty, and ye gave me drink: I was a stranger, and ye took me in:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">因為我餓了，你們給我吃，渴了，你們給我喝；我作客旅，你們留我住；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse36">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ni-mannana, ka ni-pæ-pah-koulamough-kamou jau-an: Ni-malam-kob, ka ni-donoy-ka-mou-jæuan Ni-æ'ia-koua-en-au tou sangat, ka ni-mou-koua-ka-mou jæu-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ni-mannana, ka ni-pæ-pah-koulamough-kamou jau-an: Ni-malam-kob, ka ni-donoy-ka-mou-jæuan Ni-æ'ia-koua-en-au tou sangat, ka ni-mou-koua-ka-mou jæu-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">[ick was] naeckt ende ghy hebt my gekleedt : Ick ben kranck geweelt ende ghy hebt wp besocht: Ick was n de gebangenisse ende ghy zijt tot my gekoiwen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Naked, and ye clothed me: I was sick, and ye visited me: I was in prison, and ye came unto me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我赤身露體，你們給我穿；我病了，你們看顧我；我在監裏，你們來看我。』</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse37">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta mattæ'i-v'lli-ah ty-ni-æn ta matiktik, ka k'ma-ah, Meirang, ni-k'yttæ'ni-an ka man-no ymhou-an ka mahgangei kow, ka ni-pækan'nian ymhou-an? ka meytto kow, ka ni-pæ-yt'nian ym-hou-an?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta mattæ'i-v'lli-ah ty-ni-æn ta matiktik, ka k'ma-ah, Meirang, ni-k'yttæ'ni-an ka man-no ymhou-an ka mahgangei kow, ka ni-pækan'nian ymhou-an? ka meytto kow, ka ni-pæ-yt'nian ym-hou-an?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Dan sullen de rechtbeerdige hem antwoorden seggende Heere wanneer hebben wp u hongerigh gelien ende gelpijlight + ofte dosstigh ende te drincken gegeben</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then shall the righteous answer him, saying, Lord, when saw we thee an hungred, and fed thee? or thirsty, and gave thee drink?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">義人就回答說：『主啊，我們甚麼時候見你餓了，給你吃，渴了，給你喝？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse38">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-kytta'nian ka manno ymhou-an ka ta'ä-koua kow, ka ni-pæ-ih-tallagh-nian ymhou-an? ka mannana kow, ka ni-pæpæh-koulamough-'nian ymhou-an?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-kytta'nian ka manno ymhou-an ka ta'ä-koua kow, ka ni-pæ-ih-tallagh-nian ymhou-an? ka mannana kow, ka ni-pæpæh-koulamough-'nian ymhou-an?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende wanneer hebben wp u een bremdelingy | gheefien ende gehodecght s ofte naeckt mde gekleedt $</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">When saw we thee a stranger, and took thee in? or naked, and clothed thee?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">甚麼時候見你作客旅，留你住，或是赤身露體，給你穿？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse39">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ni-kytta'nian ka manno ymhou-an, ka maälam kow, ka ton sangat, ka ni-ou-koua'-i-hou-an?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ni-kytta'nian ka manno ymhou-an, ka maälam kow, ka ton sangat, ka ni-ou-koua'-i-hou-an?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende wanneer hebben wp u kranck gelien often de gebangenisle ende zijn tot u gekomen # \</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Or when saw we thee sick, or in prison, and came unto thee?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">又甚麼時候見你病了，或是在監裏，來看你呢？』</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse40">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka matteæi-v'lli-ah ta Mei-sasou ka Sibavau mattæ'i-k'ma-hynna neini-æn, Missing koun-nau-kamou, pa-pynn'an-oumi pæ-mut [ta atta] ki saat ki tæ'i-apara-au katta ka ousysing, ni-pâmt'n-oumi [ta anna] jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka matteæi-v'lli-ah ta Mei-sasou ka Sibavau mattæ'i-k'ma-hynna neini-æn, Missing koun-nau-kamou, pa-pynn'an-oumi pæ-mut [ta atta] ki saat ki tæ'i-apara-au katta ka ousysing, ni-pâmt'n-oumi [ta anna] jau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende de koningh sal antwoorden ende tot hae feggen Doorwaee segge ick u boo soo beel ghp [ditJeen ban dese mijne minste Broeders gedaen hebc soo hebt ghy [dat] my gedaem.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And the King shall answer and say unto them, Verily I say unto you, Inasmuch as ye have done it unto one of the least of these my brethren, ye have done it unto me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">王要回答說：『我實在告訴你們，這些事你們既做在我這弟兄中一個最小的身上，就是做在我身上了。』</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse41">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta mattæ'i-k'ma-al-appa-hyuna ki sou neini-æn ka itou-u'i, D'marang-â jau-an einou-mi ka ni-pahko-avavaghen mou koua tou apoei ka myhkakoua myddarinouh, ka ni-tanangen ka à tou Lyttou-ah ki Tama-Gnau appa tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta mattæ'i-k'ma-al-appa-hyuna ki sou neini-æn ka itou-u'i, D'marang-â jau-an einou-mi ka ni-pahko-avavaghen mou koua tou apoei ka myhkakoua myddarinouh, ka ni-tanangen ka à tou Lyttou-ah ki Tama-Gnau appa tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Dan al hy seggen oock tot de gene die ter flincKer-shant zijn, } Gaet wech ban my ghy berbloeckte in het eeuwige byer het welck den Duybel ende lijnen Engelen bereydt is.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then shall he say also unto them on the left hand, Depart from me, ye cursed, into everlasting fire, prepared for the devil and his angels:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">王又要向那左邊的說：『你們這被咒詛的人，離開我！進入那為魔鬼和他的使者所預備的永火裏去！</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse42">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Kani-kagangei-en-au, ka assi-moumi ni-pakan jau-an: Ni-yht-o-en-au, ka assi-'noumi ni-pæ-yt jau-an,</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Kani-kagangei-en-au, ka assi-moumi ni-pakan jau-an: Ni-yht-o-en-au, ka assi-'noumi ni-pæ-yt jau-an,</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Want ick ben hongerigh geweelt ende ghy en eht my niet te eten gegeben: k ben dorstigh geweelt ende ghp en hebt my niet te diincken gegeben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">For I was an hungred, and ye gave me no meat: I was thirsty, and ye gave me no drink:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">因為我餓了，你們不給我吃，渴了，你們不給我喝；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse43">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ni-tæua-en-au, ka assinoumi ni-pa-ih-tallagh jau-an: Ni-pannana-en-au, ka assi-noumi ni-pæpæhkoulamough jau-an: Ni-kaälam-en-au, ka ni-itou-koua-en-au tou sangat, ka assi-moumi ni-k'ytt'an jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ni-tæua-en-au, ka assinoumi ni-pa-ih-tallagh jau-an: Ni-pannana-en-au, ka assi-noumi ni-pæpæhkoulamough jau-an: Ni-kaälam-en-au, ka ni-itou-koua-en-au tou sangat, ka assi-moumi ni-k'ytt'an jau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ick was een breemdelingh ende ghp en hebt mpniet geherbergt: Naeckt ende ghy en hebt my niet geKleedt : Kranck ende in de bangenisse ende ghp en Hebe my nier besocht.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I was a stranger, and ye took me not in: naked, and ye clothed me not: sick, and in prison, and ye visited me not.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我作客旅，你們不留我住；我赤身露體，你們不給我穿；我病了，我在監裏，你們不來看顧我。』</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse44">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta mattæ'i-v'lli-ah ta neni tyni-æn mattæ'i-k'ma-hynna, Meirang, manno ka ni-kytta'ni an ymhou-an, ka mahgangei, ka meyto, ka ta koua, ka manna-na, ka maälam, ka tou sangat la va, ka assi-mi-æn ni-illig-ben pilei-leigh ymhou-an?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta mattæ'i-v'lli-ah ta neni tyni-æn mattæ'i-k'ma-hynna, Meirang, manno ka ni-kytta'ni an ymhou-an, ka mahgangei, ka meyto, ka ta koua, ka manna-na, ka maälam, ka tou sangat la va, ka assi-mi-æn ni-illig-ben pilei-leigh ymhou-an?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Dan fullen oock dese Hem antwoorden feggende Heere wanneer hebben wp u hongerigh ghesien of dorliigh of een brcembelingh of naeckt of kranck ofte im de gebangenilse ende en hebben u niet gedients |</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then shall they also answer him, saying, Lord, when saw we thee an hungred, or athirst, or a stranger, or naked, or sick, or in prison, and did not minister unto thee?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們也要回答說：『主啊，我們甚麼時候見你餓了，或渴了，或作客旅，或赤身露體，或病了，或在監裏，不伺候你呢？』</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse45">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta mattæ'i-v'lli-ah ta teni ki sou neini-æn, Misling koun-næu-kamou-râ: Pa'-pyun-an-noumi assi pamut [ta anna] ki saät ki ousyssing k'atta, assi-appa-moumi ni-pam't-en ta atta jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta mattæ'i-v'lli-ah ta teni ki sou neini-æn, Misling koun-næu-kamou-râ: Pa'-pyun-an-noumi assi pamut [ta anna] ki saät ki ousyssing k'atta, assi-appa-moumi ni-pam't-en ta atta jau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Dan sal hy haer antwoorden ende [eggen Doorwae? segge ick u : Yoo! soo beel ghy [dit] een ban dese minlte niet gedaen en heb so enhebt ghp het my oock niet gedaen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then shall he answer them, saying, Verily I say unto you, Inasmuch as ye did it not to one of the least of these, ye did it not to me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">王要回答說：『我實在告訴你們，這些事你們既不做在我這弟兄中一個最小的身上，就是不做在我身上了。』</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse46">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka moukoua-ah ta neni katta tou pæ'i-alalam-en ka myh. kakoua myddarynnough: rå ne ni ka matiktik, tou kæuaghan ka myhkakoua myddarynnough. Kararouha kytti an 'ab ki nnum kilbæh ki soulat.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka moukoua-ah ta neni katta tou pæ'i-alalam-en ka myh. kakoua myddarynnough: rå ne ni ka matiktik, tou kæuaghan ka myhkakoua myddarynnough. Kararouha kytti an 'ab ki nnum kilbæh ki soulat.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Endedese sullen gaen in de eeuwige pyne : maer de rechtbeerdige in dat eeuwige leben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And these shall go away into everlasting punishment: but the righteous into life eternal.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">這些人要往永刑裏去；那些義人要往永生裏去。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
</TEXT>