<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEXT id="Siraya_Dutch_Matthew_Chapter2" xml:lang="fos" source="Siraya Bible, Matthew gospel" copyright="public domain" citation="Gravius, Daniël. 1661. Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa. Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang. Amsterdam: Michiel Hartogh." BibTeX_citation="@book{Gravius1661,&#10;  author    = {Gravius, Daniël},&#10;  year      = {1661},&#10;  title     = {Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa},&#10;  note      = {Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang},&#10;  address   = {Amsterdam},&#10;  publisher = {Michiel Hartogh}&#10;}" dialect="Siraya">
    <S id="verse1">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> NDa heirou ka ni-pei-alak ta ti Jesus tou Bethlehem ka [irou] Judeä, tou wæï ki Mei-sasou ka si-bavau ka ti Hero-des; Kyttey nilummad ta Makouzazyng pou-lilyt ka ni-makkareia mou-qua tou Jerusalem</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> NDa heirou ka ni-pei-alak ta ti Jesus tou Bethlehem ka [irou] Judeä, tou wæï ki Mei-sasou ka si-bavau ka ti Hero-des; Kyttey nilummad ta Makouzazyng pou-lilyt ka ni-makkareia mou-qua tou Jerusalem</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Doe nu Jesus geboren was te Bethlehem [ geleghen ] in Judea in de daghen des Honinghs Herodis siet [eenighe] Wijse ban Oolten zijn tot Jerusalem aengekomen </TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Now when Jesus was born in Bethlehem of Judaea in the days of Herod the king, behold, there came wise men from the east to Jerusalem,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">當希律王的時候，耶穌生在猶太的伯利恆。有幾個博士從東方來到耶路撒冷，說：</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse2">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Koun, Tou-mang ta ni-pei-alak ka Si-bavau ka Mei-sasou ki Joden? ka' ni-k'ytta-niæn tæ'æreia ta attatalingei tyn, ka ni-lum-mad-kame tou deip-eih tyni-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Koun, Tou-mang ta ni-pei-alak ka Si-bavau ka Mei-sasou ki Joden? ka' ni-k'ytta-niæn tæ'æreia ta attatalingei tyn, ka ni-lum-mad-kame tou deip-eih tyni-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Segghende Waer is de geborene Koning der Jodens want wy hebben gesien sijne Sterre in het Oosten ende zijn gekomen om hem te aenbidden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Saying, Where is he that is born King of the Jews? for we have seen his star in the east, and are come to worship him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">「那生下來作猶太人之王的在哪裏？我們在東方看見他的星，特來拜他。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse3">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou ka ni-illingigh [ta atta] ki Mei-sasou ka li-bavau ka ti Herodes, mi-harashasato [ta teni] ki sat ka'æumang-appa ki Jerusalem tou lam tyni-æn</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou ka ni-illingigh [ta atta] ki Mei-sasou ka li-bavau ka ti Herodes, mi-harashasato [ta teni] ki sat ka'æumang-appa ki Jerusalem tou lam tyni-æn</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> De Koningh Herodes nu [dir] gehoort hebbende wiert ontroert de geheel Jerusalem met hem.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">When Herod the king had heard these things, he was troubled, and all Jerusalem with him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">希律王聽見了，就心裏不安；耶路撒冷合城的人也都不安。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse4">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka rou ni-papa-'eui-sâl tyn ymmid ta Tama P'hgik ka Sibavau ki Makou-sasoulat-appa ki tau, ni-tmaligh neini-æn, pei-alak-auh lava tou-mang ta ti Christus?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka rou ni-papa-'eui-sâl tyn ymmid ta Tama P'hgik ka Sibavau ki Makou-sasoulat-appa ki tau, ni-tmaligh neini-æn, pei-alak-auh lava tou-mang ta ti Christus?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende by een bergadert hebbende alle de Oberpriesters ende Schriftgeleerde des bolcks braeghde ban hen waer de Christus soude geboren worden :</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And when he had gathered all the chief priests and scribes of the people together, he demanded of them where Christ should be born.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他就召齊了祭司長和民間的文士，問他們說：「基督當生在何處？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse5">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-k'ma ta ne-ni tyni-æn tou Bethlehem, ka [itou] Judea, ka ni-'æ'ǣ-k'man hynna smoulat ki Mattæi-tan;</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-k'ma ta ne-ni tyni-æn tou Bethlehem, ka [itou] Judea, ka ni-'æ'ǣ-k'man hynna smoulat ki Mattæi-tan;</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende sy seyden tot hem te Bethlehem in Judea [gelegen,] want alsoo is geschreben door den Propheet </TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And they said unto him, In Bethlehem of Judaea: for thus it is written by the prophet,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們回答說：「在猶太的伯利恆。因為有先知記着，說：</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse6">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka [ymhou] Bethlehem ta pourough ki Juda, mada 'æ'ua assi æussy-æussyng kow ki fi-bavau dmilough Mei-sasou ki Juda; alei ka makka-qua-ah ymhou-an mæu-pænæh ta Tama-D'yllough, ka kma-ding-ah ki tau-au ka Israël.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka [ymhou] Bethlehem ta pourough ki Juda, mada 'æ'ua assi æussy-æussyng kow ki fi-bavau dmilough Mei-sasou ki Juda; alei ka makka-qua-ah ymhou-an mæu-pænæh ta Tama-D'yllough, ka kma-ding-ah ki tau-au ka Israël.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende [ ghy ] Bethlehem gy land Juda en zijt geensins de minste onder de Dorsten Juda want uyt u sal de Leydseman boortboortkomen die mijn bolck Israel weyden sal.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And thou Bethlehem, in the land of Juda, art not the least among the princes of Juda: for out of thee shall come a Governor, that shall rule my people Israel.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">猶大地的伯利恆啊，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse7">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Tou kidi kanna ni-makou-ouzoung tmatæ'æm ki Makou-zazyng poulilyt k'anna ta ti Herodes, ni-mou-nḡara neini-æn ki ki-di ki ni-eu-pænæ'-en ki atta-tallin-gei neini-æn?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Tou kidi kanna ni-makou-ouzoung tmatæ'æm ki Makou-zazyng poulilyt k'anna ta ti Herodes, ni-mou-nḡara neini-æn ki ki-di ki ni-eu-pænæ'-en ki atta-tallin-gei neini-æn?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Doe heeft Herodes de Wijse heymelick gheroepen ende bernam neerstelick ban haer den tijdt wanneer de Sterre berschenen was.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then Herod, when he had privily called the wise men, enquired of them diligently what time the star appeared.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">當下，希律暗暗地召了博士來，細問那星是甚麼時候出現的，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse8">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka rou madingi-dingi neini-æn ton Bethlehem, ni k'ma, 'Oudadarang-au maki-pougas kmi'ymalei ki rauwei, ka rou paki-valei-'noumi tateni, lmi-kog-ag'nnau iau-an, alei ka irou-âl-appa-koh deip tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka rou madingi-dingi neini-æn ton Bethlehem, ni k'ma, 'Oudadarang-au maki-pougas kmi'ymalei ki rauwei, ka rou paki-valei-'noumi tateni, lmi-kog-ag'nnau iau-an, alei ka irou-âl-appa-koh deip tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> En haer na Bethlehem sendende seyde Reyst henen en ondersoeckt neerstelick na dat kindeken en als ghy het sult gebonden hebben boodschapt het my op dat ick oock kome ende dat selbe aenbidde.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And he sent them to Bethlehem, and said, Go and search diligently for the young child; and when ye have found him, bring me word again, that I may come and worship him also.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">就差他們往伯利恆去，說：「你們去仔細尋訪那小孩子，尋到了就來報信，我也好去拜他。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse9">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Neni k'anna dou ni-tna-kah'ato millingigh ki Mei-sasou ka Si-bavau, ni-d'maran'g atou-ra, Ka k'ytt'ey, ta attatalingei ka ni-ara-rau nein, tæ'ǣ-reia, ni-'t-ourourou'tauqua neini-æn tou kidi-appa k'anna, ka ni-tau-qua rihkau tou vavau ki itou-qu-'an ki rauwei-ra.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Neni k'anna dou ni-tna-kah'ato millingigh ki Mei-sasou ka Si-bavau, ni-d'maran'g atou-ra, Ka k'ytt'ey, ta attatalingei ka ni-ara-rau nein, tæ'ǣ-reia, ni-'t-ourourou'tauqua neini-æn tou kidi-appa k'anna, ka ni-tau-qua rihkau tou vavau ki itou-qu-'an ki rauwei-ra.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende sy den Koningh ghehoort hebbende zijn henen gereyst : ende siet de Sterre die sy in 't Oosten gesien hadden gingh haer boor tot dat sy quam ende stont boben [ de plaerse ] daer het kindeken was.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">When they had heard the king, they departed; and, lo, the star, which they saw in the east, went before them, till it came and stood over where the young child was.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們聽見王的話就去了。在東方所看見的那星忽然在他們前頭行，直行到小孩子的地方，就在上頭停住了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse10">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou ka k'yyt'an nein ta attatalingei nda, ni-mar-'ei ta nei-ni ki karai-jen ka ouhang irang.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou ka k'yyt'an nein ta attatalingei nda, ni-mar-'ei ta neini ki karai-jen ka ouhang irang.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Als sy nu de Sterre saghen berbreugden sy haer met seer groote breughde.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">When they saw the star, they rejoiced with exceeding great joy.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們看見那星，就大大地歡喜；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse11">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka tou 'ou-rarbo-en nein ki tallagh, ni-paki-valei nein ta rauwei lam ki Raren'an tyn ka ti Maria: ka tou pædouklou-en nein, nireip tyni-æn. Heirou ka ni-ȧ'æul'b-ben ta vangei nein, ni-æd nein tyni-æn ta hahoriouriou ka kym, lyttæu-appa ka Myrrha.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka tou 'ou-rarbo-en nein ki tallagh, ni-paki-valei nein ta rauwei lam ki Raren'an tyn ka ti Maria: ka tou pædouklou-en nein, nireip tyni-æn. Heirou ka ni-ȧ'æul'b-ben ta vangei nein, ni-æd nein tyni-æn ta hahoriouriou ka kym, lyttæu-appa ka Myrrha.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende in het huys geKomen zijnde bonden sy het kindeken met Maria sijne moeder : ende nederballende hebben sy het selbe aengebeden. En hare schatten open gedaen hebbende brachten sy hem geschencken Gout ende ende Weroock en Myrrhe.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And when they were come into the house, they saw the young child with Mary his mother, and fell down, and worshipped him: and when they had opened their treasures, they presented unto him gifts; gold, and frankincense and myrrh.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">進了房子，看見小孩子和他母親馬利亞，就俯伏拜那小孩子，揭開寶盒，拿黃金、乳香、沒藥為禮物獻給他。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse12">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou ka ni-pahkou-fou-en tou maling ka assimæ'æum-vei-ryng-ah sa-likough ti Herodes-an, ni-tauqua tou pani ki d-'arang mou-qua tou pourough nein-ra.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou ka ni-pahkou-fou-en tou maling ka assimæ'æum-vei-ryng-ah sa-likough ti Herodes-an, ni-tauqua tou pani ki d-'arang mou-qua tou pourough nein-ra.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> En door Goddelike openbaringe bermaent zijnde in de drod dat sy niet en souDE weder keert tot Herodem bertrockt sy door eent anderen weg weder na haer land.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And being warned of God in a dream that they should not return to Herod, they departed into their own country another way.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">博士因為在夢中被主指示不要回去見希律，就從別的路回本地去了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse13">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou ka ni-ta'æu-kaha d'marang ta neini, k'yytey ta Tama-Gnau ki MEIRANG moupænæh tou maling ti Josef-an, mattæi-k'ma hynna; Æhpit-tâ'æuh-au ta Rauwei [pa-toug-par-'au] ta tu Ina tyn, illup't-tâ mou-qua tou Egypten, ka itou-qua-appa hynna ka vana-vana-ei maukow: ka k'ma-alato hynna ka kmi-ym-ah ta ti Herodes ki Rauwei, ki pakapatei-eih tyni-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou ka ni-ta'æu-kaha d'marang ta neini, k'yytey ta Tama-Gnau ki MEIRANG moupænæh tou maling ti Josef-an, mattæi-k'ma hynna; Æhpit-tâ'æuh-au ta Rauwei [pa-toug-par-'au] ta tu Ina tyn, illup't-tâ mou-qua tou Egypten, ka itou-qua-appa hynna ka vana-vana-ei maukow: ka k'ma-alato hynna ka kmi-ym-ah ta ti Herodes ki Rauwei, ki pakapatei-eih tyni-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Doe sy nu bertrocken waren siet de Enghel des Heeren berschijnt Joseph in den droom seggende Staet op ende neemt tot u dat kindeken ende sijne moeder ende bliet in Egypten ende weest aldaer tot dat ick het u segghen sal. Want Herodes sal het kindeken soecken om het selbe te dooden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And when they were departed, behold, the angel of the Lord appeareth to Joseph in a dream, saying, Arise, and take the young child and his mother, and flee into Egypt, and be thou there until I bring thee word: for Herod will seek the young child to destroy him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們去後，有主的使者向約瑟夢中顯現，說：「起來！帶着小孩子同他母親逃往埃及，住在那裏，等我吩咐你；因為希律必尋找小孩子，要除滅他。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse14">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta, teni rou ni-pa-patti-mæuag-hen ni-'mmara ki Rauwei lam ki Raren-'an tyn ka euvannæn, ka ni-d'marang fah-kaqua tou Egypten.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta, teni rou ni-pa-patti-mæuag-hen ni-'mmara ki Rauwei lam ki Raren-'an tyn ka euvannæn, ka ni-d'marang fah-kaqua tou Egypten.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Hy dan opgestaen zijnde nam het kindeken ende sijne moeder tot hem in dep nacht ende bertrock nae Egypten.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">When he arose, he took the young child and his mother by night, and departed into Egypt:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">約瑟就起來，夜間帶着小孩子和他母親往埃及去，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse15">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-iton-qua hynna tou ni-kapatei-en ti Herodes: alei ka pa-væut-auh ta na sou ki MEIRANG pa-pattæi-tounoun ki Mattæi-tan, koun, nitæ-tem-au ta alak-au tou Egypten.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-iton-qua hynna tou ni-kapatei-en ti Herodes: alei ka pa-væut-auh ta na sou ki MEIRANG pa-pattæi-tounoun ki Mattæi-tan, koun, nitæ-tem-au ta alak-au tou Egypten.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> En was aldaer tot den doodt ban Herodes op dat berbult soude worden het gene ban de Heere gesproocken is door den Propheet seggende Uyt Egypten hebbe ick mijnen Sone geroepen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And was there until the death of Herod: that it might be fulfilled which was spoken of the Lord by the prophet, saying, Out of Egypt have I called my son.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">住在那裏，直到希律死了。這是要應驗主藉先知所說的話，說：「我從埃及召出我的兒子來。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse16">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou ka k'ytt'an ti Herodes, ka ni-sym ham ha tyni-æn ta Makouzazyng pou-lilyt, doumia-ka ouhang manga yddingit ta te-ni', ka rou nimadingi-dingi, ni-louh-pough ki ymmid ki rarau-wei ka tou Bethlehem, tou ym'dappa ki kari-virivyl tyn, ka makka rouha ki tauwil ka makoua-appa, na ahkaquan ki kidi ka ni-tmauki-lymmugh ki Makou-zazyng pou-arara kanna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou ka k'ytt'an ti Herodes, ka ni-sym ham ha tyni-æn ta Makouzazyng pou-lilyt, doumia-ka ouhang manga yddingit ta te-ni', ka rou nimadingi-dingi, ni-louh-pough ki ymmid ki rarau-wei ka tou Bethlehem, tou ym'dappa ki kari-virivyl tyn, ka makka rouha ki tauwil ka makoua-appa, na ahkaquan ki kidi ka ni-tmauki-lymmugh ki Makou-zazyng pou-arara kanna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Als Herodes sagh dat hy ban de Wyse bedrogen was doe wiert hy seer toornigh ende [eenige] asgesonsonden hebbende heeft omgebracht alle de kinderen die binnen Bethlehem ende in alle des selfs landtpalen [waren, ] ban twee jaren [oudt ] en daer onder nae den tijdt dien hy ban de Wyse neerstelick ondersocht hadde.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then Herod, when he saw that he was mocked of the wise men, was exceeding wroth, and sent forth, and slew all the children that were in Bethlehem, and in all the coasts thereof, from two years old and under, according to the time which he had diligently enquired of the wise men.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">希律見自己被博士愚弄，就大大發怒，差人將伯利恆城裏並四境所有的男孩，照着他向博士仔細查問的時候，凡兩歲以裏的，都殺盡了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse17">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Tou kidi kanna ni-pavtæu ta sou ka na patta-sasou ki Tama-Mattæi-tan ka ti Jeremias koun;</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Tou kidi kanna ni-pavtæu ta sou ka na patta-sasou ki Tama-Mattæi-tan ka ti Jeremias koun;</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Doe is berbult gheworden het gene gesproken is door den Propheet Jeremiam seggende :</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then was fulfilled that which was spoken by Jeremy the prophet, saying,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">這就應了先知耶利米的話，說：</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse18">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ni-'illing-hen tou Rama ta na raroungoroungo, ta na ta t'angit'angi ki na rareirei-ing-appa ka madagh: ti Rachel ta ni-tmangitangi mattæi-voulavloulas ki allalak tyn, ka ynnang ki paka-haniap-pen, alei ka aulough-ato.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ni-'illing-hen tou Rama ta na raroungoroungo, ta na ta t'angit'angi ki na rareirei-ing-appa ka madagh: ti Rachel ta ni-tmangitangi mattæi-voulavloulas ki allalak tyn, ka ynnang ki paka-haniap-pen, alei ka aulough-ato.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Een stemme is in Rama ghehoort geklagh geween ende beel gekerm : Rachel beweende hare kinderen ende en wilde niet bertroost wesen om datse niet en zijn.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">In Rama was there a voice heard, lamentation, and weeping, and great mourning, Rachel weeping for her children, and would not be comforted, because they are not.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">在拉瑪聽見號咷大哭的聲音，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse19">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou ka ni-mah-kidi ki yhkakaeuloung-an ta ti Herodes; k'yttei ta Tama-Gnau ki MEIRANG mæu-æmæh ti Josef-an tou maling tyn tou Egypten:</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou ka ni-mah-kidi ki yhkakaeuloung-an ta ti Herodes; k'yttei ta Tama-Gnau ki MEIRANG mæu-æmæh ti Josef-an tou maling tyn tou Egypten:</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Doe Herodes nn gestorben was siet de Enghel des Heeren berchijnt Joseph den droom in Egypten </TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But when Herod was dead, behold, an angel of the Lord appeareth in a dream to Joseph in Egypt,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">希律死了以後，有主的使者在埃及向約瑟夢中顯現，說：</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse20">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Koun, Mati-mæuæ-'æ æhpit, 'ar'au ta Rauwei â-lam-au ti Ina tyn, ka thabul-lâ mou-qua tou pou-rough ki Israël, ka ni-mapatei ta neni ka ni-kiy-kiym nein ta vatti ki Rauwei.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Koun, Mati-mæuæ-'æ æhpit, 'ar'au ta Rauwei â-lam-au ti Ina tyn, ka thabul-lâ mou-qua tou pou-rough ki Israël, ka ni-mapatei ta neni ka ni-kiy-kiym nein ta vatti ki Rauwei.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Seggende Staet op neemt het kindeken ende sijne moeder tot n ende treckt in 't land Israels : want sy zijn gestorben die de ziele des kindekens sochten.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Saying, Arise, and take the young child and his mother, and go into the land of Israel: for they are dead which sought the young child's life.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">「起來！帶着小孩子和他母親往以色列地去，因為要害小孩子性命的人已經死了。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse21">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta, irou ka ni-ma-ti-mæuæh ta teni, ni-mara ki Rauwei ki Razena'n-appa tyn, ka ni-lum-mad tou pourough ka Israël.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta, irou ka ni-ma-ti-mæuæh ta teni, ni-mara ki Rauwei ki Razena'n-appa tyn, ka ni-lum-mad tou pourough ka Israël.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Hy dan opgestaen zijnde heeft tot hem genowen het kindeken ende sijne moeder ende is gekomen in het landt Israels.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And he arose, and took the young child and his mother, and came into the land of Israel.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">約瑟就起來，把小孩子和他母親帶到以色列地去；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse22">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Nda irou ra 'illing-hen tyn ka Mei-sasou ka Si-bavau ta ti Archelaus tou Jud-ea mivariou ki Raraman tyn ka ti Herodes, ni-mah-takout sah-ka-qua hynna ta teni: Ra dou ni-pa-kou-sou-an tou maling, ni-thabul tou Ibæ-Ibægh ki Galilëa.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Nda irou ra 'illing-hen tyn ka Mei-sasou ka Si-bavau ta ti Archelaus tou Judea mivariou ki Raraman tyn ka ti Herodes, ni-mah-takout sah-ka-qua hynna ta teni: Ra dou ni-pa-kou-sou-an tou maling, ni-thabul tou Ibæ-Ibægh ki Galilëa.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Maer Maer als hy hoorde dar A:chelaus in Judea koning was in de plaetseshns baders Herodis breefde hy daer henen te gaen : Maer door Goddelicke openbaringe bermaent in den droom is hy bertrocken in de deelen ban Galileen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But when he heard that Archelaus did reign in Judaea in the room of his father Herod, he was afraid to go thither: notwithstanding, being warned of God in a dream, he turned aside into the parts of Galilee:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">只因聽見亞基老接着他父親希律作了猶太王，就怕往那裏去，又在夢中被主指示，便往加利利境內去了，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse23">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou ka lummalmad iroua' hynna, ni-mou-rylla tou Euma ka pa-nanang-en Nazareth: alei ka pa-væut-auh ta na sou ki Tama-Matt'æi-tan, ka pa-nanang-eih ta teni ka Nazarenus. Katatouro ki Ibægh ki Soulat</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou ka lummalmad iroua' hynna, ni-mou-rylla tou Euma ka pa-nanang-en Nazareth: alei ka pa-væut-auh ta na sou ki Tama-Matt'æi-tan, ka pa-nanang-eih ta teni ka Nazarenus. Katatouro ki Ibægh ki Soulat</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Eiidrer]Jgekome jijnde nam hy sijne woon-plaetse m de fladt genaemr Nara-reth: op dat berbult soude worden dat door de Propheten geseght is Dat n Nararenus sal geheeten worden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And he came and dwelt in a city called Nazareth: that it might be fulfilled which was spoken by the prophets, He shall be called a Nazarene.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">到了一座城，名叫拿撒勒，就住在那裏。這是要應驗先知所說，他將稱為拿撒勒人的話了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
</TEXT>