<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEXT id="Siraya_Dutch_Matthew_Chapter24" xml:lang="fos" source="Siraya Bible, Matthew gospel" copyright="public domain" citation="Gravius, Daniël. 1661. Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa. Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang. Amsterdam: Michiel Hartogh." BibTeX_citation="@book{Gravius1661,&#10;  author    = {Gravius, Daniël},&#10;  year      = {1661},&#10;  title     = {Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa},&#10;  note      = {Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang},&#10;  address   = {Amsterdam},&#10;  publisher = {Michiel Hartogh}&#10;}">
    <S id="verse1">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> KA rou samamala ta ti Jesus, ni-d'marang ki Kouva ki ta-tamd-den ki Alid, ka ni-iroua tyni-an ta Pahtatautauughan tyn, tou pakita-eih tyni-æn ki ni-peitallagh ki Kouva ki tatamd-den ki Alid.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> KA rou samamala ta ti Jesus, ni-d'marang ki Kouva ki ta-tamd-den ki Alid, ka ni-iroua tyni-an ta Pahtatautauughan tyn, tou pakita-eih tyni-æn ki ni-peitallagh ki Kouva ki tatamd-den ki Alid.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">E be Jesus gingh upt ende bertrock ban den Tempel ende stjne Discipelen quamen by hem om hem de gebouwen des Tempels te toonen. |</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And Jesus went out, and departed from the temple: and his disciples came to him for to shew him the buildings of the temple.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">耶穌出了聖殿，正走的時候，門徒進前來，把殿宇指給他看。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse2">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus neini-æn, Assi-moumi kaua ararau-en tamamang katta? Missing koun-nau-kamou, Assi pæ-itoukoua-eih hia ta [sasasat kavahto pa-itou-halap ki vahto [ka rouma,] ka assi taktak-auh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus neini-æn, Assi-moumi kaua ararau-en tamamang katta? Missing koun-nau-kamou, Assi pæ-itoukoua-eih hia ta [sasasat kavahto pa-itou-halap ki vahto [ka rouma,] ka assi taktak-auh.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Ende Jesus seyde tot haer En fiet ghy niet alle dese dingen:Doorwaer segge ick Dier en sal niet [eenen] ficen op den (anderen] steen gelaten worden die niet afgebroken en sal worden.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And Jesus said unto them, See ye not all these things? verily I say unto you, There shall not be left here one stone upon another, that shall not be thrown down.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">耶穌對他們說：「你們不是看見這殿宇嗎？我實在告訴你們，將來在這裏沒有一塊石頭留在石頭上，不被拆毀了。」 （可13‧3－13；路21‧7－19）</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse3">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou ka mieroung ta teni tou voukkyn ka makka-vavoua ki imagh, ni-moukoua tou snnegh tyni-æn ta Pahtatautau'han, ka ni k'ma, kananan'ei-kame, manno-al-ato ki kidi ta mamang katta? ka kamang-al-ato ta pou kidi-en ki kaännanoung oho, ki sah-kaha'n sa-limou-lymmou-appa ki ydda rynnoughan?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou ka mieroung ta teni tou voukkyn ka makka-vavoua ki imagh, ni-moukoua tou snnegh tyni-æn ta Pahtatautau'han, ka ni k'ma, kananan'ei-kame, manno-al-ato ki kidi ta mamang katta? ka kamang-al-ato ta pou kidi-en ki kaännanoung oho, ki sah-kaha'n sa-limou-lymmou-appa ki ydda rynnoughan?</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Ende als hy op den Olit-berg geseten was gingen de Dilcipelen tot hem alleen seggende Segt ons wanneer sullen dese dingen 3yn + ende welck [sal] het teecken [rijo] ban uwe tockomle ende ban de bolepndinge der werelt $</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And as he sat upon the mount of Olives, the disciples came unto him privately, saying, Tell us, when shall these things be? and what shall be the sign of thy coming, and of the end of the world?</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">耶穌在橄欖山上坐着，門徒暗暗地來說：「請告訴我們，甚麼時候有這些事？你降臨和世界的末了有甚麼預兆呢？」</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse4">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou ka mattæ i-vlli ta ti Je-sus ni-k'ma neini-æn, K'ytt'ei, ka assi pataurahei-ah ta timamang ymoumi-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou ka mattæ i-vlli ta ti Je-sus ni-k'ma neini-æn, K'ytt'ei, ka assi pataurahei-ah ta timamang ymoumi-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">EndeFJesus antwoordende sepde tot haer Siet toe dat n niemant en berlepde.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And Jesus answered and said unto them, Take heed that no man deceive you.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">耶穌回答說：「你們要謹慎，免得有人迷惑你們。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse5">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka mabatoung ta irou'ah tou Nanang-au, ka k'ma-ah, Ti jau ta ti. hristus, ka pataurahei-auh nein ta ta'ou ka madagh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka mabatoung ta irou'ah tou Nanang-au, ka k'ma-ah, Ti jau ta ti. hristus, ka pataurahei-auh nein ta ta'ou ka madagh.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Want bele sullen komen onde: mynen Name seggende Ick ben de Chailtus ende sy sullen bele berleyden.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">For many shall come in my name, saying, I am Christ; and shall deceive many.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">因為將來有好些人冒我的名來，說：『我是基督』，並且要迷惑許多人。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse6">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka illingigh-au-moumi ta pasacyt-an, ki ikalauakau-en-appa ki pasacyt-an. Kmytta, ka assi-ah-kamou rou pa-ouh kiap-en, ka ki-di-ato ka pavut-auh ta mamang k'atta, râ aousi-appa ki limou-limou.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka illingigh-au-moumi ta pasacyt-an, ki ikalauakau-en-appa ki pasacyt-an. Kmytta, ka assi-ah-kamou rou pa-ouh kiap-en, ka ki-di-ato ka pavut-auh ta mamang k'atta, râ aousi-appa ki limou-limou.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Ende ghp sult hooren ban oorlogen ende geruchten ban oorlogen. Siet toe en wordt niet besichrickt want alle [die] dingen moeten geschieden mae noch en het eynde niet,</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And ye shall hear of wars and rumours of wars: see that ye be not troubled: for all these things must come to pass, but the end is not yet.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">你們也要聽見打仗和打仗的風聲，總不要驚慌；因為這些事是必須有的，只是末期還沒有到。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse7">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka æhpit-ah ta ta'u mou-dumma ki tau, ta Peisasou-an-appa makou-douma ki Peisasou-an: ka irouah ki kahangei-an, ki pis-ma-mourang-en, ki nynnough tou manninni ki yttou-koua-an,</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka æhpit-ah ta ta'u mou-dumma ki tau, ta Peisasou-an-appa makou-douma ki Peisasou-an: ka irouah ki kahangei-an, ki pis-ma-mourang-en, ki nynnough tou manninni ki yttou-koua-an,</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Want het [een] bolck fal tegen Het [ander] bolck opstaen ende t [ een J konmckriick tegen het [ander] Koninckryck : ende daer ullen 3yn hongers-nooden ei pestilentien ende aertbebingen in berfchepden plaetsen.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">For nation shall rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom: and there shall be famines, and pestilences, and earthquakes, in divers places.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">民要攻打民，國要攻打國；多處必有饑荒、地震。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse8">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Nda kamamang k'atta dyk ka naunamou ki pæ'i-alalam-en.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Nda kamamang k'atta dyk ka naunamou ki pæ'i-alalam-en.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Doch alle dese dingen [zijn maer] cen beginsel der tmerten. _</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">All these are the beginning of sorrows.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">這都是災難的起頭。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse9">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Tou kidi-k'anna paä-toun-noun-ah ymoumi-æn tou sasamk-an, ka pakapatei-ah ymoumi-een ka 'aal-auh-kamou ki ymmid ki ta'utaou alei ki Nanang-au.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Tou kidi-k'anna paä-toun-noun-ah ymoumi-æn tou sasamk-an, ka pakapatei-ah ymoumi-een ka 'aal-auh-kamou ki ymmid ki ta'utaou alei ki Nanang-au.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Alfdan sullen sy u oberteberen in berdruckinge ende fullen u dooden ende gy sult. gehaet wordt ban alle bolkeren om mijns Naems wille.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Then shall they deliver you up to be afflicted, and shall kill you: and ye shall be hated of all nations for my name's sake.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">那時，人要把你們陷在患難裏，也要殺害你們；你們又要為我的名被萬民恨惡。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse10">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka tou kidi kanna paka varau-auh ta madad-agh[ki vouel,] ka ma-pæ-vlivlli-ah mapa - mado mapa a tounnou tounnoun, kamakka-v'llivlli-ah makka-mado makka-vahiehyr neini-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka tou kidi kanna paka varau-auh ta madad-agh[ki vouel,] ka ma-pæ-vlivlli-ah mapa - mado mapa a tounnou tounnoun, kamakka-v'llivlli-ah makka-mado makka-vahiehyr neini-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Ende dan sullender bele ge-ergert worden ende fullen malkanderen oberleberen ende malkanderen haten, .</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And then shall many be offended, and shall betray one another, and shall hate one another.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">那時，必有許多人跌倒，也要彼此陷害，彼此恨惡；</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse11">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka 'æhpit-ah ta mabat-oung ka assi dlligh ka Tama-mattæ'i-tan, ka pataurahei-auh nein ta madadagh ki ta'u.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka 'æhpit-ah ta mabatoung ka assi dlligh ka Tama-mattæ'i-tan, ka pataurahei-auh nein ta madadagh ki ta'u.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Ende bele baltchePropheten sullen opstaen- ende tullende; bele berlepden, |</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And many false prophets shall rise, and shall deceive many.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">且有好些假先知起來，迷惑多人。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse12">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka alei-appa ki pakæuhta-pang-auh ta katoukoul-an, ka hi-oup-eih ki væango ki madadagh ki ta'u.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka alei-appa ki pakæuhta-pang-auh ta katoukoul-an, ka hi-oup-eih ki væango ki madadagh ki ta'u.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Endeom dat de ongerechtigheyt bermenighbuldight al worden soo sal de lietde ban bele berkouden.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And because iniquity shall abound, the love of many shall wax cold.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">只因不法的事增多，許多人的愛心才漸漸冷淡了。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse13">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka timamang ta itou-tara-eugh tou limou-appa, pakariang auh ta komma-hynna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka timamang ta itou-tara-eugh tou limou-appa, pakariang auh ta komma-hynna.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Marr wie bolherden fal tot den epnde diesal sahigh worden.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">But he that shall endure unto the end, the same shall be saved.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">惟有忍耐到底的，必然得救。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse14">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka pattasasou-eih ta Ha gnau ka mariang k'anna ki Peisa-sou-an tou ymmid ki yttou-kakou-quan ki Næi, tou pattæni-hailen ki ymmid ki ta'utaou ka Heidang: anna ta irou-'ah ta limoulymmou.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka pattasasou-eih ta Ha gnau ka mariang k'anna ki Peisa-sou-an tou ymmid ki yttou-kakou-quan ki Næi, tou pattæni-hailen ki ymmid ki ta'utaou ka Heidang: anna ta irou-'ah ta limoulymmou.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Ende dit Euangelinm des koninckrijcks sal in de gheheele werelt ghepredickt worden tot een getuygenille allen bolckeren : ende dan fal het eynde komen.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And this gospel of the kingdom shall be preached in all the world for a witness unto all nations; and then shall the end come.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">這天國的福音要傳遍天下，對萬民作見證，然後末期才來到。」 （可13‧14－23；路21‧20－24）</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse15">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Jrou ka k'ytt'ei-moumi ta kakariskæus-in ki ni-ou-bulbul-en ka ni-pæsousou-en ti Daniel ka na Tama-mattæ'i-tan, tou itou-koua-an ka ni-pou-nni tou tatamd-den ki Alid (nda oum-gheilato ki Tama kting.)</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Jrou ka k'ytt'ei-moumi ta kakariskæus-in ki ni-ou-bulbul-en ka ni-pæsousou-en ti Daniel ka na Tama-mattæ'i-tan, tou itou-koua-an ka ni-pou-nni tou tatamd-den ki Alid (nda oum-gheilato ki Tama kting.)</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Wanneer ghy dansult fien den grouwel der ber woeltinge waer ban ghesproken is door Daniel den Nopheet lkaende inde heylige plaetse (die sher] leeft die mercke daer op.) -</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">When ye therefore shall see the abomination of desolation, spoken of by Daniel the prophet, stand in the holy place, (whoso readeth, let him understand:)</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">「你們看見先知但以理所說的『那行毀壞可憎的』站在聖地（讀這經的人須要會意）。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse16">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Tou kidi-k'anna na ma-mang ta tou Judea, da illipt-ah pou-bævoukkyu.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Tou kidi-k'anna na ma-mang ta tou Judea, da illipt-ah pou-bævoukkyu.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Dat alsdan die in gudea zijn blieden op de ergen.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Then let them which be in Judaea flee into the mountains:</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">那時，在猶太的，應當逃到山上；</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse17">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Na mamang ta a'ia-apang, ka assi mou-rarim ki ara-eih tyn ki mamang tou tallaghtyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Na mamang ta a'ia-apang, ka assi mou-rarim ki ara-eih tyn ki mamang tou tallaghtyn.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Die op 't dack is en kome niet af om yer uyt Cijn huys wegh te nemen.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Let him which is on the housetop not come down to take any thing out of his house:</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">在房上的，不要下來拿家裏的東西；</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse18">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka æ'ia-ouma-appa, nda assi sa-likough-ah ki ara-eih tyn ki koulamough.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka æ'ia-ouma-appa, nda assi sa-likough-ah ki ara-eih tyn ki koulamough.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">geweest ban het begin der werelt tot m toe nochoock niet zijn en al.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Neither let him which is in the field return back to take his clothes.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">在田裏的，也不要回去取衣裳。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse19">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ænnai ymoumi [ka jnæ-jna ka mavou ka pa-ouho tou wæi k'anna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ænnai ymoumi [ka jnæ-jna ka mavou ka pa-ouho tou wæi k'anna.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Maer weeden bebuuchten endeden soogenden [brouwen] in die dagen.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And woe unto them that are with child, and to them that give suck in those days!</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">當那些日子，懷孕的和奶孩子的有禍了。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse20">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Nda mako-Alilid-a ka assi pavut-auh ta illipt-ei-moumi rou amighan, rou wai lava ka pæi-habab'æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Nda mako-Alilid-a ka assi pavut-auh ta illipt-ei-moumi rou amighan, rou wai lava ka pæi-habab'æn.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Doch bidt dat uwe blucht niet en geschiede des winters noch op eenen bath.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">But pray ye that your flight be not in the winter, neither on the sabbath day:</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">你們應當祈求，叫你們逃走的時候，不遇見冬天或是安息日。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse21">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Kairou'ah dou anna ta sa-samkan ki bulbul-en ka malouas irang, ka ni-aousi ki komma-hyn na siæugh ki kidi ki naunamou ki Nai tou kidi-appa hnyn, ka aousi. al-appa dou roumang.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Kairou'ah dou anna ta sa-samkan ki bulbul-en ka malouas irang, ka ni-aousi ki komma-hyn na siæugh ki kidi ki naunamou ki Nai tou kidi-appa hnyn, ka aousi. al-appa dou roumang.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">+ Want als dan sal moote berdruckinge wesen </TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">For then shall be great tribulation, such as was not since the beginning of the world to this time, no, nor ever shall be.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">因為那時必有大災難，從世界的起頭直到如今，沒有這樣的災難，後來也必沒有。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse22">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka rou ynna papahkipo-en ta kidi ki wæi, assi paka-riang-auh ta kamamang ka vaät: rå alei ki ni-peri papahkyppo-eih ta wa'i k'anna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka rou ynna papahkipo-en ta kidi ki wæi, assi paka-riang-auh ta kamamang ka vaät: rå alei ki ni-peri papahkyppo-eih ta wa'i k'anna.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Ende foo die dagen niet berkort en wierden geen bleefch en soude behouden worden : maer om Der Uytberkorene wille sullen die dagen berkort worden.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And except those days should be shortened, there should no flesh be saved: but for the elect's sake those days shall be shortened.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">若不減少那日子，凡有血氣的總沒有一個得救的；只是為選民，那日子必減少了。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse23">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Tou kidi k'anna rou mat-tæ'i-k'ma-ah-hynna-lava ta tima-mang ki sou ymoumi-æn, Kytt'ei, tou hia ta ti thristus, tou hynna lava, ynna tnamsing-da.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Tou kidi k'anna rou mat-tæ'i-k'ma-ah-hynna-lava ta tima-mang ki sou ymoumi-æn, Kytt'ei, tou hia ta ti thristus, tou hynna lava, ynna tnamsing-da.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Alsdan fo yemant tot ulieden sal seggen Siet Hieris de Chaistus of daer en gelooft het niet.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Then if any man shall say unto you, Lo, here is Christ, or there; believe it not.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">那時，若有人對你們說：『基督在這裏』，或說：『基督在那裏』，你們不要信！</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse24">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka æhpit-ah ta mabatoung ka souh-æhristus, ka souhta Tama-mattæ'i-tan, ka pamt-ah ki pouka-kidi-en ka yrrang, ki na ryngei-appa ki ourynghauen, komn-ap-pa hynna ka pataurahei-auh nein mrou ilpoughin ka ni-peri-da.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka æhpit-ah ta mabatoung ka souh-æhristus, ka souhta Tama-mattæ'i-tan, ka pamt-ah ki pouka-kidi-en ka yrrang, ki na ryngei-appa ki ourynghauen, komn-ap-pa hynna ka pataurahei-auh nein mrou ilpoughin ka ni-peri-da.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Want datr sullen balsche fche Chiilti ende balfche Propheren opstaen ende sulen groote teeckenen ende wonderheden doen also dat sp (indien het mogelick ware) oock de uptberkorene fouden berlepden.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">For there shall arise false Christs, and false prophets, and shall shew great signs and wonders; insomuch that, if it were possible, they shall deceive the very elect.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">因為假基督、假先知將要起來，顯大神蹟、大奇事，倘若能行，連選民也就迷惑了。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse25">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> K'ytt'i, ni-pattæ'i-tan-en-au-kamou-râ.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> K'ytt'i, ni-pattæ'i-tan-en-au-kamou-râ.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Stetick hebbe [het]u boorleght.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Behold, I have told you before.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">看哪，我預先告訴你們了。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse26">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka tou pattæ'i-k'ma-hynna-eih nein ki sou ymoumi-en, K'yt-t'ei, a'ia-poulah ta teni, ynna tpa-panah: K'ytt'ei, æ'ia-las ta teni tourbo, ynna tnamsing.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka tou pattæ'i-k'ma-hynna-eih nein ki sou ymoumi-en, K'yt-t'ei, a'ia-poulah ta teni, ynna tpa-panah: K'ytt'ei, æ'ia-las ta teni tourbo, ynna tnamsing.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">So ly dan tot u ullen seggm Siet hy 1s in de woeltijne en gaee niet nyt: Siet [by is Jin de binnen-kameren en gelooft het niet. :</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Wherefore if they shall say unto you, Behold, he is in the desert; go not forth: behold, he is in the secret chambers; believe it not.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">若有人對你們說：『看哪，基督在曠野裏』，你們不要出去！或說：『看哪，基督在內屋中』，你們不要信！</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse27">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Nda mama ka makkæ-reia ta rykkat ka mæræmæh tou kidi-appa ki ta äraor-da, komm'al appa hynna ta ierrou-eih ki Alak ki kaeuloung.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Nda mama ka makkæ-reia ta rykkat ka mæræmæh tou kidi-appa ki ta äraor-da, komm'al appa hynna ta ierrou-eih ki Alak ki kaeuloung.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Want gelijk deblixem uptgaet ban het Oolten enDe sthijnt tot Het Westen also sal oock de tockomlte deg Soons des menschen wesen,</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">For as the lightning cometh out of the east, and shineth even unto the west; so shall also the coming of the Son of man be.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">閃電從東邊發出，直照到西邊。人子降臨也要這樣。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse28">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka toumamang ta na kou-lau, pauaklakl-eih tou hynna ta ahkei</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka toumamang ta na kou-lau, pauaklakl-eih tou hynna ta ahkei</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Wantalwaer het doode lichaem sal zijn daer sutle de arenden bergadert worde.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">For wheresoever the carcase is, there will the eagles be gathered together.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">屍首在哪裏，鷹也必聚在那裏。」 （可13‧24－27；路21‧25－28）</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse29">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka madys siäugh ki sa-samk-en ki oubulbul-en ki wæ'i k'anna, karimdim-eih ta wæ'i, ka assi matikanagh-ah ta voural, ka mouaryng-ah makka vullum ta attatalingei, ka pakylikalika-eih ta kailhgen ki tounnoun ki vullu-vullum.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka madys siäugh ki sa-samk-en ki oubulbul-en ki wæ'i k'anna, karimdim-eih ta wæ'i, ka assi matikanagh-ah ta voural, ka mouaryng-ah makka vullum ta attatalingei, ka pakylikalika-eih ta kailhgen ki tounnoun ki vullu-vullum.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Ende terltont na de berdyuckinge die dagen sal de Sonne berduysiert worden ende de Mane en. sal haer schynsel niet geben ende de Sterren fullen ban den Hemel ballen ende de krachten der Hemelen sullen beweeght worden, .</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Immediately after the tribulation of those days shall the sun be darkened, and the moon shall not give her light, and the stars shall fall from heaven, and the powers of the heavens shall be shaken:</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">「那些日子的災難一過去，</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse30">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka tou kidi ki anna mou-panæh-ah ta pou-kidi-en ki Alak ki kaeuloung tou vullum: ka tmangi-tangi-ah dou anna ta ym-dei-ati ki kavouyvouyllan ki Næt, ka kmyttæ-æh ki Alak ki ka'æu loung, dou ierroua tou pourararei ki vullum tou kailhgen ki kei rang-en ki kidi ka malouas.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka tou kidi ki anna mou-panæh-ah ta pou-kidi-en ki Alak ki kaeuloung tou vullum: ka tmangi-tangi-ah dou anna ta ym-dei-ati ki kavouyvouyllan ki Næt, ka kmyttæ-æh ki Alak ki ka'æu loung, dou ierroua tou pourararei ki vullum tou kailhgen ki kei rang-en ki kidi ka malouas.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Ende alsdan sal inden Hemel berschynd het teecken Des Soons des mentfchen : ende dan sullen alle de 4 acyfiathten der aerde weenen jeil fullen den Sone des menscht fien komende op de wolcken des Hemels met groote kracht ende heerlickhept.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And then shall appear the sign of the Son of man in heaven: and then shall all the tribes of the earth mourn, and they shall see the Son of man coming in the clouds of heaven with power and great glory.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">那時，人子的兆頭要顯在天上，地上的萬族都要哀哭。他們要看見人子，有能力，有大榮耀，駕着天上的雲降臨。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse31">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka padingi-eih tyn ta Ta-ma-Gnæu tyn ki joep ki oeni-appa ka irang, ka papakoi lalau-ah ki ni-peri tyn, ki pagpæt ki ni-pak ka-koua-an ki vare-vare, na soe-tounnoun ki vullu-vullum tou kidi-appa ki limoulimou ki anna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka padingi-eih tyn ta Ta-ma-Gnæu tyn ki joep ki oeni-appa ka irang, ka papakoi lalau-ah ki ni-peri tyn, ki pagpæt ki ni-pak ka-koua-an ki vare-vare, na soe-tounnoun ki vullu-vullum tou kidi-appa ki limoulimou ki anna.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">EndehysalsyneEngelenuptsenden met een Bafupne ban groot gelupt ende fn cullen syne uytberkorene by een bergaderen uyt de bier winden ban [ heteen] upterste der Hemelen tot [her ander] uptterlte der selbe.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And he shall send his angels with a great sound of a trumpet, and they shall gather together his elect from the four winds, from one end of heaven to the other.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">他要差遣使者，用號筒的大聲，將他的選民，從四方，從天這邊到天那邊，都招聚了來。」 （可13‧28－31；路21‧29－33）</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse32">
        <FORM kindOf="original">. Ka madam-mou-mhga ki perænnæh ka lakæuoung-in ki pa myh kaulaul'an: Irou ka ma aukna ta pehil tyn, ka mou-sou rah ta hapa tyn, kalang'noumi ka a'ia hylli ta da'eulang.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">. Ka madam-mou-mhga ki perænnæh ka lakæuoung-in ki pa myh kaulaul'an: Irou ka ma aukna ta pehil tyn, ka mou-sou rah ta hapa tyn, kalang'noumi ka a'ia hylli ta da'eulang.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Ende leert ban ben bijgeboom dese ghelijckenisfe : Wanneet synen tack nu teer wordt ende de bladeren nytsprupten so weet ghy dat de Some; naby 18. _</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Now learn a parable of the fig tree; When his branch is yet tender, and putteth forth leaves, ye know that summer is nigh:</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">「你們可以從無花果樹學個比方：當樹枝發嫩長葉的時候，你們就知道夏天近了。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse33">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Komm'appa-hynna ta y-moumi, jrou kytt'ei-moumi ta mamang katta, k'alangæu-moumi kaä'ia touk æia-ngatas ta anna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Komm'appa-hynna ta ymoumi, jrou kytt'ei-moumi ta mamang katta, k'alangæu-moumi kaä'ia touk æia-ngatas ta anna.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Alsooock ghylieden wanneer ghy alle dese dingen sult sten fo weet dat[her] naby 1g 0007 de dence.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">So likewise ye, when ye shall see all these things, know that it is near, even at the doors.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">這樣，你們看見這一切的事，也該知道人子近了，正在門口了。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse34">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Missing koun-nau-kamou, assi maliæuragh-ah ta kavouyl-lan katta, ka pahkahan-ato pamut ymdei-au kamamang k'anna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Missing koun-nau-kamou, assi maliæuragh-ah ta kavouyl-lan katta, ka pahkahan-ato pamut ymdei-au kamamang k'anna.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">PYoorwae? ick fegge u dit geslachte en sal geenfins boorbp gaen tot dat alle dee dinghen cullen ghefchiede3yn.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Verily I say unto you, This generation shall not pass, till all these things be fulfilled.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">我實在告訴你們，這世代還沒有過去，這些事都要成就。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse35">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Maliæuragh-ah ta vulluma ki Nai, ra assimaliæuragh-ah ta kasou-en-au.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Maliæuragh-ah ta vulluma ki Nai, ra assimaliæuragh-ah ta kasou-en-au.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">De Hemel ende de Aerde sullen boorbp gaen mae? mijne woorderi en sullen geenfins boorby gam.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Heaven and earth shall pass away, but my words shall not pass away.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">天地要廢去，我的話卻不能廢去。」 （可13‧32－37；路17‧26－30，34－36）</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse36">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Râ kidi ki wæ'i ki tæ'lei-appa k'anna assi mou-mbga ta ti-mamang, assi-appa ta Tama-Gnau ka tou tounnoun ki vullum, dyk ka Raraman-au tou saat.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Râ kidi ki wæ'i ki tæ'lei-appa k'anna assi mou-mbga ta ti-mamang, assi-appa ta Tama-Gnau ka tou tounnoun ki vullum, dyk ka Raraman-au tou saat.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Doch ban dien dagh ende yyre en weet niemandt dock niet de Engelen der Heme melen dan mijn Dader alleen</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">But of that day and hour knoweth no man, no, not the angels of heaven, but my Father only.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">「但那日子，那時辰，沒有人知道，連天上的使者也不知道，子也不知道，惟獨父知道。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse37">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka mama ki na wæï ti Nou, komm'al-appa-hynna ta ier-rou-eih ki Alak ki kaeuloung.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka mama ki na wæï ti Nou, komm'al-appa-hynna ta ier-rou-eih ki Alak ki kaeuloung.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Ende geliick de dagen No? [waren, ] alsoo sal oock tin de tockomste ban den on des Menichen. |</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">But as the days of Noe were, so shall also the coming of the Son of man be.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">挪亞的日子怎樣，人子降臨也要怎樣。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse38">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Nda mama ka komma-hynna ki kidi dou aousi-appa ta vaha ka ierrang, ka ni-mavok, ni-myt, nipoutbung, nipapoutbung ta neni, tou kidi-appa ki wæ'i k'anna ka ni-ourbo ti Nou tou sa to [ka ni-pei-avang.]</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Nda mama ka komma-hynna ki kidi dou aousi-appa ta vaha ka ierrang, ka ni-mavok, ni-myt, nipoutbung, nipapoutbung ta neni, tou kidi-appa ki wæ'i k'anna ka ni-ourbo ti Nou tou sa to [ka ni-pei-avang.]</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Want geliick p waren in de daghen boor De Zundt-bloede etende ende drinckende fouwendt ende n houwtlicke uptghebende tot den dagh toe in welcken Not in de Arke gingh:</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">For as in the days that were before the flood they were eating and drinking, marrying and giving in marriage, until the day that Noe entered into the ark,</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">當洪水以前的日子，人照常吃喝嫁娶，直到挪亞進方舟的那日；</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse39">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka assi nein ni-kalang tou kidi-appa k'anna ka iroua ta vaha ka yrrang, ka nimæeu-ymmid mæ-eu-mia neini-æn: komm'al-appa hynna ta ierrou-'eih ki Alak ki ka'euloung.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka assi nein ni-kalang tou kidi-appa k'anna ka iroua ta vaha ka yrrang, ka nimæeu-ymmid mæ-eu-mia neini-æn: komm'al-appa hynna ta ierrou-'eih ki Alak ki ka'euloung.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Ende en bekenden het niet tot dat de Zundtbloedt guam ende haer alle wech nam: alsoo sal oock zijn de tockomlte des Soons des menichen. |</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And knew not until the flood came, and took them all away; so shall also the coming of the Son of man be.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">不知不覺洪水來了，把他們全都沖去。人子降臨也要這樣。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse40">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Tou kidi k'anna æ'ia-ou-ma-'æh ta rarouha ki voual, ka ara auh ta saat, ka pa-itou-koua-auh ta saät.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Tou kidi k'anna æ'ia-ou-ma-'æh ta rarouha ki voual, ka ara auh ta saat, ka pa-itou-koua-auh ta saät.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Aisdan sullender twee sp den acker ] de een al genghenomen ende de ander fal berlaten worden.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Then shall two be in the field; the one shall be taken, and the other left.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">那時，兩個人在田裏，取去一個，撇下一個。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse41">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Darouha ka jna-jna ka mahalting-ah tou kahalting-an, saät ta ara-auh, saät ta pa-itouka-koua-auh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Darouha ka jna-jna ka mahalting-ah tou kahalting-an, saät ta ara-auh, saät ta pa-itouka-koua-auh.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Dae) sullentwee [brouwenJmalen in den menlen de eene sal aengenomen ende de andere sal berlaten worden.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Two women shall be grinding at the mill; the one shall be taken, and the other left.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">兩個女人推磨，取去一個，撇下一個。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse42">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta mahama-i alei ka asli-moumi ou-mhgan ta tælei ka manno ka ierrou-eih ki Mei-rang-oumi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta mahama-i alei ka asli-moumi ou-mhgan ta tælei ka manno ka ierrou-eih ki Mei-rang-oumi.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Waeckt dan want ghy en weet niet in welcke upre uwe Heere komen sal; eere des hups gheweten</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Watch therefore: for ye know not what hour your Lord doth come.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">所以，你們要警醒，因為不知道你們的主是哪一天來到。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse43">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Nda ou-mhgu ta anna, irou ni-oumhgan ki Tæ'i-tallagh tou souajam-en ka papynna ta irouah ta matelliau, ynna tyn mauä-, ynna tyn assi pæ-kari-an-ei ta tallagh tyn,</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Nda ou-mhgu ta anna, irou ni-oumhgan ki Tæ'i-tallagh tou souajam-en ka papynna ta irouah ta matelliau, ynna tyn mauä-, ynna tyn assi pæ-kari-an-ei ta tallagh tyn,</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Hadde inwelcke nacht-wake de dief komen oude hy fonde gewaeckt hebben mde en foude shjn huys niet hebben laten doorgraben. |</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">But know this, that if the goodman of the house had known in what watch the thief would come, he would have watched, and would not have suffered his house to be broken up.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">家主若知道幾更天有賊來，就必警醒，不容人挖透房屋；這是你們所知道的。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse44">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Alei ki atta, nda t'ma-do-appa tmanang ta ymoumi, alei ka tou kidi ki tælei ka assi-mou-mi habauat-in, irou-ah ta Alak ki ka-euloung.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Alei ki atta, nda t'ma-do-appa tmanang ta ymoumi, alei ka tou kidi ki tælei ka assi-moumi habauat-in, irou-ah ta Alak ki ka-euloung.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Daerom rije oock ghy bereyt want in welcke upre ghy t niet en meynt sal de Sone des Menschen komen. w |</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Therefore be ye also ready: for in such an hour as ye think not the Son of man cometh.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">所以，你們也要預備，因為你們想不到的時候，人子就來了。」 （路12‧41－48）</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse45">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Annata timang ta kouncia ka mashut ka mat-allah-kau, ka ni-pæsibavau-en ki Meirang tyn ki sat katallag-han tyn, alei ki phæ anei neini-æn ki kan-næuh tou kidi ka mariang.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Annata timang ta kouncia ka mashut ka mat-allah-kau, ka ni-pæsibavau-en ki Meirang tyn ki sat katallag-han tyn, alei ki phæ anei neini-æn ki kan-næuh tou kidi ka mariang.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Wie is dan de getrouwe ende boorsichtige dienstKnecht den welcken syn Heere obe: shne dienst-boden ghelteldt heeft om hen-lieden [haer] boedtsel te geben ter rechter thdt.,</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Who then is a faithful and wise servant, whom his lord hath made ruler over his household, to give them meat in due season?</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">「誰是忠心有見識的僕人，為主人所派，管理家裏的人，按時分糧給他們呢？</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse46">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Tama-tæi-riang ta koun-cia kanna, ka ka-bælei-auh ki Meirang tyn, dou iroua, ta mei-k'ma hynna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Tama-tæi-riang ta koun-cia kanna, ka ka-bælei-auh ki Meirang tyn, dou iroua, ta mei-k'ma hynna.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Saligh is die dienltknecht welcken syn Heere Komende sal binden alfoo doende.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Blessed is that servant, whom his lord when he cometh shall find so doing.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">主人來到，看見他這樣行，那僕人就有福了。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse47">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Missing koun-nan-kamou ka pa-sibavau-ah tyni-æn ki ym-mid ki hourup tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Missing koun-nan-kamou ka pa-sibavau-ah tyni-æn ki ym-mid ki hourup tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Doorwaer ick fegge u dat hy hem salsetten ober alle lijne goederen.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Verily I say unto you, That he shall make him ruler over all his goods.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">我實在告訴你們，主人要派他管理一切所有的。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse48">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Heirou-râ mattæ i-rmir-ah tou tintin tyn ta kouncia ka masa muk, Malanga iroua ta Meirang au:</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Heirou-râ mattæ i-rmir-ah tou tintin tyn ta kouncia ka masa muk, Malanga iroua ta Meirang au:</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Maer so die quade dienstknecht in lijn herte fonde seggen Mijn Heere bertoeft te oment</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">But and if that evil servant shall say in his heart, My lord delayeth his coming;</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">倘若那惡僕心裏說：『我的主人必來得遲』，</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse49">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka dou makka-naunamou bukbuk ki kouncia ka talalam tyn, ka mi-sal-ah mavok, mou sal-ah myt ki Tama-yt.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka dou makka-naunamou bukbuk ki kouncia ka talalam tyn, ka mi-sal-ah mavok, mou sal-ah myt ki Tama-yt.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Ende soude beginnen [kjae] mede-dienfknechts te Haen ende te eten efi te drincKen met de dronckaerts.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And shall begin to smite his fellowservants, and to eat and drink with the drunken;</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">就動手打他的同伴，又和酒醉的人一同吃喝。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse50">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta jerrou-ah ta Meirang ka tamia ki kouncia k'anna tou wai ki assi tyn amamat-in, tou kidi-appa ki tælei ka assi tyn oumhgan.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta jerrou-ah ta Meirang ka tamia ki kouncia k'anna tou wai ki assi tyn amamat-in, tou kidi-appa ki tælei ka assi tyn oumhgan.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Soo sal de Heere defes dienstknechts komen ten dage in welcken hy [hem] met en berwacht ende ter upre die hy niet en weet.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">The lord of that servant shall come in a day when he looketh not for him, and in an hour that he is not aware of,</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">在想不到的日子，不知道的時辰，那僕人的主人要來，</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse51">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka pasahpiagh-ah tyni-æn, ka pa-itousal-ah ki atægh tyn ki panninni-en ki rÿh ki sou. Tou hynna-al-ato ta tangi-tangi-en ki pat-iting-en-appa ki waligh. Kararouha kytti-an'æb ki rymma. ki. bæh ki soulat.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka pasahpiagh-ah tyni-æn, ka pa-itousal-ah ki atægh tyn ki panninni-en ki rÿh ki sou. Tou hynna-al-ato ta tangi-tangi-en ki pat-iting-en-appa ki waligh. Kararouha kytti-an'æb ki rymma. ki. bæh ki soulat.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">Ende al hem affcheyden ende shn deel setten met de ghebepnlde.Dae sal weeninghe zijn ende knersinge der tanden</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And shall cut him asunder, and appoint him his portion with the hypocrites: there shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">重重地處治他，定他和假冒為善的人同罪；在那裏必要哀哭切齒了。」</TRANS>
    </S>
</TEXT>