<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEXT id="Siraya_Dutch_Matthew_Chapter18" xml:lang="fos" source="Siraya Bible, Matthew gospel" copyright="public domain" citation="Gravius, Daniël. 1661. Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa. Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang. Amsterdam: Michiel Hartogh." BibTeX_citation="@book{Gravius1661,&#10;  author    = {Gravius, Daniël},&#10;  year      = {1661},&#10;  title     = {Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa},&#10;  note      = {Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang},&#10;  address   = {Amsterdam},&#10;  publisher = {Michiel Hartogh}&#10;}" dialect="Siraya">
    <S id="verse1">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Tou kidi ki tælei k'anna ni-mou-koua ta Pahtatæutau-han ti Jesus-an, k'ma, Timang ta siouro tou vavau ki kidi tou Pei-sa-sou-an ki tounoun ki vulluvullum?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Tou kidi ki tælei k'anna nimoukoua ta Pahtatæutauhan ti Jesusan, k'ma, Timang ta siouro tou vavau ki kidi tou Peisasouan ki tounoun ki vulluvullum?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">E dier selber uyre quamen de Discipelen tot Jefum leggende Wie is doch de meelte in't Koninckriick der Hemelen $</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">At the same time came the disciples unto Jesus, saying, Who is the greatest in the kingdom of heaven?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">當時，門徒進前來，問耶穌說：＂天國裏誰是最大的？＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse2">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka rou ni-tætæäm ti Jesus ta oussyng ka rauwei pa-oukoua tyni-æn, ni-pa-itou-koua tyni-æn pa-itou-toukad neini-æn,</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka rou nitætæäm ti Jesus ta oussyng ka rauwei paoukoua tyniæn, nipaitoukoua tyniæn paitoutoukad neiniæn,</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende Jesnus een kindeken tot hem geroepen hebbende stelde dat in het midden ban haer</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And Jesus called a little child unto him, and set him in the midst of them,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌便叫一個小孩子來，使他站在他們當中，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse3">
        <FORM kindOf="original">. Ka ni-k'ma, D'lligh koun-nau-kamou, hejrou assi-kamou si-lala mamyh-kaulaula ki rarauwei, madaæua assi-kamou mou-rbo-ah tou Pei-sasou-an ki tounnoun ki vulluvullum.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">. Ka nik'ma, D'lligh kounnaukamou, hejrou assikamou silala mamyhkaulaula ki rarauwei, madaæua assikamou mourboah tou Peisasouan ki tounnoun ki vulluvullum.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Endesepde Yoorwaer segge ick u indien ghy u niet en berandett ende wordt gelijk de kinderkens fo en sult pin het Koninckryck der emelen geensins ingaen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And said, Verily I say unto you, Except ye be converted, and become as little children, ye shall not enter into the kingdom of heaven.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">說：＂我實在告訴你們，你們若不回轉，變成小孩子的樣式，斷不得進天國。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse4">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Timamang ta pou-mædo-ah pou-rærim tyni-en ki kidi mama ki rauwei k'atta, teni ta tou vavau ki keirang-en tou Pei-sasou-an ki tounnoun ki vullu-vullum.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Timamang ta poumædoah pourærim tynien ki kidi mama ki rauwei k'atta, teni ta tou vavau ki keirangen tou Peisasouan ki tounnoun ki vulluvullum.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Soowic dan hem (elben sal bernederen gelyck dit kindeken dese 1s de meeste in het koninckriick der Hemelen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Whosoever therefore shall humble himself as this little child, the same is greatest in the kingdom of heaven.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">所以，凡自己謙卑像這小孩子的，他在天國裏就是最大的。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse5">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Timamang-appa ta mææuh myhtatallagh ki rauwei ka kom-ma-hynna tou Nanang-au, teni ta mææuh myhtatallagh jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Timamangappa ta mææuh myhtatallagh ki rauwei ka kommahynna tou Nanangau, teni ta mææuh myhtatallagh jauan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende foo wie foodanig een kindeken. ontfange in mijnen Name die ontfangt my.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And whoso shall receive one such little child in my name receiveth me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">凡為我的名接待一個像這小孩子的，就是接待我。＂ （可9‧42－48；路17‧1－2）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse6">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Râ timamang ta pa-sai-sala-kouap-ah (pakavarau) ki saäät ki oussyng katta ka tna-msing jau an, masaoun mariang tyni-æn ka poukakud-deih ki vahto ki pa-phud-den ta rÿh tyn, ka pa-ou-rkid-auh tou kalæuhæu-an ki vaoung.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Râ timamang ta pasaisalakouapah (pakavarau) ki saäät ki oussyng katta ka tnamsing jau an, masaoun mariang tyniæn ka poukakuddeih ki vahto ki paphudden ta rÿh tyn, ka paourkidauh tou kalæuhæuan ki vaoung.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Mae soo wie een ban dese kleyne diem my oieren ben egert Het ware Hem nutter dat een meulen-fteen aen synen hals gehangen ende dat hy bersoncken ware in de diepte de ree,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But whoso shall offend one of these little ones which believe in me, it were better for him that a millstone were hanged about his neck, and that he were drowned in the depth of the sea.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">＂凡使這信我的一個小子跌倒的，倒不如把大磨石拴在這人的頸項上，沉在深海裏。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse7">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Alai ki Næi alei ki pasæi-salakouap-pen paka varau: rå ki-di-ato ka ierou-'ah ta pasai-sala-kouap-pen pakavarau: ka alæi ki tau ka pa-ieroua ki pasai-sala-kou-ap-pen pakavarau.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Alai ki Næi alei ki pasæisalakouappen paka varau: rå kidiato ka ierou'ah ta pasaisalakouappen pakavarau: ka alæi ki tau ka paieroua ki pasaisalakouappen pakavarau.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Wee der werelt ban de ngemillen:want het is nootsakelick dac de ergernissen Komen; Doch wee dien mensche door welcken de ergerniise komt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Woe unto the world because of offences! for it must needs be that offences come; but woe to that man by whom the offence cometh!</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">這世界有禍了，因為將人絆倒；絆倒人的事是免不了的，但那絆倒人的有禍了！</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse8">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Heirou ka paka-varau ym-hou-an ta rima-'ho lava, ki rahpal appa-'mhou lava, luk't-au, aryng-an-ei smaki-tæuah ymhou-an. Ma saoun mariang ymhouan mou-rbo ki kæuag-han rou mapilei kow la va, ou mapykka kow lava, râ ka rourouha kow ki rima lava, rou-roula ki rahpal lava, aryng-an-eil ato smaki-koua tou apoei ka myh kakoua myd-darynnough.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Heirou ka pakavarau ymhouan ta rima'ho lava, ki rahpal appa'mhou lava, luk'tau, arynganei smakitæuah ymhouan. Ma saoun mariang ymhouan mourbo ki kæuaghan rou mapilei kow la va, ou mapykka kow lava, râ ka rourouha kow ki rima lava, rouroula ki rahpal lava, arynganeil ato smakikoua tou apoei ka myh kakoua myddarynnough.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Indien dan uwe handt ofte uwe boet u erghert houwt'le af ende werpt fe ban u. Het is u beter tot den leben in te gaen kreupel ofte bermincket (zijnde, JDan twee anden ofte twee boeten hebende in het eeuwighe bper geworpen te worden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Wherefore if thy hand or thy foot offend thee, cut them off, and cast them from thee: it is better for thee to enter into life halt or maimed, rather than having two hands or two feet to be cast into everlasting fire.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">倘若你一隻手，或是一隻腳，叫你跌倒，就砍下來丟掉。你缺一隻手，或是一隻腳，進入永生，強如有兩手兩腳被丟在永火裏。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse9">
        <FORM kindOf="original">. Heirou ka pakavarau ym-hou-an ta mattæ oho, kmæd-, aryng-an-ei ymhou-an. Masaoun mariang ymhou-an ka idi kow ki matta mou-rbo-ah tou kæuag-han, ka rourouha kow ki matta saki-kouaan-eih tou apoei ki kalau-hau-ani.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">. Heirou ka pakavarau ymhouan ta mattæ oho, kmæd, arynganei ymhouan. Masaoun mariang ymhouan ka idi kow ki matta mourboah tou kæuaghan, ka rourouha kow ki matta sakikouaaneih tou apoei ki kalauhauani.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende indien uwe ooge u ergere trecktse uyt ende werptse ban n. Hec is n beter mae? ten ooge hebbende tot het leben in te gaen dan twee oogen hebbende in het helhe byer gheworpen te wor en</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And if thine eye offend thee, pluck it out, and cast it from thee: it is better for thee to enter into life with one eye, rather than having two eyes to be cast into hell fire.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">倘若你一隻眼叫你跌倒，就把它剜出來丟掉。你只有一隻眼進入永生，強如有兩隻眼被丟在地獄的火裏。＂ （路15‧3－7）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse10">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Kytt'ei ka assi-kamou mou-roung-à ki saäät ki oussyng k'anna ka pa-sousou-en-au-ka-mou, ka myhkakoua mararau ta Tama-Gnau nein ki vlung ki Ræ-ma-au, ka tou tounnoun ki vullu-vullum.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Kytt'ei ka assikamou mouroungà ki saäät ki oussyng k'anna ka pasousouenaukamou, ka myhkakoua mararau ta TamaGnau nein ki vlung ki Ræmaau, ka tou tounnoun ki vulluvullum.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Hiet toe dat ghy niet een ban dese klenne en beracht: want ick segge ulieden dat hare Engelen in) de eHemelen altydt sien Het aengelicht myns Vaders die in de Hemelenis, .</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Take heed that ye despise not one of these little ones; for I say unto you, That in heaven their angels do always behold the face of my Father which is in heaven.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">＂你們要小心，不可輕看這小子裏的一個；我告訴你們，他們的使者在天上，常見我天父的面。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse11">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ierou'ato ta Alak ki ka'æuloung tou pa-ra-riang-ei ki âtta ka ni-taurumm'-ato.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ierou'ato ta Alak ki ka'æuloung tou parariangei ki âtta ka nitaurumm'ato.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Want de Sone des menlchen is gekomt om alig te makt dat berlort was.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">For the Son of man is come to save that which was lost.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse12">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Pæh-mang-kamou pæh-dimdim, heirou akoumea ta tima-mang ki tau sat kæ ætoughan ki joeko, ka rou miä-rm'ato lava ki sasat ki atta, assi kaua pa-itou-ka-kou-eih tyn ta matouda kytti-æn 'æb ki matouda, ka rou mou-vouk-ky-voukkyn, assi kaua kmi'ym-ah ki miärm'ato k'anna?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Pæhmangkamou pæhdimdim, heirou akoumea ta timamang ki tau sat kæ ætoughan ki joeko, ka rou miärm'ato lava ki sasat ki atta, assi kaua paitoukakoueih tyn ta matouda kyttiæn 'æb ki matouda, ka rou mouvoukkyvoukkyn, assi kaua kmi'ymah ki miärm'ato k'anna?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Watdunckt u mdien eenigh mensche houdert schapen hadde ende een upt deselbe af-gedwaelt ware en sal hy niet de neghen entnegentigh laten ende op de bergen henen gaende het afgedwarlde soecken $</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">How think ye? if a man have an hundred sheep, and one of them be gone astray, doth he not leave the ninety and nine, and goeth into the mountains, and seeketh that which is gone astray?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">一個人若有一百隻羊，一隻走迷了路，你們的意思如何？他豈不撇下這九十九隻，往山裏去找那隻迷路的羊嗎？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse13">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka rou k'mato-hynna ka paki-valei-en tyn ta atta: D'lligh koun-næu-kamou-râ, ka masaoun marei alei ki anna, ki matouda kytti-æn 'æb ki matouda, k'assi ni-miarma.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka rou k'matohynna ka pakivaleien tyn ta atta: D'lligh kounnæukamourâ, ka masaoun marei alei ki anna, ki matouda kyttiæn 'æb ki matouda, k'assi nimiarma.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende indien het ghefchiet dat hy het selbe bindt: Doorwae: ick seggeu dathy Hem meer betblijdt ober het Tele dan ober de negen-entmegentigh die niet af-ghedwaelt en zijn geweel.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And if so be that he find it, verily I say unto you, he rejoiceth more of that sheep, than of the ninety and nine which went not astray.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">若是找着了，我實在告訴你們，他為這一隻羊歡喜，比為那沒有迷路的九十九隻歡喜還大呢！</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse14">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Koumm-'appa-hynna assi kamoei-in ki Raraman-oumi ka tou tounnoun ki vulluvullum, ka taurumma-ah ta saäät ki oussyng k'attæ.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Koumm'appahynna assi kamoeiin ki Raramanoumi ka tou tounnoun ki vulluvullum, ka taurummaah ta saäät ki oussyng k'attæ.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Allo en is De wille niet nwes Yaders die in de Hemelen 1s dat een ban dese Klepneberloren gae.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Even so it is not the will of your Father which is in heaven, that one of these little ones should perish.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們在天上的父也是這樣，不願意這小子裏失喪一個。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse15">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka rou ni-mavarau lava ymhou-an ta tæ'i-appara oho, ou-kouâ matym'ha mak-tavægh tyni-æn tou snæh tou saät ymoumi-æn: heirou millingigh ta teni ymhou-an, doumiaka ni-pou-'than-en-hou ta tæ'i-appara oho.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka rou nimavarau lava ymhouan ta tæ'iappara oho, oukouâ matym'ha maktavægh tyniæn tou snæh tou saät ymoumiæn: heirou millingigh ta teni ymhouan, doumiaka nipou'thanenhou ta tæ'iappara oho.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Mae indien uwe broeder tegen u gesondight heeft gaet henen ende beraft hem tufschen u ende Hem alleen : indien hy u Hoort soo hebt ghy uwen broeder gewonnen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Moreover if thy brother shall trespass against thee, go and tell him his fault between thee and him alone: if he shall hear thee, thou hast gained thy brother.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">＂倘若你的弟兄得罪你，你就去，趁着只有他和你在一處的時候，指出他的錯來。他若聽你，你便得了你的弟兄；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse16">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou râ assi milling-igh ta teni ymhou-an, dou-miaka patouh-para ymhou-an ki saät lava ki rou-rouha lava ki vouel, alei ka itou-shut-al-ato itou-koua ta ymmid ki sou tou moutous ki rarouha ki tatouro lava ki Tama-heil.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou râ assi millingigh ta teni ymhouan, doumiaka patouhpara ymhouan ki saät lava ki rourouha lava ki vouel, alei ka itoushutalato itoukoua ta ymmid ki sou tou moutous ki rarouha ki tatouro lava ki Tamaheil.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Maermdienhp (u) _ niet niet en hoort soo neemt nocheen ofte twee meth: op dat in den mondt ban twee ofte drie getuygen alle woort beliae.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But if he will not hear thee, then take with thee one or two more, that in the mouth of two or three witnesses every word may be established.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他若不聽，你就另外帶一兩個人同去，要憑兩三個人的口作見證，句句都可定準。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse17">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka rou assi millingigh-a neini-æn, anna ta banna-vanna-ato ki Pako-i-sal-lan ka rou assi-appa millingigh-ah ki Pako-i-sal-lan, anna ta mamei-al-ato ta teni ym-hou-an mama ki Heidang ki Tæ-ma-imugh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka rou assi millingigha neiniæn, anna ta bannavannaato ki Pakoisallan ka rou assiappa millingighah ki Pakoisallan, anna ta mameialato ta teni ymhouan mama ki Heidang ki Tæmaimugh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende indien hy deselbe geen gehoor en geeft so seght het der Gemeynte : ende indien hy oock der Ghemeynte geen gehoor en geeft oo ry hyu als de heyden ende de tollenaer.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And if he shall neglect to hear them, tell it unto the church: but if he neglect to hear the church, let him be unto thee as an heathen man and a publican.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">若是不聽他們，就告訴教會；若是不聽教會，就看他像外邦人和稅吏一樣。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse18">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Dlligh koun-nau-kamou-rå: Kamamang ka væuut-au-mou-mi tou Næi, vuut-eih ta anna tou tounnoun ki vullum: kamamang-appa ka 'ææu-vavæuut-ei-mou-mi tou Næi, 'ææu-vavæunt-eih ta anna tou tounnoun ki vullum.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Dlligh kounnaukamourå: Kamamang ka væuutaumoumi tou Næi, vuuteih ta anna tou tounnoun ki vullum: kamamangappa ka 'ææuvavæuuteimoumi tou Næi, 'ææuvavæunteih ta anna tou tounnoun ki vullum.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doorwae segghe ick u; Al wat ghy op der aerden binden sult sal in den Hemel ghebonden wesen : ende al wat ghy op der aerden ontbinden sult sal iden Hemel ontbonden wesen,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Verily I say unto you, Whatsoever ye shall bind on earth shall be bound in heaven: and whatsoever ye shall loose on earth shall be loosed in heaven.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">＂我實在告訴你們，凡你們在地上所捆綁的，在天上也要捆綁；凡你們在地上所釋放的，在天上也要釋放。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse19">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Mila pa-sousou-en-au-ka-mou, Heirou mæuakla ki rÿh ta rourouha ki voual ymoumi-æn tou Næi, alei ki mamang ka tou-mimi-æu nein, hahei-eih neini-æn ki Raraman-au ka tou tounnoun ki vulluvullum.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Mila pasousouenaukamou, Heirou mæuakla ki rÿh ta rourouha ki voual ymoumiæn tou Næi, alei ki mamang ka toumimiæu nein, haheieih neiniæn ki Raramanau ka tou tounnoun ki vulluvullum.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Wederom segge ick n Indien daer twee ban u te faiht ttemmen op der aerden ober eenige sake die sy sonden mogen begeeren dat die hae sal gechiedt ban myn# Dade die in de Hemelen 18,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Again I say unto you, That if two of you shall agree on earth as touching any thing that they shall ask, it shall be done for them of my Father which is in heaven.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我又告訴你們，若是你們中間有兩個人在地上同心合意地求甚麼事，我在天上的父必為他們成全。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse20">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka toumamang ta mæu-i-sal-ato rarouha lava tatouro lava ki voual tou Nanang-au, a'ia-tou-kad koh hynna neini-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka toumamang ta mæuisalato rarouha lava tatouro lava ki voual tou Nanangau, a'iatoukad koh hynna neiniæn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Want waer twee ofte due bergadert zijn in mijnen Name daer ben ick in het midden ban haer.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">For where two or three are gathered together in my name, there am I in the midst of them.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">因為無論在哪裏，有兩三個人奉我的名聚會，那裏就有我在他們中間。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse21">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Tou kidi k'anna jerou-'ato tyni-æn ta ti Petrus, ka ni-k'ma, Meirang, mapynan-'ah ma-varau jau-an ta tæ'i-a-para-au, ki atta-ral-ei-mau tyni-æn ? matta-pyttoul kaua?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Tou kidi k'anna jerou'ato tyniæn ta ti Petrus, ka nik'ma, Meirang, mapynan'ah mavarau jauan ta tæ'iaparaau, ki attaraleimau tyniæn ? mattapyttoul kaua?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doe quam Petrus tot hem ende eyde Heere hoe menigmael sal myn broeder tegen my sondigen mds ick em hem bergheben + Tot sebenmael +</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then came Peter to him, and said, Lord, how oft shall my brother sin against me, and I forgive him? till seven times?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那時，彼得進前來，對耶穌說：＂主啊，我弟兄得罪我，我當饒恕他幾次呢？到七次可以嗎？＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse22">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Assi-koh matta-pyttoul k'ma ymhou-an, râ sauh-pyttou-appa kytti-æn sauh-pyttoul.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Nik'ma ta ti Jesus tyniæn, Assikoh mattapyttoul k'ma ymhouan, râ sauhpyttouappa kyttiæn sauhpyttoul.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Jesus leyde tot hem Ick en legge u niet tot lebenmael mae? tot tlebentigh mael seben-(mael.)</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus saith unto him, I say not unto thee, Until seven times: but, Until seventy times seven.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：＂我對你說，不是到七次，乃是到七十個七次。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse23">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Alei ki atta, ka papæmyh kaulaul'an ta Pei-sasou-an ki toun-noun ki vullu-vullum ki Si-bavæu ka Mei-sasou, ka mamoei mei-sal kuhtung ki koung-cia tyn-da.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Alei ki atta, ka papæmyh kaulaul'an ta Peisasouan ki tounnoun ki vulluvullum ki Sibavæu ka Meisasou, ka mamoei meisal kuhtung ki koungcia tynda.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Daeroniwort het Koninckryck de Hemelen bergeleken by een scke; Koning die reeckeninghe met shne dienstknechten hound? wilde.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Therefore is the kingdom of heaven likened unto a certain king, which would take account of his servants.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">天國好像一個王要和他僕人算帳。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse24">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka mai-naunamou kubtung ta teni, ni-ad-din tyni-æn saät ki voual ka kau-itting-en sat kytti-æn ka tounnoun-nan ki Tæ-lenten.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka mainaunamou kubtung ta teni, niaddin tyniæn saät ki voual ka kauittingen sat kyttiæn ka tounnounnan ki Tælenten.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Als hy nu begon te reeckenen wierdt tot hem gebracht een die hem schuldigh was tien duylent talenten.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And when he had begun to reckon, one was brought unto him, which owed him ten thousand talents.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">才算的時候，有人帶了一個欠一千萬銀子的來。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse25">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka aou-si ki poudada-auh ta teni, ni-madinghi ta Mei-rang ka pa-peil-an-eih ta teni, ta kaian tyn, ta alalak tyn, ki ma-mang-appa ka ah-teni, tou pa'ä-vli-en pa ä-msing poudaæuh (ki kæu-itting-en k'anna.)</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka aousi ki poudadaauh ta teni, nimadinghi ta Meirang ka papeilaneih ta teni, ta kaian tyn, ta alalak tyn, ki mamangappa ka ahteni, tou pa'ävlien pa ämsing poudaæuh (ki kæuittingen k'anna.)</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Endeals hy niet en Hadde om te betalen bebal tin Heere datmen hem sonde berkoopen ende shn wyf ende kinderen ende al wat Hy hadde ende dat(de {chult) foude betaelt worden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But forasmuch as he had not to pay, his lord commanded him to be sold, and his wife, and children, and all that he had, and payment to be made.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">因為他沒有甚麼償還之物，主人吩咐把他和他妻子兒女，並一切所有的都賣了償還。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse26">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka rou mahgakub ta koun-cia, ni-reip tyni-æn, koun, Meirang mæia-mila-appa jau-an, pa'-ymd-ei-mau kow pou-dæ-æuh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka rou mahgakub ta kouncia, nireip tyniæn, koun, Meirang mæiamilaappa jauan, pa'ymdeimau kow poudææuh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">De dienltknecht dan neder ballende aenbadt hem leggende Heere weest lanckmoedigh ober my ende ick sal n alles betalen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">The servant therefore fell down, and worshipped him, saying, Lord, have patience with me, and I will pay thee all.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那僕人就俯伏拜他，說：＂主啊，寬容我，將來我都要還清。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse27">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ha mararÿh-ato ma-harim ta Meirang ki kouncia k'an-na, ni-atta-ral tyni-æn matta tyn-no ki kæu-itting-en.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ha mararÿhato maharim ta Meirang ki kouncia k'anna, niattaral tyniæn matta tynno ki kæuittingen.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende de Heere deses dienstknechts met baymherrighepdr innerlick beweegt zijnde heeft hem ontsiiagen ende de (chult hem quijt ghesrholden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then the lord of that servant was moved with compassion, and loosed him, and forgave him the debt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那僕人的主人就動了慈心，把他釋放了，並且免了他的債。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse28">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou râ tpæpæh ta kouncia k'anna, ni-kabalei tyn ta saät ki kouncia ka na lam tyn, ka kæu-itting-en tyn sat kæ'æ̈toug-han ki malyttok, ka rou mihakub, ni-meiseyd ki rÿh tyni-æn, koun, Pou-dææug-ha jau-an ki kæu-it-ting-'nau ymhou-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou râ tpæpæh ta kouncia k'anna, nikabalei tyn ta saät ki kouncia ka na lam tyn, ka kæuittingen tyn sat kæ'æ̈toughan ki malyttok, ka rou mihakub, nimeiseyd ki rÿh tyniæn, koun, Poudææugha jauan ki kæuitting'nau ymhouan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Mae? deselbe dienltknecht knecht uytgaende heeft ghebonden eenen ijner mededienstknechten die hem hondert penningen schuldig was ende hem aenbattende geeep (hem) bp de kele seggende Betaelt my dat ghy schuldigh ryt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But the same servant went out, and found one of his fellowservants, which owed him an hundred pence: and he laid hands on him, and took him by the throat, saying, Pay me that thou owest.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">＂那僕人出來，遇見他的一個同伴欠他十兩銀子，便揪着他，掐住他的喉嚨，說：＂你把所欠的還我！＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse29">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Anna ta rou mahgakub ta na lam tyn ka k'uncia tou rahpal tyn, ni-tmoumimia tyni-æn, koun, Maia-mila-appa jæu-an, ka pa'ä-ymd-ei-mau kow pou-daæuh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Anna ta rou mahgakub ta na lam tyn ka k'uncia tou rahpal tyn, nitmoumimia tyniæn, koun, Maiamilaappa jæuan, ka pa'äymdeimau kow poudaæuh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Syn mede dienstknecht dan neder-ballen aen lhjne boets bad hem seggende Zijt lanckmoedigh ober my esi ick salu alles betalen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And his fellowservant fell down at his feet, and besought him, saying, Have patience with me, and I will pay thee all.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他的同伴就俯伏央求他，說：＂寬容我吧，將來我必還清。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse30">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Râ ni-ynnang ta teni: ka rou d'marang ni-poukoua tyni-æn tou sangat, tou kidi-appa k'anna ka pou-dææuh-an-ei tyn ta kæu-itting-en.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Râ niynnang ta teni: ka rou d'marang nipoukoua tyniæn tou sangat, tou kidiappa k'anna ka poudææuhanei tyn ta kæuittingen.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ooch hy en wilde met : mae: gingh henen ende wierp hem in de ghebancKenisse tot dat hy de schult soudebetaelt hebben,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And he would not: but went and cast him into prison, till he should pay the debt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他不肯，竟去把他下在監裏，等他還了所欠的債。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse31">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Dou kakytt'an ki kouncia ka lalam tyn ki ni-pæm'tten, ou-hang ni-mi-voulas ta neni, ka rou iroua, ni-vanna-vanna ki Meirang nein ki mamang ka ni-pamt-ten-atou-râ.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Dou kakytt'an ki kouncia ka lalam tyn ki nipæm'tten, ouhang nimivoulas ta neni, ka rou iroua, nivannavanna ki Meirang nein ki mamang ka nipamttenatourâ.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Als nu shne mededienltknechten sagen t gene geschiet was zijn sy Ceer beDroeft geworde efi komende berklaerden sy haren Heere al watter gechiee was.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">So when his fellowservants saw what was done, they were very sorry, and came and told unto their lord all that was done.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">眾同伴看見他所做的事就甚憂愁，去把這事都告訴了主人。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse32">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Tou kidi k'anna ni-tæta æm ta teni pa-oukoua tyni-æn ki Meirang tyn, ka ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Kouncia ka mat-e, ni-atta-nynno-en-au-kow atta-ral ymmid ki ni-kæu-itting-en-au k'anna, alei ka ni-tmoumimia kow jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Tou kidi k'anna nitæta æm ta teni paoukoua tyniæn ki Meirang tyn, ka nik'ma tyniæn, Kouncia ka mate, niattanynnoenaukow attaral ymmid ki nikæuittingenau k'anna, alei ka nitmoumimia kow jauan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doe heeft hem fijn Heere tot hem gheroepen ende seyde tot hem Ghy boose dienltknecht alle die schuldt hebbe ick u quijt gescholden dewyle ghy mp gebeden hebr.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then his lord, after that he had called him, said unto him, O thou wicked servant, I forgave thee all that debt, because thou desiredst me:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">於是主人叫了他來，對他說：＂你這惡奴才！你央求我，我就把你所欠的都免了，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse33">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ynna-mouhou kaua kaha-rum-ta kouncia ka na lam oho, mama ki ni-kaharum-en-au ym-hou-an?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ynnamouhou kaua kaharumta kouncia ka na lam oho, mama ki nikaharumenau ymhouan?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Behoordet ghy oock niet u ober uw? mede dienltknecht te onefermen gelijck ick oock my ober u ontfermt hebbe</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Shouldest not thou also have had compassion on thy fellowservant, even as I had pity on thee?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你不應當憐恤你的同伴，像我憐恤你嗎？＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse34">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka rou mangale ta Mei-rang tyn, ni-pæ'ǣ-tounnoun-en tyn tyni-æn ki tama-khaut, tou kidi-al-appa k'anna ka pou-daauh-an-ei tyn ta ymmid ki mamang ka kæuitting-en tyn tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka rou mangale ta Meirang tyn, nipæ'ǣtounnounen tyn tyniæn ki tamakhaut, tou kidialappa k'anna ka poudaauhanei tyn ta ymmid ki mamang ka kæuittingen tyn tyniæn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende syn Heere betoornt zijnde leberde hem den pynders oper tot dat hy soude betaelt hebben al wat hy hem schuldigh was,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And his lord was wroth, and delivered him to the tormentors, till he should pay all that was due unto him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">主人就大怒，把他交給掌刑的，等他還清了所欠的債。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse35">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Hmei-k'ma-al-appa-hynna ymoumi-æn ta Rara-man-au ka æ'ia tounnoun ki vullum, rou assi kamou matta-raryh ta maihbovoel atta-ral ki tæ'i-a-para-oumi ki væ-rau nein. Ka sasat kytti-an 'ab ki matouda kilbeh ki soulat.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Hmeik'maalappahynna ymoumiæn ta Raramanau ka æ'ia tounnoun ki vullum, rou assi kamou mattararyh ta maihbovoel attaral ki tæ'iaparaoumi ki værau nein. Ka sasat kyttian 'ab ki matouda kilbeh ki soulat.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Alsoo sal oock mijn hemelsche Dader u doen indim ghy niet ban herten en bergeeft een yeghelijck Gnen broeder shne misdaen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">So likewise shall my heavenly Father do also unto you, if ye from your hearts forgive not every one his brother their trespasses.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們各人若不從心裏饒恕你的弟兄，我天父也要這樣待你們了。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
</TEXT>
