<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEXT id="Siraya_Dutch_Matthew_Chapter22" xml:lang="fos" source="Siraya Bible, Matthew gospel" copyright="public domain" citation="Gravius, Daniël. 1661. Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa. Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang. Amsterdam: Michiel Hartogh." BibTeX_citation="@book{Gravius1661,&#10;  author    = {Gravius, Daniël},&#10;  year      = {1661},&#10;  title     = {Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa},&#10;  note      = {Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang},&#10;  address   = {Amsterdam},&#10;  publisher = {Michiel Hartogh}&#10;}" dialect="Siraya">
    <S id="verse1">
        <FORM kindOf="original">KA ni-matti-v'lli ta ti Jefus mattæ'i-la neini-æn ki pæ myhkaulaula'n, ka k'ma,</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">KA nimattiv'lli ta ti Jefus mattæ'ila neiniæn ki pæ myhkaulaula'n, ka k'ma,</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende Jesus antwoordende sprack tot haer wederom door ghelijckenissen seggende | :</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And Jesus answered and spake unto them again by parables, and said,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌又用比喻對他們說：</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse2">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Mæmyhkaulaula ta Peifa-fou-an ki tounnoun ki vullum ki voual ka Si-bavau Mei-fafou,ka ni-papahtatanang ki Alak tyn (ka parah ki vatouh-an ki pakakyt-tyl-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Mæmyhkaulaula ta Peifafouan ki tounnoun ki vullum ki voual ka Sibavau Meifafou,ka nipapahtatanang ki Alak tyn (ka parah ki vatouhan ki pakakyttylan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Het honinckriick Der Hemelen is geliick cen seker Koningh die rhnen sone een bruploft bereydt hadde,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">The kingdom of heaven is like unto a certain king, which made a marriage for his son,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">＂天國好比一個王為他兒子擺設娶親的筵席，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse3">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-madingi ki kouncia tyn patætæäm ki ni 'æitannin ba na tou ou-vavatoug-eih ki paka-kyttil-an, rå ni-ynnang mou-koua.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka nimadingi ki kouncia tyn patætæäm ki ni 'æitannin ba na tou ouvavatougeih ki pakakyttilan, rå niynnang moukoua.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende fond zijne dienstknechten uyt om de genoodde ter bruploft te roepen ende spen wilden niet kgmen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And sent forth his servants to call them that were bidden to the wedding: and they would not come.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">就打發僕人去，請那些被召的人來赴席，他們卻不肯來。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse4">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-patou-la'n tyn madingi ta pani ki kouncia, ka ni-k'ma, vana-van-ei ta ni-æi tan-nin bana, K'yt-t'ei ni-t'anang-au ta i-danga-ranga-au-mau, ni-pogh ta louang-au ka ni-æhæp, ki ni-touftouf-appa (ka laulong) ka ni-si-ymmid si-kaha si-tan, nda ou-koua-au tou ouvava-toughan ki pakakyttil-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Nipatoula'n tyn madingi ta pani ki kouncia, ka nik'ma, vanavanei ta niæi tannin bana, K'ytt'ei nit'anangau ta idangarangaaumau, nipogh ta louangau ka niæhæp, ki nitouftoufappa (ka laulong) ka nisiymmid sikaha sitan, nda oukouaau tou ouvavatoughan ki pakakyttilan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Wederom sond hy andere dienltknechten uyt seggende seght den genoodden Siet ick hebbe mijn middaghmacl bereydt mijn olsen ende de gemellte (beesten) 3yn sijn geflachtet ende alle dingen 30n gereet komt tot de</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Again, he sent forth other servants, saying, Tell them which are bidden, Behold, I have prepared my dinner: my oxen and my fatlings are killed, and all things are ready: come unto the marriage.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">王又打發別的僕人，說：＂你們告訴那被召的人，我的筵席已經預備好了，牛和肥畜已經宰了，各樣都齊備，請你們來赴席。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse5">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Rå dou asli nein ni-illigh, ni-d'marang mou-koua teni k'atta tou ouma tyn, teni k'anna tou pa'i-ass-'an tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Rå dou asli nein niilligh, nid'marang moukoua teni k'atta tou ouma tyn, teni k'anna tou pa'iass'an tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">sy (alcx) niet ach tende zijn henen gegaen pese tot fijnen acke: gene tot ine koopmanschap.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But they made light of it, and went their ways, one to his farm, another to his merchandise:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那些人不理就走了；一個到自己田裏去；一個做買賣去；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse6">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Rå neni ka rarouma dou ni-tmouroung ki kouncia tyn, ni-smamuk pakapat-ei neini-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Rå neni ka rarouma dou nitmouroung ki kouncia tyn, nismamuk pakapatei neiniæn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende de andere grepen tne dienanechten deden thaer macthept aen ende dooddense, . -</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And the remnant took his servants, and entreated them spitefully, and slew them.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">其餘的拿住僕人，凌辱他們，把他們殺了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse7">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka millingigh (ki atta) ta Mej-sasou ka Si-bavau, ni-'ah-æg-nang-a-yddyngdyngyt ta te-ni, ka rou ni-pad-ading-i-en tyn ta kabatoung-an ki ta'u ka macyt, ni-sidada tyn ta tama-lpogh k'anna, ka na pa-idigh tyn ki apoei ta euma nein;</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka millingigh (ki atta) ta Mejsasou ka Sibavau, ni'ahægnangayddyngdyngyt ta teni, ka rou nipadadingien tyn ta kabatoungan ki ta'u ka macyt, nisidada tyn ta tamalpogh k'anna, ka na paidigh tyn ki apoei ta euma nein;</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Alsnude ùomng(dat) hoorde wiert hy toormigh ende (ne kryghs-hepren sendende heeft die dootsiagers berniek ende hare tadt m. bgannt geltcken.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But when the king heard thereof, he was wroth: and he sent forth his armies, and destroyed those murderers, and burned up their city.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">王就大怒，發兵除滅那些兇手，燒毀他們的城。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse8">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Anna ta ni-koun tyn ki koun-cia tyn-nda, Peikahan-ato mei-ta-nan ta vatough ki pakakyttil-an, râ neni ka ni-i-tan-nin bana, assi mamsing irang ki kidi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Anna ta nikoun tyn ki kouncia tynnda, Peikahanato meitanan ta vatough ki pakakyttilan, râ neni ka niitannin bana, assi mamsing irang ki kidi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Dor sepde Hy tot ijne dienstknechten De bjuybddtc is wel bereydt doch DE gonoodde en waren het niet egy. :</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then saith he to his servants, The wedding is ready, but they which were bidden were not worthy.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">於是對僕人說：＂喜筵已經齊備，只是所召的人不配。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse9">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Alei ki anna u-pænæ'-u tou pta ki darang, ka papynna-pynna ki voual ka kabalei-au-moumi, tid-dau-auto pa-oukoua tou ou-vava-toug-eih ki pakakyttil-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Alei ki anna upænæ'u tou pta ki darang, ka papynnapynna ki voual ka kabaleiaumoumi, tiddauauto paoukoua tou ouvavatougeih ki pakakyttilan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Daerom gaer op de untgangen der wegen ende fo bele als gyder sult binden roeptle tot de bpuploft,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Go ye therefore into the highways, and as many as ye shall find, bid to the marriage.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">所以你們要往岔路口上去，凡遇見的，都召來赴席。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse10">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Karoutpapænælita koung-cia k'anna tou dara-darang, nipa-pakoilau ymmid ka ni-kabalei nein, ka mat'e ka matiang-appa, ka ni-matmoei ta vatough ki a ia-roung.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Karoutpapænælita koungcia k'anna tou daradarang, nipapakoilau ymmid ka nikabalei nein, ka mat'e ka matiangappa, ka nimatmoei ta vatough ki a iaroung.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende discibe dimnstknerhita apegaende op de wegt brjgaderden alle diesp bonden beyde xtade ci goede efi de buyyllofe wierde ber-</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">So those servants went out into the highways, and gathered together all as many as they found, both bad and good: and the wedding was furnished with guests.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那些僕人就出去，到大路上，凡遇見的，不論善惡都召聚了來，筵席上就坐滿了客。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse11">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka ni-mou-rbota Mei-sasou ka Si-bavau tou hi-matta-eih tyn ta aia-roung, ni-k'ytt'an tyn ta ta'u ka assi mahkoulamough tou ou-vavatough-an ki pakakyt til-an-da.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka nimourbota Meisasou ka Sibavau tou himattaeih tyn ta aiaroung, nik'ytt'an tyn ta ta'u ka assi mahkoulamough tou ouvavatoughan ki pakakyt tilanda.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende als de koning ingegaen was om de aenlittende ( gasten) te obe sien' sach Hy aldaer een mensche niet gekleedt (zijnde) met een byylofcs kleedt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And when the king came in to see the guests, he saw there a man which had not on a wedding garment:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">王進來觀看賓客，見那裏有一個沒有穿禮服的，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse12">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Diou, mamang ta ni-ou-rbo-en-hou hia rou assi-kow mah-koulamough ki ou-vavatouvatough? Ka ni-mak-digh ki marat ta teni.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka nik'ma tyniæn, Diou, mamang ta niourboenhou hia rou assikow mahkoulamough ki ouvavatouvatough? Ka nimakdigh ki marat ta teni.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende seyde tot hem Diient hoe zijt ghy hier inghekomen gheen bruploftsleedt{aen) hebbendes Ende hy berstomde.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And he saith unto him, Friend, how camest thou in hither not having a wedding garment? And he was speechless.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">就對他說：＂朋友，你到這裏來怎麼不穿禮服呢？＂那人無言可答。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse13">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Anna ta ni-k'ma ta Mei-sasou ka Si-bavau ki Pæäiroung-en tyn, Hali-rima-ei, hali-rahpal-ei, arau, 'aryngan-ei tyni-æn tou ka-rimdim-an ka siouro itou-tauagh: Tou hynna-al-ato ta tangi-tangi-en ki pat-ityng-en-appa ki waligh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Anna ta nik'ma ta Meisasou ka Sibavau ki Pæäiroungen tyn, Halirimaei, halirahpalei, arau, 'arynganei tyniæn tou karimdiman ka siouro itoutauagh: Tou hynnaalato ta tangitangien ki patityngenappa ki waligh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doe sepde de Koning tot de dienaers Bindet lijne handen ende boeten neemt Hem wegh ende werpt (hem) upt in de buytenste duysternisse:Daer sal zijn weeninge ende knersinge der tanden,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then said the king to the servants, Bind him hand and foot, and take him away, and cast him into outer darkness, there shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">於是王對使喚的人說：＂捆起他的手腳來，把他丟在外邊的黑暗裏；在那裏必要哀哭切齒了。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse14">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka mabatoung ta ni-ta-tæäm, rå matiting ta ni-peri.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka mabatoung ta nitatæäm, rå matiting ta niperi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Want bele zijn geroepen | maer wepnighe uptberoren,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">For many are called, but few are chosen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">因為被召的人多，選上的人少。＂ （可12‧13－17；路20‧19－26）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse15">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Tou kidi k'anna ni-d'ma-rang ti sariséen ka ni-mattæ'i-sal ki sou, alei ka teih-douk-ah tih-kla ki patta'i-rouh-kin ki sou nein tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Tou kidi k'anna nid'marang ti sariséen ka nimattæ'isal ki sou, alei ka teihdoukah tihkla ki patta'irouhkin ki sou nein tyniæn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doe gingen de Pharifeen henen ende hielden t'samen raet hoe sy hem berKiicken souden in (foe re: en.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then went the Pharisees, and took counsel how they might entangle him in his talk.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">當時，法利賽人出去商議，怎樣就着耶穌的話陷害他，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse16">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-padingi-en nein pa-ou-koua tyni-æn ta Pahtatæutau-ug-han.nein lam ki Herodianen, komma-koua, Tama-mahtæutau-ugh, kavana'nian ka matiktik kow ki sou, ka mahtautæuugh kow ki darang ki Alid tou katiktik-an, ka mang-au-'m hou ta tinamang ka ta'u: ka assi kow masa'u-kulkul ki vlung ki ta'u.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka nipadingien nein paoukoua tyniæn ta Pahtatæutauughan.nein lam ki Herodianen, kommakoua, Tamamahtæutauugh, kavana'nian ka matiktik kow ki sou, ka mahtautæuugh kow ki darang ki Alid tou katiktikan, ka mangau'm hou ta tinamang ka ta'u: ka assi kow masa'ukulkul ki vlung ki ta'u.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende sy sonden upt cot hem hare Discipelen met de Herodianen segghende Meelte wp weten dat ghy waerachtigh zijt ende den wegh Godes inde? waerhept leert ende na niemant en braegt: want ghy en siet den ptrsoon der menschen niet gen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And they sent out unto him their disciples with the Herodians, saying, Master, we know that thou art true, and teachest the way of God in truth, neither carest thou for any man: for thou regardest not the person of men.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">就打發他們的門徒同希律黨的人去見耶穌，說：＂夫子，我們知道你是誠實人，並且誠誠實實傳上帝的道，甚麼人你都不徇情面，因為你不看人的外貌。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse17">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Anna ta vana-van'ei-kame, Mamang ta rýh-euho? hahei-en kaua piæ ki Mei-sasou ka Si-atigh Si-bavau ta 'äymhgan, assi lava ha-hei-en?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Anna ta vanavan'eikame, Mamang ta rýheuho? haheien kaua piæ ki Meisasou ka Siatigh Sibavau ta 'äymhgan, assi lava haheien?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Seght ons dan Wat dunckt u + is het geoorloft den Hepser fchattinge te geben ofte niet +</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Tell us therefore, What thinkest thou? Is it lawful to give tribute unto Caesar, or not?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">請告訴我們，你的意見如何？納稅給凱撒可以不可以？＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse18">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Râ tou kalang-in Jesus ta sasamk'en ki ryh nein, ni-k'ma neini-en,</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Râ tou kalangin Jesus ta sasamk'en ki ryh nein, nik'ma neinien,</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">hy + Sy seyden tot hem Dabids (fone.)</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But Jesus perceived their wickedness, and said, Why tempt ye me, ye hypocrites?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌看出他們的惡意，就說：＂假冒為善的人哪，為甚麼試探我？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse19">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ymoumi ka panni-nni-en ki rýh ki sou,ka mang ta rarpung-'noumi jau-an? Pa-k'ytta-au koh ta malyttok ka "äymhgan. Kani-ad-nein tyni-æn ta denarium (ka malyttok ka ni-patag-hen.)</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ymoumi ka panninnien ki rýh ki sou,ka mang ta rarpung'noumi jauan? Pak'yttaau koh ta malyttok ka "äymhgan. Kaniadnein tyniæn ta denarium (ka malyttok ka nipataghen.)</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Shy gebepnsde wat bessoeckt ghy my + Toont my den schattingpenning. Ende sy brachten hemer eenen penningh.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Shew me the tribute money. And they brought unto him a penny.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">拿一個上稅的錢給我看！＂他們就拿一個銀錢來給他。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse20">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-kma neini-æn, Ah timang ta pa-souh-ta'u-ta'u-en k'at-ta? na 'hahalap-appa ka pa-tagh?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka nikma neiniæn, Ah timang ta pasouhta'uta'uen k'atta? na 'hahalapappa ka patagh?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende hy feyde tot hay Miens is dit beelt ende het opschyift *</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And he saith unto them, Whose is this image and superscription?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：＂這像和這號是誰的？＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse21">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'ma tyni-æn, A tou Si-atigh Si-bavau. Anna ta ni-k'ma neini-æn, P'hei-to ki Si-atigh Si-bavau ka atou Si-atigh Si-bavau,ki Alid-appa ka atou Alid-râ.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Nik'ma tyniæn, A tou Siatigh Sibavau. Anna ta nik'ma neiniæn, P'heito ki Siatigh Sibavau ka atou Siatigh Sibavau,ki Alidappa ka atou Alidrâ.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Sp leyden rot hem Des Kepsers. Doe sepde hy tot harr Geefc dan den Keyfe; dat des iensers 1s ende Gode dat Godts.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">They say unto him, Caesar's. Then saith he unto them, Render therefore unto Caesar the things which are Caesar's; and unto God the things that are God's.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們說：＂是凱撒的。＂耶穌說：＂這樣，凱撒的物當歸給凱撒；上帝的物當歸給上帝。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse22">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka millingigh ta neni ki atta, ni-mouh-kiap-ato: ka rou pa-yhka-koua tyni-æn, ni-dma-rang ta neni.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka millingigh ta neni ki atta, nimouhkiapato: ka rou payhkakoua tyniæn, nidmarang ta neni.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Endespdit hoorende berwonderden haer : ende hem berlatende 31jn \p wegh gegaen</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">When they had heard these words, they marvelled, and left him, and went their way.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們聽見就希奇，離開他走了。 （可12‧18－27；路20‧27－40）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse23">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Tou wæi k'anna ierrou ato moukoua tyni-æn ta Saddu-ceen, ka k'ma-kouakoua hynna, ka aou-si-ah ta likough-eih achpit, ka ni-tmaligh tyni-æn,</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Tou wæi k'anna ierrou ato moukoua tyniæn ta Sadduceen, ka k'makouakoua hynna, ka aousiah ta likougheih achpit, ka nitmaligh tyniæn,</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">© Te dien selben dage quamen tot hem de Sadduceen die seggen datter geen opstandinghe en 1s ende braeghden hem .</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">The same day came to him the Sadducees, which say that there is no resurrection, and asked him,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">撒都該人常說沒有復活的事。那天，他們來問耶穌說：</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse24">
        <FORM kindOf="original">K'ma, Tama-mahtæutau-ugh ni-k'ma ta ti Moses, Heirou mapatei ta timamang ka aöusi ki alalak, anna ta pou-tbung-ah ta tai-a-para tyn ki ni-keiäen tyn, ka pææhpit-ah ki æp ki tæi-a-para tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">K'ma, Tamamahtæutauugh nik'ma ta ti Moses, Heirou mapatei ta timamang ka aöusi ki alalak, anna ta poutbungah ta taiapara tyn ki nikeiäen tyn, ka pææhpitah ki æp ki tæiapara tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Seas gende Meester Moles h seght Jndien yemant stexft geen geen kinderen hebbende soo salsijnen border des selben wyf trouwen ende synen broetder raet berwecken,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Saying, Master, Moses said, If a man die, having no children, his brother shall marry his wife, and raise up seed unto his brother.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">＂夫子，摩西說：＂人若死了，沒有孩子，他兄弟當娶他的妻，為哥哥生子立後。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse25">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Nda na akou-papyttou ki mahtæiappapara ymian-æn, ka naunamou ka ni-pou-tbung ta ni-map-atei-ato, ka alei ka aousi ki alalak, ni-pa-tbli ki ni-keiæ tyn ki ta'i-apara tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Nda na akoupapyttou ki mahtæiappapara ymianæn, ka naunamou ka nipoutbung ta nimapateiato, ka alei ka aousi ki alalak, nipatbli ki nikeiæ tyn ki ta'iapara tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Nu waren daer by ons seben broeders ende de eesste (een wif) getrouwt hebbehde tef ende dewijle hy geen raedt en hadde soo liet hy sijn wijf boor ijnen broeder.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Now there were with us seven brethren: and the first, when he had married a wife, deceased, and, having no issue, left his wife unto his brother:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">從前，在我們這裏有弟兄七人，第一個娶了妻，死了，沒有孩子，撇下妻子給兄弟。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse26">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-mahkaulaula k'omma-hynna ta ti kara-rouha, ta'ti kata tourou, mah-kidi-appa ki kapa-pyttou.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Nimahkaulaula k'ommahynna ta ti kararouha, ta'ti kata tourou, mahkidiappa ki kapapyttou.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Desgelijcks oock de tweede ende de derde tot den sebenden toe.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Likewise the second also, and the third, unto the seventh.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">第二、第三，直到第七個，都是如此。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse27">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Tou 'äugh ki ymmid nei-ni-æn ni-pis-koua-appa mapatei ta jna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Tou 'äugh ki ymmid neiniæn nipiskouaappa mapatei ta jna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ten laetlten nae allen is oock de brouwe gheltor-</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And last of all the woman died also.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">末後，婦人也死了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse28">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Anna ta tou likough-eih ahpit, a timang-ah ta keijen ki pa-pyttou k'anna? dou ni-pou-ymmid nein pou-tbung tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Anna ta tou likougheih ahpit, a timangah ta keijen ki papyttou k'anna? dou nipouymmid nein poutbung tyniæn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">In de opstandinghe dan wiens wyf sal sy wesen ban die seben $ want sy hebbense alle gehadt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Therefore in the resurrection whose wife shall she be of the seven? for they all had her.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">這樣，當復活的時候，她是七個人中哪一個的妻子呢？因為他們都娶過她。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse29">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Râ ni-matte'i-vlli ta ti Je-sus, k'ma-hia neini-æn, Taura-heï-kamou tou assi kavan'an kina sasoulat ki ligh-appa ki Alid..</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Râ nimatte'ivlli ta ti Jesus, k'mahia neiniæn, Tauraheïkamou tou assi kavan'an kina sasoulat ki lighappa ki Alid..</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">ar: Jefus antwoordde ende sepde tot haer Ghy dwaelt niet weteii deSchutten noch de kracht Godts.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus answered and said unto them, Ye do err, not knowing the scriptures, nor the power of God.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌回答說：＂你們錯了；因為不明白聖經，也不曉得上帝的大能。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse30">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Nda tou likough-eih achpit assi pou-tbung-ah, assi papou-tbung-an-eih-appa: râ mam'al-ato ki Tamahnau ki Alid tou tounoun ki vullum.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Nda tou likougheih achpit assi poutbungah, assi papoutbunganeihappa: râ mam'alato ki Tamahnau ki Alid tou tounoun ki vullum.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Want in de opftandinghe en nemen sy niet ten houwclicke noch en worden niet ten houwelick uptgegeben: maer sy zijn als Engelen Godts inden hemel.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">For in the resurrection they neither marry, nor are given in marriage, but are as the angels of God in heaven.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">當復活的時候，人也不娶也不嫁，乃像天上的使者一樣。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse31">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka atou likough-eih æhpit, assi-moumi kaua ni-kting ta ni-pasousou-en ki Alid ymoumi-æn, ka k'ma,</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka atou likougheih æhpit, assimoumi kaua nikting ta nipasousouen ki Alid ymoumiæn, ka k'ma,</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende wat aengaet de opstandinghe der dooden en hebt gy niet gelesen her gene ban Godt tot u lieden ghesproken is die daer seght</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But as touching the resurrection of the dead, have ye not read that which was spoken unto you by God, saying,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">論到死人復活，上帝在經上向你們所說的，你們沒有念過嗎？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse32">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ti jau ta Alid ti Abraham, ta Alid ti Isaak, ta Alid-appa ti Jakob? Alid ta assi Alid ki patei, râ ki mæuah.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ti jau ta Alid ti Abraham, ta Alid ti Isaak, ta Alidappa ti Jakob? Alid ta assi Alid ki patei, râ ki mæuah.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ick ben de Godt Abrahams ende de Godt Tlaacs efi de Godt Jacobs? Godt en is niet cen Godt der dooden marr der lebende.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">I am the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob? God is not the God of the dead, but of the living.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他說：＂我是亞伯拉罕的上帝，以撒的上帝，雅各的上帝。＂上帝不是死人的上帝，乃是活人的上帝。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse33">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka millingigh(ki atta) ta makoilalaulau ni-mauhki-ap-ato ki na pahtatæutæuugh tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka millingigh(ki atta) ta makoilalaulau nimauhkiapato ki na pahtatæutæuugh tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende de charen (dir) hoorende wierden berslagen ober Cijne leere,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And when the multitude heard this, they were astonished at his doctrine.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">眾人聽見這話，就希奇他的教訓。 （可12‧28－34；路10‧25－28）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse34">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Rå tou illing-hen ki sari séen ka ni tkid tyn ta moutos ki Sadduceen, ni-mæua-sal mæuakla ta neni.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Rå tou illinghen ki sari séen ka ni tkid tyn ta moutos ki Sadduceen, nimæuasal mæuakla ta neni.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende dePhariseen gehoort hebbende dat hy den Sadduceen den mondt ghefiopt hadde 3hn te samen by een bergadert.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But when the Pharisees had heard that he had put the Sadducees to silence, they were gathered together.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">法利賽人聽見耶穌堵住了撒都該人的口，他們就聚集。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse35">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka saat neini-æn-ka Mah-tæutæuugh ki Tatouhko ta ni-rih-pung tmaligh tyni-æn, k'ma,</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka saat neiniænka Mahtæutæuugh ki Tatouhko ta nirihpung tmaligh tyniæn, k'ma,</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende een uyt hae? (zijnde) een Wet-geleerde heeft gebraeght hem bersoeckende ende seggende</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then one of them, which was a lawyer, asked him a question, tempting him, and saying,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">內中有一個人是律法師，要試探耶穌，就問他說：</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse36">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Tama-mahtæutæuugh,ka-mang ta sou ka pah-kousasousou ki keirang-en tou Tatouhko?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Tamamahtæutæuugh,kamang ta sou ka pahkousasousou ki keirangen tou Tatouhko?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Meelte welck is het geoot gebodt in de Wet $</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Master, which is the great commandment in the law?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">＂夫子，律法上的誡命，哪一條是最大的呢？＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse37">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Rå ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus ty-ni-an, Mava'ango-ah kow ki Mei-rang ka Alid oho tou tyntin-noho ka myhta tmouk, tou vatti-oho ka myhtatmouk, tou ymd-appa ki ou-mhga-en hou pah-dimdim.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Rå nik'ma ta ti Jesus tynian, Mava'angoah kow ki Meirang ka Alid oho tou tyntinnoho ka myhta tmouk, tou vattioho ka myhtatmouk, tou ymdappa ki oumhgaen hou pahdimdim.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende Jesus seyde tot hem Ghy sult liefhebben den Heere uwen Godt met geheel uw' herte ende met geheeluwe riele ende met gehcel uw' berstandt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus said unto him, Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thy mind.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌對他說：＂你要盡心、盡性、盡意愛主－你的上帝。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse38">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Atta ta sou ka pahkousasou-sou ka naunamou ki keirang-en.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Atta ta sou ka pahkousasousou ka naunamou ki keirangen.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Dit is het cerlte ende het groot gebodt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">This is the first and great commandment.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">這是誡命中的第一，且是最大的。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse39">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Rå kararouha ta mahkau-laula ki atta: Mavæango-ah kow ki ta'u ka rarouma mama mama-do ymhou-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Rå kararouha ta mahkaulaula ki atta: Mavæangoah kow ki ta'u ka rarouma mama mamado ymhouan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende het tweede desen geliick (is:) Ghy sult uwen Naesten lief hebben als uselben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And the second is like unto it, Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">其次也相倣，就是要愛人如己。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse40">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Tou rourouha ki pahkou-sasousou k'atta æul-in ta ymmid ki Tatouhko ki na Tama-mattai-</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Tou rourouha ki pahkousasousou k'atta æulin ta ymmid ki Tatouhko ki na Tamamattai</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Aen dese twee gheboden hanght de gantsche Wet ende de Propheten.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">On these two commandments hang all the law and the prophets.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">這兩條誡命是律法和先知一切道理的總綱。＂ （可12‧35－37；路20‧41－44）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse41">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka makoi-sal-ato ta sariséen, ni-tmaligh neini-æn ta ti Jesus,</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka makoisalato ta sariséen, nitmaligh neiniæn ta ti Jesus,</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Als nu de Phariseen t samen bergadert waren braeghde hae: Jclus</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">While the Pharisees were gathered together, Jesus asked them,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">法利賽人聚集的時候，耶穌問他們說：</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse42">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka kima, pa'mang-'noumi ta ti Christus? Alak ti mang ta te ni? Ni-k'ma ta neini tyni-æn, na Alak ti David.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka kima, pa'mang'noumi ta ti Christus? Alak ti mang ta te ni? Nik'ma ta neini tyniæn, na Alak ti David.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende sepde Wat duncktu ban de Chailtus +</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Saying, What think ye of Christ? whose son is he? They say unto him, The son of David.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">＂論到基督，你們的意見如何？他是誰的子孫呢？＂他們回答說：＂是大衛的子孫。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse43">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'ma neini-æn mamei-mang ka mananang tyni-æn ta.ti David ki Joepan, ki Meirang-tyn, dou k'ma,</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Nik'ma neiniæn mameimang ka mananang tyniæn ta.ti David ki Joepan, ki Meirangtyn, dou k'ma,</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">hy sepde tot haer Hoe noemt hem dan Dabid in den Geeft shnen Heere seggende</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">He saith unto them, How then doth David in spirit call him Lord, saying,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：＂這樣，大衛被聖靈感動，怎麼還稱他為主，說：</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse44">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-masousou ta Meirang ki Meirang-au, mieroung-a tou ouwal-au tou kidi ka pa-itou koua-aul-ato mau ta sivænæuvæu ugh ymhou-an tou kahkakou-an ki rahpal oho?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Nimasousou ta Meirang ki Meirangau, mierounga tou ouwalau tou kidi ka paitou kouaaulato mau ta sivænæuvæu ugh ymhouan tou kahkakouan ki rahpal oho?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Deheere heeft gelegt tot mynen Heere Sit aen mijne rechter-(handr, Jcot dat ick uwe byanden sal geset hebben tot een boetbanck uwer boeten</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">The LORD said unto my Lord, Sit thou on my right hand, till I make thine enemies thy footstool?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">主對我主說：</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse45">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Heirou mananang ta ti Da-vid tyni-æn, Meirang, mamei mang ka na Alak tyn ta (teni?)</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Heirou mananang ta ti David tyniæn, Meirang, mamei mang ka na Alak tyn ta (teni?)</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Indien hem dan Dabidnoemt (sijnen) Heere hoe is hy stjn Sone?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">If David then call him Lord, how is he his son?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">大衛既稱他為主，他怎麼又是大衛的子孫呢？＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse46">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka assi mattai-lpough ta timamang matte'i-vlli tyni-æn ki sasasat ki sou: ka ni-maneianei ta timamang siäugh ki kidi ki wa'i k'anna tmauki-lala tyni-æn. Kararouha kytti-æn'ab ki touro ki Ibah ki soulat.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka assi mattailpough ta timamang matte'ivlli tyniæn ki sasasat ki sou: ka nimaneianei ta timamang siäugh ki kidi ki wa'i k'anna tmaukilala tyniæn. Kararouha kyttiæn'ab ki touro ki Ibah ki soulat.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende niemandt en Konde hem een woordt antwoorden : noch niemant en durfde hem ban dien daghe gen (yet) meer braegen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And no man was able to answer him a word, neither durst any man from that day forth ask him any more questions.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們沒有一個人能回答一言。從那日以後，也沒有人敢再問他甚麼。</TRANSL>
    </S>
</TEXT>
