<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEXT id="Siraya_Dutch_Matthew_Chapter1" xml:lang="fos" source="Siraya Bible, Matthew gospel" copyright="public domain" citation="Gravius, Daniël. 1661. Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa. Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang. Amsterdam: Michiel Hartogh." BibTeX_citation="@book{Gravius1661,&#10;  author    = {Gravius, Daniël},&#10;  year      = {1661},&#10;  title     = {Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa},&#10;  note      = {Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang},&#10;  address   = {Amsterdam},&#10;  publisher = {Michiel Hartogh}&#10;}">
    <S id="verse1">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Soulat ki kavouytan ti Jezus Christus, ka na alak ti David, ka na alak ti Abraham.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Soulat ki kavouytan ti Jezus Christus, ka na alak ti David, ka na alak ti Abraham.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Get Boeck des Geslachetes Jesy Christi, des soons Dabids des soons Abrahams.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">The book of the generation of Jesus Christ, the son of David, the son of Abraham.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">亞伯拉罕的後裔，大衛的子孫，耶穌基督的家譜：</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse2">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ti Abraham ta ni-pou-alak ti Isaac-an, ti Isaac ta ni-pou-alak ti Jakob-an, ti Jacob ta ni-pou-alak ti Juda-an, ki tæ'i-a-papar'ap-pa tyn-da.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ti Abraham ta ni-pou-alak ti Isaac-an, ti Isaac ta ni-pou-alak ti Jakob-an, ti Jacob ta ni-pou-alak ti Juda-an, ki tæ'i-a-papar'ap-pa tyn-da.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Abraham gewan Jacob. ende Isaac gewan Jacob. ende Jacob ghewan Judam ende sijne broeders.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Abraham begat Isaac; and Isaac begat Jacob; and Jacob begat Judas and his brethren;</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">亞伯拉罕生以撒；以撒生雅各；雅各生猶大和他的弟兄；</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse3">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ti Judas ta ni-pou-alak na Fares-an na Zara-an-appa p'ouhkoua ti Thamar-an. Ti Fares ta ni-pou-alak ti Esrom-an. Ti Esrom ta ni-pou-alak ti Aram-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ti Judas ta ni-pou-alak na Fares-an na Zara-an-appa p'ouhkoua ti Thamar-an. Ti Fares ta ni-pou-alak ti Esrom-an. Ti Esrom ta ni-pou-alak ti Aram-an.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Ende Judas ghewan Phares ende Zara by Thamar. ende Phares ghewan Esrom. ende Esrom gewan Aram.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And Judas begat Phares and Zara of Thamar; and Phares begat Esrom; and Esrom begat Aram;</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">猶大從她瑪氏生法勒斯和謝拉；法勒斯生希斯崙；希斯崙生亞蘭；</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse4">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ti Aram ta ni-pou-alak ti Aminadab-an. Ti Aminadab-an ta ni-pou-alak ti Naasson-an. Ti Naasson ta ni-pou-alak ti Salmon-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ti Aram ta ni-pou-alak ti Aminadab-an. Ti Aminadab-an ta ni-pou-alak ti Naasson-an. Ti Naasson ta ni-pou-alak ti Salmon-an.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Ende Aram gewan Aminadab. ende Aminadab gewan Naasson. ende Naasson gewan Salmon.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And Aram begat Aminadab; and Aminadab begat Naasson; and Naasson begat Salmon;</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">亞蘭生亞米拿達；亞米拿達生拿順；拿順生撒門；</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse5">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ti Salmon ta ni-pou-alak na Boös-an p'ouh-koua ti Rachab-an. Ti Boös ta ni-pou-alak na Obed-an p'ouh-koua ti Ruth-an. Ti Obed ta ni-pou-alak ti Jesse-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ti Salmon ta ni-pou-alak na Boös-an p'ouh-koua ti Rachab-an. Ti Boös ta ni-pou-alak na Obed-an p'ouh-koua ti Ruth-an. Ti Obed ta ni-pou-alak ti Jesse-an.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Ende Salmon ghewan Booz by Rachab. ende Booz gewan Obed by Ruth. ende Obed ghewan Jesse</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And Salmon begat Booz of Rachab; and Booz begat Obed of Ruth; and Obed begat Jesse;</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">撒門從喇合氏生波阿斯；波阿斯從路得氏生俄備得；俄備得生耶西；</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse6">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ti Jesse ta ni pou-alak ti David-an ka na Mei-sasou ka Si bavau. Ti David ka na Mei-sasou ta ni-pou-alak ti Salomon-an p'ouh-koua koua tyni-an [ka ni-keia] ti Urias.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ti Jesse ta ni pou-alak ti David-an ka na Mei-sasou ka Si bavau. Ti David ka na Mei-sasou ta ni-pou-alak ti Salomon-an p'ouh-koua koua tyni-an [ka ni-keia] ti Urias.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Ende Jesse ghewan Dabid den Koningh. ende Dabid de Koningh gewan Salomon by de ghene die urias urias [ wijf was geweest.]</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And Jesse begat David the king; and David the king begat Solomon of her that had been the wife of Urias;</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">耶西生大衛王。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse7">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ti Salomon ta ni-pou-alak ti Roboam-an. Ti Roboam ta ni-pou-alak ti Abia-an. Ti Abia ta ni-pou-alakti Asa-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ti Salomon ta ni-pou-alak ti Roboam-an. Ti Roboam ta ni-pou-alak ti Abia-an. Ti Abia ta ni-pou-alakti Asa-an.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Ende Salomon ghewan Roboam. ende Roboam gewan Abia. ende Abia gewan Asa.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And Solomon begat Roboam; and Roboam begat Abia; and Abia begat Asa;</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">所羅門生羅波安；羅波安生亞比雅；亞比雅生亞撒；</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse8">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ti Asa ta ni-pou-alak ti Josafat-an. Ti Josafat ta ni-pou-alak ti Ozias-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ti Asa ta ni-pou-alak ti Josafat-an. Ti Josafat ta ni-pou-alak ti Ozias-an.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Ende Asa gewan Josaphat. ende Josaphat gewan Joram. ende Joram gewan Oziam.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And Asa begat Josaphat; and Josaphat begat Joram; and Joram begat Ozias;</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">亞撒生約沙法；約沙法生約蘭；約蘭生烏西雅；</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse9">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ti Ozias ta ni-pou-alak ti Joatham-an. Ti Joatham ta ni-pou-alak ti Achaz-an. Ti Achaz ta ni-pou-alak ti Ezechias-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ti Ozias ta ni-pou-alak ti Joatham-an. Ti Joatham ta ni-pou-alak ti Achaz-an. Ti Achaz ta ni-pou-alak ti Ezechias-an.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Ende Ozias ghewan Joatham. ende Joatham gewan Achar. ende Achaz gewan Ezekiam.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And Ozias begat Joatham; and Joatham begat Achaz; and Achaz begat Ezekias;</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">烏西雅生約坦；約坦生亞哈斯；亞哈斯生希西家；</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse10">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ti Ezechias ta ni-pou-alak ti Manasses-an. Ti Manasses ta ni-pou-alak ti Amon-an. Ti Amon ta ni-pou-alak ti Josias-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ti Ezechias ta ni-pou-alak ti Manasses-an. Ti Manasses ta ni-pou-alak ti Amon-an. Ti Amon ta ni-pou-alak ti Josias-an.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Ende Ezekias ghewan Manasse. ende Manasse gewan Amon. ende Amon gewan Josiam.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And Ezekias begat Manasses; and Manasses begat Amon; and Amon begat Josias;</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">希西家生瑪拿西；瑪拿西生亞們；亞們生約西亞；</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse11">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ti Josias ta ni-pou-alak ti Jechonias-an, ki tæ'i-a-papar'appa tyn tou [tamang ki] kidi ki takalla-eih pou-loua tou Babilon.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ti Josias ta ni-pou-alak ti Jechonias-an, ki tæ'i-a-papar'appa tyn tou [tamang ki] kidi ki takalla-eih pou-loua tou Babilon.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Ende Josias gewan Jechoniam ende sijne broeders ontrent de Babylonische oberboeringe.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And Josias begat Jechonias and his brethren, about the time they were carried away to Babylon:</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">百姓被遷到巴比倫的時候，約西亞生耶哥尼雅和他的弟兄。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse12">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Tou ǣuh-appa ki ni-ta-kall'an tou Babilon ni-pou-alak ta ti Jechonias ti Salathiël-an, Ti Salathiël ta ni-pou-alak ti Zorobabel-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Tou ǣuh-appa ki ni-ta-kall'an tou Babilon ni-pou-alak ta ti Jechonias ti Salathiël-an, Ti Salathiël ta ni-pou-alak ti Zorobabel-an.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Ende na de Babylonische oberboeringhe gewan Jechonias Salathiel. ende Salathiel gewan Zorobabel.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And after they were brought to Babylon, Jechonias begat Salathiel; and Salathiel begat Zorobabel;</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">遷到巴比倫之後，耶哥尼雅生撒拉鐵；撒拉鐵生所羅巴伯；</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse13">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ti Zorobabel ta ni-pou-alak ti Abiud-an. Ti Abiud ta ni-pou-alak ti Eliakim-an. Ti Elia-kim ta ni-pou-alak ti Azor-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ti Zorobabel ta ni-pou-alak ti Abiud-an. Ti Abiud ta ni-pou-alak ti Eliakim-an. Ti Elia-kim ta ni-pou-alak ti Azor-an.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Ende Zorobabel gewan Abiud. ende Abiud gewan Eliakim. ende Eliakim gewan Azor.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And Zorobabel begat Abiud; and Abiud begat Eliakim; and Eliakim begat Azor;</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">所羅巴伯生亞比玉；亞比玉生以利亞敬；以利亞敬生亞所；</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse14">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ti azor ta ni-pou-alak ti Sadok-an. Ti Sadokta ni-pou-alak ti Achim-an. Ti Achim ta ni-pou-alak ti Eliud-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ti azor ta ni-pou-alak ti Sadok-an. Ti Sadokta ni-pou-alak ti Achim-an. Ti Achim ta ni-pou-alak ti Eliud-an.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Ende Azor ghewan Sadok. ende Sadok ghewan Achim. ende Achim gewan Eliud.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And Azor begat Sadoc; and Sadoc begat Achim; and Achim begat Eliud;</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">亞所生撒督；撒督生亞金；亞金生以律；</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse15">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ti Eliud ta ni-pou-alak ti Eleazar-an. Ti Eleazar ta ni-pou-alak ti Matthan-an. Ti Matthan ta ni-pou-alak ti Jakob-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ti Eliud ta ni-pou-alak ti Eleazar-an. Ti Eleazar ta ni-pou-alak ti Matthan-an. Ti Matthan ta ni-pou-alak ti Jakob-an.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Ende Elind gewan EleaEleazar. ende Eleazar gewan Matthan. ende Matthan gewan Jacob.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And Eliud begat Eleazar; and Eleazar begat Matthan; and Matthan begat Jacob;</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">以律生以利亞撒；以利亞撒生馬但；馬但生雅各；</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse16">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ti Jakob ta ni-pou-alak ti Josef-an, ka mou-kou-qua-ah ti Maria-an, ka ni-pei-alak tyn ta ti Jesus, ka pa-nanang-en ki sioua ti Christus</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ti Jakob ta ni-pou-alak ti Josef-an, ka mou-kou-qua-ah ti Maria-an, ka ni-pei-alak tyn ta ti Jesus, ka pa-nanang-en ki sioua ti Christus</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Ende Jacob gewan Joseph den Man ban Maria uyt welcke geboren is Jesus, geseght Christus.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And Jacob begat Joseph the husband of Mary, of whom was born Jesus, who is called Christ.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">雅各生約瑟，就是馬利亞的丈夫。那稱為基督的耶穌是從馬利亞生的。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse17">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Anna ta ymmid ki kavouivouyl-an-na Abraham tou kidi ti David, faät-ato kyttiæn'æb ki pat ki kavouivouyl-an. Ka na David, tou kidi ki takalla-eih poukua tou Babilon faät-ato kyttiæn'æb ki pat ki kavouivouyl-an-da.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Anna ta ymmid ki kavouivouyl-an-na Abraham tou kidi ti David, faät-ato kyttiæn'æb ki pat ki kavouivouyl-an. Ka na David, tou kidi ki takalla-eih poukua tou Babilon faät-ato kyttiæn'æb ki pat ki kavouivouyl-an-da.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Alle de Gheslachten dan ban Abraham tot Dabid [zijn] beertien geslachten ende ban Dabid tot de Babylonische oberboeringhe [zijn] beertien gheslachten ende ban de Babylonische oberborringe tot Christum [ zijn ] beertien geslachten.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">So all the generations from Abraham to David are fourteen generations; and from David until the carrying away into Babylon are fourteen generations; and from the carrying away into Babylon unto Christ are fourteen generations.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">這樣，從亞伯拉罕到大衛共有十四代；從大衛到遷至巴比倫的時候也有十四代；從遷至巴比倫的時候到基督又有十四代。 （路2‧1－7）</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse18">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-pei-alak-en ti Jefus Christus-an ta na k'm'ato-hynna; Irou ka ni-maä-mamado masashut ta ti Josef ka pakakitil-eih ti Maria ka Dena tyn, ka assi-appa ni-tæ-'ǣlam, ni-ǣi-vavalei ka akoukavoui-in ta teni ki na Joep-an ka Dilligh Matiktik.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-pei-alak-en ti Jefus Christus-an ta na k'm'ato-hynna; Irou ka ni-maä-mamado masashut ta ti Josef ka pakakitil-eih ti Maria ka Dena tyn, ka assi-appa ni-tæ-'ǣlam, ni-ǣi-vavalei ka akoukavoui-in ta teni ki na Joep-an ka Dilligh Matiktik.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> De gheboorte Jesu Christti was nu aldus: want als Maria sijne Moeder met Joleph ondertrout was eer sy te samen gekomen waren wiert sy swanger bebonden uyt den Heylighen Geeat.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Now the birth of Jesus Christ was on this wise: When as his mother Mary was espoused to Joseph, before they came together, she was found with child of the Holy Ghost.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">耶穌基督降生的事記在下面：他母親馬利亞已經許配了約瑟，還沒有迎娶，馬利亞就從聖靈懷了孕。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse19">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Nda ti Josef ka 'ou-kou-quȧ-auh tyn, alei ka na matiktik ta teni, ka ni-ynnang-en tyn pakaæmægh paka-nğala tyni æn, ni-pou-rarygh ki faou-ouzoung-en fau-tau-wagh tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Nda ti Josef ka 'ou-kou-quȧ-auh tyn, alei ka na matiktik ta teni, ka ni-ynnang-en tyn pakaæmægh paka-nğala tyni æn, ni-pou-rarygh ki faou-ouzoung-en fau-tau-wagh tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Joseph nu haren man alsoo hy rechtbeerdigh was ende haer niet en wilde openbaerlick te schande maken was ban wille haer heymelick te berlaten.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Then Joseph her husband, being a just man, and not willing to make her a publick example, was minded to put her away privily.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">她丈夫約瑟是個義人，不願意明明地羞辱她，想要暗暗地把她休了。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse20">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Heirou ka pæg-dimdim-un tyn ta atta; kytt'ey ta Tama-Gnau ki MEIRANG ta ni-mou-pænæh tyni-æn tou malling, ka ni-k'ma; Josef ka na alak ti David, ynna mahtakout mæiǣ pou-qua ymhou-an ti Maria-an ka ta'æu-pæu-pæu-ei-mou-hou: ka atta ka nikavouë tyn, na Joepan ta anna ka Dilligh Matiktik.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Heirou ka pæg-dimdim-un tyn ta atta; kytt'ey ta Tama-Gnau ki MEIRANG ta ni-mou-pænæh tyni-æn tou malling, ka ni-k'ma; Josef ka na alak ti David, ynna mahtakout mæiǣ pou-qua ymhou-an ti Maria-an ka ta'æu-pæu-pæu-ei-mou-hou: ka atta ka nikavouë tyn, na Joepan ta anna ka Dilligh Matiktik.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Ende alsoo hy dese dingen in den sin hadde siet de Engel des Heeren berscheen scheen hem in den droom seggende Joseph [ghy] sone Dabids en zijt met bebreest Mariam uw' wijf tot u te nemen. Want het ghene in haer ontsangen is dat is uyt den Heyligen Geest.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">But while he thought on these things, behold, the angel of the LORD appeared unto him in a dream, saying, Joseph, thou son of David, fear not to take unto thee Mary thy wife: for that which is conceived in her is of the Holy Ghost.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">正思念這事的時候，有主的使者向他夢中顯現，說：「大衛的子孫約瑟，不要怕！只管娶過你的妻子馬利亞來，因她所懷的孕是從聖靈來的。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse21">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka mei-alak-ah ki alak ka pæræh, ka faki-nanang-ei-'mhou ta nanangah tyn Jesus; alei ka Tama-paka-ri-ang-ah ki tau tyn. ki varau nein.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka mei-alak-ah ki alak ka pæræh, ka faki-nanang-ei-'mhou ta nanangah tyn Jesus; alei ka Tama-paka-ri-ang-ah ki tau tyn. ki varau nein.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Ende sy sal eenen sone baren ende ghy sult sijnen Name heeten Jesus. Want hy sal sijn bolck saligh maken ban hare sonden.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And she shall bring forth a son, and thou shalt call his name JESUS: for he shall save his people from their sins.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">她將要生一個兒子，你要給他起名叫耶穌，因他要將自己的百姓從罪惡裏救出來。」</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse22">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka ni-mam'tato ta ma-mang k'atta alei ka pa-væut-auh ta na fou ki MERIRANG pa-pattæi-tounoun ki Tama-mattæi-tan, ka ni-k'ma;</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka ni-mam'tato ta ma-mang k'atta alei ka pa-væut-auh ta na fou ki MERIRANG pa-pattæi-tounoun ki Tama-mattæi-tan, ka ni-k'ma;</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Ende dit alles is geschiet op dat berbult soude worden het gene ban den Heere gesproken is door den Propheet seggende </TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Now all this was done, that it might be fulfilled which was spoken of the Lord by the prophet, saying,</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">這一切的事成就是要應驗主藉先知所說的話，</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse23">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Kytt'ey, akou-me-'ah ki kavoui-in ta Tmattoul ka assi 'ouparæ'-in, ka mei-alak-ah ki alak ka paræh, ka smaki-nanang-ah-kow ki uanang tyn, Emmanuël, teni ki fou dou pahaviri-viri-in tou lam ymytæn ta Alid.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Kytt'ey, akou-me-'ah ki kavoui-in ta Tmattoul ka assi 'ouparæ'-in, ka mei-alak-ah ki alak ka paræh, ka smaki-nanang-ah-kow ki uanang tyn, Emmanuël, teni ki fou dou pahaviri-viri-in tou lam ymytæn ta Alid.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Siet de Maget sal swanger worden ende eenen sone baren ende ghy sult sijnen Name heeten Emmanuel het welck is obergeset sijnde Godt met ons.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Behold, a virgin shall be with child, and shall bring forth a son, and they shall call his name Emmanuel, which being interpreted is, God with us.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">說：</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse24">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Irou ka ni-patti-mæuǣ'-in ta ti Josef ki ni'irp-en tyn, ni-ah-qua tyn mama ki na sikakidi ki Tama Gnau ki MEIRANG tyniæn, ka ni-pa-ou-qua tyni-æn ki 'ou-kouqua-auh tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Irou ka ni-patti-mæuǣ'-in ta ti Josef ki ni'irp-en tyn, ni-ah-qua tyn mama ki na sikakidi ki Tama Gnau ki MEIRANG tyniæn, ka ni-pa-ou-qua tyni-æn ki 'ou-kouqua-auh tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Joseph dan opgheweckt zijnde ban den slaep dede geliick de Engel des Heeren hem beboolen hadde ende heeft sijn wijf tot hem genomen.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Then Joseph being raised from sleep did as the angel of the Lord had bidden him, and took unto him his wife:</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">約瑟醒了，起來，就遵着主使者的吩咐把妻子娶過來；</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse25">
        <FORM kindOf="original"> Ka assi tyn kalang-en ta teni, tou kidi ki ni-pei-kah'an tyn mei-alak ta alak tyn ka si-nḡada, ka ni-smaki-nanang tyni-an ki nanang ka Jesus.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard"> Ka assi tyn kalang-en ta teni, tou kidi ki ni-pei-kah'an tyn mei-alak ta alak tyn ka si-nḡada, ka ni-smaki-nanang tyni-an ki nanang ka Jesus.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Ende en bekende haer niet tot datse desen haren eerst-geboren sone gebaert hadde: ende hiet sijnen Name Jesus. </TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And knew her not till she had brought forth her firstborn son: and he called his name JESUS.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">只是沒有和她同房，等她生了兒子，就給他起名叫耶穌。</TRANS>
    </S>
</TEXT>