<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEXT id="Siraya_Dutch_Matthew_Chapter4" xml:lang="fos" source="Siraya Bible, Matthew gospel" copyright="public domain" citation="Gravius, Daniël. 1661. Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa. Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang. Amsterdam: Michiel Hartogh." BibTeX_citation="@book{Gravius1661,&#10;  author    = {Gravius, Daniël},&#10;  year      = {1661},&#10;  title     = {Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa},&#10;  note      = {Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang},&#10;  address   = {Amsterdam},&#10;  publisher = {Michiel Hartogh}&#10;}" dialect="Siraya">
    <S id="verse1">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Tou kidi kanna ni-dyllough ta ti Jesus ki I-oep-an pou-qua tou pæulæpæulæh, alei ki r'pung-eih ki Lyttou (kmæu-eirau) tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Tou kidi kanna nidyllough ta ti Jesus ki Ioepan pouqua tou pæulæpæulæh, alei ki r'pungeih ki Lyttou (kmæueirau) tyniæn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doe wiert Jesus van den Geest wech geleydt in de woeltijne om berfocht te worden ban den Dupbel.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then was Jesus led up of the spirit into the wilderness to be tempted of the devil.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">當時，耶穌被聖靈引到曠野，受魔鬼的試探。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse2">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka rou ni-rmierkud makk'-ahpat kyttiæn ki wæ'i, makk'-ahpat kyttiæn-appa ki euvan, si-æuh ki anna ni-mah-gangei-ra.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka rou nirmierkud makk'ahpat kyttiæn ki wæ'i, makk'ahpat kyttiænappa ki euvan, siæuh ki anna nimahgangeira.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">daghen ende beertigh nachten gebalt hadde hongerde hem ten laettte.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And when he had fasted forty days and forty nights, he was afterward an hungred.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他禁食四十晝夜，後來就餓了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse3">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka rou ni-iroua tyni-æn ta Tama-rpung (kmæu-eirau) ni-k'ma; Irou ka Alak-kow ki Alid, pa-sousou-ei, ka paha-papa'ul-auh ta vahto k'atta.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka rou niiroua tyniæn ta Tamarpung (kmæueirau) nik'ma; Irou ka Alakkow ki Alid, pasousouei, ka pahapapa'ulauh ta vahto k'atta.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende de Dersoecke: tot Hem gekomen zijnde sepde Indien ghp Godts Sone zijt segh dar dese steenen brooden worden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And when the tempter came to him, he said, If thou be the Son of God, command that these stones be made bread.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那試探人的進前來，對他說：＂你若是上帝的兒子，可以吩咐這些石頭變成食物。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse4">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Nda, teni ta mattæ'i-vli ni-k'ma, Ni soulat-ten-da, Assi dyk na pa'ul ta pa-kæuægh ki ka'æu-loung, râ tou ymd-appa ki sou ka tæi-qua mou-pænæh tou moutous ki Alid</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Nda, teni ta mattæ'ivli nik'ma, Ni soulattenda, Assi dyk na pa'ul ta pakæuægh ki ka'æuloung, râ tou ymdappa ki sou ka tæiqua moupænæh tou moutous ki Alid</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doch hy antwoordende sepde Daer 1s gheschre'ben De mensche en sal by broodt alleen niet leben maer by alle woordt dat door den mondt Godts uytgaet.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But he answered and said, It is written, Man shall not live by bread alone, but by every word that proceedeth out of the mouth of God.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌卻回答說：＂經上記着說：</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse5">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Anna ta ni-mara ta Lyttoupou-pou-qua tyni-æn tou Euma ka papa anni-in pa-t'amud, ka ni-pa-itou-qua tyni-æn pa itou-sapat tou pa-hga-hakb-an ki apang ki Kouva ki ta-tamd-en ki Alid.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Anna ta nimara ta Lyttoupoupouqua tyniæn tou Euma ka papa anniin pat'amud, ka nipaitouqua tyniæn pa itousapat tou pahgahakban ki apang ki Kouva ki tatamden ki Alid.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doe nam hem de DupDuybel mede nae de heplighe Stadr ende ltelde hem op de Tinne des Tempels</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then the devil taketh him up into the holy city, and setteth him on a pinnacle of the temple,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">魔鬼就帶他進了聖城，叫他站在殿頂上，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse6">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Heirou Alak-kow ki Alid, pou-aryng-â pou-rarim pou-mado ymhou-an, alei ka ni-soulat-ten-da, Ka ma-moummou-ah ki Tama-gnau tyn alei ymhou-an, ka pa-itou halap-ah ki rima hmapoulou ymhou-an, ki assi ymhou d'æur-auh ta vahto ki rahpal oho.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka nik'ma tyniæn, Heirou Alakkow ki Alid, pouaryngâ pourarim poumado ymhouan, alei ka nisoulattenda, Ka mamoummouah ki Tamagnau tyn alei ymhouan, ka paitou halapah ki rima hmapoulou ymhouan, ki assi ymhou d'æurauh ta vahto ki rahpal oho.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Eiieyde tot hem Jndien ghy Godts Sone 3yt werpcu selben nederwwacets : want daer is geschrebe Dat Hy syne Engelen ban u bebelen (al endedat) spu op de handen fallt rtict op dat gy niet t eeniger tijd uwen boet aen eenen lteen aen en lRtoot.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And saith unto him, If thou be the Son of God, cast thyself down: for it is written, He shall give his angels charge concerning thee: and in their hands they shall bear thee up, lest at any time thou dash thy foot against a stone.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">對他說：＂你若是上帝的兒子，可以跳下去，因為經上記着說：</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse7">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka na-k'ma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Na æ'æ-lali-kough sinoulat, Assi kow r'-pung-ah ki MEIRANG ka Alid oho.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka nak'ma ta ti Jesus tyniæn, Na æ'ælalikough sinoulat, Assi kow r'pungah ki MEIRANG ka Alid oho.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Jesus sepde tot hem Daer 1s wederom geschreben Ghy en sult den Heere uwen Godt niet berfoecken.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus said unto him, It is written again, Thou shalt not tempt the Lord thy God.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌對他說：＂經上又記着說：＂不可試探主－你的上帝。＂＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse8">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-hala mara ta Lyttou pou-qua tyni-æn tou voukyng ka mara-mal, ka ni-madouk tyni-æn ym-mid ki pei-sasou-an ki ymmud ki næi, ki keirang-en-appa ki kidi nein.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Nihala mara ta Lyttou pouqua tyniæn tou voukyng ka maramal, ka nimadouk tyniæn ymmid ki peisasouan ki ymmud ki næi, ki keirangenappa ki kidi nein.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Wederomnam hem de Hera pude WP eenen seer Hoog egh mde toonde em alle de Koninckrijcken Dry werelt ende hare heer-</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Again, the devil taketh him up into an exceeding high mountain, and sheweth him all the kingdoms of the world, and the glory of them;</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">魔鬼又帶他上了一座最高的山，將世上的萬國與萬國的榮華都指給他看，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse9">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Pi'æ'æ-ym'd-ei-mau-kow pi'æ ki mamang k'atta, rou maæu-hakup kow ma-kou-Alilid jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka nik'ma tyniæn, Pi'æ'æym'deimaukow pi'æ ki mamang k'atta, rou maæuhakup kow makouAlilid jauan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Eude sepde tot hem Alle dese dingen sal ick u geben indien ghy neder ballende my sult aenbidden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And saith unto him, All these things will I give thee, if thou wilt fall down and worship me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">對他說：＂你若俯伏拜我，我就把這一切都賜給你。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse10">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Anna ta ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, D'marang-â Tama-Ma-kou-doumma: ka ni-soulat-en-ra, MEIRANG ka Alid oho ta pakou-hakub-au-'mhou, ka dyk tyni-æn ta tatam'd-ei-'mhou-ra</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Anna ta nik'ma ta ti Jesus tyniæn, D'marangâ TamaMakoudoumma: ka nisoulatenra, MEIRANG ka Alid oho ta pakouhakubau'mhou, ka dyk tyniæn ta tatam'dei'mhoura</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doe seyde Jesus tot Hem Gaet wegh Satan : want dae: (taet geschreben Den Heere uwen Godt sult ghy aenbidden ende hem alleen dienen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then saith Jesus unto him, Get thee hence, Satan: for it is written, Thou shalt worship the Lord thy God, and him only shalt thou serve.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：＂撒但，退去吧！因為經上記着說：</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse11">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Anna ta ni-atta-ral tyni-æn æn ta Lyttou; Ka kytt'ey, ni-iroua ta Tama Gnau milligh tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Anna ta niattaral tyniæn æn ta Lyttou; Ka kytt'ey, niiroua ta Tama Gnau milligh tyniæn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doe liet de Duybel ban hem af endesiet de Engelen zijn toegekomen ende Dienden hem.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then the devil leaveth him, and, behold, angels came and ministered unto him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">於是，魔鬼離了耶穌，有天使來伺候他。 （可1‧14－15；路4‧14－15）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse12">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka ni-millingigh ta ti Jesus, ka ni-pæ'æ-tounnoun (pa-pou-sangat) ta ti Joannes, ni-sa-likough (mou-'nni) mou-qua tou Galilæa</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka nimillingigh ta ti Jesus, ka nipæ'ætounnoun (papousangat) ta ti Joannes, nisalikough (mou'nni) mouqua tou Galilæa</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Als nu Jesus ghehoordt hadde dat Joannes oberghelebe:t was is hy weder ghekeert nae GaliTeen,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Now when Jesus had heard that John was cast into prison, he departed into Galilee;</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌聽見約翰下了監，就退到加利利去；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse13">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka rou ni-irouä taulla tou Kapernaum, ka tou tamang ki va-oung, tou kidi ki pourou-pou-rough ki Zabulon-appa ki Nesta-lim-appa.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka rou niirouä taulla tou Kapernaum, ka tou tamang ki vaoung, tou kidi ki pouroupourough ki Zabulonappa ki Nestalimappa.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende Narareth berlatten hebbende 1s komen woonen te Capernaum gelegen aen de ree in de landtpalen ban Zabulon ende Nephtalim.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And leaving Nazareth, he came and dwelt in Capernaum, which is upon the sea coast, in the borders of Zabulon and Nephthalim:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">後又離開拿撒勒，往迦百農去，就住在那裏。那地方靠海，在西布倫和拿弗他利的邊界上。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse14">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Alei ka pa-väut-auh ta na sou ki na Tama Mattä'i-tan ka ti Esajas, ka koun,</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Alei ka paväutauh ta na sou ki na Tama Mattä'itan ka ti Esajas, ka koun,</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Op dat berbult soude worden t ghene ghesproken is door Jelaiam den Pr0pheet seggende</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">That it might be fulfilled which was spoken by Esaias the prophet, saying,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">這是要應驗先知以賽亞的話，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse15">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Pourough ki Zabulon, pourough-appa ki Nestalim tou darang ki vaoung, tou arough ki Jordaan, Galiläa ki ta'uta'u.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Pourough ki Zabulon, pouroughappa ki Nestalim tou darang ki vaoung, tou arough ki Jordaan, Galiläa ki ta'uta'u.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Het landt Zabulon efi het landt Nephtalim (aen denJweg der ree ober de Jordaen OGalilea der bolckeren,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">The land of Zabulon, and the land of Nephthalim, by the way of the sea, beyond Jordan, Galilee of the Gentiles;</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">說：</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse16">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ta'uta'u ka miroung ton karumdum-an ni-kmytta ki ræ-mæh ka irang: Neni ka ni-mi-roung tou pourough tou haloung-appa ki kapatei-an, ni-'ou-tiæg-han ki ræmæh neini-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ta'uta'u ka miroung ton karumduman nikmytta ki ræmæh ka irang: Neni ka nimiroung tou pourough tou haloungappa ki kapateian, ni'outiæghan ki ræmæh neiniæn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Het bolck dat in duy' sternisse sat heeft een groot licht gesien: ende de ghene die saten in den lande ende fchaduwe des doodts den selyen 18 een licht opgegaen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">The people which sat in darkness saw great light; and to them which sat in the region and shadow of death light is sprung up.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那坐在黑暗裏的百姓看見了大光；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse17">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Tou kidi k'anna ni-matta-naunamon ta ti Jesus matta-sasou, mattæ'i-k'ma-hynna, Si-lala, pa-sa likough-a ki vanna-oumi ki ryh, ka ni-mou-touk ta pei-sasou-an ki tounnoun ki vullu-vullum.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Tou kidi k'anna nimattanaunamon ta ti Jesus mattasasou, mattæ'ik'mahynna, Silala, pasa likougha ki vannaoumi ki ryh, ka nimoutouk ta peisasouan ki tounnoun ki vulluvullum.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Pan doen aen heefc Jesus begonnenteprediken ende te seggen Bekeert u want het Koninckrhck Der Hemelen is nae-by ghekomen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">From that time Jesus began to preach, and to say, Repent: for the kingdom of heaven is at hand.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">從那時候，耶穌就傳起道來，說：＂天國近了，你們應當悔改！＂ （可1‧16－20；路5‧1－11）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse18">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka tou hi-ryttoung-en mou-mou-nounang ti Jesus tou Saidd ki vaoung ki Galilæa, ni-kytt-'an tyn ta rarouha ki mahta-tæ'i-appa-ra, ta ti Simon ka Petrus ki siouwa, ti Andreas-appa ka tæ'i-appara tyn, ka smaki-vaoung ki rarei-houl (ka na-tama-'ou-d'llum ta neni.)</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka tou hiryttoungen moumounounang ti Jesus tou Saidd ki vaoung ki Galilæa, nikytt'an tyn ta rarouha ki mahtatæ'iappara, ta ti Simon ka Petrus ki siouwa, ti Andreasappa ka tæ'iappara tyn, ka smakivaoung ki rareihoul (ka natama'oud'llum ta neni.)</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende Jesus wandelende lende aen de ree ban Galilea sagh twee broeders (namelick) Simon geseght Petrus ende Andreas ijnen broeder het net in de ree werpende: (want sy waren bischers. )</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And Jesus, walking by the sea of Galilee, saw two brethren, Simon called Peter, and Andrew his brother, casting a net into the sea: for they were fishers.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌在加利利海邊行走，看見弟兄二人，就是那稱呼彼得的西門和他兄弟安得烈，在海裏撒網；他們本是打魚的。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse19">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-k'm-'ato-hynna nei-ni-æn, mæu-æuu-hâ jau-an, ka pa-sih-qua-au-mau-kamou pa-'ou-d'llum ki kaæuloung.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka nik'm'atohynna neiniæn, mæuæuuhâ jauan, ka pasihquaaumaukamou pa'oud'llum ki kaæuloung.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende hy sepde cot haer Dolght mpnae ende ick al u bichers der menfchen maken. :</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And he saith unto them, Follow me, and I will make you fishers of men.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌對他們說：＂來跟從我，我要叫你們得人如得魚一樣。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse20">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka dou madys atta-ral ki rarei-houl, ni-æu-æuug-han nein-tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka dou madys attaral ki rareihoul, niæuæuughan neintyniæn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Sy dan tesltont be netten berlatende rhjn hem nae gebolght.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And they straightway left their nets, and followed him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們就立刻捨了網，跟從了他。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse21">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Heirou ka ni-mali-deua ta teni makka-qua-hynna, ni-k'ytt'an tyn ta rarouha ki mahta-tæ'i-appa-ra ka pani, ta ti Jakobus (k'allak) ti Zebedæus, ti Joannes-appa ka tæ'i-appara tyn touh-para ti Ama nein ka ti Zebedæus tou avang si-ä-papat ki k'akæuæur nein, ka ni-t'æt'æ-æm tyn ta teni.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Heirou ka nimalideua ta teni makkaquahynna, nik'ytt'an tyn ta rarouha ki mahtatæ'iappara ka pani, ta ti Jakobus (k'allak) ti Zebedæus, ti Joannesappa ka tæ'iappara tyn touhpara ti Ama nein ka ti Zebedæus tou avang siäpapat ki k'akæuæur nein, ka nit'æt'ææm tyn ta teni.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende Hy ban daer boort ghegaen 3ynde sagh twee andere broeders (namelick} Jacobum den (sone) Sebedet ende Joannem lhnen broeder in het schip mee haren bader Zebedeus hare netten bermaeckende ende heeft haer geroepen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And going on from thence, he saw other two brethren, James the son of Zebedee, and John his brother, in a ship with Zebedee their father, mending their nets; and he called them.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">從那裏往前走，又看見弟兄二人，就是西庇太的兒子雅各和他兄弟約翰，同他們的父親西庇太在船上補網，耶穌就招呼他們，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse22">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ra neni k'anna dou ni-ma-dys d'marang ki avang ka talou, ki Raram'an-appa nein, ni-mæu-'æuugh tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ra neni k'anna dou nimadys d'marang ki avang ka talou, ki Raram'anappa nein, nimæu'æuugh tyniæn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Sy dan terftonc berlatende het ichip ende haren bade rzijn hem nae gebolght.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And they immediately left the ship and their father, and followed him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們立刻捨了船，別了父親，跟從了耶穌。 （路6‧17－19）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse23">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-hmæ-veiæh tau-ryt-toung ta ti Jesus tou ymmud ki Galilæa, mahtatæutæuugh tou Pæui-sa-saäl-en nein, matta-sasou ki Ha-gnau ka Mariang ki Pei-sasou-an, pæh-darkiagh ymmid ki maälam, ymd-appa ki mi-væuǣloung tou tautau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka nihmæveiæh tauryttoung ta ti Jesus tou ymmud ki Galilæa, mahtatæutæuugh tou Pæuisasaälen nein, mattasasou ki Hagnau ka Mariang ki Peisasouan, pæhdarkiagh ymmid ki maälam, ymdappa ki mivæuǣloung tou tautauan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende Jesus ommegingh geheel Galileen leerende in hare Synagogen ende predikende het Euangelium des Koninckrijcks ende genesende alle fieckce ende alle quale onder den</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And Jesus went about all Galilee, teaching in their synagogues, and preaching the gospel of the kingdom, and healing all manner of sickness and all manner of disease among the people.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌走遍加利利，在各會堂裏教訓人，傳天國的福音，醫治百姓各樣的病症。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse24">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-pa-'ou-louma-lou-ma'n ta 'illing-hen ki nanang tyn tou ymmid ki Siria, ka ni-æd nein tyni-æn ymmid neini-æn ka assi mariang ki voäl ka mannini ki ma-lam, ki pæ'i-alalam-en, ka 'isasaun-nen ki Lyttou, ka dimmi-dimmi-en (ki voäl) ka ni-papædari-kagh tyn ta neni.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka nipa'ouloumalouma'n ta 'illinghen ki nanang tyn tou ymmid ki Siria, ka niæd nein tyniæn ymmid neiniæn ka assi mariang ki voäl ka mannini ki malam, ki pæ'ialalamen, ka 'isasaunnen ki Lyttou, ka dimmidimmien (ki voäl) ka nipapædarikagh tyn ta neni.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende Ende syn geruchte gingh (ban daer) uyt in geHeel Sprien : ende sy brachfen tot hem alle die qualick geltele waren met bericheyden sieckten ende pijnen bebangyer zijnde ende ban den Duybel beseten ende maen-siecke ende geraeckte ende hy genas de felbe.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And his fame went throughout all Syria: and they brought unto him all sick people that were taken with divers diseases and torments, and those which were possessed with devils, and those which were lunatick, and those that had the palsy; and he healed them.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他的名聲就傳遍了敘利亞。那裏的人把一切害病的，就是害各樣疾病、各樣疼痛的和被鬼附的、癲癇的、癱瘓的，都帶了來，耶穌就治好了他們。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse25">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka mabatoung ta Makoui-lalaulau ka ni-mæu-æuah tyni-æn, makka Galilæa, makka Deka-polis, makka Jerusalem, makka Judeä, makka-arough-appa ki Jordaan. Kararima ki lbæh ki soulat</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka mabatoung ta Makouilalaulau ka nimæuæuah tyniæn, makka Galilæa, makka Dekapolis, makka Jerusalem, makka Judeä, makkaaroughappa ki Jordaan. Kararima ki lbæh ki soulat</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende beele fcharen bolgden hem na ban Galilea ende (ban) Decapolis ende (ban) Jerusalem ende (ban) Judea ende (ban) ober den Jordaen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And there followed him great multitudes of people from Galilee, and from Decapolis, and from Jerusalem, and from Judaea, and from beyond Jordan.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">當下，有許多人從加利利、低加坡里、耶路撒冷、猶太、約旦河外來跟着他。</TRANSL>
    </S>
</TEXT>
