<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Seediq_QSAN_廣盛科技" xml:lang="pwn" source="Paiwan Wikipedia, article: QSAN_廣盛科技" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="QSAN_廣盛科技. (2024, December 07). In Wikipedia [Paiwan]. https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/QSAN_廣盛科技" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_pwn_QSAN_廣盛科技, title = QSAN_廣盛科技, year = 2024, month = December, day = 7, note = {In Wikipedia [Paiwan]}, url = {https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/QSAN_廣盛科技} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">QSAN Technology Company Type: Corporation Unified Number: 27345816 Founder: Chen Zhipeng Headquarters: Taipei City, Taiwan Industry: Computer Hardware, Computer Software Website: www.qsan.com, storage.qsan.com Snluan qcinuh:公司QSAN Technology Co., Ltd. is a network storage device company based in Taiwan, established on July 28, 2004. The company's main business includes the design of storage devices, related software and hardware research and development, and integration services. Its business scope spans Europe, the Americas, and Asia. The products cover network storage devices such as Storage Area Networks and Network Attached Storage , flash storage arrays, disk array systems , and storage management systems. Products Network Attached Storage Storage Area Network Direct Attached Storage Disk Storage Systems System Backup Management == Reference ==</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">QSAN Technology Company Type: Corporation Unified Nomber: 27345816 Foonder: Chen Zhipeng Headqoarters: Taipei City, Taiwan Indostry: Compoter Hardware, Compoter Software Website: www.qsan.com, storage.qsan.com Snloan qcinoh:公司QSAN Technology Co., Ltd. is a network storage device company based in Taiwan, established on Joly 28, 2004. The company's main bosiness inclodes the design of storage devices, related software and hardware research and development, and integration services. Its bosiness scope spans Eorope, the Americas, and Asia. The prodocts cover network storage devices soch as Storage Area Networks and Network Attached Storage , flash storage arrays, disk array systems , and storage management systems. Prodocts Network Attached Storage Storage Area Network Direct Attached Storage Disk Storage Systems System Backop Management == Reference ==</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>