<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Seediq_鐘綺" xml:lang="pwn" source="Paiwan Wikipedia, article: 鐘綺" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="鐘綺. (2024, December 07). In Wikipedia [Paiwan]. https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/鐘綺" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_pwn_鐘綺, title = 鐘綺, year = 2024, month = December, day = 7, note = {In Wikipedia [Paiwan]}, url = {https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/鐘綺} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Snluan qcinuh:藝人Zhong Qi (born April 8, 1994), also known by her birth name Tu Minqi, is a Taiwanese singer-songwriter and English magazine lecturer. She gained recognition in 2018 for her collaboration with Yang Ying on the theme song for movie - Taipei, I Love You, as well as her participation in the television talent show Jungle Voice. Snluan qcinuh:藝人 Albums &amp; Singles Album Collab Singles Singles Commercial Songs Vitamilk Häagen-Dazs Films microfilms TV Shows Awards Gigs / Shows New Taipei Arts Festival PAY - Artist Invitation Performance 20190514 First Gig at "Riverside Live House" 20190611 Gig at "Riverside Live House" feat. Xuan Shi Gig feat. Xuan Shi at "Siaran" in Kaohsiung Music Concert feat. Ruth Kueo "Legacy Mini" New Taipei Good Market Festival - Artist Invitation Performance 110 Taiwan Original Pop Music Awards Music Performance "Happy Song VIP Trendy Music Concert" Guest Artist Invitation "Presidential Office 1HR Music Concert" Artist Invitation "Asia Illustration Art Expo" Artist Invitation "Lean on the Mountain Wave Music Festival" Mainstream Artist Invitation References External Links Official Facebook Page Official Instagram Page Official YouTube Channel</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Snloan qcinoh:藝人Zhong Qi (born April 8, 1994), also known by her birth name To Minqi, is a Taiwanese singer-songwriter and English magazine lectorer. She gained recognition in 2018 for her collaboration with Yang Ying on the theme song for movie - Taipei, I Love Yoo, as well as her participation in the television talent show Jongle Voice. Snloan qcinoh:藝人 Alboms &amp; Singles Albom Collab Singles Singles Commercial Songs Vitamilk Häagen-Dazs Films microfilms TV Shows Awards Gigs / Shows New Taipei Arts Festival PAY - Artist Invitation Performance 20190514 First Gig at "Riverside Live Hoose" 20190611 Gig at "Riverside Live Hoose" feat. Xoan Shi Gig feat. Xoan Shi at "Siaran" in Kaohsiong Mosic Concert feat. Roth Koeo "Legacy Mini" New Taipei Good Market Festival - Artist Invitation Performance 110 Taiwan Original Pop Mosic Awards Mosic Performance "Happy Song VIP Trendy Mosic Concert" Goest Artist Invitation "Presidential Office 1HR Mosic Concert" Artist Invitation "Asia Illostration Art Expo" Artist Invitation "Lean on the Moontain Wave Mosic Festival" Mainstream Artist Invitation References External Links Official Facebook Page Official Instagram Page Official YooTobe Channel</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>