<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="PA_Thao" xml:lang="ssf" citation="" BibTeX_citation="" copyright="public domain">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM>mathuaw mara’in a shanautuan Chua-Ing-Bun patu’iaw guan-cu-min a patashan</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">蔡英文總統代表政府 向原住民族道歉文。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">President Tsai Ing-wen's Apology to the Indigenous Peoples on Behalf of the Government.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="1">
        <FORM>mapushaz qamishan a thuini, mita wa hian- huat pulhipathan a patashan, san-paw pingqthan mzai guan-cu-min. haya sa sunda guan-cu-min a lhanaz, mataliza tu itia shmararuzi a lhanaz shururuniza, pu’apaw izai guan-cu-min mzai naur Taiwan a talima wa thau. miazithu milhilhi, thuini amuqthawan kmangqtha tata wa kinangqtha. yaku amia’awan cing-hu masai guan-cu-min-cok patu’iaw. munsai mashpatiz shaba wa qamishan, pashtay manuin guan-cu-min-cok inangqtu maniun kashpar masa antu manazithu, yaku mia’awan cing-hu patu’iaw maniun guan-cu-min- cok. </FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">二十二年前的今天，我們憲法 增修條文裡的「山胞」正式正 名為「原住民」。這個正名， 不僅去除了長期以來帶有歧視 的稱呼，更突顯了原住民族是 台灣「原來的主人」的地位。 站在這個基礎上，今天，我們 要更往前踏出一步。我要代表 政府，向全體原住民族，致上 我們最深的歉意。對於過去 四百年來，各位承受的苦痛和 不公平待遇，我代表政府，向 各位道歉。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">On this day 22 years ago, the term &quot;shanbao&quot; (mountain people) in the Additional Articles of our Constitution was replaced with the proper name: &quot;indigenous people&quot;. This correction not only did away with a discriminatory term, but also highlighted the status of indigenous peoples as Taiwan's &quot;original owners&quot;. From this basis, today, we are taking another step forward. To all indigenous peoples of Taiwan: On behalf of the government, I express to you our deepest apology. For the four centuries of pain and mistreatment you have endured, I apologize to you on behalf of the government.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="2">
        <FORM>yaku mriqaz, kahiwan kunathathuinian inai mingqulhmuz itiawan mani sa thau mzai ingqaiza patu’iaw. izai sa yaku amia’awan cing-hu patu’iza a lalawa. rinataqan ita antu manazithu zain thaythuy naur amiazithu, rinataqan ita wa numanuma, naur mita thau a shinkudaan naur ita thau amiazithu a shkuda, haya inai yaku thuini milhilhi, mangqtu yaku mzai apingqthan mindamriz minshuqish.					</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我相信，一直到今天，在我們 生活周遭裡，還是有一些人認 為不需要道歉。而這個，就是 今天我需要代表政府道歉的最 重要原因。把過去的種種不公 平視為理所當然，或者，把過 去其他族群的苦痛，視為人類 發展的必然結果，這是我今天 站在這裡，企圖要改變和扭轉 的第一個觀念。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I know that even now, there are some around us who see no need to apologize. But that is the most important reason why I am representing the government to issue this apology today. To see what was unfair in the past as a matter of course, or to treat the pain of other ethnic peoples as an unavoidable part of human development, this is the first mindset that we, standing here today, resolve to change and overturn.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="3">
        <FORM>thuini apasik malalabaza wa lalawa malhinuna maniun, minu qa amatsai guan-cu-min-cok patu’iaw. inai Taiwan a pruq mashpatiz shaba wa qamishan nauriza sa thau inai, inai a thau naur mrataq thaythuy ananak a ininthawan. itia thaythuy a lalawa, itia thaythuy a kazakazash, itia thaythuy a shashumshum, itia mani thaythuy a ininthawan a pruq. kanuniza makitnanai itia tata qbit a thau antu minakikalhi min’ananakiza makunanai mriway inai a pruq. </FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">讓我用很簡單的語言，來表達 為什麼要向原住民族道歉的原 因。台灣這塊土地，四百年前 早有人居住。這些人原本過著 自己的生活，有著自己的語言、 文化、習俗、生活領域。接著， 在未經他們同意之下，這塊土 地上來了另外一群人。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Let me put in simple terms why we are apologizing to the indigenous peoples. Four hundred years ago, there were already people living in Taiwan. These first inhabitants lived their lives and had their own languages, cultures, customs, and domains. But then, without their consent, another group of people arrived on these shores, and in the course of history, took everything from the first inhabitants who, on the land they have known most intimately, became displaced, foreign, non-mainstream, and marginalized.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="4">
        <FORM>sasaz a lalawa wa shumpazaw mzai miarikurikus a thau matsai mimamuqtha wa thau numanuma ingqulhmuzin thithu kmalaw. naur ininai a thau minamaza uka sa pruq a’ianan, numawan inai mingkakalungkun, uka sa taun a’ianan, minmiazai sa aminakantua wa thau, miaqay isai thaythuy a pruq min’ala’alash, numa thuini miazai sa antu talima wa thau, min’ishirshiriza wa thau. tata qbit a thau a mindadu, miazai sa inisai miaqbit a thau a shkuda. miazai ita antu manazithu a kok- ka, ya miazithu haya wa sasaz a lalawa iabrith ita mriqaz, izai sunda wa numanuma pulhkiz pu’apaw malhinuna. ya miazithu, sa mathuaw izai amunsai s acing-hu tiasasaz a lalawa sunda shnaw amingqtha mangqtu, haya inai yaku thuini milhilhi malhinuna. </FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">歷史的發展是，後來的這一 群人，剝奪了原先這一群人 的一切。讓他們在最熟悉的 土地上流離失所，成為異鄉 人，成為非主流，成為邊緣。一個族群的成功，很有可能 是建立在其他族群的苦難之 上。除非我們不宣稱自己是 一個公義的國家，否則這一 段歷史必須正視，真相必須 說出來。然後，最重要的， 政府必須為這段過去真誠反 省，這就是我今天站在這裡 的原因。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The success of one ethnic people can be built on the suffering of another. Unless we deny that we are a country of justice, we must face up to this history. We must tell the truth. And then, most importantly, the government must genuinely reflect on this past. This is why I stand here today.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="5">
        <FORM>itia tata wa patashan thithu a lhanaz mzai “Taiwan a sasaz a lalawa” thithu miahala tata wa qahil mzai, “Taiwan naur uka sa sasaz a lalawa, Huran a thau miahala munai, numa Te-sing-kung thithu sa miahala mani munai malhkakrikriw, numa ti Ching-kuq mintamaz malhkakrikriw.” haya sunda Shpuut a sasaz a lalawa wa mriqaz. guan-cu-min- cok nauriza pizza wa matilaw a kawash tu inaiza, itia manasha sa thaythuy a kazakazash, numa thaythuy a inin’ania, makitdaudauk puwanaz. kanuniza muqay yamin pasai makushwit a qbit a thau a mriqaz matash sasaz a lalawa, miazithu amiz’awan yaku matsai cing-hu patu’iaw. </FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">有一本書叫做「台灣通史」。 它的序言的第一段提到:「台 灣固無史也。荷人啟之，鄭 氏作之，清代營之。」。這 就是典型的漢人史觀。原住 民族，早在幾千年前，就在 這塊土地上，有豐富的文化 和智慧，代代相傳。不過， 我們只會用強勢族群的角度 來書寫歷史，為此，我代表 政府向原住民族道歉。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">There is a book called &quot;The General History of Taiwan&quot; published in 1920. In its foreword are these words: &quot;Taiwan had no history. The Dutch pioneered it, the Koxinga Kingdom built it, and the Qing Empire managed it.&quot; This is a typical Han view of history. The truth is that indigenous peoples have been here for thousands of years, with rich culture and wisdom that have been passed down through generations. But we only know to write history from the perspective of the dominant. For this, I apologize to the indigenous peoples on behalf of the government.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="6">
        <FORM>Huran numa Te-sing-kung a cing-hu munsai Alishay mathuaw kmaipathay numa kmalaw sa pruq masa kmalaw sa ininthawan a farifariw a aniamin, numa tu shiwanin izai Cing-kuq lhungqizi, mathuawiza kmaipathay mapa’urushrush a talhum, numa tu Litpuuniza sa lhungqizi mathuawiza mara’iniza wa antu pidaza sa guan-cu-min-cuk, miazai sa kmiskis sa guan-cu-min-cuk. miazithuiza shaunanai Tiong- hua-min-kuq-cing-hu miazithu mani guan-cu-min apinshpuutan dai. Lashpaat shaba wa qamishan, mashtay munai Taiwan a cing-hu mingqulhmuz pasain thaythuy mashampanaq numa kmalaw sa guan-cu-min-cok a pruq, mathuaw pingqarman sa guan-cu-min-cok naur itia wa numanuma. miazithu, yaku amia’awan cing-hu patu’iaw. </FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">荷蘭及鄭成功政權對平埔族群 的屠殺和經濟剝削，清朝時代 重大的流血衝突及鎮壓，日本 統治時期全面而深入的理番政 策，一直到戰後中華民國政府 施行的山地平地化政策。四百 年來，每一個曾經來到台灣的 政權，透過武力征伐、土地掠 奪，強烈侵害了原住民族既有 的權利。為此，我代表政府向 原住民族道歉。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The Dutch and the Koxinga Kingdom massacred and exploited the Pingpu ethnic group. The Qing Empire presided over bloody confrontations and suppression. Colonial Japan put in place comprehensive savage policies. And the post- war ROC government undertook assimilation policies. For 400 years, every regime that has come to Taiwan has brutally violated the rights of indigenous peoples through armed invasion and land seizure. For this, I apologize to the indigenous peoples on behalf of the government.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="7">
        <FORM>Guan-cu-min-cok pasain thaythuy a kazakazash lhungqizi naur itia wa numanuma, numa pasain mani Guan-cu-min-cok a kafazaqin a kazakazash lhungqizi hudun masa wazaqan numanuma, miazithu mashtay maqitan lhungqizi. kanuniza thuini a kok-ka kmalawa wa rinataqan, sa Guan- cu-min-cok antu maniun a min’ananak kmalawa ananak a palhkakrikriw, numa mani mut’uka sa ananak lhungqizi a kushwit. numa sasaz a shiduq mulawashwash, numa naur min-cok a miasuun a ininthawan antu shnurun mani sa suma. miazithu mani amunsai yaku cing-hu patu’iaw. </FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">原住民族依傳統慣習維繫部落 的秩序，並以傳統智慧維繫生 態的平衡。但是，在現代國家 體制建立的過程中，原住民族 對自身事務失去自決、自治的 權利。傳統社會組織瓦解，民 族集體權利也不被承認。為 此，我代表政府向原住民族道 歉。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Indigenous peoples maintain tribal order according to traditional customs, and ecological balance according to traditional wisdom. But in the process of modern state-building, indigenous peoples lost the right to steer their own course and govern their own affairs. The fabric of traditional societies was torn apart, and the collective rights of peoples were not recognized. For this, I apologize to the indigenous peoples on behalf of the government.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="8">
        <FORM>Guna-cu-min-cok nauriza thaythuy itia thaythuy a lalawa, numa pasain thaythuy a kazakazash a kafazaqin lhungqizi thaythuy numanuma wa ininthawan. kanuniza shwanin Litpuun lhungqizi, apiazain maniun apinlitpuun a thau, apingqthan thithu minlitpuun, shaunatusi tata makatanathu shpaat larima wa kawash, cing-hu apin’uka sa naam a lalawa, min’uka sa guna- cu-min-cok a lalawa. mashtaan sa Alishay a lalawa min’ukaiza. mulhkiz minakanantua wa cing-hu, antu munsai guna-cu-min-cok a kazakazash makarishkish lhungqizi, miazithu mani amunsai yaku cing-hu patu’iaw. </FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">原住民族本來有他們的母 語，歷經日本時代的同化 和皇民化政策，以及 1945 年之後，政府禁止說族語， 導致原住民族語言嚴重流 失。絕大多數的平埔族語 言已經消失。歷來的政府， 對原住民族傳統文化的維 護不夠積極，為此，我代 表政府向原住民族道歉。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Indigenous peoples had their own languages. However, with Japanese rule aiming to assimilate and turn all into imperial subjects, and with the ROC government banning tribal languages after 1945, indigenous peoples' languages suffered great losses. Most Pingpu languages have disappeared. Successive governments have been negligent in the protection of indigenous cultures. For this, I apologize to the indigenous peoples on behalf of the government.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="9">
        <FORM>kahiwan , cing-hu isui Yami a thau antu kafazaqin izai ho-hui-liaw pisain thaythuy Yami a thau a pruq. pingqarman sa Yami a thau, miazithu mani amunsai yaku cing-hu patu’iaw.						</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">當年，政府在雅美族人 不知情的情況下，將核 廢料存置在蘭嶼。蘭嶼 的族人承受核廢料的傷 害。為此，我要代表政 府向雅美族人道歉。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Without the knowledge of the Yami tribe, the government stored nuclear waste on Orchid Island. Tribe members on the island had to suffer the negative consequences. For this, I apologize to the Yami people on behalf of the government.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="10">
        <FORM>minakantua cing-hu shaunanai Taiwan, isai tanaraus a Alishay mathuaw pikraruzin sa cing-fu, tatata wa lhungqizi a cing-hu mingqulhmuz miku ping’uka sa Alishay a guan-cu-min a tinuran. miazithu amunsai yaku Alishay patu’iaw. 					</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">自外來者進入台灣以 來，居住在西部平原的 平埔族群首當其衝。歷 來統治者消除平埔族群 個人及民族身分，為此， 我代表政府，向平埔族 群道歉。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Ever since outsiders began arriving in Taiwan, the Pingpu ethnic group on the western plains have born the brunt of the impact. One ruling power after another eroded the individual and collective identities of the Pingpu ethnic group. For this, I apologize to the Pingpu ethnic group on behalf of the government.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="11">
        <FORM>min-cuu pingqthaniza, numa kok-ka itia shuntaam guan-cu-min-cok a pinalhinuna wa numanuma. cing-hu itia mani minalhinuna numa kinalawa ladadu a palhkakrikriw. thuini yamin itia maqitan a shumpazaw sa “guan- cu-min-cok a naur itia wa fat”, kanuniza izai a fat antu sa cing-hu miazithu a mabrith. mita wa kinalawa antu mabiskaw, ani mani mingqulhmuz, ani mani maqitan kinalawa. miazithu mani amunsai yaku cing-hu patu’iaw.					</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">民主轉型後，國家曾經回應原住民 族運動的訴求。政府做過一些承諾、 也做過一些努力。我們有相當進步 的「原住民族基本法」，不過，這 部法律，並沒有獲得政府機關的普 遍重視。我們做得不夠快、不夠全 面、不夠完善。為此，我要代表政 府，向原住民族道歉。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">After the democratic transition, the country began to respond to the appeals of indigenous movements. The government made certain promises and efforts. Today, we have an Indigenous Peoples Basic Law that is quite advanced. However, government agencies have not given sufficient weight to this law. Our actions have not been fast enough, comprehensive enough or sound enough. For this, I apologize to the indigenous peoples on behalf of the government.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="12">
        <FORM>Taiwan mzai manasha sa kazakazash a pruq, kanuniza shaunathathuinian, guan-cu-min- cok a maqitan a makalingkin, minfazaq numa farifari, cing-ti......numanuma wa piakazash, miazithu mani munsai antu guan-cu-min-cok a thau itia mara’in a antu tataal. tataal thuini, munsai guan-cu-min-cok mriqaz shmalaruzi. miazithu mani uka nanashnash. cing-hu antu manasha sa kinalawa, numawan guan-cu- min-cok mathuaw shkuda, numawan sh’uka. miazithu mani amunsai yaku guan-cu-min- cok patu’iaw. </FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">台灣號稱「多元文化」的社會。但 是，一直到今天，原住民族在健康、 教育、經濟生活、政治參與等許多 層面的指標，仍然跟非原住民存在 著落差。同時，對原住民族的刻板 印象、甚至是歧視，仍然沒有消失。 政府做得不夠多，讓原住民族承受 了一些其他族群沒有經歷過、感受 過的痛苦和挫折。為此，我要代表 政府，向原住民族道歉。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Taiwan is known as a culturally diverse society. But even today, indicators on health, education, economic livelihood, political participation and more still show gaps between indigenous and non- indigenous peoples. Meanwhile, stereotypes and even discrimination against indigenous peoples have not gone away. The government has not done enough, so indigenous peoples have suffered pain and frustration unknown to other ethnic peoples. For this, I apologize to the indigenous peoples on behalf of the government.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="13">
        <FORM>ita antu shduu iningkarishkishan, tatata wa minalangqtha mulhkiz ani yamin tu makarishkish. numa maniun mathuaw shkuda, shaunathathuinian mani miaqawan shkuda. yaku munmaniun mathuaw amazaiza! thuini a patu’iaw mathuawiza shrikkusan, kanuniza thuini lhmazawan. ani yaku tu mzai lashpaat shaba wa qamishan guan-cu-min-cok a shingkudaan numa piaqarman az’az sh’uka, kanuniza yaku munsai shnaw mangqtu thuini a patu’iaw, izai a kok-ka wa itmaz a thau lhmazawan mapaqaqitan. </FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我們不夠努力，而且世世代代， 都未能及早發現我們不夠努 力，才會讓各位身上的苦，一 直持續到今天。真的很抱歉。今天的道歉，雖然遲到了非 常久，卻是一個開始。我不 期望四百年來原住民族承受 的苦難傷害，會只因為一篇 文稿、一句道歉而弭平。但 是，我由衷地期待，今天的 道歉，是這個國家內部所有 人邁向和解的開始。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Our efforts have fallen short, and succeeding generations have been blind to this inadequacy. Because of this, your hardship has continued to this day. For this we are truly sorry. Today's apology is long overdue, but it is a beginning. I do not expect any one speech or phrase of apology to wipe away four centuries of pain and suffering by the indigenous peoples. But I do hope with all my heart that today's apology will set this country and all its people on the path towards reconciliation.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="14">
        <FORM>malalawa maniun yakin pasain tata wa guan- cu-min-cok a lalawa pishfazaq maniun tu thuini a miasusuun. isa Taiyal a lalawa, “dadu” mzai “Sbalay”, izai Taiyal a lalawa isa balay a ianamuqtha puqthaan “S” minsbalay. “dadu” masa “mapaqaqitan” itia sa tataal a inangqtu. pariri tata wa lalawa palhinuna, sunda wa mapaqaqitan amathuaw yamin mabahba mriqaz dadu a palhkakrikriw. ya miazithu shduuiza mukaktun. </FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">請容我用一個原住民族的智 慧，來說明今天的場合。在泰 雅族的語言裡，「真相」， 叫做 Balay。而「和解」叫做 Sbalay，也就是在 Balay 之前 加一個 S 的音。真相與和解， 其實是兩個相關的概念。換句 話說，真正的和解，只有透過 誠懇面對真相，才有可能達成。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Please allow me to shed light on this occasion with a piece of indigenous wisdom. In the Atayal language, truth is called &quot;Balay&quot;, and reconciliation is called &quot;Sbalay&quot;, so you simply add an &quot;S&quot; sound to &quot;Balay&quot;. Truth and reconciliation are in fact two related concepts. In other words, only by facing the truth sincerely can reconciliation be attained.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="15">
        <FORM>isa guan-cu-min-cok a kazakazash a itmaz, ya itia sa thau mapathay sa suma wa thau, ya mangqtu amapaqaqitan, tanatuqash a thau, thithu sa malalawa pishduhalan a thau, numa pingqarmanin a thau mulhkizin thithu malalawa pusuun. miasuun antu mzai apatu’iaw, apalhinuna thaythuy mabaraz a lalawa, ya malhinuna sunda wa palhkakrikriw, numa tanatuqash pashtay malhintal miqilha tata barukuz a qilha. rinataqan ita piazithuiza mrataq, haya mzai “Sbalay”. mangqtu yaku mzai thuini mzai cing-hu masa guan-cu-min-cok a Sbalay. rinataqan a muririw pulhkizin pu’apaw malhinuna, ani yaku tu puil, ani </FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">在原住民族的文化裡，當 有人得罪了部落裡的其 他人，有意想要和解的時 候，長老會把加害者和被 害者，都聚在一起。聚在 一起，不是直接道歉，而 是每個人都坦誠地，講出 自己的心路歷程。這個說 出真相的過程結束之後， 長老會要大家一起喝一 杯，讓過去的，真的過去。 這就是 Sbalay。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">In indigenous cultures, when a tribe member has offended another and intends to reconcile, an elder brings together the offender and the offended – not to produce a direct apology, but to allow each side to frankly share their inner journeys. When this truth-telling concludes, the elder calls for everyone to drink together, so that what is past is truly past. This is &quot;Sbalay&quot;.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="16">
        <FORM>yaku tu smamik. italhawan itia mani guan-cu-min-cok a huruy amalhinuna thithu a inangqtu. ani yaku tu malhinuna maniun thuini mzai piazithuiza, kanuniza yaku amalalawa maniun rinataqan a muririw niza tu amaqaqtha, haya wa kok-ka, itia tata wa qali mashtay amapaqaqitan. 					</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我期待今天這個場合，就是 一個政府和原住民族之間的 Sbalay。我把過去的錯誤，過 去的真相，竭盡所能、毫無保 留地講出來。等一下，原住民 族的朋友，也會說出想法。我 不敢要求各位現在就原諒，但 是，我懇請大家保持希望，過 去的錯誤絕不會重複，這個國 家，有朝一日，可以真正走向 和解。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I hope today's occasion can be a &quot;Sbalay&quot; between the government and the indigenous peoples. I have spoken of past mistakes and truths the best I can, with nothing held back. In a moment, our indigenous friends will speak. I do not dare ask you to forgive, here and now. But I sincerely ask you to sustain the hope that past wrongs will not be repeated, and that one day, this country can see true reconciliation.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="17">
        <FORM>thuini muqay tata wa lhmazawan, kazaiku amupaqaqitan antu isai guan-cu-min-sok masa Alishay, is acing-hu. mafazaq yaku, ya muqay ruzith a patu’iaw, antu sunda wa patu’iaw, munsai guan-cu-min-cok mulhkiz a palhkakrikriw izai a kok-ka ashiruan dadu amapaqaqitan.					</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">今天只是一個開始，會不會和解 的責任，不在原住民族及平埔族 群身上，而在政府身上。我知 道，光是口頭的道歉是不夠的， 政府從現在開始，為原住民族所 做的一切，將是這個國家是否真 正能夠和解的關鍵。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Today is only a beginning. The duty for reconciliation lies not with the indigenous peoples and the Pingpu ethnic group, but with the government. I know that words of apology alone are not enough. What we actually do for the indigenous peoples will decide whether reconciliation succeeds or stumbles.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="18">
        <FORM>a’inai yaku dadu a pishfazaq, mathuaw mara’in a shanautuan a taun amakalawa sa “guan-cu-min- cok a sasaz a lalawa dadu masa patungkariri wa malhkaktha”, yaku amunsai kok-ka mara’in a shanautuan, minananak yaku pusuun a thau, yaku amunsai tatata wa cok a mia’azu mashtay musuun kmilhim sunda tiasasaz a lalawa, mashtay mani malhkaktha haya wa kok-ka kahiza wa lalawa.					</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我要在此正式宣布，總統府將 設置「原住民族歷史正義與轉 型正義委員會」。我會以國家 元首的身分，親自擔任召集 人，與各族代表共同追求歷史 正義，也會對等地協商這個國 家往後的政策方向。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Therefore, I am here to announce that we are setting up an Indigenous Historical Justice and Transitional Justice Commission under the Presidential Office. As the head of state, I will serve as convener and work hand in hand with tribal representatives to pursue historical justice. We will also discuss, on the basis of equality, the future policy direction of this country.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="19">
        <FORM>amalhinuna yaku, mathuaw mara’in a shanautuan a taun a malhkaktha, sa sunda mabrith izai kok- ka masa guan-cu-min-cok mashtay manazithu a inra’inan. tatata wa cok a mia’azu mulhkiz masa Alishay a mia’azu, mulhkiz cok masa kataunan a miasuun a riniqaz, az’az minbangqir. ya miazithu a kinalawa tu guan-cu-min-cok a pashtay miasuun a palhkakrikriw, shduu guan-cu-min-cok a shnaw a inangqtu a lalawa pu’apaw. </FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我要強調，總統府的委員會， 最高度重視的，是國家和原住 民族的對等關係。各族代表的 產生，包括平埔族群，都會以 民族和部落的共識為基礎。這 個機制，將會是一個原住民族 集體決策的機制，可以把族人 的心聲真正傳達出來。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I want to stress that this commission places the greatest importance on equality between the country and the indigenous peoples. The election of tribal representatives, including for the Pingpu ethnic group, will take as basis the consensus of peoples and tribes. This commission will serve as a mechanism for collective decision-making by indigenous peoples, and will ensure that the voices of tribe members find true expression.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="20">
        <FORM>miaqbit, yaku amathaduq hing-cing-inn amalhkaktha “guan-cu-min-cok naur mita wa fat a smukus malhkaktha”. haya wa palhkaktha pinu’apaw a lalawa, min mita w acing-hu kmalawa palhkakrikriw a piakazash. haya wa palhkakrikriw mingqulhmuz sasaz a lalawa wa inangqtu, guan-cu-min-cok min’ananak lhungqizi thaythuy a palhkakrikriw, manazithu a farifariwan a palhkakrikriw, numa pinfazaq masa kazakazash a pulhaqlha, numa buut a makalingkin a lhungqizi, numa isa mawalhnaq a guan-cu-min-cok lhungqizi numanuma. </FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">另外，我也會要求行政院定 期召開「原住民族基本法推 動會」。委員會中所形成的 政策共識，未來的政府，會 在院的層級，來協調及處理 相關事務。這些事務包括歷 史記憶的追尋、原住民族自 治的推動、經濟的公平發展、 教育與文化的傳承、健康的 保障，以及都市族人權益的 維護等等。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">In addition, I will request that our Executive Yuan convene regularly the Indigenous Peoples Basic Law Promotion Committee, and use the Yuan's authority to coordinate and handle matters related to any consensus reached by the above-mentioned commission. These matters include the following: to retrieve historical memories, to promote indigenous self-government, to seek fair economic development, to ensure continuation of culture and education, to safeguard indigenous health, and to protect the rights of urban indigenous peoples, etc.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="21">
        <FORM>thuini a fat munsai guan-cu-min-cok a kazakazash itia sa antu mubalabalay, ita amakalawa s izai itia sa kazakazash tnuran a fat, zain “guan-cu-min-cok a fat a malhkakrikriw a ifazfaz a taun”, miazithu kmalawa aput’uka guan-cu-min-cok a kazakazash masa kok-ka wa fat antu antu mubalabalay.				</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">對於現代法律與原住民族傳 統文化，有些格格不入的地 方，我們要建立具有文化敏 感度的「原住民族法律服務中 心」，透過制度化的設計，來 緩和原住民族傳統慣習和現 行國家法律規範之間，日益頻 繁的衝突。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Where modern laws and indigenous traditional cultures are at odds, we will set up an Indigenous Legal Service Center with a high degree of cultural sensitivity, to reduce through institutional design the growing clashes between indigenous customs and modern laws.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="22">
        <FORM>yamin thuini amunsai cing-hu thmadup iahiaw kmalawa kmashiqitan, guan-cu-min-cok maqa thaythuy a kazakazash isa thaythuy a pruq muribush, antu mzai afariwin thaythuy, muribush antu lhqizin a lhkaribush, anunin dai qa asakpin numa alumin? yamin thuini amunsai izai a lalawa qazii ya amiakuza. </FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我會要求相關部門，立刻著 手整理，原住民族因為傳統 習俗，在傳統領域內，基於 非交易的需要，狩獵非保育類 動物，而遭受起訴與判刑的案 例。針對這些案例，我們來研 議解決的方案。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I will ask the relevant agencies to immediately pull together cases in which indigenous community members have been indicted or sentenced for hunting, where the hunting was done in accordance with traditional customs, on traditional lands, and for non-transactional needs, and where the animals hunted were not protected by conservation laws. For such cases we will deliberate solutions.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="23">
        <FORM>yaku amunsai cing-hu thmaduq, amafazaq minu sa ho-hui-liaw apisain Lan-su? pu’apaw izai dadu a lalawa. sa ho-hui-liaw ya niwan tu kinashiqitan cing- hu apulhipas Yami a thau sa numanuma.					</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我也會要求相關部門，針對核 廢料儲存在蘭嶼的相關決策經 過，提出真相調查報告。在核 廢料尚未最終處置之前，給予 雅美族人適當的補償。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I will also direct relevant agencies to present an investigative report on the decision-making process of nuclear waste storage on Orchid Island. Before finding a permanent solution for the nuclear waste, we will provide the Yami tribe appropriate compensation.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="24">
        <FORM>tataal a thuini, atunduu Alishay a munsai thaythuy a ananak a shnuru, shnurun Alishay a guan-cu-min a thithu a lhanaz. yamin makatanathu a furaz numa maturuz a qali miahala, amalhkaktha fat a lalawa, amaqa ungqtuan sa Alishay a guan-cu-min-cok a lhanaz, numa thaythuy a lhinqizi numa thaythuy a shuqrumin.					</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">同時，在尊重平埔族群的自我 認同、承認身分的原則下，我 們將會在九月三十日之前，檢 討相關法規，讓平埔族身分得 到應有的權利和地位。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">At the same time, under the principle of respecting the Pingpu ethnic group's self- identity, and recognizing their identity, we will examine relevant laws before September 30 of this year, so that Pingpu ethnic group identity will receive the rights and status it deserves.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="25">
        <FORM>thuini a kawash makthin tata wa furaz numa tata wa qali, ita alhmaza matash numa kmalawa pishfazaq guan-cu-min-cok a kazakazash a pruq. kataunan min-kung-fat-zin a palhkakrikriw, ita lhmaza smukus numa kmalawaiza, ya kahiza, guan-cu-min-cok amin’ananak lhungqizi a inangqtu, tatata wa kinangqtha mingqulhmuz akalawan. ita amabiskawuan, guan-cu-min-cok a mathuaw taraan a fat mzai, “guan-cu-min- cok lhungqizi ananak a fat”, “guan-cu-min-cok a pruq numa wazaqan a fat”, “guan-cu-min-cok a lalawa wa fat” numanuma, alhai sa lip-fat-inn palhkakaktha. </FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">今年的十一月一日，我們會開 始劃設、公告原住民族傳統領 域土地。部落公法人的制度， 我們已經推動上路，未來，原 住民族自治的理想，將會一步 一步落實。我們會加快腳步， 將原住民族最重視的「原住民 族自治法」、「原住民族土地及 海域法」、「原住民族語言發展 法」等法案，送請立法院審議。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">On November 1 of this year, we will begin to delineate and announce indigenous traditional territories and lands. The system of tribal public corporation is already in place. In the future, the ideals of indigenous self-government will be realized step by step. We will step up the pace and submit for legislative deliberation three laws of great importance to indigenous peoples: the Indigenous Peoples Self-Government Law, the Indigenous Peoples Land and Sea Areas Law, and the Indigenous Languages Development Law.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="26">
        <FORM>thuini a saqazi, yamin amingqulhmuz malhkaktha sa guan-cu-min-cok palhkakrikriw a malhkaktha. isai izai a malhkaktha, cing-hu munsai thithu a palhkakrikriw a’itia manasha wa pinalhkaktha. ya kahiza, tatata kawash makashpashpat a furaz tata wa qali, hing-cing-inn amunsai mingqulhmuz a thau pishfazaq sa guan-cu-min-cok a sasaz a lalawa patungkaririn thithu mzai mubalabalay, kmalawa ya shaunanantua. adadu kmalawa guan-cu-min-cok a sasaz a lalawa patungkaririn, nuna kmalawa sa guan-cu-min-cok min’ananak lhungqizi a bangqir, hay acing-hu amakalawa munsai guan-cu-nin-cok a laturu a palhkakrikriw. </FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">今天下午，我們就要召開全 國原住民族行政會議。在會 議中，政府會有更多政策的說 明。以後每一年的八月一日， 行政院都會向全國人民報告原 住民族歷史正義及轉型正義的 執行進度。落實原住民族基本 法，達成原住民族的歷史正 義，並建立原住民族的自治基 礎，就是政府原住民族政策上 的三大目標。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Later this afternoon, we will convene a national indigenous peoples administrative meeting. In that meeting, the government will elaborate on the policies. On every August 1 to come, the Executive Yuan will report to the indigenous peoples our progress on restoring historical justice and transitional justice. To implement the Indigenous Peoples Basic Law, to serve indigenous historical justice, and to lay the foundation for indigenous self- government – these are the three major goals for the government's policy towards indigenous peoples.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="27">
        <FORM>yaku thuini amalalawa inai a thau, numa izai tian- si a tanamuqtha wa guan-cu-min-cok a huruy, malhintal minmriqaz a thau. malalawa yaku maniun alhungqizi, antu mzai malalawa maniun munai amatash. malalawa yaku maniun guan-cu-min-cok a huruy lhungqizi numa pinfazaq yakin, apariqaz cing- hu pu’apaw kinalawa thithu a lalawa, dadu apu’uka sa kahiwan a muririw. </FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我要邀請在場的、在電視及 網路轉播前的全體原住民族 朋友們，一起來當見證人。 我邀請大家來監督，而不是 來背書。請族人朋友們用力 鞭策、指教，讓政府實現承 諾，真正改進過往的錯誤。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">To all of our indigenous friends here and watching on TV and online: I invite you to stand witness. I invite you not to endorse, but to oversee. Please keep pressure on the government and right its course where necessary, so that it will realize its commitments and right historical wrongs.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="28">
        <FORM>yaku amunsai mingqulhmuz a guan-cu-min- cok a huruy anuniza, maniun sa pishfazaq sa itia wa thau mzai, kangqthaan ita wa pruq numa kahiwan a kazakazash sa antu kauriwan a aniamin. izai pashtay itia mara’in a shmuqrum.					</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我感謝所有的原住民族朋友， 是你們提醒了這個國家的所有 人，腳踏的土地，以及古老的 傳統，有著無可取代的價值。 這些價值，應該給予它尊嚴。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I want to thank all of our indigenous friends. You remind everyone in this country that there is irreplaceable value in the land we tread on and the traditions we inherit. This value deserves dignity.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="29">
        <FORM>ita ya kahiza, amunsai cing-hu smakus inai cing- hu a palhkakrikriw, amaqa ita minalangqtha wa thau, numa az’az minalangqtha wa thau, numa inai Taiwan a pruq a itia wa thau, antu amin’uka sa lalawa, antu min’uka sa rinataqan ita wa inangqtu, ani mani min’aura mita wa kazakazash, niza tu amiaqay isai mita wa pruq min’ala’alash. </FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">未來，我們會透過政策的推 動，讓下一代的族人、讓世世 代代的族人，以及台灣這塊土 地上所有族群，都不會再失 語，不會再失去記憶，更不會 再與自己的文化傳統疏離，不 會繼續在自己的土地上流浪。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">In the future, we will push for policies to ensure that succeeding generations of indigenous tribes and all ethnic peoples in Taiwan never lose their languages and memories, that they are never separated from their cultural traditions, and that never again are they lost in a land of their own.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="30">
        <FORM>amalalawa yaku az’az a thau ulhkiz makarishkish malhkakrikriw, mafazaq mita wa sasaz a lalawa, mafazaq mita wa pruq, mafazaq mani mita wa tatata wa thau a qbit a kazakazash. az’az sa thau ulhkiz mapaqaqitan, pashtay maqitan miasusuun numa pashtay mapaqaqitan, pashtay Taiwan a thau itia maqitan numa faqlhu a kahiza wa ininthawan.	</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我請求整個社會一起努 力，認識我們的歷史，認 識我們的土地，也認識我 們不同族群的文化。走向 和解，走向共存和共榮， 走向台灣新的未來。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I call upon our entire society to come together and get to know our history, get to know our land, and get to know the cultures of our many ethnic peoples. Let us work towards reconciliation, a shared existence and shared prosperity, and a new future for Taiwan.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="31">
        <FORM>malalawa yaku maniun mingqulhmuz itia wa thau, isai inai maqitan a qali, pashtay ita palhintal kmalawa itia maqitan a kok-ka, kmalawa dadu marium numa mashtay manazithu a kok-ka.				</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我請求所有國人，藉著今 天的機會，一起努力來打 造一個正義的國家，一個 真正多元而平等的國家。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I call upon all citizens to seize the opportunities offered by this day – to join together, work hard, and build a country of justice, a country of true diversity and equality.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="32">
        <FORM>anuniza pashtay maniun!</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">謝謝大家。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Thank you all</TRANSL>
    </S>
</TEXT>
