<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="PA_Puyuma" xml:lang="pyu" citation="" BibTeX_citation="" copyright="public domain">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM>a tilin a patalru kana sēhu sibalu kana yēncumincu i Ceaiy ing un soto</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">蔡英文總統代表政府 向原住民族道歉文。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">President Tsai Ing-wen's Apology to the Indigenous Peoples on Behalf of the Government.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="1">
        <FORM>pakanguwayan kana makabetraan misama dra druwaya ami garem kana wari. nanta inasalr temelru kana siyēnhua i sabak na “sanpaw” i, pinatedrelran lra pungalad dra “yēncumin” kema. idri na penatedrelr na ngalad i, amelri a maumau emitrul dratu ipuwangalad na melralrimus na temariyaama. mangaleb kurenauwan lra tu kinaretigiran. “amau na miyadare” kadri Taiwan kema kana yēncumincu. maretigir kandri na danapan i isatr. garem kana wari i, piyanguwayan ta penasa dra sadepa. aru patatalru ku kana sēhu. sasungal mi kanemu. panauwa mi driya kanemu dra naniyam kinaasabakan dra naniyam sibaluwa igelayan kanemu kana yēncumincu driya mapiyapiya. kananemu kinakawangan a adriyu driya kana pata leman amiyan i, nanemu kinudrekudran mu kinaulepan. aw na adri pinarisan na adri penauwa tu iyanau kanemu i, patalrua ku driya kana sēhu semungal kanmu. 					</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">二十二年前的今天，我們憲法 增修條文裡的「山胞」正式正 名為「原住民」。這個正名， 不僅去除了長期以來帶有歧視 的稱呼，更突顯了原住民族是 台灣「原來的主人」的地位。 站在這個基礎上，今天，我們 要更往前踏出一步。我要代表 政府，向全體原住民族，致上 我們最深的歉意。對於過去 四百年來，各位承受的苦痛和 不公平待遇，我代表政府，向 各位道歉。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">On this day 22 years ago, the term &quot;shanbao&quot; (mountain people) in the Additional Articles of our Constitution was replaced with the proper name: &quot;indigenous people&quot;. This correction not only did away with a discriminatory term, but also highlighted the status of indigenous peoples as Taiwan's &quot;original owners&quot;. From this basis, today, we are taking another step forward. To all indigenous peoples of Taiwan: On behalf of the government, I express to you our deepest apology. For the four centuries of pain and mistreatment you have endured, I apologize to you on behalf of the government.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="2">
        <FORM>pakupanaan ku. palru garem kananta kinakadruwan i paliyuliyus i, ulraya driya a miyasama a trau na aemana pakalrang kandri na sibaluwan kema tu wanger. idrini i, amau tu rami drananku iyadruwa kadrini kana wari garem. druwa ku patalrua kana sēhu semungala kanemu. na kinadriwan driya na trau tu nirangeran i, an semamisi ta dra trau i, kakuda amaw, an aludrun lra, an maulep lra dratu kinabaawan i, nantu kakakawang idrunu i! aru kakuda mi amaw kema tu nirangeran dra trau i sidrumayan. druwa mi garem maretigira kadrini. amau naniyam kiniyangeran na palralribakan meliyus aw benelis. 					</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我相信，一直到今天，在我們 生活周遭裡，還是有一些人認 為不需要道歉。而這個，就是 今天我需要代表政府道歉的最 重要原因。把過去的種種不公 平視為理所當然，或者，把過 去其他族群的苦痛，視為人類 發展的必然結果，這是我今天 站在這裡，企圖要改變和扭轉 的第一個觀念。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I know that even now, there are some around us who see no need to apologize. But that is the most important reason why I am representing the government to issue this apology today. To see what was unfair in the past as a matter of course, or to treat the pain of other ethnic peoples as an unavoidable part of human development, this is the first mindset that we, standing here today, resolve to change and overturn.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="3">
        <FORM>ti pakalranganay dra apatraran dra ngai pakalradram. muka dra manay daw semungal ku kana yēncumincu. pakanguwayan kana pata leman amiyan i, kandri kana dare i Tiwan. ulraya lra a trau a kikaadru. nadri na trau i, ulraya tu piningaiyan, ulraya tu kakuwayanan tu lregiyan, ulraya tu nirabakan tu babuyulr kantu dare. salaw inaba tu iwabaaw. likudran lra i, pabekubeku lra druwa kikadruwa a kemay i sidrumayan a trau a salepunan. 					</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">讓我用很簡單的語言，來表達 為什麼要向原住民族道歉的原 因。台灣這塊土地，四百年前 早有人居住。這些人原本過著 自己的生活，有著自己的語言、 文化、習俗、生活領域。接著， 在未經他們同意之下，這塊土 地上來了另外一群人。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Let me put in simple terms why we are apologizing to the indigenous peoples. Four hundred years ago, there were already people living in Taiwan. These first inhabitants lived their lives and had their own languages, cultures, customs, and domains. But then, without their consent, another group of people arrived on these shores, and in the course of history, took everything from the first inhabitants who, on the land they have known most intimately, became displaced, foreign, non-mainstream, and marginalized.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="4">
        <FORM>nadru na salepunan na trau na pakalikudran druwa i, tu araway tu pinimanayan peniya kana kurengaway kikadrukadru na trau. tu burekay lra nantu kinaladaman na dare. aw meresis lra mutusidrumayan lra. adri tu seeran lra aw makasanininin lra. tu iwadaway tu kinakeseran dra samauwan i, alra muka dratu tinariyamayan tu kinaulepan kana druma mauwan. an adri ta maranger patrirebeng pakalradram drata kanatal dra, amau mi na saigu parisarisan an kakuwa ta i, aru pasaseket ta menau kandri kana nilrangan. aru babati ta kana penanaan. na sēhu i, kapananaan parebeliyas kemiyanger dratu pinakalrangan kinadruwan. idrini i, amau ku iyadruwa garem maretigira kadrini tu pauwayan. 					</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">歷史的發展是，後來的這一 群人，剝奪了原先這一群人 的一切。讓他們在最熟悉的 土地上流離失所，成為異鄉 人，成為非主流，成為邊緣。一個族群的成功，很有可能 是建立在其他族群的苦難之 上。除非我們不宣稱自己是 一個公義的國家，否則這一 段歷史必須正視，真相必須 說出來。然後，最重要的， 政府必須為這段過去真誠反 省，這就是我今天站在這裡 的原因。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The success of one ethnic people can be built on the suffering of another. Unless we deny that we are a country of justice, we must face up to this history. We must tell the truth. And then, most importantly, the government must genuinely reflect on this past. This is why I stand here today.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="5">
        <FORM>ulraya a saya a tilin. “Taiwan tong se” kema. tu tinililran i, “i Taiwan i, uniyan dra tilin dra nilrangan. tu parebuwaaw kana Helan; tu tililray kan Cencenkong; tu palenakanay kana Cingtay.” idri tu iyanau i, panaan dra makapairang. na yēncumincu kana pakanguwayan dra munuma lra kudrulr amiyan i, kikadru lra kandri kana dare. aw ulraya tu kakuwayanan tu kinalradraman a salaw bulay. tu trungutrungulraw tu tralitraliyaw. amawna, ta iyanau i, pakalranganay drata ikakeser temililr dra nilrangan. muka kandrini i, patatalru ku kana sēhu semungal kana yēncumincu. 					</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">有一本書叫做「台灣通史」。 它的序言的第一段提到:「台 灣固無史也。荷人啟之，鄭 氏作之，清代營之。」。這 就是典型的漢人史觀。原住 民族，早在幾千年前，就在 這塊土地上，有豐富的文化 和智慧，代代相傳。不過， 我們只會用強勢族群的角度 來書寫歷史，為此，我代表 政府向原住民族道歉。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">There is a book called &quot;The General History of Taiwan&quot; published in 1920. In its foreword are these words: &quot;Taiwan had no history. The Dutch pioneered it, the Koxinga Kingdom built it, and the Qing Empire managed it.&quot; This is a typical Han view of history. The truth is that indigenous peoples have been here for thousands of years, with rich culture and wisdom that have been passed down through generations. But we only know to write history from the perspective of the dominant. For this, I apologize to the indigenous peoples on behalf of the government.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="6">
        <FORM>a kuredikes driya kana Helan aw kan Cencenkong i, tu ranakaw pinatray aw tu raperapay tu pinimanayan na Pinpucu. kana Cingcawsetay i, masaseredr palru dra marepinatray aw tu depedepanay. kana Dripung lra i, tu pakasayay temariyama patarisesek. palru kana druwa lra na Minkuk i, parekasenengaw na makadrenadrenan aw na marayarayas na sanpaw. pata leman amiyan lra. na druwa driya kuredikesa kadri Taiwan i, tu pakalranganay dratu kedrang demepedep emaraw dra dare. tu araway dratu kinuredikesan kana yēncumin. muka kandrini i, patatalru ku kana sēhu semungal kana yēncumincu. 					</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">荷蘭及鄭成功政權對平埔族群 的屠殺和經濟剝削，清朝時代 重大的流血衝突及鎮壓，日本 統治時期全面而深入的理番政 策，一直到戰後中華民國政府 施行的山地平地化政策。四百 年來，每一個曾經來到台灣的 政權，透過武力征伐、土地掠 奪，強烈侵害了原住民族既有 的權利。為此，我代表政府向 原住民族道歉。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The Dutch and the Koxinga Kingdom massacred and exploited the Pingpu ethnic group. The Qing Empire presided over bloody confrontations and suppression. Colonial Japan put in place comprehensive savage policies. And the post- war ROC government undertook assimilation policies. For 400 years, every regime that has come to Taiwan has brutally violated the rights of indigenous peoples through armed invasion and land seizure. For this, I apologize to the indigenous peoples on behalf of the government.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="7">
        <FORM>na yēncumincu i, tu pakalranganay kantu kakuwayanan tu lregiyan. murekes kemirungetr pakabulay dratu drekalr. aw kemay kantu kinalradraman parepauwauwa dratu wabaawan. amawna, kana gareman na kanatal, kana demadaway kantu kinuretan na kuwarenangan i, na yēncumin i, mulremes lra tu kuwaredikesan dra kiyakarunan. muparesis lra tu niyamunan dra drekalr. adri lra tu seeran tu inukasayan kana maunan. muka kandrini i, patatalru ku kana sēhu semungal kana yēncumin. 					</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">原住民族依傳統慣習維繫部落 的秩序，並以傳統智慧維繫生 態的平衡。但是，在現代國家 體制建立的過程中，原住民族 對自身事務失去自決、自治的 權利。傳統社會組織瓦解，民 族集體權利也不被承認。為 此，我代表政府向原住民族道 歉。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Indigenous peoples maintain tribal order according to traditional customs, and ecological balance according to traditional wisdom. But in the process of modern state-building, indigenous peoples lost the right to steer their own course and govern their own affairs. The fabric of traditional societies was torn apart, and the collective rights of peoples were not recognized. For this, I apologize to the indigenous peoples on behalf of the government.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="8">
        <FORM>na yēncumincu kemay awatr kadru lra tu piningaiyan. pakalranganay kana Dripung driya tu putudripudripungaw. kana 1945 amiyan i, rengay temaraminkuk kema na sēhu. tu pakasayay benuut marengay dratu piningaiyan. amau na mulralremes lra tu piningaiyan kana yēncumincu. tu ngaiyan kana Pinpucu i, marasadru lra na mulremes. kana kuredikes driya na sēhu i, adri pakirungetr palenak melrama dratu kakuwayanan kana yēncumincu. muka kandrini i, patatalru ku kana sēhu semungal kana yēncumincu. 						</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">原住民族本來有他們的母 語，歷經日本時代的同化 和皇民化政策，以及 1945 年之後，政府禁止說族語， 導致原住民族語言嚴重流 失。絕大多數的平埔族語 言已經消失。歷來的政府， 對原住民族傳統文化的維 護不夠積極，為此，我代 表政府向原住民族道歉。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Indigenous peoples had their own languages. However, with Japanese rule aiming to assimilate and turn all into imperial subjects, and with the ROC government banning tribal languages after 1945, indigenous peoples' languages suffered great losses. Most Pingpu languages have disappeared. Successive governments have been negligent in the protection of indigenous cultures. For this, I apologize to the indigenous peoples on behalf of the government.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="9">
        <FORM>adrunu kana ami. adri malradralradram dra mamanamanay na Yami kadri Butrulr. na sēhu tu ukayaw apetraw na hehuyliyaw i Butrulr. na mauwan kadri Butrulr. tu aludrunan tu binulian dratu anger i, a kemay kana hehuyliyaw. muka kandrini i, patatalru ku kana sēhu semungal kana mauwan i Butrulr. 					</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">當年，政府在雅美族人 不知情的情況下，將核 廢料存置在蘭嶼。蘭嶼 的族人承受核廢料的傷 害。為此，我要代表政 府向雅美族人道歉。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Without the knowledge of the Yami tribe, the government stored nuclear waste on Orchid Island. Tribe members on the island had to suffer the negative consequences. For this, I apologize to the Yami people on behalf of the government.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="10">
        <FORM>kemirami tu drinuwayan i Taiwan kana kemay i sidrumayan na trau. na kikaadru i makadrayadraya kana marayarayas na Pinpucu i, amau na pinalribakan kurepatrepa. na druwa driya kuredikesa kadri na trau i, tu itrulaw aw tu ribasaw tu ngalad kana karamisasayan lra, nantu maunan lra, tu ikapinpucu. muka kandrini i, patatalru ku kana sēhu semungal kana Pinpucu . 					</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">自外來者進入台灣以 來，居住在西部平原的 平埔族群首當其衝。歷 來統治者消除平埔族群 個人及民族身分，為此， 我代表政府，向平埔族 群道歉。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Ever since outsiders began arriving in Taiwan, the Pingpu ethnic group on the western plains have born the brunt of the impact. One ruling power after another eroded the individual and collective identities of the Pingpu ethnic group. For this, I apologize to the Pingpu ethnic group on behalf of the government.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="11">
        <FORM>kana mubalis lra na lremak i, na kanatal kadru tu iyatubang kana mincuyuntong dratu kiniamiyan kana yēncumincu. na sēhu i, “aiwa!” aw niyam kiyangeraw aw pakirungetra mi kema. garem i, ulraya a salaw inaba a kinuret a tilin “yēncumincu cipenhua”. amawna, idri na tilin na kinuret. adri tu seeran kana sēhu kana kiyakarun kandrini. naniyam kinikarunan i, puwari lra, adri tu rabaki peniya lra, adri driya penauwa. muka kandrini i, patatalru ku kana sēhu semungal kana yēncumincu. 				</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">民主轉型後，國家曾經回應原住民 族運動的訴求。政府做過一些承諾、 也做過一些努力。我們有相當進步 的「原住民族基本法」，不過，這 部法律，並沒有獲得政府機關的普 遍重視。我們做得不夠快、不夠全 面、不夠完善。為此，我要代表政 府，向原住民族道歉。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">After the democratic transition, the country began to respond to the appeals of indigenous movements. The government made certain promises and efforts. Today, we have an Indigenous Peoples Basic Law that is quite advanced. However, government agencies have not given sufficient weight to this law. Our actions have not been fast enough, comprehensive enough or sound enough. For this, I apologize to the indigenous peoples on behalf of the government.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="12">
        <FORM>salaw mingalad na Taiwan dra, “marekamenimeni dalaman tu kakuwayanan.” kema. amawna, palru garem, na yēncumincu kemay kanantu kaarekedran tu dradrek lra, tu takakesian lra, tu wabaawan lra, tu kuwarenangan mutugiing lra. kandri tu kuwarenangan na marekudakuda i, adri pakadalrep kana Paireng. aw tu iyanau kana yēncumincu dra kemadru kemadru kema. aw dratu iyalrimus itariyama kana yēncumincu i, adri muasalr. idrini i, amau na sēhu na adri penauwa tu kinikarunan. tu pakakuwatisaw lra aw mialudrunan lra tu anger kana yēncumincu. muka kandrini i, patatalru ku kana sēhu semungal kana yēncumincu. 					</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">台灣號稱「多元文化」的社會。但 是，一直到今天，原住民族在健康、 教育、經濟生活、政治參與等許多 層面的指標，仍然跟非原住民存在 著落差。同時，對原住民族的刻板 印象、甚至是歧視，仍然沒有消失。 政府做得不夠多，讓原住民族承受 了一些其他族群沒有經歷過、感受 過的痛苦和挫折。為此，我要代表 政府，向原住民族道歉。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Taiwan is known as a culturally diverse society. But even today, indicators on health, education, economic livelihood, political participation and more still show gaps between indigenous and non- indigenous peoples. Meanwhile, stereotypes and even discrimination against indigenous peoples have not gone away. The government has not done enough, so indigenous peoples have suffered pain and frustration unknown to other ethnic peoples. For this, I apologize to the indigenous peoples on behalf of the government.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="13">
        <FORM>adri penauwa naniyam nirukedrangan. aw mutrungutrungulr a amiyan i, adri mi palamu marulradram. amau na kemay kaniyam kinaadriyan pakirungetr. aw niyam pakaulepaw mu palru garem. iuwa dra igelayan kemaya ku driya. ku iyasungal garem kana wari i, alra puwari lra dradru. amawna, amau a kiyaramiyan lra. adri ku kemiyanger dra, pakalranganay dra saya tilin, dra saya ngaiyan dra igelayan kema. aw mupualak muparayas tu kinudrekudran na aludrunan tu kinabulian tu anger kana yēncumincu. amawna, panaan ku dra kiyalriman. idri ku iyasungal garem kana wari i, amanaya aw, na murabak driya kandri na kanatal na tratrautrau. amau tu kiyaramiyan marekainabanaba kema ku. 				</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我們不夠努力，而且世世代代， 都未能及早發現我們不夠努 力，才會讓各位身上的苦，一 直持續到今天。真的很抱歉。今天的道歉，雖然遲到了非 常久，卻是一個開始。我不 期望四百年來原住民族承受 的苦難傷害，會只因為一篇 文稿、一句道歉而弭平。但 是，我由衷地期待，今天的 道歉，是這個國家內部所有 人邁向和解的開始。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Our efforts have fallen short, and succeeding generations have been blind to this inadequacy. Because of this, your hardship has continued to this day. For this we are truly sorry. Today's apology is long overdue, but it is a beginning. I do not expect any one speech or phrase of apology to wipe away four centuries of pain and suffering by the indigenous peoples. But I do hope with all my heart that today's apology will set this country and all its people on the path towards reconciliation.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="14">
        <FORM>ti pakalranganay dratu kinalradraman kana yēncumincu. pakalradram tu pauwayan dra iuwaadruk garem. kanantu piningaiyan kana Taiyal na mauwan i, na “penanaan”i “balay” kema. na “parekainabanabayan” i “sbalay” kema. na penanaan aw na parekainabanabayan i, marisan tu pauwayan. na panaan na marekainaba i, auka drata nirangeran muka trempaya kandru kana penanaan i, karuwa ta melaesi. 			</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">請容我用一個原住民族的智 慧，來說明今天的場合。在泰 雅族的語言裡，「真相」， 叫做 Balay。而「和解」叫做 Sbalay，也就是在 Balay 之前 加一個 S 的音。真相與和解， 其實是兩個相關的概念。換句 話說，真正的和解，只有透過 誠懇面對真相，才有可能達成。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Please allow me to shed light on this occasion with a piece of indigenous wisdom. In the Atayal language, truth is called &quot;Balay&quot;, and reconciliation is called &quot;Sbalay&quot;, so you simply add an &quot;S&quot; sound to &quot;Balay&quot;. Truth and reconciliation are in fact two related concepts. In other words, only by facing the truth sincerely can reconciliation be attained.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="15">
        <FORM>kanantu kakuwayanan kana yēncumincu. an kadru a trau a benuli dra druma dra trau i drekalr. an maranger marekainaba. na yawan i drekalr. tu daulraw na benuli aw na binulian miyadruwa. aw tu pararutungaw. adri payas semibalu. tu parengayaw driya dratu pinakalrangan nadru na miyadruwa. an mukalradram driya na penanaan i, karatakitakilr karatreketrekel lra nadru na maaidrangan. na bulretreng lra i tu paelipasaw peniya. idrini i, amau idru na parekainabanabayan tu pauwayan. 			</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">在原住民族的文化裡，當 有人得罪了部落裡的其 他人，有意想要和解的時 候，長老會把加害者和被 害者，都聚在一起。聚在 一起，不是直接道歉，而 是每個人都坦誠地，講出 自己的心路歷程。這個說 出真相的過程結束之後， 長老會要大家一起喝一 杯，讓過去的，真的過去。 這就是 Sbalay。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">In indigenous cultures, when a tribe member has offended another and intends to reconcile, an elder brings together the offender and the offended – not to produce a direct apology, but to allow each side to frankly share their inner journeys. When this truth-telling concludes, the elder calls for everyone to drink together, so that what is past is truly past. This is &quot;Sbalay&quot;.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="16">
        <FORM>kiyalriman ku kanta inuwadrukan garam. amau na sēhu aw na yēncumincu tu parekainabanabayan lra. na pinamelriyan a kinadriwan driya, na penanaan a kinadriwan driya i, adriya ku semama aw ti pulrataw benabati. an garemay i, aru rarengay dratu kiniyangeran na yēncumincu. adri ku malemu kiami kanemu dra payas kilraman garem. amawna, kadruwa ta kiyaangeran kemaya ku. aw na pinamelriyan a kinadriwan i, adri lra aasalr. likudran lra idri na kanatal i, adrikaadri muka trempaya kana parekainabanabayan. 			</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我期待今天這個場合，就是 一個政府和原住民族之間的 Sbalay。我把過去的錯誤，過 去的真相，竭盡所能、毫無保 留地講出來。等一下，原住民 族的朋友，也會說出想法。我 不敢要求各位現在就原諒，但 是，我懇請大家保持希望，過 去的錯誤絕不會重複，這個國 家，有朝一日，可以真正走向 和解。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I hope today's occasion can be a &quot;Sbalay&quot; between the government and the indigenous peoples. I have spoken of past mistakes and truths the best I can, with nothing held back. In a moment, our indigenous friends will speak. I do not dare ask you to forgive, here and now. But I sincerely ask you to sustain the hope that past wrongs will not be repeated, and that one day, this country can see true reconciliation.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="17">
        <FORM>garem i, amau na kemiyarami driya. alra parekainabanaba dra adrii, amelri tu tratrepa benasak kana yēncumincu aw kana Pinpucu. ulraya kana sēhu. malradram ku. an tu pakalranganay dra indan marengay dra igelayan kema i, adri driya penauwa. alra uwadaway nay idri na parekainabanabayan. aru nanau ta kana sēhu dranantu kinikarunan tu ipakababulay kana yēncumincu kakuwa ta. </FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">今天只是一個開始，會不會和解 的責任，不在原住民族及平埔族 群身上，而在政府身上。我知 道，光是口頭的道歉是不夠的， 政府從現在開始，為原住民族所 做的一切，將是這個國家是否真 正能夠和解的關鍵。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Today is only a beginning. The duty for reconciliation lies not with the indigenous peoples and the Pingpu ethnic group, but with the government. I know that words of apology alone are not enough. What we actually do for the indigenous peoples will decide whether reconciliation succeeds or stumbles.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="18">
        <FORM>kaadru ku kadrini patrirebeng marengay. na Congtonghu i, aru pararagan dra “yēncumincu drise cengi aw na cuwansing cengi uēiyēnhuy”. pakakalrang ku kananku itaudrung kana kanatal. aw kuwaredikes ku kana demaulr paradruk dra trau. wakasakasa kana kasamaumauwan tu pinutrepayan muka trempaya kana nilrangan na penatedrelr. aw pararisan ta kinaretigiran madrayadrayar dra kuwadakudayan paragan pakamakeser kananta kanatal. 					</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我要在此正式宣布，總統府將 設置「原住民族歷史正義與轉 型正義委員會」。我會以國家 元首的身分，親自擔任召集 人，與各族代表共同追求歷史 正義，也會對等地協商這個國 家往後的政策方向。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Therefore, I am here to announce that we are setting up an Indigenous Historical Justice and Transitional Justice Commission under the Presidential Office. As the head of state, I will serve as convener and work hand in hand with tribal representatives to pursue historical justice. We will also discuss, on the basis of equality, the future policy direction of this country.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="19">
        <FORM>pasaseket ku marengay. na uēiyēnhuy kadri Congtonghu. tu pinakapadrangalan menau i, amau na kanatal aw na yēncumincu i mararisan tu kinaretigiran. na mudaway na cice i, kemay kana kasamaumauwan pinutrepa. aw murabak na Pinpucu. na maunan lra aw na drekalr lra i, tu pakakalrangan kemay kanantu pinarekalradraman. idri na kinuretan i, amau tu wakasayan kemuret kana yēncumincu. karuwa pupatraran dratu kiniyangeran kana yēncumincu. 					</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我要強調，總統府的委員會， 最高度重視的，是國家和原住 民族的對等關係。各族代表的 產生，包括平埔族群，都會以 民族和部落的共識為基礎。這 個機制，將會是一個原住民族 集體決策的機制，可以把族人 的心聲真正傳達出來。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I want to stress that this commission places the greatest importance on equality between the country and the indigenous peoples. The election of tribal representatives, including for the Pingpu ethnic group, will take as basis the consensus of peoples and tribes. This commission will serve as a mechanism for collective decision-making by indigenous peoples, and will ensure that the voices of tribe members find true expression.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="20">
        <FORM>ulraya driya a druma, aru paaisel ku kana sincengyēn kemureta dra wari paradruk kana “yēncumincu cipenhua tuytonghuēiy” dratu padrayadrayaran. kemay kantu pinadrayadrayaran aw marepadunudunun dratu kinuretan kanadru na uēiyēn. na sēfu lra i tu pakuwarenangan i sabak kana sincengyēn dratu parepauwauwayan semeket kantu kinuretan. nadrini driya na kiyakarunan i, uwarabak na aaya dratu kinalradraman na nilrangan, na sasulrud kana Inanuwayan na taytaya na kemirungetr, na parisarisan palenak dra piyamanayan, na truwalrtrulr dra palaladamanan malradram dra kakuwayanan, na pakainabayan dra dradrek. na pakababulayan kantu kuwaredikesan kana kaadru i sinkinki na mawan tu puwarabakan peniya. 				</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">另外，我也會要求行政院定 期召開「原住民族基本法推 動會」。委員會中所形成的 政策共識，未來的政府，會 在院的層級，來協調及處理 相關事務。這些事務包括歷 史記憶的追尋、原住民族自 治的推動、經濟的公平發展、 教育與文化的傳承、健康的 保障，以及都市族人權益的 維護等等。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">In addition, I will request that our Executive Yuan convene regularly the Indigenous Peoples Basic Law Promotion Committee, and use the Yuan's authority to coordinate and handle matters related to any consensus reached by the above-mentioned commission. These matters include the following: to retrieve historical memories, to promote indigenous self-government, to seek fair economic development, to ensure continuation of culture and education, to safeguard indigenous health, and to protect the rights of urban indigenous peoples, etc.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="21">
        <FORM>na gareman na kuret aw tu kakuwayanan tu lregiyan kana yēncumincu i, ulraya tu kinasaseredran dar. aw aru pararagan mi dratu kiyarepauwayan dra “yēncumincu huwali huu congsin”. pakalranganay kandri tu dinaway na kuwarenangan. maruwaya adri masaseredr dratu kakuwayanan kana yēncumincu aw na gareman na kuret kana kanatal. 			</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">對於現代法律與原住民族傳 統文化，有些格格不入的地 方，我們要建立具有文化敏 感度的「原住民族法律服務中 心」，透過制度化的設計，來 緩和原住民族傳統慣習和現 行國家法律規範之間，日益頻 繁的衝突。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Where modern laws and indigenous traditional cultures are at odds, we will set up an Indigenous Legal Service Center with a high degree of cultural sensitivity, to reduce through institutional design the growing clashes between indigenous customs and modern laws.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="22">
        <FORM>aru pakakarun mi kana murabak driya kandri na lremak. payasa kuredikes melieli parepauwauwa. na yēncumincu kemay kantu kakuwayanan. kadru murabak kantu niyabuyulran. amelri a matrimatrima; amelri a sasamaan benaaw. tu alrupaw na garamgaman aw muka lra kandru mudrimutr muimeng. madrayadrayara ta dra kuwadakudayan pakabulay. 				</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我會要求相關部門，立刻著 手整理，原住民族因為傳統 習俗，在傳統領域內，基於 非交易的需要，狩獵非保育類 動物，而遭受起訴與判刑的案 例。針對這些案例，我們來研 議解決的方案。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I will ask the relevant agencies to immediately pull together cases in which indigenous community members have been indicted or sentenced for hunting, where the hunting was done in accordance with traditional customs, on traditional lands, and for non-transactional needs, and where the animals hunted were not protected by conservation laws. For such cases we will deliberate solutions.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="23">
        <FORM>aru pakakarun ku kana murabak driya kandri na lremak. kemay dratu inapetran na hehuyliyaw kadri Butrulr. kemudakuda tu pinakalrangan kikarun i, pupatrarana mu dra tilin dra penanaan. an adri driya mukalradram dra aapetran isuwa i, maruwaya ta semabung kana trau i Butrulr. 		</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我也會要求相關部門，針對核 廢料儲存在蘭嶼的相關決策經 過，提出真相調查報告。在核 廢料尚未最終處置之前，給予 雅美族人適當的補償。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I will also direct relevant agencies to present an investigative report on the decision-making process of nuclear waste storage on Orchid Island. Before finding a permanent solution for the nuclear waste, we will provide the Yami tribe appropriate compensation.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="24">
        <FORM>aw, kemay kanta iyaseer kana Pinpucu dratu ipakumauwan dratu ikapinpucu. pakanguwayan kana 9 bulan 30 wari i, aru padrayadrayar mi kandru na kinuretan. aw maruwaya pasekat mukalradram tu kuwaredikesan tu kinaretigiran kana Pinpucu. 		</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">同時，在尊重平埔族群的自我 認同、承認身分的原則下，我 們將會在九月三十日之前，檢 討相關法規，讓平埔族身分得 到應有的權利和地位。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">At the same time, under the principle of respecting the Pingpu ethnic group's self- identity, and recognizing their identity, we will examine relevant laws before September 30 of this year, so that Pingpu ethnic group identity will receive the rights and status it deserves.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="25">
        <FORM>garem kana ami kana 11 bulan 1 wari i, aru patriyarebang mi pakalradram dratu babuyubuyulr na dare kana yēncumincu. na kinuretan na konghuwalen i, semasulrud mi pakakawang garem. likudran i, tu kiniyaangeran kana yēncumincu na Yencumincu cece na kuret i, patatawar mudalan. paduwakeduk mi garem. nantu kinapadrangalan menau kana yēncumincu na “yēncumincu cecehua”, “yēncumincu tuti aw hayiv hua” , “yēncumincu yiēn huacanhua” nadrini i, aru tatuludran kana lihuayiēn parepauwauwa. </FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">今年的十一月一日，我們會開 始劃設、公告原住民族傳統領 域土地。部落公法人的制度， 我們已經推動上路，未來，原 住民族自治的理想，將會一步 一步落實。我們會加快腳步， 將原住民族最重視的「原住民 族自治法」、「原住民族土地及 海域法」、「原住民族語言發展 法」等法案，送請立法院審議。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">On November 1 of this year, we will begin to delineate and announce indigenous traditional territories and lands. The system of tribal public corporation is already in place. In the future, the ideals of indigenous self-government will be realized step by step. We will step up the pace and submit for legislative deliberation three laws of great importance to indigenous peoples: the Indigenous Peoples Self-Government Law, the Indigenous Peoples Land and Sea Areas Law, and the Indigenous Languages Development Law.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="26">
        <FORM>garem kana paelipas kana karealri na wari i, aru pararadruk mi kana yēncumincu kandri kana padrayadrayaran. kaulralraya tu pakalralradraman kana sēhu. likudran kana aamiami kana 8 bulan 1 wari. na sincengyēn i, auka pakalradrama kana trau driya kana kanatal dra kemudakuda lra tu kinikarunan. na pasasekadran na penatedrelr tu nilrangan kana yēncumincu. pararagan dratu danapan kana cece kana yēncumincu. amau idru na tuluwa tu tratrepayan kana sēhu . 				</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">今天下午，我們就要召開全 國原住民族行政會議。在會 議中，政府會有更多政策的說 明。以後每一年的八月一日， 行政院都會向全國人民報告原 住民族歷史正義及轉型正義的 執行進度。落實原住民族基本 法，達成原住民族的歷史正 義，並建立原住民族的自治基 礎，就是政府原住民族政策上 的三大目標。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Later this afternoon, we will convene a national indigenous peoples administrative meeting. In that meeting, the government will elaborate on the policies. On every August 1 to come, the Executive Yuan will report to the indigenous peoples our progress on restoring historical justice and transitional justice. To implement the Indigenous Peoples Basic Law, to serve indigenous historical justice, and to lay the foundation for indigenous self- government – these are the three major goals for the government's policy towards indigenous peoples.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="27">
        <FORM>dadaulr ku kana kadru driya kadrini garem. na kadru i nguwayan kana tilibi aw kana wanglu na yēncumincu peniya. mukasaya ta mutuwasay. demaulr ku kanemu i dra, druwaya mu mukasaya temaranau kana sēhu. turuwi mi. paladamu mi. mulaesia tu itatubang kanemu kana sēhu. panaana emasalr dratu pinatrepelran a kinadriwan driya kana sēhu. 				</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我要邀請在場的、在電視及 網路轉播前的全體原住民族 朋友們，一起來當見證人。 我邀請大家來監督，而不是 來背書。請族人朋友們用力 鞭策、指教，讓政府實現承 諾，真正改進過往的錯誤。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">To all of our indigenous friends here and watching on TV and online: I invite you to stand witness. I invite you not to endorse, but to oversee. Please keep pressure on the government and right its course where necessary, so that it will realize its commitments and right historical wrongs.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="28">
        <FORM>sasungl ku kanemu kana yēncumincu peniya. amau muymu na parubalruk(pasenkin) kana trau driya na kadru kadri kana kanatal, na dineelran na dare aw na belretrenganan na trungutrungulran i, salaw mitrima. adri ta karuwa padrulun dratu padrangalan. idri tu padrangalan i, a puwaluangan. 				</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我感謝所有的原住民族朋友， 是你們提醒了這個國家的所有 人，腳踏的土地，以及古老的 傳統，有著無可取代的價值。 這些價值，應該給予它尊嚴。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I want to thank all of our indigenous friends. You remind everyone in this country that there is irreplaceable value in the land we tread on and the traditions we inherit. This value deserves dignity.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="29">
        <FORM>likudran i, pakakalrang mi kana kinuretan semulrud. na marakiyaludusan na mawan, na mutrungutrungulr na mawan, aw na kaadru driya kandri kana dare i Taiwan na mawan i, adri lra uwalremes tu piningaiyan; adri lra kaabalu dratu kinabaawan; adri lra baburaw dratu kakuwayanan; adri lra drelalengan kantu kinadruwan driya kantu dare. 			</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">未來，我們會透過政策的推 動，讓下一代的族人、讓世世 代代的族人，以及台灣這塊土 地上所有族群，都不會再失 語，不會再失去記憶，更不會 再與自己的文化傳統疏離，不 會繼續在自己的土地上流浪。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">In the future, we will push for policies to ensure that succeeding generations of indigenous tribes and all ethnic peoples in Taiwan never lose their languages and memories, that they are never separated from their cultural traditions, and that never again are they lost in a land of their own.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="30">
        <FORM>kiyaami ku kana kadruwadruwanan na inukasayan. mukasaya ta merukedrang. malradrama ta drata nilrangan; malradrama ta drata dare. aw malradrama ta kantu kakuwayanan kana adri marisarisan na mauwan. mukaya ta kanta parekainabanabayan. trempaya ta kanta wakasayan mubaaw aw ta wakasayan pakabulay semangal aw trempaya ta kana pinakabekalan i Taiwan. 			</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我請求整個社會一起努 力，認識我們的歷史，認 識我們的土地，也認識我 們不同族群的文化。走向 和解，走向共存和共榮， 走向台灣新的未來。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I call upon our entire society to come together and get to know our history, get to know our land, and get to know the cultures of our many ethnic peoples. Let us work towards reconciliation, a shared existence and shared prosperity, and a new future for Taiwan.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="31">
        <FORM>kiyaami ku kana trau driya na kaadru kandri kana kanatal. pakalranganay garem kana wari. ta ukasayay pakirungetr demaway dra tratrepa kana penatedrelr na kanatal. amau a panaan dra tu bulayan dalaman aw a pinarisarisan tu kinaretigiran a kanatal.		</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我請求所有國人，藉著今 天的機會，一起努力來打 造一個正義的國家，一個 真正多元而平等的國家。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I call upon all citizens to seize the opportunities offered by this day – to join together, work hard, and build a country of justice, a country of true diversity and equality.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="32">
        <FORM>semangalan mapiyapiya.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">謝謝大家。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Thank you all</TRANSL>
    </S>
</TEXT>
