<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_Al-Farouq_Aminu" xml:lang="szy" source="Sakizaya Wikipedia, article: Al-Farouq_Aminu" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="Al-Farouq_Aminu. (2025, May 05). In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]. https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al-Farouq_Aminu" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_szy_Al-Farouq_Aminu, title = Al-Farouq_Aminu, year = 2025, month = May, day = 5, note = {In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]}, url = {https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al-Farouq_Aminu} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== Al-Farouq Aminu == siwkay niza Al-Farouq Aminu (9 a bulad 21 a demiad, 1991 a mihcan nalecuhan), tatama, lumeniay a tademaw. miunduay, u kanas-mali a mimaliay nu Amilika NBA. namakay Nayciliya a kanatal, micumud tu ku Amilika kanatal-mueneng. u sulit nu Hulam atu Amilika 艾爾-法魯克·阿米努(英語:Al-Farouq Aminu,1990年9月21日－),為美國NBA .他在2010年的NBA . Al-Farouq Ajiede Aminu (born September 21, 1990) is a Nigerian-American professional basketball player for the Portland Trail Blazers of the National Basketball Association (NBA). He plays internationally with the Nigeria national basketball team. Aminu was selected by the Los Angeles Clippers in the 2010 NBA draft with the eighth overall pick. kakuniza kalunasulitan-sulu</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== Al-Farooq Amino == siwkay niza Al-Farooq Amino (9 a bolad 21 a demiad, 1991 a mihcan nalecohan), tatama, lomeniay a tademaw. miondoay, o kanas-mali a mimaliay no Amilika NBA. namakay Nayciliya a kanatal, micomod to ko Amilika kanatal-moeneng. o solit no Holam ato Amilika 艾爾-法魯克·阿米努(英語:Al-Farooq Amino,1990年9月21日－),為美國NBA .他在2010年的NBA . Al-Farooq Ajiede Amino (born September 21, 1990) is a Nigerian-American professional basketball player for the Portland Trail Blazers of the National Basketball Association (NBA). He plays internationally with the Nigeria national basketball team. Amino was selected by the Los Angeles Clippers in the 2010 NBA draft with the eighth overall pick. kakoniza kalonasolitan-solo</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>