<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_Alex_Bradley" xml:lang="pwn" source="Paiwan Wikipedia, article: Alex_Bradley" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="Alex_Bradley. (2024, December 07). In Wikipedia [Paiwan]. https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alex_Bradley" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_pwn_Alex_Bradley, title = Alex_Bradley, year = 2024, month = December, day = 7, note = {In Wikipedia [Paiwan]}, url = {https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alex_Bradley} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== Alex Bradley == u siwkay niza Alex Bradley,tatama, nalecuhan 1959 a mihcan 10 a bulad 30 a demiad, miunduay, mimali i Amilika NBA. u sulit nu Hulam atu Amilika Alex Bradley III is a retired American professional basketball player. Born in Bradenton, Florida, Bradley played high school basketball for Long Branch High School in Long Branch, New Jersey. Bradley played collegiately for the Villanova Wildcats from 1977 to 1981. Bradley made an impact at Villanova immediately, setting the single-game freshman scoring record in 1978, a record that stood until it was eclipsed by Scottie Reynolds in 2007. Bradley was the first three-year captain at Villanova since 1952. Bradley was selected to the 1981 Big East All-Tournament Team. He led the Wildcats to three NCAA Tournament appearances. Bradley played in the NBA for the New York Knicks in 1981-82. kakuniza kalunasulitan-sulu</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== Alex Bradley == o siwkay niza Alex Bradley,tatama, nalecohan 1959 a mihcan 10 a bolad 30 a demiad, miondoay, mimali i Amilika NBA. o solit no Holam ato Amilika Alex Bradley III is a retired American professional basketball player. Born in Bradenton, Florida, Bradley played high school basketball for Long Branch High School in Long Branch, New Jersey. Bradley played collegiately for the Villanova Wildcats from 1977 to 1981. Bradley made an impact at Villanova immediately, setting the single-game freshman scoring record in 1978, a record that stood ontil it was eclipsed by Scottie Reynolds in 2007. Bradley was the first three-year captain at Villanova since 1952. Bradley was selected to the 1981 Big East All-Toornament Team. He led the Wildcats to three NCAA Toornament appearances. Bradley played in the NBA for the New York Knicks in 1981-82. kakoniza kalonasolitan-solo</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>