<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_Allan_Bristow" xml:lang="pwn" source="Paiwan Wikipedia, article: Allan_Bristow" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="Allan_Bristow. (2024, December 07). In Wikipedia [Paiwan]. https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allan_Bristow" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_pwn_Allan_Bristow, title = Allan_Bristow, year = 2024, month = December, day = 7, note = {In Wikipedia [Paiwan]}, url = {https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allan_Bristow} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Allan Bristow nilacul u siwkay niza u etul niza sa, u tatama ciniza, nalecuhan ciniza i 1951 a mihcaan, 8 a bulad, 23 a demiad. u miunduay a kawaw niza, namimali i Amilika NBA. i 1973 a mihcaan, mapili' ciniza nu Feichen 79 tademaw. kakuniza kalunasulitan-sulu u sulit nu Hulam atu Amilika Allan Mercer Bristow, Jr. is a retired American professional basketball player, coach, and executive. Bristow played college basketball at Virginia Tech, and was selected by the Philadelphia 76ers in the second round of the 1973 NBA draft. A 6 ft 7 in, 210 lb (95 kg) forward, he had a 10-year career in both the NBA and the ABA, playing for the Sixers, the San Antonio Spurs , the Utah Jazz, and finishing his playing career with the Dallas Mavericks. His nickname was "Disco".</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Allan Bristow nilacol o siwkay niza o etol niza sa, o tatama ciniza, nalecohan ciniza i 1951 a mihcaan, 8 a bolad, 23 a demiad. o miondoay a kawaw niza, namimali i Amilika NBA. i 1973 a mihcaan, mapili' ciniza no Feichen 79 tademaw. kakoniza kalonasolitan-solo o solit no Holam ato Amilika Allan Mercer Bristow, Jr. is a retired American professional basketball player, coach, and execotive. Bristow played college basketball at Virginia Tech, and was selected by the Philadelphia 76ers in the second roond of the 1973 NBA draft. A 6 ft 7 in, 210 lb (95 kg) forward, he had a 10-year career in both the NBA and the ABA, playing for the Sixers, the San Antonio Spors , the Utah Jazz, and finishing his playing career with the Dallas Mavericks. His nickname was "Disco".</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>