<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_babaledaw" xml:lang="pwn" source="Paiwan Wikipedia, article: babaledaw" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="babaledaw. (2024, December 07). In Wikipedia [Paiwan]. https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/babaledaw" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_pwn_babaledaw, title = babaledaw, year = 2024, month = December, day = 7, note = {In Wikipedia [Paiwan]}, url = {https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/babaledaw} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== babaledaw == 擬稻蝗/ sa lebulebud ku babaledaw i umaumahan. siwkay nu babaledaw u kulit nu babaledaw a kidu sa, u landaway atu makulahay . sapilimet i liwliw , u midiputay a kulit 保護色. mukan tu nipaluma' ku babaledaw, sisa mabidang ku malukay tu babaledaw. itawya, tuduhen ikiken nu malukay ku babaledaw, bangsis a'su tu. hali mukan tu niyazu'ay a tademaw. mibabaledaw 抓蝗蟲/ mibabaledaw kaku i umaumahan nacila. sibabaledawan 有蝗蟲的地方/ sibabaledaw ku umah ni Kacaw. u sulit nu Amilika Locusts are certain species of short-horned grasshoppers in the family Acrididae that have a swarming phase. These insects are usually solitary, but under certain circumstances, become more abundant and change their behaviour and habits, becoming gregarious. No taxonomic distinction is made between locust and grasshopper species; the basis for the definition is whether a species forms swarms under intermittently suitable conditions.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== babaledaw == 擬稻蝗/ sa lebolebod ko babaledaw i omaomahan. siwkay no babaledaw o kolit no babaledaw a kido sa, o landaway ato makolahay . sapilimet i liwliw , o midipotay a kolit 保護色. mokan to nipaloma' ko babaledaw, sisa mabidang ko malokay to babaledaw. itawya, todohen ikiken no malokay ko babaledaw, bangsis a'so to. hali mokan to niyazo'ay a tademaw. mibabaledaw 抓蝗蟲/ mibabaledaw kako i omaomahan nacila. sibabaledawan 有蝗蟲的地方/ sibabaledaw ko omah ni Kacaw. o solit no Amilika Locosts are certain species of short-horned grasshoppers in the family Acrididae that have a swarming phase. These insects are osoally solitary, bot onder certain circomstances, become more abondant and change their behavioor and habits, becoming gregarioos. No taxonomic distinction is made between locost and grasshopper species; the basis for the definition is whether a species forms swarms onder intermittently soitable conditions.</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>