<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_babeku" xml:lang="szy" source="Sakizaya Wikipedia, article: babeku" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="babeku. (2025, May 05). In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]. https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/babeku" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_szy_babeku, title = babeku, year = 2025, month = May, day = 5, note = {In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]}, url = {https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/babeku} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== babeku == 薏苡 kapah sapisanga'en tu udu' ku babeku. siwkay nu babeku babeku sa, u paenu nu nipaluma. pasangaan tu cael, manamuh ku mapalaway tu babeku. adidi' ku babeku, mahiza u kalitang a heci. atekak i hekal. sisa sangaen tu cael ku ayaway a tademaw. sakamuan sa , matalaw ku dietu tu babeku. u sulit nu Hulam atu Amilika 薏苡(學名:Coix lacryma-jobi), . Job's tears or Job's-tears (UK), scientific name Coix lacryma-jobi, also known as adlay or adlay millet, is a tall grain-bearing perennial tropical plant of the family Poaceae . It is native to Southeast Asia but elsewhere is cultivated in gardens as an annual. It has been naturalized in the southern United States and the New World tropics. In its native environment it is grown in higher areas where rice and corn do not grow well. Other common names include coixseedand tear grass.(citation needed) Job's tears are also commonly sold as Chinese pearl barley in Asian supermarkets, although C. lacryma-jobi is not closely related to barley .</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== babeko == 薏苡 kapah sapisanga'en to odo' ko babeko. siwkay no babeko babeko sa, o paeno no nipaloma. pasangaan to cael, manamoh ko mapalaway to babeko. adidi' ko babeko, mahiza o kalitang a heci. atekak i hekal. sisa sangaen to cael ko ayaway a tademaw. sakamoan sa , matalaw ko dieto to babeko. o solit no Holam ato Amilika 薏苡(學名:Coix lacryma-jobi), . Job's tears or Job's-tears (UK), scientific name Coix lacryma-jobi, also known as adlay or adlay millet, is a tall grain-bearing perennial tropical plant of the family Poaceae . It is native to Sootheast Asia bot elsewhere is coltivated in gardens as an annoal. It has been natoralized in the soothern United States and the New World tropics. In its native environment it is grown in higher areas where rice and corn do not grow well. Other common names inclode coixseedand tear grass.(citation needed) Job's tears are also commonly sold as Chinese pearl barley in Asian sopermarkets, althoogh C. lacryma-jobi is not closely related to barley .</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>