<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_bacu" xml:lang="szy" source="Sakizaya Wikipedia, article: bacu" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="bacu. (2025, May 05). In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]. https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/bacu" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_szy_bacu, title = bacu, year = 2025, month = May, day = 5, note = {In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]}, url = {https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/bacu} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== bacu == / izaw ku bacu nina kilang. siwkay nu bacu bacu sa, napatuzu' ku zuma a kawaw masaheciay saca canacanan a tuutuud. bacu sa kapah tu ku nu sulit kulit suni saca kawih nu lima, pasubana' tu tawan, u canan ku pakatineng nu tademaw. u bacu nu lacul hakay yadah ku patinengay. u ayzaay a subal nu binawlan, yadah ku bacu, caykalecad ku kuma, malecad ku bacu, sisa izaw ku bacu matahkal i kitakitakit. kya matineng ku caykalecad kamuay a tademaw, u canan ku pasubana'ay. u bacu a bana'-kakuziza , u tatengaay a bana' tuway. katuuday ku minanamay. mapabacu mapabacu 已做記號/ mipabacu tu ku luma' nu tumuk. mipabacu mipabacu 做記號/ mipabacu kaku tu laed nu umah. pabacuan pabacuan 被標示記號的地方/ pabacuan tu ku luma' ni Kacaw. sibacuay sibacuay 有記號的/ katinengan ku sibacuay ku badahung a luma'. u sulit nu Hulam atu Amilika A sign is an object, quality, event, or entity whose presence or occurrence indicates the probable presence or occurrence of something else. A natural sign bears a causal relation to its object—for instance, thunder is a sign of storm, or medical symptoms signify a disease. A conventional sign signifies by agreement, as a full stop signifies the end of a sentence; similarly the words and expressions of a language, as well as bodily gestures, can be regarded as signs, expressing particular meanings. The physical objects most commonly referred to as signs (notices, road signs, etc., collectively known as signage) generally inform or instruct using written text, symbols, pictures or a combination of these. The philosophical study of signs and symbols is called semiotics; this includes the study of semiosis, which is the way in which signs operate.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== baco == / izaw ko baco nina kilang. siwkay no baco baco sa, napatozo' ko zoma a kawaw masaheciay saca canacanan a tootood. baco sa kapah to ko no solit kolit soni saca kawih no lima, pasobana' to tawan, o canan ko pakatineng no tademaw. o baco no lacol hakay yadah ko patinengay. o ayzaay a sobal no binawlan, yadah ko baco, caykalecad ko koma, malecad ko baco, sisa izaw ko baco matahkal i kitakitakit. kya matineng ko caykalecad kamoay a tademaw, o canan ko pasobana'ay. o baco a bana'-kakoziza , o tatengaay a bana' toway. katooday ko minanamay. mapabaco mapabaco 已做記號/ mipabaco to ko loma' no tomok. mipabaco mipabaco 做記號/ mipabaco kako to laed no omah. pabacoan pabacoan 被標示記號的地方/ pabacoan to ko loma' ni Kacaw. sibacoay sibacoay 有記號的/ katinengan ko sibacoay ko badahong a loma'. o solit no Holam ato Amilika A sign is an object, qoality, event, or entity whose presence or occorrence indicates the probable presence or occorrence of something else. A natoral sign bears a caosal relation to its object—for instance, thonder is a sign of storm, or medical symptoms signify a disease. A conventional sign signifies by agreement, as a foll stop signifies the end of a sentence; similarly the words and expressions of a langoage, as well as bodily gestores, can be regarded as signs, expressing particolar meanings. The physical objects most commonly referred to as signs (notices, road signs, etc., collectively known as signage) generally inform or instroct osing written text, symbols, pictores or a combination of these. The philosophical stody of signs and symbols is called semiotics; this inclodes the stody of semiosis, which is the way in which signs operate.</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>