<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_badahung" xml:lang="szy" source="Sakizaya Wikipedia, article: badahung" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="badahung. (2025, May 05). In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]. https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/badahung" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_szy_badahung, title = badahung, year = 2025, month = May, day = 5, note = {In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]}, url = {https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/badahung} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== badahung == 屋頂 siwkay nu badahung u misaluma' sa, sibadahung tu. u papatuzu'an sa sapiading tu nanum. u kakuniza nu badahung sa, izaw ku masazayay izaw ku matikenihay. anu yadah ku udad, mangasiw tu matikenih. u Sakizaya a luma' sa, kya badahung sa, sangaen nu eli. badahung badahung 屋頂 / i badahung ku lesa' nu udad. badahungen badahungen 去蓋屋頂 / badahungen nu tau ku luma' aku! mabadahung mabadahung 已蓋屋頂 / mabadahung tu uli' ku luma' ni Payu. mibadahung mibadahung 蓋屋頂 / maaedaedap ku babalaki mibadahung tu luma'. pibadahungi pibadahungi 去蓋屋頂 / pibadahungi tu luma' isu tadu amulesa'! sibadahung sibadahung 有屋頂 / sibadahung amin kita u tademaw tu luma'. sibadahungay sibadahungay 有屋頂的 / sibadahungay tu sumanahay kiya patikedan. u sulit nu Hulam atu Amilika A roof is part of a building envelope. It is the covering on the uppermost part of a building or shelter which provides protection from animals and weather, notably rain or snow, but also heat, wind and sunlight. The word also denotes the framing or structure which supports that covering.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== badahong == 屋頂 siwkay no badahong o misaloma' sa, sibadahong to. o papatozo'an sa sapiading to nanom. o kakoniza no badahong sa, izaw ko masazayay izaw ko matikenihay. ano yadah ko odad, mangasiw to matikenih. o Sakizaya a loma' sa, kya badahong sa, sangaen no eli. badahong badahong 屋頂 / i badahong ko lesa' no odad. badahongen badahongen 去蓋屋頂 / badahongen no tao ko loma' ako! mabadahong mabadahong 已蓋屋頂 / mabadahong to oli' ko loma' ni Payo. mibadahong mibadahong 蓋屋頂 / maaedaedap ko babalaki mibadahong to loma'. pibadahongi pibadahongi 去蓋屋頂 / pibadahongi to loma' iso tado amolesa'! sibadahong sibadahong 有屋頂 / sibadahong amin kita o tademaw to loma'. sibadahongay sibadahongay 有屋頂的 / sibadahongay to somanahay kiya patikedan. o solit no Holam ato Amilika A roof is part of a boilding envelope. It is the covering on the oppermost part of a boilding or shelter which provides protection from animals and weather, notably rain or snow, bot also heat, wind and sonlight. The word also denotes the framing or stroctore which sopports that covering.</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>