<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_baduwac" xml:lang="szy" source="Sakizaya Wikipedia, article: baduwac" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="baduwac. (2025, May 05). In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]. https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/baduwac" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_szy_baduwac, title = baduwac, year = 2025, month = May, day = 5, note = {In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]}, url = {https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/baduwac} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== baduwac == 肋骨 / makudusay a tademaw sa maazih ku baduwac. siwkay nu baduwac baduwac sa u ukak nu tademaw, itiza i baluwang. midiput tu balucu' , bala', atu ilabuay nu kidu. sisiwa ku baduwac a ukak. u aadupan sa, izaw tu ku baduwac. malecad tu tademaw a kidu. tinaku a kamu sibaduwac 有肋骨 / sibaduwac ku misakabian tu dungec nu uway. u sulit nu Hulam atu Amilika 肋骨(拉丁語Costa,複數Costae,形容詞costalis) . In vertebrate anatomy, ribs are the long curved bones which form the rib cage. In most tetrapods, ribs surround the chest, enabling the lungs to expand and thus facilitate breathing by expanding the chest cavity. They serve to protect the lungs, heart, and other internal organs of the thorax. In some animals, especially snakes, ribs may provide support and protection for the entire body.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== badowac == 肋骨 / makodosay a tademaw sa maazih ko badowac. siwkay no badowac badowac sa o okak no tademaw, itiza i balowang. midipot to baloco' , bala', ato ilaboay no kido. sisiwa ko badowac a okak. o aadopan sa, izaw to ko badowac. malecad to tademaw a kido. tinako a kamo sibadowac 有肋骨 / sibadowac ko misakabian to dongec no oway. o solit no Holam ato Amilika 肋骨(拉丁語Costa,複數Costae,形容詞costalis) . In vertebrate anatomy, ribs are the long corved bones which form the rib cage. In most tetrapods, ribs sorroond the chest, enabling the longs to expand and thos facilitate breathing by expanding the chest cavity. They serve to protect the longs, heart, and other internal organs of the thorax. In some animals, especially snakes, ribs may provide sopport and protection for the entire body.</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>