<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_baeket" xml:lang="pwn" source="Paiwan Wikipedia, article: baeket" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="baeket. (2024, December 07). In Wikipedia [Paiwan]. https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/baeket" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_pwn_baeket, title = baeket, year = 2024, month = December, day = 7, note = {In Wikipedia [Paiwan]}, url = {https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/baeket} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== baeket == 重,沉重 / baeket kina mamukuen a ba'tu. u zuma ku baeket nu nizateng ni Kacaw. siwkay nu baeket u baeket sanay, namatengteng ku Kitakit. u canacanan a tuutuud, pabahekul i pabaw, amahetik i lala' tu. u baetu sa baeket, u kazizeng sa baeket tu. u kizmu a tademaw baeket, u makudusay a tademaw sa caay kabaeket. hacica ku baeket sa, si sakaluk, u daduy. tinaku a kamu baeketay 重的 / baeketay azihen kiya nimuku ni Ubad a mukin. baeketen 覺得太重 / baeketen kaku tu daduy nu maku. pabaeketen 加重 / pabaeketen ku nimuku nu tatama tu pawti nu tipus! sabaeket 很重 / sabaeket sa ku niculil ni Benel. sabaeketay 最重的 / sabaeketay ku ni katabaki nu uzip ni Pasang. u sulit nu Hulam atu Amilika In science and engineering, the weight of an object is usually taken to be the force on the object due to gravity.Weight is a vector whose magnitude , often denoted by an italic letter W, is the product of the mass m of the object and the magnitude of the local gravitational acceleration g; thus: W = mg. The unit of measurement for weight is that of force, which in the International System of Units is the newton. For example, an object with a mass of one kilogram has a weight of about 9.8 newtons on the surface of the Earth, and about one-sixth as much on the Moon. In this sense of weight, a body can be weightless only if it is distant from any other mass. Although weight and mass are scientifically distinct quantities, the terms are often confused with each other in everyday use (i.e. comparing and converting force weight in pounds to mass in kilograms and vice versa).</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== baeket == 重,沉重 / baeket kina mamokoen a ba'to. o zoma ko baeket no nizateng ni Kacaw. siwkay no baeket o baeket sanay, namatengteng ko Kitakit. o canacanan a tootood, pabahekol i pabaw, amahetik i lala' to. o baeto sa baeket, o kazizeng sa baeket to. o kizmo a tademaw baeket, o makodosay a tademaw sa caay kabaeket. hacica ko baeket sa, si sakalok, o dadoy. tinako a kamo baeketay 重的 / baeketay azihen kiya nimoko ni Ubad a mokin. baeketen 覺得太重 / baeketen kako to dadoy no mako. pabaeketen 加重 / pabaeketen ko nimoko no tatama to pawti no tipos! sabaeket 很重 / sabaeket sa ko nicolil ni Benel. sabaeketay 最重的 / sabaeketay ko ni katabaki no ozip ni Pasang. o solit no Holam ato Amilika In science and engineering, the weight of an object is osoally taken to be the force on the object doe to gravity.Weight is a vector whose magnitode , often denoted by an italic letter W, is the prodoct of the mass m of the object and the magnitode of the local gravitational acceleration g; thos: W = mg. The onit of measorement for weight is that of force, which in the International System of Units is the newton. For example, an object with a mass of one kilogram has a weight of aboot 9.8 newtons on the sorface of the Earth, and aboot one-sixth as moch on the Moon. In this sense of weight, a body can be weightless only if it is distant from any other mass. Althoogh weight and mass are scientifically distinct qoantities, the terms are often confosed with each other in everyday ose (i.e. comparing and converting force weight in poonds to mass in kilograms and vice versa).</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>