<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_bahel" xml:lang="pwn" source="Paiwan Wikipedia, article: bahel" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="bahel. (2024, December 07). In Wikipedia [Paiwan]. https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/bahel" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_pwn_bahel, title = bahel, year = 2024, month = December, day = 7, note = {In Wikipedia [Paiwan]}, url = {https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/bahel} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== bahel == bahel飛, mapabahel不小心飛走, mubahel在飛, mubahelay在飛的 siwkay nu bahel bahel sa, u mauzip saca tuutuud talaayaw i tapuku. tinaku ayam atu hikuki. anu ahemaw ku tuutuud, taneng tu mabahel i tapuku, mahiza ku besu. mapabahel mapabahel nu maku ku banul i nasawni. mubahel saliyuliyut sa ku adipapang mubahel i tapuku. mubahelay mubahelay i paduku sa u ayam hang niyam. u sulit nu Hulam atu Lipun Flight is the process by which an object moves, through an atmosphere or beyond it, as in the case of spaceflight. This can be achieved by generating aerodynamic lift, propulsive thrust, aerostatically using buoyancy, or by ballistic movement. Many things fly, from natural aviators such as birds, bats and insects to human inventions such as missiles, aircraft such as airplanes, helicopters and balloons, to rockets such as spacecraft. The engineering aspects of flight are the purview of aerospace engineering which is subdivided into aeronautics, the study of vehicles that travel through the air, and astronautics, the study of vehicles that travel through space, and in ballistics, the study of the flight of projectiles. namakayniay a nasulitan nasakamuan atu natinenganː</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== bahel == bahel飛, mapabahel不小心飛走, mobahel在飛, mobahelay在飛的 siwkay no bahel bahel sa, o maozip saca tootood talaayaw i tapoko. tinako ayam ato hikoki. ano ahemaw ko tootood, taneng to mabahel i tapoko, mahiza ko beso. mapabahel mapabahel no mako ko banol i nasawni. mobahel saliyoliyot sa ko adipapang mobahel i tapoko. mobahelay mobahelay i padoko sa o ayam hang niyam. o solit no Holam ato Lipon Flight is the process by which an object moves, throogh an atmosphere or beyond it, as in the case of spaceflight. This can be achieved by generating aerodynamic lift, propolsive throst, aerostatically osing booyancy, or by ballistic movement. Many things fly, from natoral aviators soch as birds, bats and insects to homan inventions soch as missiles, aircraft soch as airplanes, helicopters and balloons, to rockets soch as spacecraft. The engineering aspects of flight are the porview of aerospace engineering which is sobdivided into aeronaotics, the stody of vehicles that travel throogh the air, and astronaotics, the stody of vehicles that travel throogh space, and in ballistics, the stody of the flight of projectiles. namakayniay a nasolitan nasakamoan ato natinenganː</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>