<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_balakas" xml:lang="pwn" source="Paiwan Wikipedia, article: balakas" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="balakas. (2024, December 07). In Wikipedia [Paiwan]. https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/balakas" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_pwn_balakas, title = balakas, year = 2024, month = December, day = 7, note = {In Wikipedia [Paiwan]}, url = {https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/balakas} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== balakas == 說笑 人名 海神之子名 siwkay nu balakas u balakas sa, musakamu ku taw, patawa tu zuma a tademaw. u ngangan nu tademaw u ngangan nu wawama nu Bayu' Dietu-Kabit. tinaku a kamu balakasen 去逗他 / balakasen ni Abu ku wacu ni Benel! mababalakas 玩遊戲 / mababalakas kiza adiwawa i kakabi'an. mabalakas 幽默 / mabalakas kiza tademaw sa. mabalakasay 幽默的 / mabalakasay ci Pelac i niyazu' nu Maibul. mibalakas 在玩遊戲；在開玩笑 / mibalakas ku wacu tu nani'. pibalakas 去逗他；去玩遊戲 / amana pibalakas i zazan! pibalakasi 去玩遊戲 / pibalakasi kisu tu mali i putah! sapibalakas 玩具 / u culen ku sapibalakas nu wawa i putah. u sulit nu Hulam atu Amilika Humour or humor is the tendency of particular cognitive experiences to provoke laughter and provide amusement. The term derives from the humoral medicine of the ancient Greeks, which taught that the balance of fluids in the human body, known as humours , controlled human health and emotion.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== balakas == 說笑 人名 海神之子名 siwkay no balakas o balakas sa, mosakamo ko taw, patawa to zoma a tademaw. o ngangan no tademaw o ngangan no wawama no Bayo' Dieto-Kabit. tinako a kamo balakasen 去逗他 / balakasen ni Abo ko waco ni Benel! mababalakas 玩遊戲 / mababalakas kiza adiwawa i kakabi'an. mabalakas 幽默 / mabalakas kiza tademaw sa. mabalakasay 幽默的 / mabalakasay ci Pelac i niyazo' no Maibol. mibalakas 在玩遊戲；在開玩笑 / mibalakas ko waco to nani'. pibalakas 去逗他；去玩遊戲 / amana pibalakas i zazan! pibalakasi 去玩遊戲 / pibalakasi kiso to mali i potah! sapibalakas 玩具 / o colen ko sapibalakas no wawa i potah. o solit no Holam ato Amilika Homoor or homor is the tendency of particolar cognitive experiences to provoke laoghter and provide amosement. The term derives from the homoral medicine of the ancient Greeks, which taoght that the balance of floids in the homan body, known as homoors , controlled homan health and emotion.</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>