<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_balaut" xml:lang="szy" source="Sakizaya Wikipedia, article: balaut" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="balaut. (2025, May 05). In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]. https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/balaut" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_szy_balaut, title = balaut, year = 2025, month = May, day = 5, note = {In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]}, url = {https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/balaut} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== balaut == 蛙 yadah ku balaut i laku nu niyam. siwkay nu balat balaut sa, nu Pangcah a kamu sa, u &quot;takula&quot;. maazih tu i sawac i tukus i buyu. sademiad sa maazih, yadah i niyazu'. taneng yu mukan. asu' tu ku titi, mahiza tu tulakuk. u kabi' sa kapah tu ukak nu tademaw. anu mapetek ku ukak, mukan tuyniyan a kabi'. tinaku a kamu mibalaut 抓青蛙 mibalaut kita i laku. mibalautay 抓青蛙的 kau kisu Taymu ku mibalautay i laku. pibalauti 去抓青蛙 pibalauti tu sakalabi nu mita! sibalaut 有青蛙 sibalaut ku lakulakuan nu pongkang. sibalautay 有青蛙的 ni Taymu a pubu ku sibalautay. u sulit nu Hulam atu Amilika A frog is any member of a diverse and largely carnivorous group of short-bodied, tailless amphibians composing the orderAnura (Ancient Greek an-, without + oura, tail). The oldest fossil &quot;proto-frog&quot; appeared in the early Triassic of Madagascar, but molecular clock dating suggests their origins may extend further back to the Permian, 265 million years ago. Frogs are widely distributed, ranging from the tropics to subarctic regions, but the greatest concentration of species diversity is in tropical rainforests. There are approximately 4,800 recorded species, accounting for over 85% of extant amphibian species. They are also one of the five most diverse vertebrate orders.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== balaot == 蛙 yadah ko balaot i lako no niyam. siwkay no balat balaot sa, no Pangcah a kamo sa, o &quot;takola&quot;. maazih to i sawac i tokos i boyo. sademiad sa maazih, yadah i niyazo'. taneng yo mokan. aso' to ko titi, mahiza to tolakok. o kabi' sa kapah to okak no tademaw. ano mapetek ko okak, mokan toyniyan a kabi'. tinako a kamo mibalaot 抓青蛙 mibalaot kita i lako. mibalaotay 抓青蛙的 kao kiso Taymo ko mibalaotay i lako. pibalaoti 去抓青蛙 pibalaoti to sakalabi no mita! sibalaot 有青蛙 sibalaot ko lakolakoan no pongkang. sibalaotay 有青蛙的 ni Taymo a pobo ko sibalaotay. o solit no Holam ato Amilika A frog is any member of a diverse and largely carnivoroos groop of short-bodied, tailless amphibians composing the orderAnora (Ancient Greek an-, withoot + oora, tail). The oldest fossil &quot;proto-frog&quot; appeared in the early Triassic of Madagascar, bot molecolar clock dating soggests their origins may extend forther back to the Permian, 265 million years ago. Frogs are widely distriboted, ranging from the tropics to sobarctic regions, bot the greatest concentration of species diversity is in tropical rainforests. There are approximately 4,800 recorded species, accoonting for over 85% of extant amphibian species. They are also one of the five most diverse vertebrate orders.</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>