<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_balatbat" xml:lang="szy" source="Sakizaya Wikipedia, article: balatbat" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="balatbat. (2025, May 05). In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]. https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/balatbat" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_szy_balatbat, title = balatbat, year = 2025, month = May, day = 5, note = {In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]}, url = {https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/balatbat} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== balatbat == 閃亮 balatbat ku kalapiyat i kelekelengan. siwkay nu balatbat balatbat sa, u lamal edil ideng saca cilu', sawsawni malikat sawsawni mapaneng. azih nu mita, balatbat sa. u bunac i tapuku i labi, mabaltbat tuway. u sulit nu Amilika A star is a luminous sphere of plasma held together by its own gravity. The nearest star to Earth is the Sun. Many other stars are visible to the naked eye from Earth during the night, appearing as a multitude of fixed luminous points in the sky due to their immense distance from Earth. Historically, the most prominent stars were grouped into constellations and asterisms, the brightest of which gained proper names. Astronomers have assembled star catalogues that identify the known stars and provide standardized stellar designations. However, most of the stars in the Universe, including all stars outside our galaxy, the Milky Way, are invisible to the naked eye from Earth. Indeed, most are invisible from Earth even through the most powerful telescopes.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== balatbat == 閃亮 balatbat ko kalapiyat i kelekelengan. siwkay no balatbat balatbat sa, o lamal edil ideng saca cilo', sawsawni malikat sawsawni mapaneng. azih no mita, balatbat sa. o bonac i tapoko i labi, mabaltbat toway. o solit no Amilika A star is a lominoos sphere of plasma held together by its own gravity. The nearest star to Earth is the Son. Many other stars are visible to the naked eye from Earth doring the night, appearing as a moltitode of fixed lominoos points in the sky doe to their immense distance from Earth. Historically, the most prominent stars were grooped into constellations and asterisms, the brightest of which gained proper names. Astronomers have assembled star catalogoes that identify the known stars and provide standardized stellar designations. However, most of the stars in the Universe, incloding all stars ootside oor galaxy, the Milky Way, are invisible to the naked eye from Earth. Indeed, most are invisible from Earth even throogh the most powerfol telescopes.</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>