<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_bala'" xml:lang="pwn" source="Paiwan Wikipedia, article: bala'" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="bala'. (2024, December 07). In Wikipedia [Paiwan]. https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/bala'" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_pwn_bala', title = bala', year = 2024, month = December, day = 7, note = {In Wikipedia [Paiwan]}, url = {https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/bala'} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== bala' == 肺 u angangan nu hanhan ita ku bala'. siwkay nu balat u bala' sa, u kidu-sakaluk nu tademaw atu aadupan. anu mihanhan kita, macumuden ku bali tayza i bala', zikuzan sa, tayza tu labu nuizang. sisa mauzip kita. u kakalimaan a kidu-sakaluk nu tademaw. buting, kacumuli...izaw tu ku bala'. u pacucu'ay a aadupan sa , situsa a bala'. pabeli ku bali katukuh i kidu-mahmin. pabeli ku O2,mibalic ku CO2. kyu mauzip kita. tinaku a kamu u angangan nu hanhan ita ku bala'. u sulit nu Hulam atu Amilika The lungs are the primary organs of the respiratory system in humans and many other animals including a few fish and some snails. In mammals and most other vertebrates, two lungs are located near the backbone on either side of the heart. Their function in the respiratory system is to extract oxygen from the atmosphere and transfer it into the bloodstream, and to release carbon dioxide from the bloodstream into the atmosphere, in a process of gas exchange. Respiration is driven by different muscular systems in different species. Mammals, reptiles and birds use their different muscles to support and foster breathing. In early tetrapods, air was driven into the lungs by the pharyngeal muscles via buccal pumping, a mechanism still seen in amphibians. In humans, the main muscle of respiration that drives breathing is the diaphragm. The lungs also provide airflow that makes vocal sounds including human speech possible.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== bala' == 肺 o angangan no hanhan ita ko bala'. siwkay no balat o bala' sa, o kido-sakalok no tademaw ato aadopan. ano mihanhan kita, macomoden ko bali tayza i bala', zikozan sa, tayza to labo noizang. sisa maozip kita. o kakalimaan a kido-sakalok no tademaw. boting, kacomoli...izaw to ko bala'. o pacoco'ay a aadopan sa , sitosa a bala'. pabeli ko bali katokoh i kido-mahmin. pabeli ko O2,mibalic ko CO2. kyo maozip kita. tinako a kamo o angangan no hanhan ita ko bala'. o solit no Holam ato Amilika The longs are the primary organs of the respiratory system in homans and many other animals incloding a few fish and some snails. In mammals and most other vertebrates, two longs are located near the backbone on either side of the heart. Their fonction in the respiratory system is to extract oxygen from the atmosphere and transfer it into the bloodstream, and to release carbon dioxide from the bloodstream into the atmosphere, in a process of gas exchange. Respiration is driven by different moscolar systems in different species. Mammals, reptiles and birds ose their different moscles to sopport and foster breathing. In early tetrapods, air was driven into the longs by the pharyngeal moscles via boccal pomping, a mechanism still seen in amphibians. In homans, the main moscle of respiration that drives breathing is the diaphragm. The longs also provide airflow that makes vocal soonds incloding homan speech possible.</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>