<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_balulu" xml:lang="pwn" source="Paiwan Wikipedia, article: balulu" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="balulu. (2024, December 07). In Wikipedia [Paiwan]. https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/balulu" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_pwn_balulu, title = balulu, year = 2024, month = December, day = 7, note = {In Wikipedia [Paiwan]}, url = {https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/balulu} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== balulu == 背簍 u balulu ku saculu' tu tubah i sumamad. siwkay nu balulu balulu sa, nu sanga'an nu uway saca auk. mahiza ku kabgang, apaen i kulul nu tademaw. kapah macumut ku tuutuud saca nipaluma saca sakalut.... naayaw a demiad, tayza mimalukay, sibalulu tu. ayzasa, sikawaway micudaday si balulu tu. caay kalecaday a balulu, caay masangaay ku uway saca auk, u ayzaay a balulu kuyza. tinaku a kamu kasibalulu 要背簍 kasibalulu tu tayza i buyu'. sibaluluay 有背簍的 uyza sibaluluay ci Kacaw. u sulit nu Hulam atu Amilika 簍, "rucksack" "backpack"；越南語用詞是"ba lô"是法語詞"ballot" . A backpack — also called bookbag, kitbag, knapsack, rucksack, pack, or sackpack backsack — is, in its simplest form, a cloth sackcarried on one's back and secured with two straps that go over the shoulders, but there can be variations to this basic design. Lightweight types of backpacks are sometimes worn on only one shoulder strap.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== balolo == 背簍 o balolo ko sacolo' to tobah i somamad. siwkay no balolo balolo sa, no sanga'an no oway saca aok. mahiza ko kabgang, apaen i kolol no tademaw. kapah macomot ko tootood saca nipaloma saca sakalot.... naayaw a demiad, tayza mimalokay, sibalolo to. ayzasa, sikawaway micodaday si balolo to. caay kalecaday a balolo, caay masangaay ko oway saca aok, o ayzaay a balolo koyza. tinako a kamo kasibalolo 要背簍 kasibalolo to tayza i boyo'. sibaloloay 有背簍的 oyza sibaloloay ci Kacaw. o solit no Holam ato Amilika 簍, "rocksack" "backpack"；越南語用詞是"ba lô"是法語詞"ballot" . A backpack — also called bookbag, kitbag, knapsack, rocksack, pack, or sackpack backsack — is, in its simplest form, a cloth sackcarried on one's back and secored with two straps that go over the shoolders, bot there can be variations to this basic design. Lightweight types of backpacks are sometimes worn on only one shoolder strap.</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>