<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_Bobby_Chen" xml:lang="pwn" source="Paiwan Wikipedia, article: Bobby_Chen" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="Bobby_Chen. (2024, December 07). In Wikipedia [Paiwan]. https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bobby_Chen" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_pwn_Bobby_Chen, title = Bobby_Chen, year = 2024, month = December, day = 7, note = {In Wikipedia [Paiwan]}, url = {https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bobby_Chen} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== Bobby Chen == u siwkay niza 陳昇 (1958.10.29) nalecuhan i Taywan Changhua sien Sicou siang. u sapuyaay a kakuniza u kawaw niza u kawlah niza u uzip niza amicunus henay tu sulit 待補充 u sulit nu Hulam MTV . Bobby Chen is a Taiwanese singer and record producer. Chen was born in Xizhou, Changhua County in Taiwan. In primary school he was the only male student to take part in a singing competition, representing the school's choir group. He dreamt of becoming a drawing artist at young age, and involved in music industries later. After graduation, he moved to the North and started his career at Taipei. He then engaged in various work such as car repairing, designing artist, and advertising. After failing three times, he finally gained admittance into Zhong Yi recording company right after he changed his name. He involved in backstage preparation and became the assistant of Liew Jia Chang starting from year 1982. Several years later he attempted composing own music and finally made an entrance to Rock Records with the help of the manager of Li Feng Sound Recording , Xu Chong Xian . He published his first personal album named "The Crowded Playground" in 1988.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== Bobby Chen == o siwkay niza 陳昇 (1958.10.29) nalecohan i Taywan Changhoa sien Sicoo siang. o sapoyaay a kakoniza o kawaw niza o kawlah niza o ozip niza amiconos henay to solit 待補充 o solit no Holam MTV . Bobby Chen is a Taiwanese singer and record prodocer. Chen was born in Xizhoo, Changhoa Coonty in Taiwan. In primary school he was the only male stodent to take part in a singing competition, representing the school's choir groop. He dreamt of becoming a drawing artist at yoong age, and involved in mosic indostries later. After gradoation, he moved to the North and started his career at Taipei. He then engaged in varioos work soch as car repairing, designing artist, and advertising. After failing three times, he finally gained admittance into Zhong Yi recording company right after he changed his name. He involved in backstage preparation and became the assistant of Liew Jia Chang starting from year 1982. Several years later he attempted composing own mosic and finally made an entrance to Rock Records with the help of the manager of Li Feng Soond Recording , Xo Chong Xian . He poblished his first personal albom named "The Crowded Playgroond" in 1988.</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>