<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_caca'" xml:lang="szy" source="Sakizaya Wikipedia, article: caca'" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="caca'. (2025, May 05). In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]. https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/caca'" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_szy_caca', title = caca', year = 2025, month = May, day = 5, note = {In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]}, url = {https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/caca'} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== caca' == / matineng ci bayi misanga' tu caca'. siwkay nu caca' u caca' sa , nu sanga'en nu wuway saca penen. sapimabi' saca pahalhal. tinaku a kamu sicaca' 有蓆子 / sicaca' kita i putah malikalik. sicaca'ay 有蓆子的 / ci Dungi dada' ku sicaca'ay i niyazu'. u sulit nu Hulam Lipun atu Amilika 藤是省藤族(學名:Calameae) . 五節芒(Miscanthus floridulus) . A mat is a piece of fabric material that generally is placed on a floor or other flat surface. Mats serve a range of purposes including: serving to clean items passed over it, such as a doormat, which removes dirt from the soles of shoes protecting that which is above the mat, such as a wrestling or gymnastics mat, or an anti-vibration mat protecting that which is beneath the mat, such as a place mat or the matting used in archival framing and preservation of documents and paintings providing a regular or flat surface, such as a cushioned computer mousepad Calameae is a palm tree tribe in the subfamily Calamoideae. Many of its members are rattans. Miscanthus floridulus, Pacific Island silvergrass, is a species of perennial grass in the Poaceae family.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== caca' == / matineng ci bayi misanga' to caca'. siwkay no caca' o caca' sa , no sanga'en no woway saca penen. sapimabi' saca pahalhal. tinako a kamo sicaca' 有蓆子 / sicaca' kita i potah malikalik. sicaca'ay 有蓆子的 / ci Dongi dada' ko sicaca'ay i niyazo'. o solit no Holam Lipon ato Amilika 藤是省藤族(學名:Calameae) . 五節芒(Miscanthos floridolos) . A mat is a piece of fabric material that generally is placed on a floor or other flat sorface. Mats serve a range of porposes incloding: serving to clean items passed over it, soch as a doormat, which removes dirt from the soles of shoes protecting that which is above the mat, soch as a wrestling or gymnastics mat, or an anti-vibration mat protecting that which is beneath the mat, soch as a place mat or the matting osed in archival framing and preservation of docoments and paintings providing a regolar or flat sorface, soch as a coshioned compoter moosepad Calameae is a palm tree tribe in the sobfamily Calamoideae. Many of its members are rattans. Miscanthos floridolos, Pacific Island silvergrass, is a species of perennial grass in the Poaceae family.</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>