<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_cacay" xml:lang="szy" source="Sakizaya Wikipedia, article: cacay" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="cacay. (2025, May 05). In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]. https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/cacay" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_szy_cacay, title = cacay, year = 2025, month = May, day = 5, note = {In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]}, url = {https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/cacay} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== cacay == 1 一個 / cacay ku luma' i buyu' ni Panay. 一致 / ka lacacay ku nizateng nu mita. siwkay nu cacay teban i inayi' atu tusa. u asip nu Sakizaya. nu aayawan a asip sa ku &quot;tinacay&quot;. u babalakiay a asip kuyza. u nikayadah a sulit. tinaku a kamu cacay1 hacacacacay 逐一的 / hacacacacay sa mipalita tu pisakakawawan. hacacay 一個一個 / sima hacacay kami makaala tu kawlah. sacacay 獨自 / sacacay sa ciniza a mauzip. sakacacay 第一 / sakacacay a kawaw sa a hicaen nu mita? cacay2 lacacay 團結；一致 / ka lacacay ku nizateng nu mita. lacacayen 要團結起來 / lacacayen nu mita! malacacay 團結一致 / malacacay ku nizateng tu sakay kawaw nu niyazu'. malacacay ku niyazu'ay nu heni. masacacay 團結一致 / masacacay ku balucu' tawya icelang kita. palacacayen 放置在一起 / palacacayen ku nipipazeng! u sulit nu Hulam Lipun atu Amilika 1 是0與2 . 1 (one, also called unit, unity, and identity) is a number, numeral, and glyph. It represents a single entity, the unit of counting or measurement. For example, a line segment of unit length is a line segment of length 1. It is also the first of the infinite sequence of natural numbers, followed by 2. 1 は, ,1st,firstとなる.ラテン語では unus で,接頭辞 uni- はこれに由来する.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== cacay == 1 一個 / cacay ko loma' i boyo' ni Panay. 一致 / ka lacacay ko nizateng no mita. siwkay no cacay teban i inayi' ato tosa. o asip no Sakizaya. no aayawan a asip sa ko &quot;tinacay&quot;. o babalakiay a asip koyza. o nikayadah a solit. tinako a kamo cacay1 hacacacacay 逐一的 / hacacacacay sa mipalita to pisakakawawan. hacacay 一個一個 / sima hacacay kami makaala to kawlah. sacacay 獨自 / sacacay sa ciniza a maozip. sakacacay 第一 / sakacacay a kawaw sa a hicaen no mita? cacay2 lacacay 團結；一致 / ka lacacay ko nizateng no mita. lacacayen 要團結起來 / lacacayen no mita! malacacay 團結一致 / malacacay ko nizateng to sakay kawaw no niyazo'. malacacay ko niyazo'ay no heni. masacacay 團結一致 / masacacay ko baloco' tawya icelang kita. palacacayen 放置在一起 / palacacayen ko nipipazeng! o solit no Holam Lipon ato Amilika 1 是0與2 . 1 (one, also called onit, onity, and identity) is a nomber, nomeral, and glyph. It represents a single entity, the onit of coonting or measorement. For example, a line segment of onit length is a line segment of length 1. It is also the first of the infinite seqoence of natoral nombers, followed by 2. 1 は, ,1st,firstとなる.ラテン語では onos で,接頭辞 oni- はこれに由来する.</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>