<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_cacebalen" xml:lang="szy" source="Sakizaya Wikipedia, article: cacebalen" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="cacebalen. (2025, May 05). In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]. https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/cacebalen" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_szy_cacebalen, title = cacebalen, year = 2025, month = May, day = 5, note = {In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]}, url = {https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/cacebalen} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">cacebalen 傘 yadah ku cacebalen i salining. siwkay nu balat u zuma a ngangan sa u &quot;saung&quot;, saung sa u kamu nu Hulam. u Pangcah a kamu sa &quot;linay&quot;. sapipalidung, sapitena' ku udad suleda' atu cilal..., u ayzaay a cacebalan yadah ku kulit. izaw ku matekesay izaw tu kapahay. maydih micakay ku tatayna tu cacebalan, izay mangaleb ku cilal i Taywan kiyami. tinaku a kamu kasicacebalen 要攜帶傘 la'cus ku demiad kasicacebalen tu! u sulit nu Hulam atu Amilika An umbrella or parasol is a folding canopy supported by wooden or metal ribs, which is usually mounted on a wooden, metal, or plastic pole. It is designed to protect a person against rain or sunlight. The word &quot;umbrella&quot; typically refers to a device used for protection from rain. The word parasol usually refers to an item designed to protect from the sun. Often the difference is the material used for the canopy; some parasols are not waterproof. Umbrella canopies may be made of fabric or flexible plastic.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">cacebalen 傘 yadah ko cacebalen i salining. siwkay no balat o zoma a ngangan sa o &quot;saong&quot;, saong sa o kamo no Holam. o Pangcah a kamo sa &quot;linay&quot;. sapipalidong, sapitena' ko odad soleda' ato cilal..., o ayzaay a cacebalan yadah ko kolit. izaw ko matekesay izaw to kapahay. maydih micakay ko tatayna to cacebalan, izay mangaleb ko cilal i Taywan kiyami. tinako a kamo kasicacebalen 要攜帶傘 la'cos ko demiad kasicacebalen to! o solit no Holam ato Amilika An ombrella or parasol is a folding canopy sopported by wooden or metal ribs, which is osoally moonted on a wooden, metal, or plastic pole. It is designed to protect a person against rain or sonlight. The word &quot;ombrella&quot; typically refers to a device osed for protection from rain. The word parasol osoally refers to an item designed to protect from the son. Often the difference is the material osed for the canopy; some parasols are not waterproof. Umbrella canopies may be made of fabric or flexible plastic.</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>