<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_caheni" xml:lang="szy" source="Sakizaya Wikipedia, article: caheni" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="caheni. (2025, May 05). In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]. https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/caheni" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_szy_caheni, title = caheni, year = 2025, month = May, day = 5, note = {In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]}, url = {https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/caheni} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== caheni == 因外物影響而發癢 i pilangecan caheni sa ku tipus. siwkay nu caheni i banges nu mita, nay nu ihekalay a tuutuud saca cilekay macalenged sanay. izaw ku namaky banges , izaw ku namakay balucu'. maydih mikuskus kita. anu mangaleb mikuskus, maduka' tuway. anu macaheni ku kidu, pililuci, pasapayui, akamikuskus, alaw maduka', maizang. tinaku a kamu i pilangecan caheni sa ku tipus. u sulit nu Hulam atu Amilika Itch is a sensation that causes the desire or reflex to scratch. Itch has resisted many attempts to classify it as any one type of sensory experience. Modern science has shown that itch has many similarities to pain, and while both are unpleasant sensory experiences, their behavioral response patterns are different. Pain creates a withdrawal reflex, whereas itch leads to a scratch reflex.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== caheni == 因外物影響而發癢 i pilangecan caheni sa ko tipos. siwkay no caheni i banges no mita, nay no ihekalay a tootood saca cilekay macalenged sanay. izaw ko namaky banges , izaw ko namakay baloco'. maydih mikoskos kita. ano mangaleb mikoskos, madoka' toway. ano macaheni ko kido, pililoci, pasapayoi, akamikoskos, alaw madoka', maizang. tinako a kamo i pilangecan caheni sa ko tipos. o solit no Holam ato Amilika Itch is a sensation that caoses the desire or reflex to scratch. Itch has resisted many attempts to classify it as any one type of sensory experience. Modern science has shown that itch has many similarities to pain, and while both are onpleasant sensory experiences, their behavioral response patterns are different. Pain creates a withdrawal reflex, whereas itch leads to a scratch reflex.</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>