<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_cakay" xml:lang="szy" source="Sakizaya Wikipedia, article: cakay" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="cakay. (2025, May 05). In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]. https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/cakay" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_szy_cakay, title = cakay, year = 2025, month = May, day = 5, note = {In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]}, url = {https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/cakay} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== cakay == 買 siwkay nu cakay cakay sa, sikalisiw saca pida' mibalic tu canacanan(tuutuud), malecad ku tadamaan . tinaku a kamu cakayan 1.被買 cakayan tu nu tau kiya kazizeng. cakayen 1.去買 cakayen ku tayu! macakay 1.被買 macakay nu maku ku lami'. mapacakay 1.被賣 mapacakay kiya wawelwel nu maku. mapacakayan 1.被賣了 mapacakayan tu kiya kazizeng. micakay 1.去買 micakay henay kaku tu padingad. pacakay 1.賣；銷售 pacakay tu lami' kaku i iciba. pacakayan 1.賣店 pacakayan tu cudad ku luma' nu maku. pacakayay 1.銷售的 pacakayay ku kakawaw nu cabay aku. pacakayen 1.拿去銷售掉 pacakayen kina kalitang! picakayan 1.市場 timamuwang sa ku tademaw i tiza picakayan tu lami'. pipacakayan 1.賣場 yadah ku canacanan i pipacakayan. u sulit nu Amilika Purchasing refers to a business or organization attempting to acquire goods or services to accomplish its goals. Alhough there are several organizations that attempt to set standards in the purchasing process, processes can vary greatly between organizations. Typically the word &quot;purchasing&quot; is not used interchangeably with the word &quot;procurement&quot;, since procurement typically includes expediting, supplier quality, and transportation and logistics in addition to purchasing.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== cakay == 買 siwkay no cakay cakay sa, sikalisiw saca pida' mibalic to canacanan(tootood), malecad ko tadamaan . tinako a kamo cakayan 1.被買 cakayan to no tao kiya kazizeng. cakayen 1.去買 cakayen ko tayo! macakay 1.被買 macakay no mako ko lami'. mapacakay 1.被賣 mapacakay kiya wawelwel no mako. mapacakayan 1.被賣了 mapacakayan to kiya kazizeng. micakay 1.去買 micakay henay kako to padingad. pacakay 1.賣；銷售 pacakay to lami' kako i iciba. pacakayan 1.賣店 pacakayan to codad ko loma' no mako. pacakayay 1.銷售的 pacakayay ko kakawaw no cabay ako. pacakayen 1.拿去銷售掉 pacakayen kina kalitang! picakayan 1.市場 timamowang sa ko tademaw i tiza picakayan to lami'. pipacakayan 1.賣場 yadah ko canacanan i pipacakayan. o solit no Amilika Porchasing refers to a bosiness or organization attempting to acqoire goods or services to accomplish its goals. Alhoogh there are several organizations that attempt to set standards in the porchasing process, processes can vary greatly between organizations. Typically the word &quot;porchasing&quot; is not osed interchangeably with the word &quot;procorement&quot;, since procorement typically inclodes expediting, sopplier qoality, and transportation and logistics in addition to porchasing.</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>