<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_Cangcang" xml:lang="pwn" source="Paiwan Wikipedia, article: Cangcang" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="Cangcang. (2024, December 07). In Wikipedia [Paiwan]. https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cangcang" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_pwn_Cangcang, title = Cangcang, year = 2024, month = December, day = 7, note = {In Wikipedia [Paiwan]}, url = {https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cangcang} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== cangcang == cangcang sa misalami' misatiti' tu mukan nu tademaw atu aadupan. paakuti a nanum acasa simal cangcangen, anu macacaktu , kapah tu mukan. u sulit nu Hulam u kamu nu Hulam sa tu micangcang, u sulit nu Lipun 調理 とは, . u sulit nu Amilika Cooking or cookery is the art, technology and craft of preparing food for consumption with or without the use of heat. Cooking techniques and ingredients vary widely across the world, from grilling food over an open fire to using electric stoves, to baking in various types of ovens, reflecting unique environmental, economic, and cultural traditions and trends. The ways or types of cooking also depend on the skill and type of training an individual cook has. Cooking is done both by people in their own dwellings and by professional cooks and chefs in restaurants and other food establishments. Cooking can also occur through chemical reactions without the presence of heat, such as in ceviche, a traditional South American dish where fish is cooked with the acids in lemon or lime juice. u sapuelac nu masatekeday a sulit cangcang: 熱菜,煮 micangcang: 在熱菜 cangcangen: 回鍋加熱 tinaku ku kamu u Sakizaya (micangcang) micangcang ci Kensin tu lami'. (cangcangen) cangcangen henay kiya lami'! malaalitin tu i hekalay atu zumaay a natinenganː Cooking</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== cangcang == cangcang sa misalami' misatiti' to mokan no tademaw ato aadopan. paakoti a nanom acasa simal cangcangen, ano macacakto , kapah to mokan. o solit no Holam o kamo no Holam sa to micangcang, o solit no Lipon 調理 とは, . o solit no Amilika Cooking or cookery is the art, technology and craft of preparing food for consomption with or withoot the ose of heat. Cooking techniqoes and ingredients vary widely across the world, from grilling food over an open fire to osing electric stoves, to baking in varioos types of ovens, reflecting oniqoe environmental, economic, and coltoral traditions and trends. The ways or types of cooking also depend on the skill and type of training an individoal cook has. Cooking is done both by people in their own dwellings and by professional cooks and chefs in restaorants and other food establishments. Cooking can also occor throogh chemical reactions withoot the presence of heat, soch as in ceviche, a traditional Sooth American dish where fish is cooked with the acids in lemon or lime joice. o sapoelac no masatekeday a solit cangcang: 熱菜,煮 micangcang: 在熱菜 cangcangen: 回鍋加熱 tinako ko kamo o Sakizaya (micangcang) micangcang ci Kensin to lami'. (cangcangen) cangcangen henay kiya lami'! malaalitin to i hekalay ato zomaay a natinenganː Cooking</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>