<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_Kim_Soo-hyun" xml:lang="pwn" source="Paiwan Wikipedia, article: Kim_Soo-hyun" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="Kim_Soo-hyun. (2024, December 07). In Wikipedia [Paiwan]. https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kim_Soo-hyun" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_pwn_Kim_Soo-hyun, title = Kim_Soo-hyun, year = 2024, month = December, day = 7, note = {In Wikipedia [Paiwan]}, url = {https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kim_Soo-hyun} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">=== u siwkay niza === Ciinsiwsien, upalaway nu Korea kanatl. u ngangan niza sa, "siw" sa, u makedemecay a tademaw. "sien"sa, u sipunuay a tademaw. u ngangan niza sa , mahiza ku tatayna, sisa panganganen ciniza ku " man". mala upalaway a kawaw i 2007 a mihca. mipalaw tu tilibi atu iga. malakapah ciniza, sisa katuud ku manamuhay a tatayna. (amicunus henay tu sulit.待補充) u sapuyaay a kakuniza u kawaw niza u sulit nu Hulam Kim Soo-hyun (Hangul: 김수현; Hanja: 金秀賢; born February 16, 1988) is a South Korean actor best known for his roles in the television dramas Dream High(2011), Moon Embracing the Sun (2012), My Love from the Star (2013) and The Producers (2015), as well as the movies The Thieves (2012) and Secretly, Greatly(2013). Kim was Gallup Korea's Actor of the Year in 2014. He was first included in Forbes Korea Power Celebrity list in 2013 placing 4th, subsequently ranking 2nd in 2015 and 5th in 2016. The business magazine's Asia edition also listed him in its 30 under 30 in 2016. The success of his television dramas throughout Asia established him as a top Hallyu star. u kawlah niza (amicunus henay tu sulit.待補充) u uzip niza (amicunus henay tu sulit.待補充)</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">=== o siwkay niza === Ciinsiwsien, opalaway no Korea kanatl. o ngangan niza sa, "siw" sa, o makedemecay a tademaw. "sien"sa, o siponoay a tademaw. o ngangan niza sa , mahiza ko tatayna, sisa panganganen ciniza ko " man". mala opalaway a kawaw i 2007 a mihca. mipalaw to tilibi ato iga. malakapah ciniza, sisa katood ko manamohay a tatayna. (amiconos henay to solit.待補充) o sapoyaay a kakoniza o kawaw niza o solit no Holam Kim Soo-hyon (Hangol: 김수현; Hanja: 金秀賢; born Febroary 16, 1988) is a Sooth Korean actor best known for his roles in the television dramas Dream High(2011), Moon Embracing the Son (2012), My Love from the Star (2013) and The Prodocers (2015), as well as the movies The Thieves (2012) and Secretly, Greatly(2013). Kim was Gallop Korea's Actor of the Year in 2014. He was first incloded in Forbes Korea Power Celebrity list in 2013 placing 4th, sobseqoently ranking 2nd in 2015 and 5th in 2016. The bosiness magazine's Asia edition also listed him in its 30 onder 30 in 2016. The soccess of his television dramas throoghoot Asia established him as a top Hallyo star. o kawlah niza (amiconos henay to solit.待補充) o ozip niza (amiconos henay to solit.待補充)</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>