<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_Lin_Yi_Chen" xml:lang="szy" source="Sakizaya Wikipedia, article: Lin_Yi_Chen" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="Lin_Yi_Chen. (2025, May 05). In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]. https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lin_Yi_Chen" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_szy_Lin_Yi_Chen, title = Lin_Yi_Chen, year = 2025, month = May, day = 5, note = {In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]}, url = {https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lin_Yi_Chen} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ariel Lin Ariel Lin u siwkay niza Ariel Lin (1982.10.29) tatayna, nalecuhan i Taywan. 2008 a mihcan nay &quot;mibalakas micepcep 2&quot;maala saka43 Cincung kawlah palaway ngatu tatayna a kawlah, u sakacacay maala nu kanamuhan a palaway. 2011.9 mipalaw tilibi a ngatu&quot;caay kaku maidih tisuwan&quot;singangantu. u sapuyaay a kakuniza u kawaw niza u kawlah niza u nasulitan nu Hulam atu Amilika Ariel Lin is a Taiwanese actress and singer. She rose to fame for her role as Yuan Xiangqin in the Taiwanese drama It Started with a Kiss (2005) and the Chinese fantasy drama The Little Fairy (2006). Lin won Best Actress at the 43rd and 47th Golden Bell Awards for her roles in They Kiss Again (2007) and In Time with You (2011) respectively. (u kamu nu Hulam: 林依晨, .) namakayniay a nasulitan nasakamuan atu natinengan 林依晨</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ariel Lin Ariel Lin o siwkay niza Ariel Lin (1982.10.29) tatayna, nalecohan i Taywan. 2008 a mihcan nay &quot;mibalakas micepcep 2&quot;maala saka43 Cincong kawlah palaway ngato tatayna a kawlah, o sakacacay maala no kanamohan a palaway. 2011.9 mipalaw tilibi a ngato&quot;caay kako maidih tisowan&quot;singanganto. o sapoyaay a kakoniza o kawaw niza o kawlah niza o nasolitan no Holam ato Amilika Ariel Lin is a Taiwanese actress and singer. She rose to fame for her role as Yoan Xiangqin in the Taiwanese drama It Started with a Kiss (2005) and the Chinese fantasy drama The Little Fairy (2006). Lin won Best Actress at the 43rd and 47th Golden Bell Awards for her roles in They Kiss Again (2007) and In Time with Yoo (2011) respectively. (o kamo no Holam: 林依晨, .) namakayniay a nasolitan nasakamoan ato natinengan 林依晨</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>