<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_nipaluma-sumanahay_tana,_somanahay_tana" xml:lang="pwn" source="Paiwan Wikipedia, article: nipaluma-sumanahay_tana,_somanahay_tana" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="nipaluma-sumanahay_tana,_somanahay_tana. (2024, November 18). In Wikipedia [Paiwan]. https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/nipaluma-sumanahay_tana,_somanahay_tana" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_pwn_nipaluma-sumanahay_tana,_somanahay_tana, title = nipaluma-sumanahay_tana,_somanahay_tana, year = 2024, month = November, day = 18, note = {In Wikipedia [Paiwan]}, url = {https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/nipaluma-sumanahay_tana,_somanahay_tana} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM> sumanahay tana, somanahay tana ( : , , , , , , , , , ) kagak kakuniza subal: Eukaryota salaedan: Plantae panan: Magnoliophyta upiz: Magnoliopsida mata: (Sapindales) sapamat: (Rutaceae) mikitinay: (Zanthoxylum) hicahicaay: (Z. ailanthoides) u siwkay nu nipaluma u sanek nu nipaluma malaheci tu imelang pasubana i cacudadan a lacul u zuma a cidekay a kamu, saungay misapayu' a cidekay u sulit nu zuma a kamu Hulam atu Amilika . . 30 80 12 . . . , , . 0.5 0.6 . Zanthoxylum ailanthoides, also called ailanthus like prickly ash, (Chinese: ; pinyin: chun ye hua jiao, lit. &quot;Ailanthus leaved pepper&quot;, Chinese: ; pinyin: yue jiao; Wade Giles: yüeh chiao, lit. &quot;Yue pepper&quot;, shi zhu yu, lit. &quot;edible sh n zh yú&quot;; Japanese: , karasu zansh , karasu no sansh , lit. &quot;crow prickly ash&quot;) is an Asiatic plant of the prickly ash genus Zanthoxylum, natively occurring in forest covered parts of southeastern China, Taiwan, Southeast Asia, and Japan from Honshu southward. The piquant fruit serves as a local &quot;substitute for the ordinary red pepper&quot; in China. In Taiwan, the young leaves are used in cuisines. Though some refer to the species as &quot;Japanese prickly ash&quot;, that name is confusing since it is sometimes applied to the sansh which is Z. piperitum. Z. ailanthoides is not normally exploited for human consumption in Japan, unless you count the prehistoric people from the J mon period. It is foraged in the wild by the Japanese macaque. A regional nickname is tara, and in fact, its young shoots are often mistaken for the true tara (Aralia elata) by gatherers of wild plants. The Latin name ailanthoides of the species comes from its leaves resembling those of the Ailanthus. Like other genera of plants in the rue family, it serves as the host food plant for the larvae of several Asian swallowtail butterflyspecies, such as Papilio bianor, Papilio helenus, Papilio protenor, and Papilio xuthus. namakayniay a nasulitan nasakamuan atu natinengan . . [2009 02 24]. 2009 p164 2001 ISDN:957 97452 1 8 http: plant.tesri.gov.tw plant100 WebPlantDetail.aspx?tno 417020010 5. p81 87 7 30 (5) 108 p122 1735 p868 http: subject.forest.gov.tw .. book4 198.htm http: www.moxa.org.tw .. summer ingredient18.pdf 43(2) 035 PDF 92 10 278 </FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>
