<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_nipaluma-alupal,_alopal" xml:lang="pwn" source="Paiwan Wikipedia, article: nipaluma-alupal,_alopal" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="nipaluma-alupal,_alopal. (2024, December 07). In Wikipedia [Paiwan]. https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/nipaluma-alupal,_alopal" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_pwn_nipaluma-alupal,_alopal, title = nipaluma-alupal,_alopal, year = 2024, month = December, day = 7, note = {In Wikipedia [Paiwan]}, url = {https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/nipaluma-alupal,_alopal} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== alupal, alopal == 柿 kagak kakuniza subal :真核域 Eukaryota salaedan :植物界 Plantae panan :被子植物門 Magnoliophyta upiz :雙子葉植物綱 Magnoliopsida mata :柿樹目 Ericales sapamat :柿樹科 Ebenaceae mikitinay :柿樹屬 Diospyros hicahicaay : u siwkay nu nipaluma u sanek nu nipaluma malaheci tu imelang pasubana i cacudadan a lacul u zuma a cidekay a kamu, saungay misapayu' a cidekay u sulit nu zuma a kamu-Hulam atu Amilika The persimmon /pər'sɪmən/ (sometimes spelled persimon) is the edible fruit of a number of species of trees in the genus Diospyros. The most widely cultivated of these is the Oriental or Japanese persimmon, Diospyros kaki. Diospyros is in the family Ebenaceae, and a number of non-persimmon species of the genus are grown for ebony timber.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== alopal, alopal == 柿 kagak kakoniza sobal :真核域 Eokaryota salaedan :植物界 Plantae panan :被子植物門 Magnoliophyta opiz :雙子葉植物綱 Magnoliopsida mata :柿樹目 Ericales sapamat :柿樹科 Ebenaceae mikitinay :柿樹屬 Diospyros hicahicaay : o siwkay no nipaloma o sanek no nipaloma malaheci to imelang pasobana i cacodadan a lacol o zoma a cidekay a kamo, saongay misapayo' a cidekay o solit no zoma a kamo-Holam ato Amilika The persimmon /pər'sɪmən/ (sometimes spelled persimon) is the edible froit of a nomber of species of trees in the genos Diospyros. The most widely coltivated of these is the Oriental or Japanese persimmon, Diospyros kaki. Diospyros is in the family Ebenaceae, and a nomber of non-persimmon species of the genos are grown for ebony timber.</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>