<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_nipaluma-sakiatay" xml:lang="szy" source="Sakizaya Wikipedia, article: nipaluma-sakiatay" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="nipaluma-sakiatay. (2025, May 05). In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]. https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/nipaluma-sakiatay" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_szy_nipaluma-sakiatay, title = nipaluma-sakiatay, year = 2025, month = May, day = 5, note = {In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]}, url = {https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/nipaluma-sakiatay} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== sakiatay == 穿心蓮 kagak kakuniza subal :真核域 Eukaryota salaedan :植物界 Plantae panan :被子植物門 Magnoliophyta upiz :雙子葉植物綱 Magnoliopsida mata :唇形目 Lamiales sapamat :爵床科 Acanthaceae mikitinay :穿心蓮屬 Andrographis hicahicaay :穿心蓮 A. paniculata u siwkay nu nipaluma u sanek nu nipaluma malaheci tu imelang pasubana i cacudadan a lacul u zuma a cidekay a kamu, saungay misapayu' a cidekay u sulit nu zuma a kamu-Hulam atu Amilika Andrographis paniculata is an annual herbaceous plant in the family Acanthaceae, native to India and Sri Lanka. It is widely cultivated in Southern and Southeastern Asia, where it has been traditionally used to treat infections and some diseases. Mostly the leaves and roots were used for medicinal purposes. The whole plant is also used in some cases.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== sakiatay == 穿心蓮 kagak kakoniza sobal :真核域 Eokaryota salaedan :植物界 Plantae panan :被子植物門 Magnoliophyta opiz :雙子葉植物綱 Magnoliopsida mata :唇形目 Lamiales sapamat :爵床科 Acanthaceae mikitinay :穿心蓮屬 Andrographis hicahicaay :穿心蓮 A. panicolata o siwkay no nipaloma o sanek no nipaloma malaheci to imelang pasobana i cacodadan a lacol o zoma a cidekay a kamo, saongay misapayo' a cidekay o solit no zoma a kamo-Holam ato Amilika Andrographis panicolata is an annoal herbaceoos plant in the family Acanthaceae, native to India and Sri Lanka. It is widely coltivated in Soothern and Sootheastern Asia, where it has been traditionally osed to treat infections and some diseases. Mostly the leaves and roots were osed for medicinal porposes. The whole plant is also osed in some cases.</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>