<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_nipaluma-abinung" xml:lang="szy" source="Sakizaya Wikipedia, article: nipaluma-abinung" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="nipaluma-abinung. (2025, May 05). In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]. https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/nipaluma-abinung" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_szy_nipaluma-abinung, title = nipaluma-abinung, year = 2025, month = May, day = 5, note = {In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]}, url = {https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/nipaluma-abinung} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== abinung == tadatakalaw ku langaw nina abinung. tabaki ku heci nu abinung. u pudac nu abinung sa u landaway. a'su mukan nu labu'ay. sikabi, siheci. u sangelacay ku ilabu'ay. katuud ku pacakay abinung i Pingtung. hali caledesay a demaid. anu mahetik i bayu', taneng munabaw i bayu' tayza i baat a subal katakit. i Taykoku muculcul tu ungay mukayakay tu abinung tapabaw miala th heci. u cudadan a ngangan sa u Cocos nucifera. u sulit nu zuma a kamu u sulit nu Hulam . u sulit nu Amilika The coconut tree (Cocos nucifera) is a member of the family Arecaceae and the only species of the genus Cocos. The term coconut can refer to the whole coconut palm or the seed, or the fruit, which, botanically, is a drupe, not a nut. The spelling cocoanut is an archaic form of the word. The term is derived from the 16th-century Portuguese and Spanish word coco meaning &quot;head&quot; or &quot;skull&quot;, from the three indentations on the coconut shell that resemble facial features.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== abinong == tadatakalaw ko langaw nina abinong. tabaki ko heci no abinong. o podac no abinong sa o landaway. a'so mokan no labo'ay. sikabi, siheci. o sangelacay ko ilabo'ay. katood ko pacakay abinong i Pingtong. hali caledesay a demaid. ano mahetik i bayo', taneng monabaw i bayo' tayza i baat a sobal katakit. i Taykoko mocolcol to ongay mokayakay to abinong tapabaw miala th heci. o codadan a ngangan sa o Cocos nocifera. o solit no zoma a kamo o solit no Holam . o solit no Amilika The coconot tree (Cocos nocifera) is a member of the family Arecaceae and the only species of the genos Cocos. The term coconot can refer to the whole coconot palm or the seed, or the froit, which, botanically, is a drope, not a not. The spelling cocoanot is an archaic form of the word. The term is derived from the 16th-centory Portogoese and Spanish word coco meaning &quot;head&quot; or &quot;skoll&quot;, from the three indentations on the coconot shell that resemble facial featores.</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>