<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_nipaluma-sumanahay_tana,_somanahay_tana" xml:lang="szy" source="Sakizaya Wikipedia, article: nipaluma-sumanahay_tana,_somanahay_tana" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="nipaluma-sumanahay_tana,_somanahay_tana. (2025, May 05). In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]. https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/nipaluma-sumanahay_tana,_somanahay_tana" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_szy_nipaluma-sumanahay_tana,_somanahay_tana, title = nipaluma-sumanahay_tana,_somanahay_tana, year = 2025, month = May, day = 5, note = {In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]}, url = {https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/nipaluma-sumanahay_tana,_somanahay_tana} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== sumanahay tana, somanahay tana == 紅刺蔥 kagak kakuniza subal :真核域 Eukaryota salaedan :植物界 Plantae panan :被子植物門 Magnoliophyta upiz :雙子葉植物綱 Magnoliopsida mata :無患子目 sapamat :芸香科 mikitinay :花椒屬 hicahicaay :食茱萸(Z. ailanthoides) u siwkay nu nipaluma u sanek nu nipaluma malaheci tu imelang pasubana i cacudadan a lacul u zuma a cidekay a kamu, saungay misapayu' a cidekay u sulit nu zuma a kamu-Hulam atu Amilika Zanthoxylum ailanthoides, also called ailanthus-like prickly ash, (Chinese: 椿叶花椒; pinyin: chun ye hua jiao, lit. &quot;Ailanthus-leaved pepper&quot;, Chinese: 越椒; pinyin: yue-jiao; Wade–Giles: yüeh-chiao, lit. &quot;Yue pepper&quot;, 食茱萸 shi zhu yu, lit. &quot;edible shān zhū yú&quot;; Japanese: カラスザンショウ, からすのさんしょう karasu-zanshō, karasu-no-sanshō, lit. &quot;crow prickly ash&quot;) is an Asiatic plant of the prickly-ash genus Zanthoxylum, natively occurring in forest-covered parts of southeastern China, Taiwan, Southeast Asia, and Japan from Honshu southward. The piquant fruit serves as a local &quot;substitute for the ordinary red-pepper&quot; in China. In Taiwan, the young leaves are used in cuisines. Though some refer to the species as &quot;Japanese prickly-ash&quot;, that name is confusing since it is sometimes applied to the sanshōwhich is Z. piperitum. Z. ailanthoides is not normally exploited for human consumption in Japan, unless you count the prehistoric people from the Jōmon period. It is foraged in the wild by the Japanese macaque. A regional nickname is tara, and in fact, its young shoots are often mistaken for the true tara (Aralia elata) by gatherers of wild plants. The Latin name ailanthoides of the species comes from its leaves resembling those of the Ailanthus. Like other genera of plants in the rue family, it serves as the host food plant for the larvae of several Asian swallowtail butterflyspecies, such as Papilio bianor, Papilio helenus, Papilio protenor, and Papilio xuthus.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== somanahay tana, somanahay tana == 紅刺蔥 kagak kakoniza sobal :真核域 Eokaryota salaedan :植物界 Plantae panan :被子植物門 Magnoliophyta opiz :雙子葉植物綱 Magnoliopsida mata :無患子目 sapamat :芸香科 mikitinay :花椒屬 hicahicaay :食茱萸(Z. ailanthoides) o siwkay no nipaloma o sanek no nipaloma malaheci to imelang pasobana i cacodadan a lacol o zoma a cidekay a kamo, saongay misapayo' a cidekay o solit no zoma a kamo-Holam ato Amilika Zanthoxylom ailanthoides, also called ailanthos-like prickly ash, (Chinese: 椿叶花椒; pinyin: chon ye hoa jiao, lit. &quot;Ailanthos-leaved pepper&quot;, Chinese: 越椒; pinyin: yoe-jiao; Wade–Giles: yüeh-chiao, lit. &quot;Yoe pepper&quot;, 食茱萸 shi zho yo, lit. &quot;edible shān zhū yú&quot;; Japanese: カラスザンショウ, からすのさんしょう karaso-zanshō, karaso-no-sanshō, lit. &quot;crow prickly ash&quot;) is an Asiatic plant of the prickly-ash genos Zanthoxylom, natively occorring in forest-covered parts of sootheastern China, Taiwan, Sootheast Asia, and Japan from Honsho soothward. The piqoant froit serves as a local &quot;sobstitote for the ordinary red-pepper&quot; in China. In Taiwan, the yoong leaves are osed in coisines. Thoogh some refer to the species as &quot;Japanese prickly-ash&quot;, that name is confosing since it is sometimes applied to the sanshōwhich is Z. piperitom. Z. ailanthoides is not normally exploited for homan consomption in Japan, onless yoo coont the prehistoric people from the Jōmon period. It is foraged in the wild by the Japanese macaqoe. A regional nickname is tara, and in fact, its yoong shoots are often mistaken for the troe tara (Aralia elata) by gatherers of wild plants. The Latin name ailanthoides of the species comes from its leaves resembling those of the Ailanthos. Like other genera of plants in the roe family, it serves as the host food plant for the larvae of several Asian swallowtail botterflyspecies, soch as Papilio bianor, Papilio helenos, Papilio protenor, and Papilio xothos.</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>