<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_nipaluma-tabakiay_apalu,_tabakiay_apalo" xml:lang="szy" source="Sakizaya Wikipedia, article: nipaluma-tabakiay_apalu,_tabakiay_apalo" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="nipaluma-tabakiay_apalu,_tabakiay_apalo. (2025, May 05). In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]. https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/nipaluma-tabakiay_apalu,_tabakiay_apalo" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_szy_nipaluma-tabakiay_apalu,_tabakiay_apalo, title = nipaluma-tabakiay_apalu,_tabakiay_apalo, year = 2025, month = May, day = 5, note = {In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]}, url = {https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/nipaluma-tabakiay_apalu,_tabakiay_apalo} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">tabakiay apalu, tabakiay apalo 波羅蜜 u satabakiay a heci i kanatal. maka 10-20m talakaw. baeket ku heci maka 5-20kg. kagak kakuniza subal : salaedan :植物界 Plantae panan :被子植物門 Magnoliophyta upiz : mata :薔薇目 Rosales sapamat :桑科 Moraceae mikitinay :桂木屬 Artocarpus hicahicaay :波羅蜜 A. heterophyllus u siwkay nu nipaluma u sanek nu nipaluma malaheci tu imelang pasubana i cacudadan a lacul u zuma a cidekay a kamu, saungay misapayu' a cidekay u sulit nu zuma a kamu-Hulam atu Amilika The jackfruit (Artocarpus heterophyllus), also known as jack tree, fenne, jakfruit, or sometimes simply jack or jak, is a species of tree in the fig, mulberry, and breadfruit family native to South India. The jackfruit tree is well suited to tropical lowlands, and its fruit is the largest tree-borne fruit, reaching as much as 35 kg (80 lb) in weight, 90 cm (35 in) in length, and 50 cm (20 in) in diameter.A mature jackfruit tree can produce about 100 to 200 fruits in a year. The jackfruit is a multiple fruit, composed of hundreds to thousands of individual flowers, and it is the fleshy petals that are eaten. The jackfruit tree is a widely cultivated and popular food item throughout the tropical regions of the world. Jackfruit is the national fruit of Bangladesh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">tabakiay apalo, tabakiay apalo 波羅蜜 o satabakiay a heci i kanatal. maka 10-20m talakaw. baeket ko heci maka 5-20kg. kagak kakoniza sobal : salaedan :植物界 Plantae panan :被子植物門 Magnoliophyta opiz : mata :薔薇目 Rosales sapamat :桑科 Moraceae mikitinay :桂木屬 Artocarpos hicahicaay :波羅蜜 A. heterophyllos o siwkay no nipaloma o sanek no nipaloma malaheci to imelang pasobana i cacodadan a lacol o zoma a cidekay a kamo, saongay misapayo' a cidekay o solit no zoma a kamo-Holam ato Amilika The jackfroit (Artocarpos heterophyllos), also known as jack tree, fenne, jakfroit, or sometimes simply jack or jak, is a species of tree in the fig, molberry, and breadfroit family native to Sooth India. The jackfroit tree is well soited to tropical lowlands, and its froit is the largest tree-borne froit, reaching as moch as 35 kg (80 lb) in weight, 90 cm (35 in) in length, and 50 cm (20 in) in diameter.A matore jackfroit tree can prodoce aboot 100 to 200 froits in a year. The jackfroit is a moltiple froit, composed of hondreds to thoosands of individoal flowers, and it is the fleshy petals that are eaten. The jackfroit tree is a widely coltivated and popolar food item throoghoot the tropical regions of the world. Jackfroit is the national froit of Bangladesh.</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>