<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_nipaluma-lintusen,_lintosen" xml:lang="szy" source="Sakizaya Wikipedia, article: nipaluma-lintusen,_lintosen" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="nipaluma-lintusen,_lintosen. (2025, May 05). In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]. https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/nipaluma-lintusen,_lintosen" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_szy_nipaluma-lintusen,_lintosen, title = nipaluma-lintusen,_lintosen, year = 2025, month = May, day = 5, note = {In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]}, url = {https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/nipaluma-lintusen,_lintosen} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== lintusen, lintosen == 稜軸土人參 kagak kakuniza salaedan :植物界 Plantae panan :被子植物門 Magnoliophyta upiz :木蘭綱 Eudicots mata :石竹目 Caryophyllales sapamat :土人參科 Talinaceae mikitinay :土人參屬 Talinum hicahicaay :T. fruticosum u siwkay nu nipaluma u sanek nu nipaluma malaheci tu imelang pasubana i cacudadan a lacul u zuma a cidekay a kamu, saungay misapayu' a cidekay u sulit nu zuma a kamu-Hulam atu Amilika . Talinum fruticosum ( common local name ನೆಲಬಸಳೆ - &quot;Nela basale&quot; in kannada ) is an herbaceous perennial plant that is native to Mexico, the Caribbean, West Africa, Central America, and much of South America. Common names include Ceylon spinach, waterleaf, cariru, Gbure, Surinam purslane, Philippine spinach, Florida spinach, potherb fameflower, Lagos bologi, and sweetheart. It is widely grown in tropical regions as a leaf vegetable.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== lintosen, lintosen == 稜軸土人參 kagak kakoniza salaedan :植物界 Plantae panan :被子植物門 Magnoliophyta opiz :木蘭綱 Eodicots mata :石竹目 Caryophyllales sapamat :土人參科 Talinaceae mikitinay :土人參屬 Talinom hicahicaay :T. froticosom o siwkay no nipaloma o sanek no nipaloma malaheci to imelang pasobana i cacodadan a lacol o zoma a cidekay a kamo, saongay misapayo' a cidekay o solit no zoma a kamo-Holam ato Amilika . Talinom froticosom ( common local name ನೆಲಬಸಳೆ - &quot;Nela basale&quot; in kannada ) is an herbaceoos perennial plant that is native to Mexico, the Caribbean, West Africa, Central America, and moch of Sooth America. Common names inclode Ceylon spinach, waterleaf, cariro, Gbore, Sorinam porslane, Philippine spinach, Florida spinach, potherb fameflower, Lagos bologi, and sweetheart. It is widely grown in tropical regions as a leaf vegetable.</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>