<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_nipaluma-kikul_nu_tumay,_kikol_no_tomay" xml:lang="pwn" source="Paiwan Wikipedia, article: nipaluma-kikul_nu_tumay,_kikol_no_tomay" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="nipaluma-kikul_nu_tumay,_kikol_no_tomay. (2024, December 07). In Wikipedia [Paiwan]. https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/nipaluma-kikul_nu_tumay,_kikol_no_tomay" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_pwn_nipaluma-kikul_nu_tumay,_kikol_no_tomay, title = nipaluma-kikul_nu_tumay,_kikol_no_tomay, year = 2024, month = December, day = 7, note = {In Wikipedia [Paiwan]}, url = {https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/nipaluma-kikul_nu_tumay,_kikol_no_tomay} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== kikul nu tumay, kikol no tomay == 虎尾蘭 u kakuniza salaedan :植物界 Plantae panan :被子植物門 Magnoliophyta upiz :單子葉植物綱 Liliopsida mata :天門冬目Asparagales sapamat :天門冬科Asparagaceae mikitinay :虎尾蘭屬Sansevieria hicahicaay :虎尾蘭 S. trifasciata u siwkay nu nipaluma u sanek nu nipaluma malaheci tu imelang pasubana i cacudadan a lacul u zuma a cidekay a kamu, saungay misapayu' a cidekay u sulit nu zuma a kamu-Hulam atu Amilika Sansevieria trifasciata is a species of flowering plant in the family Asparagaceae, native to tropical West Africa from Nigeria east to the Congo. It is most commonly known as the snake plant, mother-in-law's tongue, and viper's bowstring hemp, among other names.It is an evergreen perennial plant forming dense stands, spreading by way of its creeping rhizome, which is sometimes above ground, sometimes underground. Its stiff leaves grow vertically from a basal rosette. Mature leaves are dark green with light gray-green cross-banding and usually range between 70–90 centimetres (28–35 in) long and 5–6 centimetres (2.0–2.4 in) wide, though it can reach heights above 2 m (6 ft) in optimal conditions.(citation needed) The specific epithet trifasciata means "three bundles".</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== kikol no tomay, kikol no tomay == 虎尾蘭 o kakoniza salaedan :植物界 Plantae panan :被子植物門 Magnoliophyta opiz :單子葉植物綱 Liliopsida mata :天門冬目Asparagales sapamat :天門冬科Asparagaceae mikitinay :虎尾蘭屬Sansevieria hicahicaay :虎尾蘭 S. trifasciata o siwkay no nipaloma o sanek no nipaloma malaheci to imelang pasobana i cacodadan a lacol o zoma a cidekay a kamo, saongay misapayo' a cidekay o solit no zoma a kamo-Holam ato Amilika Sansevieria trifasciata is a species of flowering plant in the family Asparagaceae, native to tropical West Africa from Nigeria east to the Congo. It is most commonly known as the snake plant, mother-in-law's tongoe, and viper's bowstring hemp, among other names.It is an evergreen perennial plant forming dense stands, spreading by way of its creeping rhizome, which is sometimes above groond, sometimes ondergroond. Its stiff leaves grow vertically from a basal rosette. Matore leaves are dark green with light gray-green cross-banding and osoally range between 70–90 centimetres (28–35 in) long and 5–6 centimetres (2.0–2.4 in) wide, thoogh it can reach heights above 2 m (6 ft) in optimal conditions.(citation needed) The specific epithet trifasciata means "three bondles".</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>