<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_nipaluma-mawkuswn,mawkosen" xml:lang="pwn" source="Paiwan Wikipedia, article: nipaluma-mawkuswn,mawkosen" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="nipaluma-mawkuswn,mawkosen. (2024, December 07). In Wikipedia [Paiwan]. https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/nipaluma-mawkuswn,mawkosen" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_pwn_nipaluma-mawkuswn,mawkosen, title = nipaluma-mawkuswn,mawkosen, year = 2024, month = December, day = 7, note = {In Wikipedia [Paiwan]}, url = {https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/nipaluma-mawkuswn,mawkosen} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== mawkusen, mawkosen == mawkusen sa, mauzip i caledesay sicilalay a subal. hali i sadipan. kiptul ku papah. sibanuh i kalang atu papah.tabaki ku heci. u siwkay nu nipaluma u sanek nu nipaluma malaheci tu imelang pasubana i cacudadan a lacul u zuma a cidekay a kamu, saungay misapayu' a cidekay u sulit nu zuma a kamu-Hulam atu Amilika Sophora tomentosa, also known as necklacepod, yellow necklacepod, and occasionally as silver bush, is a pantropical shrub or small tree in the family Fabaceae. It commonly ranges in height from 4 to 10 feet and often occurs in coastal conditions and near wetlands. The common name Necklacepod is derived from the characteristic string of seed pods that develop after its yellow flowers germinate into seeds.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== mawkosen, mawkosen == mawkosen sa, maozip i caledesay sicilalay a sobal. hali i sadipan. kiptol ko papah. sibanoh i kalang ato papah.tabaki ko heci. o siwkay no nipaloma o sanek no nipaloma malaheci to imelang pasobana i cacodadan a lacol o zoma a cidekay a kamo, saongay misapayo' a cidekay o solit no zoma a kamo-Holam ato Amilika Sophora tomentosa, also known as necklacepod, yellow necklacepod, and occasionally as silver bosh, is a pantropical shrob or small tree in the family Fabaceae. It commonly ranges in height from 4 to 10 feet and often occors in coastal conditions and near wetlands. The common name Necklacepod is derived from the characteristic string of seed pods that develop after its yellow flowers germinate into seeds.</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>