<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_nipaluma-kawayna" xml:lang="pwn" source="Paiwan Wikipedia, article: nipaluma-kawayna" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="nipaluma-kawayna. (2024, December 07). In Wikipedia [Paiwan]. https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/nipaluma-kawayna" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_pwn_nipaluma-kawayna, title = nipaluma-kawayna, year = 2024, month = December, day = 7, note = {In Wikipedia [Paiwan]}, url = {https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/nipaluma-kawayna} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== kawayna == 金銀花 taneng miazih atu mukan. sikapahay a sangek i labii. u masay-kilang a nipaluma'. malicangay a balu taneng micebus tu akuti'ay a nanum, taneng mukan. kagak kakuniza subal :真核域 Eukaryota salaedan :植物界 Plantae panan :被子植物門 Magnoliophyta upiz :雙子葉植物綱 Magnoliopsida mata :川續斷目 Dipsacales sapamat :忍冬科 Caprifoliaceae mikitinay :忍冬屬 Lonicera hicahicaay :忍冬 L. japonica u siwkay nu nipaluma u sanek nu nipaluma malaheci tu imelang pasubana i cacudadan a lacul u zuma a cidekay a kamu, saungay misapayu' a cidekay u sulit nu zuma a kamu-Hulam atu Amilika 忍冬 , . Lonicera japonica, known as golden-and-silver honeysuckle or Japanese honeysuckle in English, suikazura in Japanese, jinyinhua or rendongteng in Chinese, indongdeonggul in Korean, and kim ngân hoa in Vietnamese, is a species of honeysuckle native to eastern Asia including China, Japan and Korea. It is a twining vine able to climb up to 10 m (33 ft) high or more in trees, with opposite, simple oval leaves 3–8 cm (1.2–3.1 in) long and 2–3 cm (0.79–1.18 in) broad. The flowers are double-tongued, opening white and fading to yellow, and sweetly vanilla scented. The fruit is a black spherical berry 3–4 mm (0.12–0.16 in) diameter containing a few seeds.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== kawayna == 金銀花 taneng miazih ato mokan. sikapahay a sangek i labii. o masay-kilang a nipaloma'. malicangay a balo taneng micebos to akoti'ay a nanom, taneng mokan. kagak kakoniza sobal :真核域 Eokaryota salaedan :植物界 Plantae panan :被子植物門 Magnoliophyta opiz :雙子葉植物綱 Magnoliopsida mata :川續斷目 Dipsacales sapamat :忍冬科 Caprifoliaceae mikitinay :忍冬屬 Lonicera hicahicaay :忍冬 L. japonica o siwkay no nipaloma o sanek no nipaloma malaheci to imelang pasobana i cacodadan a lacol o zoma a cidekay a kamo, saongay misapayo' a cidekay o solit no zoma a kamo-Holam ato Amilika 忍冬 , . Lonicera japonica, known as golden-and-silver honeysockle or Japanese honeysockle in English, soikazora in Japanese, jinyinhoa or rendongteng in Chinese, indongdeonggol in Korean, and kim ngân hoa in Vietnamese, is a species of honeysockle native to eastern Asia incloding China, Japan and Korea. It is a twining vine able to climb op to 10 m (33 ft) high or more in trees, with opposite, simple oval leaves 3–8 cm (1.2–3.1 in) long and 2–3 cm (0.79–1.18 in) broad. The flowers are dooble-tongoed, opening white and fading to yellow, and sweetly vanilla scented. The froit is a black spherical berry 3–4 mm (0.12–0.16 in) diameter containing a few seeds.</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>