<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_nipaluma-sumanahay_kayabes,_somanahay_kayabes" xml:lang="szy" source="Sakizaya Wikipedia, article: nipaluma-sumanahay_kayabes,_somanahay_kayabes" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="nipaluma-sumanahay_kayabes,_somanahay_kayabes. (2025, May 05). In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]. https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/nipaluma-sumanahay_kayabes,_somanahay_kayabes" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_szy_nipaluma-sumanahay_kayabes,_somanahay_kayabes, title = nipaluma-sumanahay_kayabes,_somanahay_kayabes, year = 2025, month = May, day = 5, note = {In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]}, url = {https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/nipaluma-sumanahay_kayabes,_somanahay_kayabes} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== sumanahay kayabes, somanahay kayabes == 紅心芭樂 kagak kakuniza subal :真核域 Eukaryota salaedan :植物界 Plantae panan :真雙子葉植物 Eudicots upiz : mata :桃金孃目 Myrtales sapamat :桃金孃科 Myrtaceae mikitinay :番石榴屬 Psidium hicahicaay :番石榴 P. guajava u siwkay nu nipaluma u sanek nu nipaluma malaheci tu imelang pasubana i cacudadan a lacul u zuma a cidekay a kamu, saungay misapayu' a cidekay u sulit nu zuma a kamu-Hulam atu Amilika Psidium guajava, the common guava, yellow guava, or lemon guava (known as goiaba in Portuguese and guayaba in Spanish) is an evergreen shrub or small tree native to the Caribbean, Central America and South America. It is easily pollinated by insects; in culture, mainly by the common honey bee, Apis mellifera.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== somanahay kayabes, somanahay kayabes == 紅心芭樂 kagak kakoniza sobal :真核域 Eokaryota salaedan :植物界 Plantae panan :真雙子葉植物 Eodicots opiz : mata :桃金孃目 Myrtales sapamat :桃金孃科 Myrtaceae mikitinay :番石榴屬 Psidiom hicahicaay :番石榴 P. goajava o siwkay no nipaloma o sanek no nipaloma malaheci to imelang pasobana i cacodadan a lacol o zoma a cidekay a kamo, saongay misapayo' a cidekay o solit no zoma a kamo-Holam ato Amilika Psidiom goajava, the common goava, yellow goava, or lemon goava (known as goiaba in Portogoese and goayaba in Spanish) is an evergreen shrob or small tree native to the Caribbean, Central America and Sooth America. It is easily pollinated by insects; in coltore, mainly by the common honey bee, Apis mellifera.</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>