<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_nipaluma-culal,_colal" xml:lang="pwn" source="Paiwan Wikipedia, article: nipaluma-culal,_colal" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="nipaluma-culal,_colal. (2024, December 07). In Wikipedia [Paiwan]. https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/nipaluma-culal,_colal" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_pwn_nipaluma-culal,_colal, title = nipaluma-culal,_colal, year = 2024, month = December, day = 7, note = {In Wikipedia [Paiwan]}, url = {https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/nipaluma-culal,_colal} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== culal, colal == 昭和草 . kagak kakuniza subal :真核域 Eukaryota salaedan :植物界 Plantae panan :被子植物門 Magnoliophyta upiz :雙子葉植物綱 Magnoliopsida mata :菊目 Asterales sapamat :菊科 Asteraceae mikitinay :昭和草屬 Crassocephalum hicahicaay :昭和草 C. crepidioides u siwkay nu nipaluma u sanek nu nipaluma malaheci tu imelang pasubana i cacudadan a lacul u zuma a cidekay a kamu, saungay misapayu' a cidekay u sulit nu zuma a kamu-Hulam atu Amilika 昭和草(學名:Crassocephalum crepidioides,俗稱:ebolo,thickhead,redflower ragleaf,fireweed), . Crassocephalum crepidioides, also called ebolo, thickhead, redflower ragleaf, or fireweed, is an erect annual slightly succulent herb growing up to 180 cm tall. Its use is widespread in many tropical and subtropical regions, but is especially prominent in tropical Africa. Its fleshy, mucilaginous leaves and stems are eaten as a vegetable, and many parts of the plant have medical uses. However, the safety of internal use needs further research due to the presence of plant toxins.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== colal, colal == 昭和草 . kagak kakoniza sobal :真核域 Eokaryota salaedan :植物界 Plantae panan :被子植物門 Magnoliophyta opiz :雙子葉植物綱 Magnoliopsida mata :菊目 Asterales sapamat :菊科 Asteraceae mikitinay :昭和草屬 Crassocephalom hicahicaay :昭和草 C. crepidioides o siwkay no nipaloma o sanek no nipaloma malaheci to imelang pasobana i cacodadan a lacol o zoma a cidekay a kamo, saongay misapayo' a cidekay o solit no zoma a kamo-Holam ato Amilika 昭和草(學名:Crassocephalom crepidioides,俗稱:ebolo,thickhead,redflower ragleaf,fireweed), . Crassocephalom crepidioides, also called ebolo, thickhead, redflower ragleaf, or fireweed, is an erect annoal slightly soccolent herb growing op to 180 cm tall. Its ose is widespread in many tropical and sobtropical regions, bot is especially prominent in tropical Africa. Its fleshy, mocilaginoos leaves and stems are eaten as a vegetable, and many parts of the plant have medical oses. However, the safety of internal ose needs forther research doe to the presence of plant toxins.</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>