<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_nipaluma-salahebal" xml:lang="szy" source="Sakizaya Wikipedia, article: nipaluma-salahebal" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="nipaluma-salahebal. (2025, May 05). In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]. https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/nipaluma-salahebal" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_szy_nipaluma-salahebal, title = nipaluma-salahebal, year = 2025, month = May, day = 5, note = {In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]}, url = {https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/nipaluma-salahebal} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== salahebal == 向日葵 mahiza ku cilal, u balu sa midudu ku cilal. taneng mukan, taneng pasapayu'. kapah miazih. yadah ku ngangan. u siwkay nu nipaluma u sanek nu nipaluma malaheci tu imelang pasubana i cacudadan a lacul u zuma a cidekay a kamu, saungay misapayu' a cidekay u sulit nu zuma a kamu-Hulam atu Amilika 向日葵(學名:Helianthus annuus) :ji̍t-thâu-hue) , . Helianthus annuus, the common sunflower, is a large annual forb of the genus Helianthus grown as a crop for its edible oil and edible fruits . This sunflower species is also used as bird food, as livestock forage (as a meal or a silageplant), and in some industrial applications. The plant was first domesticated in the Americas. Wild Helianthus annuus is a widely branched annual plant with many flower heads. The domestic sunflower, however, often possesses only a single large inflorescence atop an unbranched stem. The name sunflower may derive from the flower's head's shape, which resembles the sun, or from the impression that the blooming plant appears to slowly turn its flower towards the sun as the latter moves across the sky on a daily basis. Sunflower seeds were brought to Europe from the Americas in the 16th century, where, along with sunflower oil, they became a widespread cooking ingredient.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== salahebal == 向日葵 mahiza ko cilal, o balo sa midodo ko cilal. taneng mokan, taneng pasapayo'. kapah miazih. yadah ko ngangan. o siwkay no nipaloma o sanek no nipaloma malaheci to imelang pasobana i cacodadan a lacol o zoma a cidekay a kamo, saongay misapayo' a cidekay o solit no zoma a kamo-Holam ato Amilika 向日葵(學名:Helianthos annoos) :ji̍t-thâo-hoe) , . Helianthos annoos, the common sonflower, is a large annoal forb of the genos Helianthos grown as a crop for its edible oil and edible froits . This sonflower species is also osed as bird food, as livestock forage (as a meal or a silageplant), and in some indostrial applications. The plant was first domesticated in the Americas. Wild Helianthos annoos is a widely branched annoal plant with many flower heads. The domestic sonflower, however, often possesses only a single large inflorescence atop an onbranched stem. The name sonflower may derive from the flower's head's shape, which resembles the son, or from the impression that the blooming plant appears to slowly torn its flower towards the son as the latter moves across the sky on a daily basis. Sonflower seeds were brooght to Eorope from the Americas in the 16th centory, where, along with sonflower oil, they became a widespread cooking ingredient.</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>