<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_nipaluma-tabakiay_apalu,_tabakiay_apalo" xml:lang="pwn" source="Paiwan Wikipedia, article: nipaluma-tabakiay_apalu,_tabakiay_apalo" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="nipaluma-tabakiay_apalu,_tabakiay_apalo. (2024, November 18). In Wikipedia [Paiwan]. https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/nipaluma-tabakiay_apalu,_tabakiay_apalo" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_pwn_nipaluma-tabakiay_apalu,_tabakiay_apalo, title = nipaluma-tabakiay_apalu,_tabakiay_apalo, year = 2024, month = November, day = 18, note = {In Wikipedia [Paiwan]}, url = {https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/nipaluma-tabakiay_apalu,_tabakiay_apalo} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM>tabakiay apalu, tabakiay apalo ( : , , , , , , , , , , , , ) u satabakiay a heci i kanatal. maka 10 20m talakaw. baeket ku heci maka 5 20kg. kagak kakuniza subal: salaedan: Plantae panan: Magnoliophyta upiz: mata: Rosales sapamat: Moraceae mikitinay: Artocarpus hicahicaay: A. heterophyllus u siwkay nu nipaluma u sanek nu nipaluma malaheci tu imelang pasubana i cacudadan a lacul u zuma a cidekay a kamu, saungay misapayu' a cidekay u sulit nu zuma a kamu Hulam atu Amilika ( :Artocarpus heterophyllus) , , . The jackfruit (Artocarpus heterophyllus), also known as jack tree, fenne, jakfruit, or sometimes simply jack or jak, is a species of tree in the fig, mulberry, and breadfruit family (Moraceae) native to South India. The jackfruit tree is well suited to tropical lowlands, and its fruit is the largest tree borne fruit, reaching as much as 35 kg (80 lb) in weight, 90 cm (35 in) in length, and 50 cm (20 in) in diameter.A mature jackfruit tree can produce about 100 to 200 fruits in a year. The jackfruit is a multiple fruit, composed of hundreds to thousands of individual flowers, and it is the fleshy petals that are eaten. The jackfruit tree is a widely cultivated and popular food item throughout the tropical regions of the world. Jackfruit is the national fruit of Bangladesh. namakayniay a nasulitan nasakamuan atu natinengan . . [2009 02 24]. 2009 p133 2003 Boluomi </FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>
