<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_nipaluma-landaway_bunac" xml:lang="szy" source="Sakizaya Wikipedia, article: nipaluma-landaway_bunac" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="nipaluma-landaway_bunac. (2025, May 05). In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]. https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/nipaluma-landaway_bunac" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_szy_nipaluma-landaway_bunac, title = nipaluma-landaway_bunac, year = 2025, month = May, day = 5, note = {In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]}, url = {https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/nipaluma-landaway_bunac} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== landaway bunac == u sulit nu Hulam mauzip mabulak i 500-1200m a buyu , uyaan a kilankilangan. i dihep i lunabay, hali malalemeday lutulutukan a lala'. akenek ku sanek, siledek. kapah tu misapayu' tu makalat tu bau atu cilekay. u takalaw sa 40-90cm, u yadah a mihcaay a lamit. u heci a kulit sa u sumanahay. mulu ku heci. siheci i 8-10 bulad. u siwkay nu nipaluma u sanek nu nipaluma malaheci tu imelang pasubana i cacudadan a lacul u zuma a cidekay a kamu, saungay misapayu' a cidekay u sulit nu zuma a kamu-Hulam atu Amilika u sulit nu Amilika Paris polyphylla is an Asian species of plants native to China, the Indian Subcontinent, and Indochina. It produces spider-like flowers that throw out long, thread-like, yellowish green petals throughout most of the warm summer months and into the autumn. In the fall, the flowers are followed by small, scarlet berries. It is a perennial, which slowly spreads, is fully hardy in Britain, and survives in leafy, moist soil in either complete or partial shade. This flowering plant usually grows up to 90 cm (3 ft) high and spreads out about 30 cm (1 ft) wide. Its leaves grow in a single whorl below a flower growing in two whorls. It is used as an ornamental plant for woodland gardens or for planting under deciduous trees.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== landaway bonac == o solit no Holam maozip mabolak i 500-1200m a boyo , oyaan a kilankilangan. i dihep i lonabay, hali malalemeday lotolotokan a lala'. akenek ko sanek, siledek. kapah to misapayo' to makalat to bao ato cilekay. o takalaw sa 40-90cm, o yadah a mihcaay a lamit. o heci a kolit sa o somanahay. molo ko heci. siheci i 8-10 bolad. o siwkay no nipaloma o sanek no nipaloma malaheci to imelang pasobana i cacodadan a lacol o zoma a cidekay a kamo, saongay misapayo' a cidekay o solit no zoma a kamo-Holam ato Amilika o solit no Amilika Paris polyphylla is an Asian species of plants native to China, the Indian Sobcontinent, and Indochina. It prodoces spider-like flowers that throw oot long, thread-like, yellowish green petals throoghoot most of the warm sommer months and into the aotomn. In the fall, the flowers are followed by small, scarlet berries. It is a perennial, which slowly spreads, is folly hardy in Britain, and sorvives in leafy, moist soil in either complete or partial shade. This flowering plant osoally grows op to 90 cm (3 ft) high and spreads oot aboot 30 cm (1 ft) wide. Its leaves grow in a single whorl below a flower growing in two whorls. It is osed as an ornamental plant for woodland gardens or for planting onder decidooos trees.</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>