<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_Song_Hui_Qiyaw_(Korea)" xml:lang="szy" source="Sakizaya Wikipedia, article: Song_Hui_Qiyaw_(Korea)" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="Song_Hui_Qiyaw_(Korea). (2025, May 05). In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]. https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Song_Hui_Qiyaw_(Korea)" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_szy_Song_Hui_Qiyaw_(Korea), title = Song_Hui_Qiyaw_(Korea), year = 2025, month = May, day = 5, note = {In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]}, url = {https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Song_Hui_Qiyaw_(Korea)} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== Song Hui Qiyaw == u siwkay niza Song Hui Qiyaw(1981.11.22), tatayna, u palaway nu Korea. natahkal ciniza i 1996 a mihca. namipalaw tu tilibi atu iga. sangulan ku bihid, nasikawaw tu motul. 2017.7.5 macawa tu, u acawama niza sa ci Song Cong Ci, u palaway tu. (amicunus henay tu sulit.待補充) u sapuyaay a kakuniza u kawaw niza u sulit nu Hulam 自1996 &quot; 與Rain . u sulit nu Amilika Song Hye-kyo (born November 22, 1981) is a South Korean actress. She gained popularity through her leading roles in television dramas Autumn in My Heart(2000), All In (2003), Full House (2004), That Winter, the Wind Blows (2013) and Descendants of the Sun (2016) which achieved pan-Asia success. She has also starred in films Hwang Jin Yi (2007), The Grandmaster (2013), My Brilliant Life (2014) and The Queens (2015). In 2017, she ranked 7th in Forbes magazine's Korea Power Celebrity list. The success of Song's television dramas internationally established her as a top Hallyustar. u sulit nu Lipun u kawlah niza . (amicunus henay tu sulit.待補充) u uzip niza (amicunus henay tu sulit.待補充)</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== Song Hoi Qiyaw == o siwkay niza Song Hoi Qiyaw(1981.11.22), tatayna, o palaway no Korea. natahkal ciniza i 1996 a mihca. namipalaw to tilibi ato iga. sangolan ko bihid, nasikawaw to motol. 2017.7.5 macawa to, o acawama niza sa ci Song Cong Ci, o palaway to. (amiconos henay to solit.待補充) o sapoyaay a kakoniza o kawaw niza o solit no Holam 自1996 &quot; 與Rain . o solit no Amilika Song Hye-kyo (born November 22, 1981) is a Sooth Korean actress. She gained popolarity throogh her leading roles in television dramas Aotomn in My Heart(2000), All In (2003), Foll Hoose (2004), That Winter, the Wind Blows (2013) and Descendants of the Son (2016) which achieved pan-Asia soccess. She has also starred in films Hwang Jin Yi (2007), The Grandmaster (2013), My Brilliant Life (2014) and The Qoeens (2015). In 2017, she ranked 7th in Forbes magazine's Korea Power Celebrity list. The soccess of Song's television dramas internationally established her as a top Hallyostar. o solit no Lipon o kawlah niza . (amiconos henay to solit.待補充) o ozip niza (amiconos henay to solit.待補充)</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>