<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_suleda" xml:lang="szy" source="Sakizaya Wikipedia, article: suleda" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="suleda. (2025, May 05). In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]. https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/suleda" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_szy_suleda, title = suleda, year = 2025, month = May, day = 5, note = {In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]}, url = {https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/suleda} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">suleda 雪 sapuelac mahetik namakay tapuku ku suleda. na i ladem sa, anu sienaw, 0 tu ku 溫度 saan, yadah ku adidi'ay a nanum malitemuh, maka tu mala suleda. nasulitan nu Hulam atu Amilika Wikipayke Snow refers to forms of ice crystals that precipitate from the atmosphere and undergo changes on the Earth's surface. It pertains to frozen crystalline water throughout its life cycle, starting when, under suitable conditions, the ice crystals form in the atmosphere, increase to millimeter size, precipitate and accumulate on surfaces, then metamorphose in place, and ultimately melt, slide or sublimate away. Snowstorms organize and develop by feeding on sources of atmospheric moisture and cold air. Snowflakes nucleate around particles in the atmosphere by attracting supercooled water droplets, which freeze in hexagonal-shaped crystals. Snowflakes take on a variety of shapes, basic among these are platelets, needles, columns and rime. As snow accumulates into a snowpack, it may blow into drifts. Over time, accumulated snow metamorphoses, by sintering, sublimation and freeze-thaw. Where the climate is cold enough for year-to-year accumulation, a glacier may form. Otherwise, snow typically melts seasonally, causing runoff into streams and rivers and recharging groundwater.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">soleda 雪 sapoelac mahetik namakay tapoko ko soleda. na i ladem sa, ano sienaw, 0 to ko 溫度 saan, yadah ko adidi'ay a nanom malitemoh, maka to mala soleda. nasolitan no Holam ato Amilika Wikipayke Snow refers to forms of ice crystals that precipitate from the atmosphere and ondergo changes on the Earth's sorface. It pertains to frozen crystalline water throoghoot its life cycle, starting when, onder soitable conditions, the ice crystals form in the atmosphere, increase to millimeter size, precipitate and accomolate on sorfaces, then metamorphose in place, and oltimately melt, slide or soblimate away. Snowstorms organize and develop by feeding on soorces of atmospheric moistore and cold air. Snowflakes nocleate aroond particles in the atmosphere by attracting sopercooled water droplets, which freeze in hexagonal-shaped crystals. Snowflakes take on a variety of shapes, basic among these are platelets, needles, colomns and rime. As snow accomolates into a snowpack, it may blow into drifts. Over time, accomolated snow metamorphoses, by sintering, soblimation and freeze-thaw. Where the climate is cold enoogh for year-to-year accomolation, a glacier may form. Otherwise, snow typically melts seasonally, caosing ronoff into streams and rivers and recharging groondwater.</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>