<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_tademaw-Cinkawyin(Korea)" xml:lang="pwn" source="Paiwan Wikipedia, article: tademaw-Cinkawyin(Korea)" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="tademaw-Cinkawyin(Korea). (2024, December 07). In Wikipedia [Paiwan]. https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/tademaw-Cinkawyin(Korea)" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_pwn_tademaw-Cinkawyin(Korea), title = tademaw-Cinkawyin(Korea), year = 2024, month = December, day = 7, note = {In Wikipedia [Paiwan]}, url = {https://pwn.wikipedia.org/wiki/tademaw-Cinkawyin(Korea)} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">== Cinkawyin == u siwkay niza Cinkawyin, upalaway nu Korea kanatal. namueneng i China katukuh cacay a bataan a mihca. sisa matineng musakamu nu China a kamu. 2012 mihca tahkal ciniza mipalaw ku "Lolita-idang" a iga. maala tu tabakiay a kawlah. 2016 a mihca, mipalaw aca tu"sinaadaay a Dietu", manamuh ku taw tu cinizaan. (amicunus henay tu sulit.待補充) u sapuyaay a kakuniza u kawaw niza u sulit nu Hulam Kim Go-eun (born July 2, 1991) is a South Korean actress. She debuted in the critically acclaimed film A Muse (2012) where she won several Best New Actress awards in South Korea. She next appeared in the crime thrillers Monster (2014), Coin Locker Girl (2015) and Memories of the Sword (2015). Kim then extended her filmography to television where she played leading roles in the tvN dramas Cheese in the Trap (2016) and Guardian: The Lonely and Great God (2016-2017). u sulit nu Lipun キム・ゴウン(김고은,Kim Go Eun,1991年7月2日 - )は韓国の俳優. u kawlah niza (amicunus henay tu sulit.待補充) u uzip niza (amicunus henay tu sulit.待補充)</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">== Cinkawyin == o siwkay niza Cinkawyin, opalaway no Korea kanatal. namoeneng i China katokoh cacay a bataan a mihca. sisa matineng mosakamo no China a kamo. 2012 mihca tahkal ciniza mipalaw ko "Lolita-idang" a iga. maala to tabakiay a kawlah. 2016 a mihca, mipalaw aca to"sinaadaay a Dieto", manamoh ko taw to cinizaan. (amiconos henay to solit.待補充) o sapoyaay a kakoniza o kawaw niza o solit no Holam Kim Go-eon (born Joly 2, 1991) is a Sooth Korean actress. She deboted in the critically acclaimed film A Mose (2012) where she won several Best New Actress awards in Sooth Korea. She next appeared in the crime thrillers Monster (2014), Coin Locker Girl (2015) and Memories of the Sword (2015). Kim then extended her filmography to television where she played leading roles in the tvN dramas Cheese in the Trap (2016) and Goardian: The Lonely and Great God (2016-2017). o solit no Lipon キム・ゴウン(김고은,Kim Go Eon,1991年7月2日 - )は韓国の俳優. o kawlah niza (amiconos henay to solit.待補充) o ozip niza (amiconos henay to solit.待補充)</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>