<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Wiki_Sakizaya_Wu_Bai" xml:lang="szy" source="Sakizaya Wikipedia, article: Wu_Bai" copyright="CC BY-SA" citation="Wu_Bai. (2025, May 05). In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]. https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wu_Bai" BibTeX_citation="@misc{Wiki_szy_Wu_Bai, title = Wu_Bai, year = 2025, month = May, day = 5, note = {In Wikipedia [Sakizaya]}, url = {https://szy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wu_Bai} }">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Wu Bai Wu Bai u siwkay niza 伍佰(1968.1.14) ,tatama, nalecuh i Taywan Cyayi sian Liukuy siang. u Taywan palaway, mudadiway, misulit ku dadiway, misanga' tu dadiway. u yawkun dadiw putiputay a mudadiway atu mikitaay. u sapuyaay a kakuniza u kawaw niza u sulit nu Hulam :Gōo-pah) &quot;伍佰 &amp; China Blue&quot;的主唱及主音吉他手. u sulit nu Amilika Wu Chun-lin (Chinese: 吳俊霖; pinyin: Wú Jùnlín; born 14 January 1968), better known by his stage name Wu Bai (Chinese: 伍佰; pinyin: Wǔ Bǎi; Pe̍h-ōe-jī: Gō͘-pah), is a Taiwanese rock singer and songwriter. He formed the band Wu Bai &amp; China Blue with Dean Zavolta , Yu Ta-hao and Chu Chien-hui , while Wu himself is the lead guitarist and vocalist of the band. Dubbed &quot;The King of Live Music&quot;, Wu is considered to be one of the biggest pop music stars in East and Southeast Asia. u kawlah niza u uzip niza (amicunus henay tu sulit.待補充)</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Wo Bai Wo Bai o siwkay niza 伍佰(1968.1.14) ,tatama, nalecoh i Taywan Cyayi sian Liokoy siang. o Taywan palaway, modadiway, misolit ko dadiway, misanga' to dadiway. o yawkon dadiw potipotay a modadiway ato mikitaay. o sapoyaay a kakoniza o kawaw niza o solit no Holam :Gōo-pah) &quot;伍佰 &amp; China Bloe&quot;的主唱及主音吉他手. o solit no Amilika Wo Chon-lin (Chinese: 吳俊霖; pinyin: Wú Jùnlín; born 14 Janoary 1968), better known by his stage name Wo Bai (Chinese: 伍佰; pinyin: Wǔ Bǎi; Pe̍h-ōe-jī: Gō͘-pah), is a Taiwanese rock singer and songwriter. He formed the band Wo Bai &amp; China Bloe with Dean Zavolta , Yo Ta-hao and Cho Chien-hoi , while Wo himself is the lead goitarist and vocalist of the band. Dobbed &quot;The King of Live Mosic&quot;, Wo is considered to be one of the biggest pop mosic stars in East and Sootheast Asia. o kawlah niza o ozip niza (amiconos henay to solit.待補充)</FORM>
    </S>
</TEXT>