<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEXT id="Siraya_Dutch_John_Chapter3" xml:lang="fos" source="Siraya Bible, John gospel" copyright="public domain" citation="Gravius, Daniël. 1661. Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa. Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang. Amsterdam: Michiel Hartogh." BibTeX_citation="@book{Gravius1661,&#10;  author    = {Gravius, Daniël},&#10;  year      = {1661},&#10;  title     = {Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa},&#10;  note      = {Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang},&#10;  address   = {Amsterdam},&#10;  publisher = {Michiel Hartogh}&#10;}" dialect="Siraya">
    <S id="verse1">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-akoumea ta ta'u ka na Farisëen, ka ti Nikodemus ta nanang tyn, ka Sih-bavau ki Joden.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka niakoumea ta ta'u ka na Farisëen, ka ti Nikodemus ta nanang tyn, ka Sihbavau ki Joden.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende daer was een mensche uyt de Phariseen wiens name was Nicodemus een Oberste der Joden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">There was a man of the Pharisees, named Nicodemus, a ruler of the Jews:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">有一個法利賽人，名叫尼哥德慕，是猶太人的官。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse2">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Teni ta ni-iroua ka euvanan mou-qua ti Jesus-an, ka ni-koun tyn tyni-æn, Rabbi, kavana 'ni-en ka Tama-Mahtæutæuugh-kow ka ni-makka-qua ki Alid: alei ka assi pa-'lpouh ta ti-mamang pa-mut ki pou-kidi-en k'atta ka pam't-en-hou-ra, dou assi tou lam tyni-æn ta Alid.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Teni ta niiroua ka euvanan mouqua ti Jesusan, ka nikoun tyn tyniæn, Rabbi, kavana 'nien ka TamaMahtæutæuughkow ka nimakkaqua ki Alid: alei ka assi pa'lpouh ta timamang pamut ki poukidien k'atta ka pam'tenhoura, dou assi tou lam tyniæn ta Alid.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Dese quam des nachts tot Jesum ende seyde tot hem Rabbi wy weten dat ghy zijt een Leeraer ban Godt ghekomen : want niemant en kan dese teerkenen doen die ghy doet foo Godt met hem niet en id.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">The same came to Jesus by night, and said unto him, Rabbi, we know that thou art a teacher come from God: for no man can do these miracles that thou doest, except God be with him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">這人夜裏來見耶穌，說：＂拉比，我們知道你是由上帝那裏來作師傅的；因為你所行的神蹟，若沒有上帝同在，無人能行。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse3">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-mattæ'i-vli ta ti Jesus ka ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Missing, missing koun-au-kow, Heirou assi pei-la-en mei-alak ta ti-mamang, assi kmi-'lpouh kmytta ta teni ki Pei-sasou-an ki Alid.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Nimattæ'ivli ta ti Jesus ka nik'ma tyniæn, Missing, missing kounaukow, Heirou assi peilaen meialak ta timamang, assi kmi'lpouh kmytta ta teni ki Peisasouan ki Alid.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Jesus antwoorde ende seyde tot hem Doorwaer boorboorwaer segge ick u Ten zy dat yemant wederom gebooren worde hyen kan het koninckrijcke Godts niet sien.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus answered and said unto him, Verily, verily, I say unto thee, Except a man be born again, he cannot see the kingdom of God.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌回答說：＂我實實在在地告訴你，人若不重生，就不能見上帝的國。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse4">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'ma ta ti Nikodemus tyni-æn; Pei-lpough-au-lato mei-alak ta ka'euloung mamei-mang (rou) mamou-ato ta teni? Mou-'lpouh kaua mouh-pouhal mou-vouijl ki dena tyn, ka pei-la-auh mei-alak?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Nik'ma ta ti Nikodemus tyniæn; Peilpoughaulato meialak ta ka'euloung mameimang (rou) mamouato ta teni? Mou'lpouh kaua mouhpouhal mouvouijl ki dena tyn, ka peilaauh meialak?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Nicodemus seyde tot hem; Noe kan een mensche geboren worden (nu) oudt zijnde? Kan hy oock andermael in sijns moeders buyck ingaen ende geboren worden?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Nicodemus saith unto him, How can a man be born when he is old? can he enter the second time into his mother's womb, and be born?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">尼哥德慕說：＂人已經老了，如何能重生呢？豈能再進母腹生出來嗎？＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse5">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-pattæ'i-vli-enti Jesus, Missing, missing koun-au-kow; Rou assi pei-alak-in ta ti-mamang ki raloum ki Joep-an, assi tyn 'ou-'lpouh-in mou-rbo tou Pei-sasou-an ki Alid.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Nipattæ'ivlienti Jesus, Missing, missing kounaukow; Rou assi peialakin ta timamang ki raloum ki Joepan, assi tyn 'ou'lpouhin mourbo tou Peisasouan ki Alid.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Jesus antwoorde Doorwaer boordaer segge ick u; So yemant niet gheboren en wort uyt water ende Geest hy en kam in't koninckrijcke Godts niet ingaen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus answered, Verily, verily, I say unto thee, Except a man be born of water and of the Spirit, he cannot enter into the kingdom of God.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：＂我實實在在地告訴你，人若不是從水和聖靈生的，就不能進上帝的國。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse6">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-pei-alak ki vât, vât ta anna: pei-alak ki Joep-an, Joep-an ta anna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka nipeialak ki vât, vât ta anna: peialak ki Joepan, Joepan ta anna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Net gene uyt bleesch geboren is (dat) is bleesch: ende het gene uyt den Geest geboren is (dat) is Geest.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">That which is born of the flesh is flesh; and that which is born of the Spirit is spirit.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">從肉身生的就是肉身；從靈生的就是靈。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse7">
        <FORM kindOf="original">In-â mou-ryng-hau ka ni-vana-en-au kow, Kidi-ato ka pei-la-auh-kamou mei-alak ta ym-ou-mi-ra.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Inâ mourynghau ka nivanaenau kow, Kidiato ka peilaauhkamou meialak ta ymoumira.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">En berwondert u niet dat ick u geseght hebbe Ghylieden moet wederom gebooren worden</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Marvel not that I said unto thee, Ye must be born again.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我說：＂你們必須重生＂，你不要以為希奇。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse8">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Bavarè ta varè tou ma-mang ka kâmoei-in tyn, ka'illingig-en-hou ta harimhim tyn, ra assi 'mou-hou 'ou-mbân ka makka-kouna ka sah-kakoun-ah ta anna: kma-hyna ta mai-boävoual ka pei-alak ki Joep-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Bavarè ta varè tou mamang ka kâmoeiin tyn, ka'illingigenhou ta harimhim tyn, ra assi 'mouhou 'oumbân ka makkakouna ka sahkakounah ta anna: kmahyna ta maiboävoual ka peialak ki Joepan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">De wind blaest waer henen hy wil ende ghy hoort zijt geluyt maer ghy en weer Niet ban waer h henen gaet : alfoo is een yegeliick die uyt den Geest geboren is.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">The wind bloweth where it listeth, and thou hearest the sound thereof, but canst not tell whence it cometh, and whither it goeth: so is every one that is born of the Spirit.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">風隨着意思吹，你聽見風的響聲，卻不曉得從哪裏來，往哪裏去；凡從聖靈生的，也是如此。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse9">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-mattæ'i-vli ta ti Nikodemus k'ma tyni-æn; Pa-il poug-g-hen pamut ta mamang k'atta mame'i mang?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Nimattæ'ivli ta ti Nikodemus k'ma tyniæn; Pail pougghen pamut ta mamang k'atta mame'i mang?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Nicodemus antoorde ende seyde tot hen ; Noe kon-konnen dese dingen gheschieden?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Nicodemus answered and said unto him, How can these things be?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">尼哥德慕問他說：＂怎能有這事呢？＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse10">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-mattæ'i-vli ta ti Jesus ka ni k'ma tyni-æn; Mahtatæu-tæuuh kow kaua tou Israel ka kauro-en-appa-'m hou ta atta-ra?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Nimattæ'ivli ta ti Jesus ka ni k'ma tyniæn; Mahtatæutæuuh kow kaua tou Israel ka kauroenappa'm hou ta attara?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Jesus antwoorde ende seyde tot hem ; Zijt ghy een Leeraer israels ende en weet ghy dese dingen niet?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus answered and said unto him, Art thou a master of Israel, and knowest not these things?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌回答說：＂你是以色列人的先生，還不明白這事嗎？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse11">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Missing, missing koun-au kow, ka kavanân-niæn ta pa-sasoun-ni-æn, ka ni-k'yttan-niæn ta pa-ttæi-hail-nian, ka assi-mou-mi atta-rarijh-en ta pattæ'i-hail-miæn-da.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Missing, missing kounau kow, ka kavanânniæn ta pasasounniæn, ka nik'yttanniæn ta pattæihailnian, ka assimoumi attararijhen ta pattæ'ihailmiænda.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doorwaer boorwaer segge ick u Wy spyreken dat wy weten ende getuygen dat wy gesien hebben ende ghylieden en neemt ons' getuygenisse niet aen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Verily, verily, I say unto thee, We speak that we do know, and testify that we have seen; and ye receive not our witness.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我實實在在地告訴你，我們所說的是我們知道的；我們所見證的是我們見過的；你們卻不領受我們的見證。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse12">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Heirou ni-pa-sousou-en-au-kamou ki makka-næi, ka assi-moumi tna-'msing, tna-'msing-ah-kamou mame'i-mang, rou pa-sousou-en-au-kamou ki makka tounnoun.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Heirou nipasousouenaukamou ki makkanæi, ka assimoumi tna'msing, tna'msingahkamou mame'imang, rou pasousouenaukamou ki makka tounnoun.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Indien iek u-lieden de aerdtsche dingen geseght henbe ende ghy niet en gelooft hoe sult ghy getooben indien ick u-lieden de hemelsche soude seggen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">If I have told you earthly things, and ye believe not, how shall ye believe, if I tell you of heavenly things?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我對你們說地上的事，你們尚且不信，若說天上的事，如何能信呢？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse13">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka assi ni-sa-bavau sah-tounnoun ta ti-mamang, dyk ty-ni-æn ka ni-mourarum makka tounnoun, (teni) ta Alak ki kæ'euloung ka æ'ia-tounnoun.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka assi nisabavau sahtounnoun ta timamang, dyk tyniæn ka nimourarum makka tounnoun, (teni) ta Alak ki kæ'euloung ka æ'iatounnoun.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende niemant en is opgebaren in den hemel dan die uyt den hemel nedergekomen is ( namelick ) de Sone des menschen die in den hemel is.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And no man hath ascended up to heaven, but he that came down from heaven, even the Son of man which is in heaven.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">除了從天降下、仍舊在天的人子，沒有人升過天。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse14">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka mama ka ni-pou-va-vau-in ti Moses tou peu-læ-pou-læh ta voeley, kidi-ato ka pou-va-vau-auh kma-hynna ta Alak ki kæ'eulong.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka mama ka nipouvavauin ti Moses tou peulæpoulæh ta voeley, kidiato ka pouvavauauh kmahynna ta Alak ki kæ'eulong.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende gheliick Moses de slange in de woestjne berhooght heeft also moet De Sone des menschen berhoogt worden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And as Moses lifted up the serpent in the wilderness, even so must the Son of man be lifted up:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">摩西在曠野怎樣舉蛇，人子也必照樣被舉起來，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse15">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Alei ka assi tau-rumma-ah ta mei-bovoel ka tna-'msing tyni-æn ka akoume-âl-appa ki kæua'g-han ka myhkaqua myddaryn-nouh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Alei ka assi taurummaah ta meibovoel ka tna'msing tyniæn ka akoumeâlappa ki kæua'ghan ka myhkaqua myddarynnouh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Op dat een yegelick die in hem gelooft niet en berderbe maer het eewighe ghe leben hebbe.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">That whosoever believeth in him should not perish, but have eternal life.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">叫一切信他的都得永生。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse16">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-kævæ'angö-en kma-hyn na ki Alid ta næy, ka ni-phæ'n tyn ta Alak tyn ka Pei-sât-an, alei k'assi tau-rumma-ah ta mei-bo-voel ka tna-'msing tyni-æn, ka a-koume-âl-appa ki kæu'ag'-han ka myh-kaqua myddarynnouh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka nikævæ'angöen kmahyn na ki Alid ta næy, ka niphæ'n tyn ta Alak tyn ka Peisâtan, alei k'assi taurummaah ta meibovoel ka tna'msing tyniæn, ka akoumeâlappa ki kæu'ag'han ka myhkaqua myddarynnouh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Want alfoo lief heeft Godt de werelt gehat dat hy sijneneenigh-geborenen Sone ne gepeben heeft op dat een pegelick die in hem ghelooft niet en derderbe maer het enwige leben hebbe.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">For God so loved the world, that he gave his only begotten Son, that whosoever believeth in him should not perish, but have everlasting life.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">＂上帝愛世人，甚至將他的獨生子賜給他們，叫一切信他的，不致滅亡，反得永生。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse17">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Nda ka assi ni-pa-din-gi-en ki Alid ta Alak tyn tou næi alei ka dungdung-auh tyn ta næi,alei-appa ka pakariang-auh tyn ta næi alei tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Nda ka assi nipadingien ki Alid ta Alak tyn tou næi alei ka dungdungauh tyn ta næi,aleiappa ka pakariangauh tyn ta næi alei tyniæn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Want Godt en heeft fijnen Sone niet gesonden in de werelt op dat hy de werelt beroordeelen soude maer op dat de werelt door hem soude behouden worden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">For God sent not his Son into the world to condemn the world; but that the world through him might be saved.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">因為上帝差他的兒子降世，不是要定世人的罪，乃是要叫世人因他得救。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse18">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ty-mang ta tna-'msing tyni-æn, assi dungdung-auh, ra ti-mang ta assi tna-'msing kah-'an-ato hnyn dmungdung : alei ka assi ni-tna-'msing tou Nanang ki Alak ki Alid ka Pei-saät-en.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Tymang ta tna'msing tyniæn, assi dungdungauh, ra timang ta assi tna'msing kah'anato hnyn dmungdung : alei ka assi nitna'msing tou Nanang ki Alak ki Alid ka Peisaäten.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Die in hem gelooft en wordt niet beroordeelt maer die niet en gelooft is alreede eroordeelt: dewijle hy niet en heeft gelooft in den Name des eenig-geboren Soons Gods.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">He that believeth on him is not condemned: but he that believeth not is condemned already, because he hath not believed in the name of the only begotten Son of God.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">信他的人，不被定罪；不信的人，罪已經定了，因為他不信上帝獨生子的名。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse19">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka att'-appa ta dung-dung-un, ka irou-ato ta ræmæh tou Næi, ka ni-kasaoun-nun ma-væ ängö ki kaeuloung ta karum-dum-man, ki ræmæh: alei ka mat-ë ta na ringei nein-nda.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka att'appa ta dungdungun, ka irouato ta ræmæh tou Næi, ka nikasaounnun mavæ ängö ki kaeuloung ta karumdumman, ki ræmæh: alei ka matë ta na ringei neinnda.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende dit is het oordeel dat het licht in de werelt gekomen is ende de menschen hebben de duysternisse lieber ghehadt dan het licht: want hare werrken waren boos.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And this is the condemnation, that light is come into the world, and men loved darkness rather than light, because their deeds were evil.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">光來到世間，世人因自己的行為是惡的，不愛光，倒愛黑暗，定他們的罪就是在此。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse20">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Kati-mamangka pamut ki kat-'è-en, 'æ'æs-in tyn ta ræmæh, ka assi mou-qua tou ræmæh ta teni, alei ka assi patym 'h'eil'a-to ta na ringeityn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Katimamangka pamut ki kat'èen, 'æ'æsin tyn ta ræmæh, ka assi mouqua tou ræmæh ta teni, alei ka assi patym 'h'eil'ato ta na ringeityn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Want een yegelick die quaet doet haet het licht ende en komt tot het licht niet op dat fijne wercken niet besiraft en worden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">For every one that doeth evil hateth the light, neither cometh to the light, lest his deeds should be reproved.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">凡作惡的便恨光，並不來就光，恐怕他的行為受責備。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse21">
        <FORM kindOf="original">. Ra ti-mamang ta pamut ki katiktik-an ki fou, mou-qua tou ræmæh ta teni, ki paka-æmæ'-euh ta na ringei tyn, alei ka ni-pamut tou Alilid-den.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">. Ra timamang ta pamut ki katiktikan ki fou, mouqua tou ræmæh ta teni, ki pakaæmæ'euh ta na ringei tyn, alei ka nipamut tou Alilidden.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Maer die de waer heyt doet komt tot het licht op dat sijne wercken openbaer worden dat sy in: Gode gedaen zijn.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But he that doeth truth cometh to the light, that his deeds may be made manifest, that they are wrought in God.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">但行真理的必來就光，要顯明他所行的是靠上帝而行。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse22">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Si-ǣ-'uh ki anna ni-iroua ta ti Jesus, ki Pahtatæu tæuæu-han-appatyn mou-qua tou pourogh. ki Judæä ka ni-malanga ta teni hynna lam neini-æn, mæu-læu 'u-lough-da.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Siǣ'uh ki anna niiroua ta ti Jesus, ki Pahtatæu tæuæuhanappatyn mouqua tou pourogh. ki Judæä ka nimalanga ta teni hynna lam neiniæn, mæulæu 'uloughda.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Na desen quam Jesus ende sijne Discipulen in het landt ban Judea ende ont-onthielt hem aldaer met haer ende doopte.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">After these things came Jesus and his disciples into the land of Judaea; and there he tarried with them, and baptized.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">這事以後，耶穌和門徒到了猶太地，在那裏居住，施洗。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse23">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-m'æuloug-appa ta ti Johannes tou Enon tou tamang ki Salim, alei ka madagh hynna ta raloum: ka ni-iroua mou-qua hynna, ka ni-uloug-han-atou-ra.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka nim'æulougappa ta ti Johannes tou Enon tou tamang ki Salim, alei ka madagh hynna ta raloum: ka niiroua mouqua hynna, ka niuloughanatoura.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende Joannes doopte oock in Enon by Salim dewijle aldaer beele wateren waren : ende sy quamen daer ende wierden gedoopt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And John also was baptizing in Aenon near to Salim, because there was much water there: and they came, and were baptized.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">約翰在靠近撒冷的哀嫩也施洗；因為那裏水多，眾人都去受洗。（</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse24">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka assi-appa pou-sang-at-tin ta ti Joannes.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka assiappa pousangattin ta ti Joannes.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Want Joannes en was noch niet in de gebanckenisse geworpen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">For John was not yet cast into prison.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那時約翰還沒有下在監裏。）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse25">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Anna ta ni-æhpit ta pa-tig-til-lan ki sou ki Pæhtæutæu-han ti Joannes lam-appa ki Joden alei ki paka-kouptyg-han.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Anna ta niæhpit ta patigtillan ki sou ki Pæhtæutæuhan ti Joannes lamappa ki Joden alei ki pakakouptyghan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Daer rees dan een brage ( van eenige) uyt de Discipulen Joannis met De Joden ober de reyniginge.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then there arose a question between some of John's disciples and the Jews about purifying.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">約翰的門徒和一個猶太人辯論潔淨的禮，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse26">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-mou-qua ti Joannes-an, ka ni-koun nein tyni-æn; Rabbi, teni ka nalam-ohou tou arouh ki Jordaan, ka ni-pattæ'i-hail-en-hou tyni-æn, k'ytt-ei, mæ'u-lulouh ta teni, ka mou-ym-mud tyni-æn mou-qua.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka nimouqua ti Joannesan, ka nikoun nein tyniæn; Rabbi, teni ka nalamohou tou arouh ki Jordaan, ka nipattæ'ihailenhou tyniæn, k'yttei, mæ'ululouh ta teni, ka mouymmud tyniæn mouqua.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende sy quamen tot Joannem ende seyden tot hem; Gabbi die met u was ober den Jordaen welcken ghy getuygenisse gaeft siet die doot ende sy komen alle tot hem.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And they came unto John, and said unto him, Rabbi, he that was with thee beyond Jordan, to whom thou barest witness, behold, the same baptizeth, and all men come to him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">就來見約翰，說：＂拉比，從前同你在約旦河外、你所見證的那位，現在施洗，眾人都往他那裏去了。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse27">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-mattæ'i-vlita ti Joan-nes, ka ni-k'ma-hynna, Assi a-lpough-en mara ta kaeulong ki-mamang, rou assi ni-phæn tyni-æn makka tounnoun ki vullum.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Nimattæ'ivlita ti Joannes, ka nik'mahynna, Assi alpoughen mara ta kaeulong kimamang, rou assi niphæn tyniæn makka tounnoun ki vullum.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Joannes antwoorde ende seyde Een mensche en ban gheen dingh aennemen soo het hem uyt den hemel niet gegeben en zy.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">John answered and said, A man can receive nothing, except it be given him from heaven.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">約翰說：＂若不是從天上賜的，人就不能得甚麼。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse28">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Tama-hail-kamou jau-an ta ymoumi mamado, ka ni-pa-sousou-en-au, Assi tijau ta ti Christus, ra ni-pa-dingi-en-koh pa-si-ouro tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Tamahailkamou jauan ta ymoumi mamado, ka nipasousouenau, Assi tijau ta ti Christus, ra nipadingienkoh pasiouro tyniæn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ghy selbe zijt mijne getuygen dat ick gheseght hebbe Ick en ben de Christus niet maer dat ick boor hem henen uyt gesonden ben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Ye yourselves bear me witness, that I said, I am not the Christ, but that I am sent before him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我曾說：＂我不是基督，是奉差遣在他前面的＂，你們自己可以給我作見證。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse29">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ti-mang ta akou-Ina ka væ'æu, teni ta Paræh ka væ'æu: nda diou ka Paræh ka væ'æu ka mi-touhko millingigh tyni-æn;ta marai-ja ki karai-jan ki ryh,alei ki yngau ki Paræh ka væ'æu. Anna ta pa-katmoei-en-ato ta karai-jen-au k'atta.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Timang ta akouIna ka væ'æu, teni ta Paræh ka væ'æu: nda diou ka Paræh ka væ'æu ka mitouhko millingigh tyniæn;ta maraija ki karaijan ki ryh,alei ki yngau ki Paræh ka væ'æu. Anna ta pakatmoeienato ta karaijenau k'atta.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Die de Bruyt heeft is de Bruydegom : maer de bzient briend des Bruydegoms die fraet ende hem hoort berblijt sich met blijdschap om de scemme des Bruydegoms. Soo ig dan dese mijne blijdtschap berbult geworden</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">He that hath the bride is the bridegroom: but the friend of the bridegroom, which standeth and heareth him, rejoiceth greatly because of the bridegroom's voice: this my joy therefore is fulfilled.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">娶新婦的就是新郎；新郎的朋友站着，聽見新郎的聲音就甚喜樂。故此，我這喜樂滿足了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse30">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Kidi ka tou saoun-ah kæuh-irang ta teni, ra l'auaeih-koh ta ti jau.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Kidi ka tou saounah kæuhirang ta teni, ra l'auaeihkoh ta ti jau.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Hy moet waffen maer ick minder worden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">He must increase, but I must decrease.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他必興旺，我必衰微。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse31">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Teni ka makka-vavau, itou ymmid itou vavau : Teni ka makka-qua ki næi, mak-ka næi ta teni , ka pa-sousou-en tyn ta a tou næi. Teni ka makka-tounnoun ki vullum, si-bavau ta teni ki ymmid.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Teni ka makkavavau, itou ymmid itou vavau : Teni ka makkaqua ki næi, makka næi ta teni , ka pasousouen tyn ta a tou næi. Teni ka makkatounnoun ki vullum, sibavau ta teni ki ymmid.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Die ban boben komt is boben alle : Die uyt der aerden is ( voortgekomen) die is uyt der aerden ende spreeckt uyt der aerden. Die uyt den hemel komt is boken alle.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">He that cometh from above is above all: he that is of the earth is earthly, and speaketh of the earth: he that cometh from heaven is above all.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">＂從天上來的是在萬有之上；從地上來的是屬乎地，他所說的也是屬乎地。從天上來的是在萬有之上。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse32">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka na kak'yttatyn ka na'il-lalingig tyn, pattæ'i-hail-lun tyn ma-sousou ta anna: ka assi pæh-balei matta-rijh sasasat ka ti-maman ki pattæ'i-hail-en-tyn-da.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka na kak'yttatyn ka na'illalingig tyn, pattæ'ihaillun tyn masousou ta anna: ka assi pæhbalei mattarijh sasasat ka timaman ki pattæ'ihailentynda.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende't gene hy gezien ende gehoort heeft dat ghetuyght hy : ende zijn geteuygenisse en neemt niemant aen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And what he hath seen and heard, that he testifieth; and no man receiveth his testimony.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他將所見所聞的見證出來，只是沒有人領受他的見證。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse33">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Timang ta ni-pæh-balei matta-rijh ki pattæ'i-hail-en tyn, ni-pou-tapoejou pou-shut ka ma-tiktik ki sou ta Alid.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Timang ta nipæhbalei mattarijh ki pattæ'ihailen tyn, nipoutapoejou poushut ka matiktik ki sou ta Alid.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Die sijn getuygenisse aengenomen heeft die heeft bersegelt Dat Godt waerach: tigh is.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">He that hath received his testimony hath set to his seal that God is true.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那領受他見證的，就印上印，證明上帝是真的。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse34">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Nda ti-mang ta ni-padin-gi-en ki Alid, pa-sousou-en tyn ta sou ki Alid, ka assi phæn ki Alid (tyni-æn) ta J-oep-an toup ou-kakidi en rih-pung.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Nda timang ta nipadingien ki Alid, pasousouen tyn ta sou ki Alid, ka assi phæn ki Alid (tyniæn) ta Joepan toup oukakidi en rihpung.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">. Want dien Godt ghesonden heeft die spreeckt De woorden Godts want Godt en geeft (hem) den Geeft niet met mate.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">For he whom God hath sent speaketh the words of God: for God giveth not the Spirit by measure unto him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">上帝所差來的就說上帝的話，因為上帝賜聖靈給他是沒有限量的。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse35">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Mavæ'angö ta Rama ki Alak, ka ni-pǣ'ǣ-ymd-an ta ma-mang pi-'æ tou rima tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Mavæ'angö ta Rama ki Alak, ka nipǣ'ǣymdan ta mamang pi'æ tou rima tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">De Dader heeft den Sone lief ende heeft alle dingen in fijne hant gegeben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">The Father loveth the Son, and hath given all things into his hand.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">父愛子，已將萬有交在他手裏。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse36">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ti-mang ta tna-'msing ki Alak akoume'-ato ki keu 'æhan ka myh kaqua myddarynnouh: Ra ti-mang ta assi miligh ki Alak, assi kmytt-ah ta teni ki kæu'æ-han: ra mæ-ijli misasaoun tou ha-lap tyni-æn ta ngale ki Alid.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Timang ta tna'msing ki Alak akoume'ato ki keu 'æhan ka myh kaqua myddarynnouh: Ra timang ta assi miligh ki Alak, assi kmyttah ta teni ki kæu'æhan: ra mæijli misasaoun tou halap tyniæn ta ngale ki Alid.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Die in den Sone gelooft die heeft eeuwige leben: ben: Maer die den Sone ongehoorsaem is die en sal het leben niet zien : maer de toorn Godts bijft op hem.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">He that believeth on the Son hath everlasting life: and he that believeth not the Son shall not see life; but the wrath of God abideth on him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">信子的人有永生；不信子的人得不着永生，上帝的震怒常在他身上。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
</TEXT>
