<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEXT id="Siraya_Dutch_John_Chapter10" xml:lang="fos" source="Siraya Bible, John gospel" copyright="public domain" citation="Gravius, Daniël. 1661. Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa. Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang. Amsterdam: Michiel Hartogh." BibTeX_citation="@book{Gravius1661,&#10;  author    = {Gravius, Daniël},&#10;  year      = {1661},&#10;  title     = {Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa},&#10;  note      = {Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang},&#10;  address   = {Amsterdam},&#10;  publisher = {Michiel Hartogh}&#10;}" dialect="Siraya">
    <S id="verse1">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Missing, missing ko un-nau-kamou, Ti mamang taassi tau-koua tou ngataf sa-rar-bo tou æræh ki ioekko, ra mak-dahei makdak-kin tou pani, tama-haousoung ta teni ki tama-riough-appa.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Missing, missing ko unnaukamou, Ti mamang taassi taukoua tou ngataf sararbo tou æræh ki ioekko, ra makdahei makdakkin tou pani, tamahaousoung ta teni ki tamarioughappa.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Woorwaer boorwaer segge ick u-lieden Die niet in en gaer door de deure in Den stal Der schapen maer ban elders in-Klimt Die is een Dief ende moordenaer.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Verily, verily, I say unto you, He that entereth not by the door into the sheepfold, but climbeth up some other way, the same is a thief and a robber.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">＂我實實在在地告訴你們，人進羊圈，不從門進去，倒從別處爬進去，那人就是賊，就是強盜。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse2">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Rati mamang ta sa-rarbo tou ngataf tama-kading ta teni ki ioekko.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Rati mamang ta sararbo tou ngataf tamakading ta teni ki ioekko.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Maer die boor de deure in-gaet is een Herder Der schapen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But he that entereth in by the door is the shepherd of the sheep.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">從門進去的，才是羊的牧人。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse3">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Tenita ææu-lif-fen ki sou-aajam ki ngatat, ka millingigh ta ioekko ki yngau tyn: ka pa-kou-vous voual-len tyn ki na-nang tmætæm ta ioekko tyn, tou d'ylloug-ei neini-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Tenita ææuliffen ki souaajam ki ngatat, ka millingigh ta ioekko ki yngau tyn: ka pakouvous vouallen tyn ki nanang tmætæm ta ioekko tyn, tou d'yllougei neiniæn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Desen Doet De denrwachter open ende De schapen hooren sijne steemme : enDe hy roept sijne schapen by namen ende leydt se uyt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">To him the porter openeth; and the sheep hear his voice: and he calleth his own sheep by name, and leadeth them out.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">看門的就給他開門；羊也聽他的聲音。他按着名叫自己的羊，把羊領出來。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse4">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka ni-pou-mala-en tyn ta ioekko tyn, moudada-rang fi-ourou neini-æn, kamæu-æugh tyni-æn ta ioekko, alei ka k alang-in nein ta yngau tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka nipoumalaen tyn ta ioekko tyn, moudadarang fiourou neiniæn, kamæuæugh tyniæn ta ioekko, alei ka k alangin nein ta yngau tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende wanneer hy sijne schayen uyt gebreben Heeft so gaet hy boor haer henen ende De schapen bolghen Hem obermits sy sijne stemme kennen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And when he putteth forth his own sheep, he goeth before them, and the sheep follow him: for they know his voice.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">既放出自己的羊來，就在前頭走，羊也跟着他，因為認得他的聲音。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse5">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Assi mææuug-ah ta neni maravei ki pani, rail pout-al-ap-pa tyni-æn: alei ka assi nein k'a lang-in ta yngau ki pani.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Assi mææuugah ta neni maravei ki pani, rail poutalappa tyniæn: alei ka assi nein k'a langin ta yngau ki pani.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Maer eenen breemden en sullen sy geensins bolgen maer sullen ban Hem blieDen: obermits sy De stemme Der bremde niet en kennen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And a stranger will they not follow, but will flee from him: for they know not the voice of strangers.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">羊不跟着生人；因為不認得他的聲音， 必要逃跑。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse6">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Pamyh kaulaul'-an k'atta ni-pa-sousou-en ti Jesus neini-æn: ra assi nein 'cu-mhgan, mang ta na fou tyn neini-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Pamyh kaulaul'an k'atta nipasousouen ti Jesus neiniæn: ra assi nein 'cumhgan, mang ta na fou tyn neiniæn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Dese gelijckenisse seyDe Jesus tot haer : maer sy en berstonden niet wat het was dat hy tot haer sprack</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">This parable spake Jesus unto them: but they understood not what things they were which he spake unto them.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌將這比喻告訴他們，但他們不明白所說的是甚麼意思。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse7">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-mattæ'i-la ta ti Jesus neini-æn, Missing, missing koun-nau-kamou-ra tijau ta nga-tafki ioekko.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata nimattæ'ila ta ti Jesus neiniæn, Missing, missing kounnaukamoura tijau ta ngatafki ioekko.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">JeJesus Dan seyde wederom tot haer Doorwaer boorwaer segge ick u Ick ben De deure der schapen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then said Jesus unto them again, Verily, verily, I say unto you, I am the door of the sheep.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">所以，耶穌又對他們說：＂我實實在在地告訴你們，我就是羊的門。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse8">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ma-ymmid tana mamang ka ni-si-ourou ierroua jau-an, tama-haouzoung ta neni ki tama-riough-appa, ra assi ni-millin-gigh ta i-oekko neini-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Maymmid tana mamang ka nisiourou ierroua jauan, tamahaouzoung ta neni ki tamarioughappa, ra assi nimillingigh ta ioekko neiniæn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Alle soo bele alsser boor my zijn gekomen zijn Dieben ende moordenaers maer de schapen en hebben haer niet gehoort.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">All that ever came before me are thieves and robbers: but the sheep did not hear them.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">凡在我以先來的都是賊，是強盜；羊卻不聽他們。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse9">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ti jau ta ngataf: heirou ti-mamang ta ta'u-koua jau-an sa-rarbou, K'ading-aul-ato ta teni pa-kariang: ka sa-rarbou-ah, sa-mamala, ka maki-valei-ah ki ǣæuf-vun.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ti jau ta ngataf: heirou timamang ta ta'ukoua jauan sararbou, K'adingaulato ta teni pakariang: ka sararbouah, samamala, ka makivaleiah ki ǣæufvun.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ick ben De deure : inDien yemandt door my in gaet Die sal behouden worDen : ende hy sal ingaen enDe uyt gaen ende weyde binDen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">I am the door: by me if any man enter in, he shall be saved, and shall go in and out, and find pasture.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我就是門；凡從我進來的，必然得救，並且出入得草吃。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse10">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Assi mou-koua ta tama-haouzoung dijk ka haou-zoung-eih tyn, louhpouh, pidada: Iier-rou-'ato-koh ti jau, aleika akou-me'-ah ta neni ki kæuag-han, ki kahouvar-an-appa.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Assi moukoua ta tamahaouzoung dijk ka haouzoungeih tyn, louhpouh, pidada: Iierrou'atokoh ti jau, aleika akoume'ah ta neni ki kæuaghan, ki kahouvaranappa.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">De Dief en komt niet Dan op Dat hy stele ende slachte ende berderde : Ick ben gekomen op Dat sy het leben hebben ende oberbloedt hebben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">The thief cometh not, but for to steal, and to kill, and to destroy: I am come that they might have life, and that they might have it more abundantly.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">盜賊來，無非要偷竊，殺害，毀壞；我來了，是要叫羊得生命，並且得的更豐盛。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse11">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Tijau ta Tama-Kading ka mariang: Tama-k'ading ka ma-riang pou-ka koua ki kæuag-han tyn pou-bli ki ioekko.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Tijau ta TamaKading ka mariang: Tamak'ading ka mariang pouka koua ki kæuaghan tyn poubli ki ioekko.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ick ben De goede Nerder de goede Nerder stelt sijn leben boor: de schapen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">I am the good shepherd: the good shepherd giveth his life for the sheep.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我是好牧人；好牧人為羊捨命。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse12">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ra mou-varugh ki dæugh ka assi tama-k'ading, ka assi tæ'i-ioekko, irou kmytta ki ierrou-an ki tama-mahkakan ki ioekko, da-rang-en tyn ta ioekko, ka yl pout-ten tyn-da: ka miäkkub ta tama-mahkakan pa-pa-vavouhak ki ioekko.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ra mouvarugh ki dæugh ka assi tamak'ading, ka assi tæ'iioekko, irou kmytta ki ierrouan ki tamamahkakan ki ioekko, darangen tyn ta ioekko, ka yl poutten tynda: ka miäkkub ta tamamahkakan papavavouhak ki ioekko.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Maer de huerlingh ende Die geen Nerder en is wiens De schapen niet engen en zijn siet Den wolf komen ende berlaet desechapen ende bliedt : ende De wolf grijpise ende berstoyt de schapen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But he that is an hireling, and not the shepherd, whose own the sheep are not, seeth the wolf coming, and leaveth the sheep, and fleeth: and the wolf catcheth them, and scattereth the sheep.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">若是雇工，不是牧人，羊也不是他自己的，他看見狼來，就撇下羊逃走；狼抓住羊，趕散了羊群。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse13">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ilpout ta mou-va-rugh ki dæugh, alei ka'ou-var'g-han tynta dæugh, ka assi tyn 'illig-hin ta ioekko.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ilpout ta mouvarugh ki dæugh, alei ka'ouvar'ghan tynta dæugh, ka assi tyn 'illighin ta ioekko.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende de huerligh bliedt obermits hy een huerlinghhuerligh is ende en heeft geen sorge boor de schapen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">The hireling fleeth, because he is an hireling, and careth not for the sheep.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">雇工逃走，因他是雇工，並不顧念羊。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse14">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ti jau ta Tama-K'ading ka mariang: ka kmalang-koh ki a-jau, ka k'alang-'n-app-oh ki a-jau.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ti jau ta TamaK'ading ka mariang: ka kmalangkoh ki ajau, ka k'alang'nappoh ki ajau.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ick ben de goede HerDer: ende ick kenne De mijne ende worde ban De Mijne ghekent.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">I am the good shepherd, and know my sheep, and am known of mine.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我是好牧人；我認識我的羊，我的羊也認識我，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse15">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Mama ka K'alang-in koh ki Rama, ( komma-hynna ) kma-lang-app 'oh ti R ama-an: ka pou-kakoua-koh ki kuag-an-nau pæu-bli ki ioekko.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Mama ka K'alangin koh ki Rama, ( kommahynna ) kmalangapp 'oh ti R amaan: ka poukakouakoh ki kuagannau pæubli ki ioekko.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Gelijckerwijs De DaDer my kent (alfoo) kenne ick oock Den Dader : ende ick stelle mijn leben boor De schapen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">As the Father knoweth me, even so know I the Father: and I lay down my life for the sheep.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">正如父認識我，我也認識父一樣；並且我為羊捨命。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse16">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Akoume' app'-oh ki ioek-koka pani, kaassi na æræh kat-ta: ad-eil-appa-mau ta anna: ka millingigh-ah ki yngau-au, ka saisat-al-ato k'anna ka ioeag-han, sasat-al-appa ki Tama ka-ding.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Akoume' app'oh ki ioekkoka pani, kaassi na æræh katta: adeilappamau ta anna: ka millingighah ki yngauau, ka saisatalato k'anna ka ioeaghan, sasatalappa ki Tama kading.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ick hebbe noch andere schapen Die ban Desen stal niet en zijn : Die moet ick toebrengen: ende sy sullen mijne stemme hooren enyh het sal worden een kundde (ende) een Herder.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And other sheep I have, which are not of this fold: them also I must bring, and they shall hear my voice; and there shall be one fold, and one shepherd.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我另外有羊，不是這圈裏的；我必須領他們來，他們也要聽我的聲音，並且要合成一群，歸一個牧人了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse17">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Alei ki anna kavæ'angs-en-koh ki R ama, ka pou-ka koua-koh ki kuag-han-au, tou a-lijk koug-ei-mau mara ki atta.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Alei ki anna kavæ'angsenkoh ki R ama, ka pouka kouakoh ki kuaghanau, tou alijk kougeimau mara ki atta.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Daerom heeft my De Dader lief obermits ick mijn lebben aflegge op dat ick het selbe wederom neme.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Therefore doth my Father love me, because I lay down my life, that I might take it again.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我父愛我；因我將命捨去，好再取回來。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse18">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Assi mæ'eumia ki atta ta ti mamang jau-an, ré sykkoun-noung-koh ki atta pou-koua: a-kou-ligh-koh tou pou-kouan ki atta, akou il'gh-app-'oh tou i-lijkkoug-han ki atta. Sou katta ki na pahkou-sasou ni-'ara'-au ti Ram'an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Assi mæ'eumia ki atta ta ti mamang jauan, ré sykkounnoungkoh ki atta poukoua: akoulighkoh tou poukouan ki atta, akou il'ghapp'oh tou ilijkkoughan ki atta. Sou katta ki na pahkousasou ni'ara'au ti Ram'an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Niemandt en neemt het selbe ban my maer ick legge het ban my selbe af: ick hebbe macht Het selbe af te leggen ende hebbe macht 't selbe wederem te nemen. Dit gebod hebbe ick ban mij: nen Dader ontfangen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">No man taketh it from me, but I lay it down of myself. I have power to lay it down, and I have power to take it again. This commandment have I received of my Father.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">沒有人奪我的命去，是我自己捨的。我有權柄捨了，也有權柄取回來。這是我從我父所受的命令。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse19">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ma-mæu-douh'a-ato mi-latasou kiJoden, alei ki sou k'atta.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata mamæudouh'aato milatasou kiJoden, alei ki sou k'atta.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Daer Wiert dan weDerom tweedracht Onder De Joden om deser woorden wille.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">There was a division therefore again among the Jews for these sayings.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">猶太人為這些話又起了紛爭。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse20">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka mabatoung neini-æn ta ni-k'ma, Akou Littou tyni-æn, ka sa-dar'man-appa ki ryh: mang ka millingig-kamou tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka mabatoung neiniæn ta nik'ma, Akou Littou tyniæn, ka sadar'manappa ki ryh: mang ka millingigkamou tyniæn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende bele ban haer seyseyden Hy heeft den Duybel ende is uyt sijnmigh mat Hoort ghy hem :</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And many of them said, He hath a devil, and is mad; why hear ye him?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">內中有好些人說：＂他是被鬼附着，而且瘋了，為甚麼聽他呢？＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse21">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'ma ta rarouma, Assi sou k'anna ki 'ou-al Littou-in: yl pough kauwa ta Littou pa-rkyl-lat ki mavoutta?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Nik'ma ta rarouma, Assi sou k'anna ki 'oual Littouin: yl pough kauwa ta Littou parkyllat ki mavoutta?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Andere seyden Dit en zijn geen woorden eens besetenen: kan oock De Duybel Der blinden oogen openen?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Others said, These are not the words of him that hath a devil. Can a devil open the eyes of the blind?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">又有人說：＂這不是鬼附之人所說的話。鬼豈能叫瞎子的眼睛開了呢？＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse22">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka wæ'i-ato ki 'ou-vava-toug-han ki ni-pæi-væ-'æu-in ki Kouva ki tatam'd-den tou Jerusalem, ka kidi-ato ki amyg-han.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka wæ'iato ki 'ouvavatoughan ki nipæivæ'æuin ki Kouva ki tatam'dden tou Jerusalem, ka kidiato ki amyghan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende het was Het feest Der ber nieu winge Des Tempels te Jerusalem ende het Was winter</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And it was at Jerusalem the feast of the dedication, and it was winter.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">在耶路撒冷有修殿節，是冬天的時候。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse23">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-mou-naunang ta ti Jesus tou Kouva ki ta tam'd-dem ki Alid, tou doumma ki talagh ki tatam'd-den ti Salomon.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka nimounaunang ta ti Jesus tou Kouva ki ta tam'ddem ki Alid, tou doumma ki talagh ki tatam'dden ti Salomon.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende Jesus wandelDe in Den Tempel in het boorhof Salomons.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And Jesus walked in the temple in Solomon's porch.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌在殿裏所羅門的廊下行走。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse24">
        <FORM kindOf="original">. Annata ni-'ou-ryttoung-en ta teni ki Joden k'ma tyni-æn, Makka-mang makka-dallia ka pa-rkau-au-'mhou ta vatti-jan? Hei-rou ti Christus-kow, pou-pænæ'i-kame bana.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">. Annata ni'ouryttoungen ta teni ki Joden k'ma tyniæn, Makkamang makkadallia ka parkauau'mhou ta vattijan? Heirou ti Christuskow, poupænæ'ikame bana.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">De Joden dan omringhden Hem ende seyden tot hemn Hoe lange houd ghy onse ziele op : indien ghy De Christus zijt feght het ons bry uyt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then came the Jews round about him, and said unto him, How long dost thou make us to doubt? If thou be the Christ, tell us plainly.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">猶太人圍着他，說：＂你叫我們猶疑不定到幾時呢？你若是基督，就明明地告訴我們。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse25">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-mattæ'i-v'-lli ta ti Jesus neini-æn, Pattæ'i-ka han-ato-mau-kamou, ra assi-kamou tna-msing. Ryngei k'anna ka pam't-ten-nau tou Nanang ki Rama-au, annata gmail jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Nimattæ'iv'lli ta ti Jesus neiniæn, Pattæ'ika hanatomaukamou, ra assikamou tnamsing. Ryngei k'anna ka pam'ttennau tou Nanang ki Ramaau, annata gmail jauan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Jesus antwoordde haer Ick heb't u geseght ende sy en gelooft Het niet, De wercken die ick Doe in Den Name mijns Daders die getuygen ban my.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus answered them, I told you, and ye believed not: the works that I do in my Father's name, they bear witness of me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌回答說：＂我已經告訴你們，你們不信。我奉我父之名所行的事可以為我作見證；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse26">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ra ymoumi ta assi tna-'mfing, alei ka assi-kamou ioek-ko-au, mama ki ni-pa-sousou-en-nau ymoumi-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ra ymoumi ta assi tna'mfing, alei ka assikamou ioekkoau, mama ki nipasousouennau ymoumiæn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Maer ghy-lieden en geloeft niet Want ghy zijt niet ban mijne schapen geliick ich u geseght hebbe.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But ye believe not, because ye are not of my sheep, as I said unto you.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">只是你們不信，因為你們不是我的羊。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse27">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Millingigh ta ioekko-au ki yngau-au, ka kmalang-koh nei-ni-æn, ka mæ'æu-ugh ta neni jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Millingigh ta ioekkoau ki yngauau, ka kmalangkoh neiniæn, ka mæ'æuugh ta neni jauan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Mijne schapen hooren mijne stemme ende ick kenne deselbe ende sy bolgen my.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">My sheep hear my voice, and I know them, and they follow me:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我的羊聽我的聲音，我也認識他們，他們也跟着我。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse28">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka phæ-en-nau neini-æn ta kæuag-han ka myhkakoua myddarynnough:ka assi tau-rum-ma-ah ta neni tou 'yhkakou -an myddaryhnough, ka asfibihyt-ah ta ti mamang hmi-mourang neini-æn tou rima-au.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka phæennau neiniæn ta kæuaghan ka myhkakoua myddarynnough:ka assi taurummaah ta neni tou 'yhkakou an myddaryhnough, ka asfibihytah ta ti mamang hmimourang neiniæn tou rimaau.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">EnEnde ick gebe haer Vet eeuwige leben : ende sy en sullen niet berloren gaen in Der eeuwigheydt ende niemant en sal deselbe uyt mijne handt rucken.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And I give unto them eternal life; and they shall never perish, neither shall any man pluck them out of my hand.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我又賜給他們永生；他們永不滅亡，誰也不能從我手裏把他們奪去。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse29">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Kama-au ka ni-pi'æ nei-ni-anjau-an, ta si-ourou maligh ki ynmud, ka asfi hmi-lpough ta ti mamang hmi-mourang nei-ni-æn tou rima ki Rama-au.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Kamaau ka nipi'æ neinianjauan, ta siourou maligh ki ynmud, ka asfi hmilpough ta ti mamang hmimourang neiniæn tou rima ki Ramaau.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Mijn Dader diese my gegeben heeft is meerder Dan alle ende niemandt en kanse (rucken uyt De handt mijns Daders.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">My Father, which gave them me, is greater than all; and no man is able to pluck them out of my Father's hand.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我父把羊賜給我，他比萬有都大，誰也不能從我父手裏把他們奪去。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse30">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Tijau ki Rama-appa fas-sat-kame.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Tijau ki Ramaappa fassatkame.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ick ende De Dader zijn een.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">I and my Father are one.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我與父原為一。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse31">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-dmaugh ta Joden mi-la ki vahtou ka cyt-an-nei tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata nidmaugh ta Joden mila ki vahtou ka cytannei tyniæn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">De Joden Dan namen wederom steenen op om Hem te steenigen</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then the Jews took up stones again to stone him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">猶太人又拿起石頭來要打他。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse32">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-mattæ'i-vili ta ti Jesus neini-æn, Madagh ki ryngei ka matiang ta na paka kytta-au y-moumi-æn ki Rama-au: alei ki ringei kamang ta cyt-tei-moumi ki vahtou jau-an?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Nimattæ'ivili ta ti Jesus neiniæn, Madagh ki ryngei ka matiang ta na paka kyttaau ymoumiæn ki Ramaau: alei ki ringei kamang ta cytteimoumi ki vahtou jauan?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Jesus antwoordde haer Ick hebbe u bele treslicke wercken getoont ban mijn Dader: om welck werck ban die steenight ghy my :</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus answered them, Many good works have I shewed you from my Father; for which of those works do ye stone me?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌對他們說：＂我從父顯出許多善事給你們看，你們是為哪一件拿石頭打我呢？＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse33">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-mattæ'i-vlli tyni-n ta Joden, kma, Assi-kame smyt'-a' ki vahtou ymhou-an alei ki ryn-gei ka mariang, ré alei-appa ki ba' g-hen, alei ka kzeuloung kow ta ymhou, pou-madou-kow pou-Alid ymhou-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Nimattæ'ivlli tynin ta Joden, kma, Assikame smyt'a' ki vahtou ymhouan alei ki ryngei ka mariang, ré aleiappa ki ba' ghen, alei ka kzeuloung kow ta ymhou, poumadoukow pouAlid ymhouan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">De Joden antwoorden hem seggende Wy en steenigen u niet ober (eenigh) goet werk maer ober (Gods)lasteringe ende om dat ghy een mensche zijnde U selben Godt maeckt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">The Jews answered him, saying, For a good work we stone thee not; but for blasphemy; and because that thou, being a man, makest thyself God.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">猶太人回答說：＂我們不是為善事拿石頭打你，是為你說僭妄的話；又為你是個人，反將自己當作上帝。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse34">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-mattæ'i-v'llita ti Jesus neini-æn, Assi kauwa ni-sa-soulat-ten tou Tatouhko-oumi, Ni-pa-fousou-en-nau ka Ali-alid-kamou?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Nimattæ'iv'llita ti Jesus neiniæn, Assi kauwa nisasoulatten tou Tatouhkooumi, Nipafousouennau ka Alialidkamou?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Jesus antwoordde haer En isse niet geschreben in uwe Wet Ick hebbe geseght ghy zijt Goden?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus answered them, Is it not written in your law, I said, Ye are gods?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：＂你們的律法上豈不是寫着＂我曾說你們是神＂嗎？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse35">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Heirou Alid k'ma (ta Tatouhko) neini-æn, ka ni-pou-pænæ-'in ta sou ki Alid, ra assi 'ǣæu-lpoug-in mææu kakierrigh ta na sa soulat:</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Heirou Alid k'ma (ta Tatouhko) neiniæn, ka nipoupænæ'in ta sou ki Alid, ra assi 'ǣæulpougin mææu kakierrigh ta na sa soulat:</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">InIndien (de Wet) die Goden ghenaemt Heeft tot welcke het woort Godts geschiet is ende De Schrift niet en kan gebroken worden :</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">If he called them gods, unto whom the word of God came, and the scripture cannot be broken;</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">經上的話是不能廢的；若那些承受上帝道的人尚且稱為神，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse36">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Mattæ'i-komma-hynna-kamou (jau-an) ka ni-pa-sa-nni ki Rama (pa-si-touk kad) madin-gi tou næi, barugh-kow (ki Alid), alei ka ni-pa-sousou-en-nau, A-lak-koh ki Alid?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Mattæ'ikommahynnakamou (jauan) ka nipasanni ki Rama (pasitouk kad) madingi tou næi, barughkow (ki Alid), alei ka nipasousouennau, Alakkoh ki Alid?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Seght ghy lieden (tot my,) Dien De Dader gheheylight ende in De werelt gesonden heeft ghy lastert (God), om Dat ick geseght hebbe ick ben Godts Sone?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Say ye of him, whom the Father hath sanctified, and sent into the world, Thou blasphemest; because I said, I am the Son of God?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">父所分別為聖、又差到世間來的，他自稱是上帝的兒子，你們還向他說＂你說僭妄的話＂嗎？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse37">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Heirou assi-koh pamut ki pei-raryngeiki Rama-au, ynna tna-msing jau-an:</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Heirou assikoh pamut ki peiraryngeiki Ramaau, ynna tnamsing jauan:</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Indien ick niet en doe De wercken mijns Daders so en gelooft my niet :</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">If I do not the works of my Father, believe me not.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我若不行我父的事，你們就不必信我；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse38">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Heirou-ra pam't-ten-nau ta anna, rou assi-kamou tna-msing jau-an, annata tna-msing-appa ki ryngei: alei ka kmalang-ah-ka-mou ka tna-msing-ah-kamou ka i-tou-koua ta Rama jou-an, ka i-tou-koua app-'oh tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Heiroura pam'ttennau ta anna, rou assikamou tnamsing jauan, annata tnamsingappa ki ryngei: alei ka kmalangahkamou ka tnamsingahkamou ka itoukoua ta Rama jouan, ka itoukoua app'oh tyniæn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Maer indien ickse doe ende so ghy my niet en geloobet so gelooft de wercken: op Dat ghy menght bekennen ende gelooben Dat De Dader in my is ende ick in hem.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But if I do, though ye believe not me, believe the works: that ye may know, and believe, that the Father is in me, and I in him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我若行了，你們縱然不信我，也當信這些事，叫你們又知道又明白父在我裏面，我也在父裏面。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse39">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-ki'ym nein mila ki touroung-an-ei tyni-æn, ra ni-sahtatauwagh ta teni ki rima nein.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata niki'ym nein mila ki tourounganei tyniæn, ra nisahtatauwagh ta teni ki rima nein.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Sy sochen dan weDerom Hem te grijpen ende hy ontgingh uyt Hare handt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Therefore they sought again to take him: but he escaped out of their hand,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們又要拿他，他卻逃出他們的手走了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse40">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-sa-lyk kough mou-arough ki Jordaan tou i-tou-kou-'an ka ni-æuloug-han si-ourou ti Joannes, ka ni-pæyllili-en tyn hynna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka nisalyk kough mouarough ki Jordaan tou itoukou'an ka niæuloughan siourou ti Joannes, ka nipæyllilien tyn hynna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende hy gingh wederom ober den Jordaen tot De plaetse Daer Joannes eerst doopte ende hy bleef aldaer.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And went away again beyond Jordan into the place where John at first baptized; and there he abode.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌又往約旦河外去，到了約翰起初施洗的地方，就住在那裏。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse41">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka mabatoung ta ni-ierroua tyni-æn, kma, Assi ni-pa-mut ta ti Joannes ki pou-kidi-en: râ ka ma-mang ka ni-pattæ'i-mymmi'-en ti Joannes tyni-æn maymmud ma-tiktik k'anna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka mabatoung ta niierroua tyniæn, kma, Assi nipamut ta ti Joannes ki poukidien: râ ka mamang ka nipattæ'imymmi'en ti Joannes tyniæn maymmud matiktik k'anna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende bele quamen tot hem ende seyden Joannes en Dede wel geen teeckenen: maer alles dat Joannes ban desen seyde Was waer</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And many resorted unto him, and said, John did no miracle: but all things that John spake of this man were true.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">有許多人來到他那裏。他們說：＂約翰一件神蹟沒有行過，但約翰指着這人所說的一切話都是真的。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse42">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka mabatoung ta ni-tna-msing hynna tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka mabatoung ta nitnamsing hynna tyniæn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">EnEnde bele geloofden aldaer in hem.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And many believed on him there.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">在那裏，信耶穌的人就多了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
</TEXT>
