<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEXT id="Siraya_Dutch_John_Chapter21" xml:lang="fos" source="Siraya Bible, John gospel" copyright="public domain" citation="Gravius, Daniël. 1661. Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa. Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang. Amsterdam: Michiel Hartogh." BibTeX_citation="@book{Gravius1661,&#10;  author    = {Gravius, Daniël},&#10;  year      = {1661},&#10;  title     = {Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa},&#10;  note      = {Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang},&#10;  address   = {Amsterdam},&#10;  publisher = {Michiel Hartogh}&#10;}" dialect="Siraya">
    <S id="verse1">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Si-æ'æugh ki anna ni - pa-kytta ta ti Jesus mi-la ty-ni-æn ki Pahtatæutæu-han tou vaoung ki Tiberias. Ka ni pa-kitt'-an tyn komma hynna tyni-æn:</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Si-æ'æugh ki anna ni - pa-kytta ta ti Jesus mi-la ty-ni-æn ki Pahtatæutæu-han tou vaoung ki Tiberias. Ka ni pa-kitt'-an tyn komma hynna tyni-æn:</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">. Na desen openbaerde Jesus hem selben wederom den Discipelen aen de Zee ban Tiberias. Ende hy hy openbaerde hem aldus:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">After these things Jesus shewed himself again to the disciples at the sea of Tiberias; and on this wise shewed he himself.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">這些事以後，耶穌在提比哩亞海邊又向門徒顯現。他怎樣顯現記在下面：</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse2">
        <FORM kindOf="original">I-tou-saal ta ti Simon Petrus, ti Thomas ka si-ouä Didymus, ti Nathanael ka makka Kana tou Galilea, ta alalak ti Zebedeus, ki rarouh'-appa ka pani ki Pahtatæutæu-han tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">I-tou-saal ta ti Simon Petrus, ti Thomas ka si-ouä Didymus, ti Nathanael ka makka Kana tou Galilea, ta alalak ti Zebedeus, ki rarouh'-appa ka pani ki Pahtatæutæu-han tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Daer waren te samen Simon Petrus ende Thomas geseght Didymus ende Nathanael Die ban Cana in Galilea was ende De [sonen] Zebedei ende twee andere ban sijne Discipelen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">There were together Simon Peter, and Thomas called Didymus, and Nathanael of Cana in Galilee, and the sons of Zebedee, and two other of his disciples.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">有西門‧彼得和稱為低土馬的多馬，並加利利的迦拿人拿但業，還有西庇太的兩個兒子，又有兩個門徒，都在一處。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse3">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-k'ma ta ti Simon Petrus neini-æn, Mou-koua-ah-koh mou-dillum. Ni-kma ta neni tyni-æn, Tau-lam-ah-kame ym-hou-an. Ka ni-tpæpænæh ta neni madis maddakkin tou avangh, ka assi ni-mara ta neni ki mamang makka-sat ki euvanan k'anna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-k'ma ta ti Simon Petrus neini-æn, Mou-koua-ah-koh mou-dillum. Ni-kma ta neni tyni-æn, Tau-lam-ah-kame ym-hou-an. Ka ni-tpæpænæh ta neni madis maddakkin tou avangh, ka assi ni-mara ta neni ki mamang makka-sat ki euvanan k'anna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Simon Petrus seyde tot haer Ick gae bisschen. Sy seyden tot Hem Wy gaen oock Met u. Sy gingen uyt ende traden terstondt in Het schip ende in Dien nacht en bingen sy niets.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Simon Peter saith unto them, I go a fishing. They say unto him, We also go with thee. They went forth, and entered into a ship immediately; and that night they caught nothing.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">西門‧彼得對他們說：「我打魚去。」他們說：「我們也和你同去。」他們就出去，上了船；那一夜並沒有打着甚麼。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse4">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka mæræmæh-ato ma-dama, ni-myttouhko ta ti Jesus tou karivil: râ assi mou-mhga ta Pahtatæutæu-han ka ti Jesus ta ti anna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka mæræmæh-ato ma-dama, ni-myttouhko ta ti Jesus tou karivil: râ assi mou-mhga ta Pahtatæutæu-han ka ti Jesus ta ti anna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende als Het nu morgen-stondt geworden was stont Jesus op Den oeber: doch de Discipelen en wisten niet Dat Het Jesus was.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But when the morning was now come, Jesus stood on the shore: but the disciples knew not that it was Jesus.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">天將亮的時候，耶穌站在岸上，門徒卻不知道是耶穌。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse5">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-kma ta ti Jesus neini-æn, Kallalak, ä-ou-si-ka-mou kauwa ki avovok ka 'ou-pa-para mavok? Ni-mattæ'i-v'lli tyni-æn, Ä-'ou-si-kame.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-kma ta ti Jesus neini-æn, Kallalak, ä-ou-si-ka-mou kauwa ki avovok ka 'ou-pa-para mavok? Ni-mattæ'i-v'lli tyni-æn, Ä-'ou-si-kame.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jefus Dan seyde tot haer Kinderkens hebt ghy niet eenige toe-spijse : Sy antwoordden hem Neen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then Jesus saith unto them, Children, have ye any meat? They answered him, No.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌就對他們說：「小子！你們有吃的沒有？」他們回答說：「沒有。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse6">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'ma ta teni neini-æn, Smaki-raloumm-â ki sa-samlid smaki-ouwal ki avang, ka mara-ah-kamou. Annata ni-s'aki-ra-loum-men nein, ka assi nein hi-Ipough-in vihit ta anna, alei ki ta-pang ki't' hung.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-k'ma ta teni neini-æn, Smaki-raloumm-â ki sa-samlid smaki-ouwal ki avang, ka mara-ah-kamou. Annata ni-s'aki-ra-loum-men nein, ka assi nein hi-Ipough-in vihit ta anna, alei ki ta-pang ki't' hung.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende hy seyde tot haer Werpt het net aen De rechterzijde ban Het Schip ende ghy sult binden. Sp wierpen het dan ende en konden het selbe niet Meer trecken ban wegen de menighte Der bisschen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And he said unto them, Cast the net on the right side of the ship, and ye shall find. They cast therefore, and now they were not able to draw it for the multitude of fishes.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：「你們把網撒在船的右邊，就必得着。」他們便撒下網去，竟拉不上來了，因為魚甚多。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse7">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata Pahtatæutæu-han k'anna ka kava'angs-en ti Jesus: ni-K'ma ti Petrus-an, Meirangta ti atta. Irou kamillingigh ta ti-Simon Petrus ka Meirangta ti atta, ni æht-tin tyn ta pa-haalap-pen tynmammia, ('alei kKa mananata teni) kani-pou-raloum tyni-an pou-vaoung.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata Pahtatæutæu-han k'anna ka kava'angs-en ti Jesus: ni-K'ma ti Petrus-an, Meirangta ti atta. Irou kamillingigh ta ti-Simon Petrus ka Meirangta ti atta, ni æht-tin tyn ta pa-haalap-pen tynmammia, ('alei kKa mananata teni) kani-pou-raloum tyni-an pou-vaoung.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> De Discipel dan welcken Jesus lief hadde seyde tot Petrum Het is de Herre. Simon Petrus Dan hoorenDe dat het De Neere was omgordde Het opper-kleet (want hy was naeckt) ende wierp hem-selben in de Zee.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Therefore that disciple whom Jesus loved saith unto Peter, It is the Lord. Now when Simon Peter heard that it was the Lord, he girt his fisher's coat unto him, (for he was naked,) and did cast himself into the sea.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌所愛的那門徒對彼得說：「是主！」那時西門‧彼得赤着身子，一聽見是主，就束上一件外衣，跳在海裏。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse8">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka Pahtatæutau-han ka ra-rouma ni-ierroua Jam ki avang (nda assi madallia neini-æn ta pourough rouha lava kæætoug-han kina rarpung ki pariou) ka vihit-ten nein ta sasamlid ka yd-dad-'ing-en.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka Pahtatæutau-han ka ra-rouma ni-ierroua Jam ki avang (nda assi madallia neini-æn ta pourough rouha lava kæætoug-han kina rarpung ki pariou) ka vihit-ten nein ta sasamlid ka yd-dad-'ing-en.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende De andere Discipelen quamen met het scheepken (want sy en waren niet berre ban het lant maer ontrent twee hondert ellen) slepende Het net met De bisschen. </TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And the other disciples came in a little ship; (for they were not far from land, but as it were two hundred cubits,) dragging the net with fishes.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">其餘的門徒離岸不遠，約有二百肘，就在小船上把那網魚拉過來。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse9">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka ni-mou-pourough ta neni, ni-kytt'an nein ta ni-at-ta-kou-'an ki apoei ka væ', ka pakah-halap-pan ki't' hungh ki pasul.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka ni-mou-pourough ta neni, ni-kytt'an nein ta ni-at-ta-kou-'an ki apoei ka væ', ka pakah-halap-pan ki't' hungh ki pasul.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Als sy Dan aen 't landt gegaen waren sagen sy een kood byer liggen ende bisch Daer op liggen ende broodt</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">As soon then as they were come to land, they saw a fire of coals there, and fish laid thereon, and bread.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們上了岸，就看見那裏有炭火，上面有魚，又有餅。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse10">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'ma ta tiJesus neini-æn,'Ad-dei ki 't' hungh k'anna ka ni-'ara-oumi hnyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-k'ma ta tiJesus neini-æn,'Ad-dei ki 't' hungh k'anna ka ni-'ara-oumi hnyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus seyde tot haer Brenght ban de bisschen Die ghy nu gebangen hebt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus saith unto them, Bring of the fish which ye have now caught.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌對他們說：「把剛才打的魚拿幾條來。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse11">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-mou-vavau ta tiSimon Petrus vihit ki sa-samlid pou-pourough kamatmoei ki 't' hung ka irirang sat kæ'ætoug - han 'æb ki rymma kytti-æn 'æb ki tou-ro: moukouna ka dagh ka kma-hynna, ashi ni-'k-hyt ta sa-samlid.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-mou-vavau ta tiSimon Petrus vihit ki sa-samlid pou-pourough kamatmoei ki 't' hung ka irirang sat kæ'ætoug - han 'æb ki rymma kytti-æn 'æb ki tou-ro: moukouna ka dagh ka kma-hynna, ashi ni-'k-hyt ta sa-samlid.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Simon Petrus gingh op ende trock het net op Het lant bol groote bischen [tot] hondert drie ende bijstigh:onDe hoewel'er so bele waren so en scheurde het net niet.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Simon Peter went up, and drew the net to land full of great fishes, an hundred and fifty and three: and for all there were so many, yet was not the net broken.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">西門‧彼得就去，把網拉到岸上。那網滿了大魚，共一百五十三條；魚雖這樣多，網卻沒有破。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse12">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus neini-æn, Mou-kouw'-appa hia, mi-ran-ga-ranga mavok. Ka mangala ta ti-mamang ki Pahta-tutæu-hantmaligh tyni-æn, Ti mang kow? ra'ou-mhgan nein ka Meirang ta ti atta.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus neini-æn, Mou-kouw'-appa hia, mi-ran-ga-ranga mavok. Ka mangala ta ti-mamang ki Pahta-tutæu-hantmaligh tyni-æn, Ti mang kow? ra'ou-mhgan nein ka Meirang ta ti atta.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus seyde tot haer Komt herwaerts houdt Het middaghmael. Ende niemant ban de Discipelen en durfde hem bragen Wie zijt ghy : wewetende dat het de Heere was.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus saith unto them, Come and dine. And none of the disciples durst ask him, Who art thou? knowing that it was the Lord.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：「你們來吃早飯。」門徒中沒有一個敢問他：「你是誰？」因為知道是主。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse13">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-mou-koua ta ti Jesus ka ni-'ara tyn ta paoul ka ni-phæn tyn nei-ni-æn mahkaulaulau ki t'hungh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-mou-koua ta ti Jesus ka ni-'ara tyn ta paoul ka ni-phæn tyn nei-ni-æn mahkaulaulau ki t'hungh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus dan quam ende nam het broodt ende gaf het haer ende den bisch desgelijcks.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus then cometh, and taketh bread, and giveth them, and fish likewise.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌就來拿餅和魚給他們。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse14">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ka tatouro-ato k'anna ki ni-pa-k'yt-t'-an ti Jesus tyni-æn ki Pahtatæutæu-han tyn, si-ǣæugh ki ni-pæ-æh-pit-ten tyni-æn ki ni-kapatei-en tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ka tatouro-ato k'anna ki ni-pa-k'yt-t'-an ti Jesus tyni-æn ki Pahtatæutæu-han tyn, si-ǣæugh ki ni-pæ-æh-pit-ten tyni-æn ki ni-kapatei-en tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Dit was nu de derde-mael dat Jesus sijnen Discipelen geopenbaert is na dat hy ban den dooden obgeweckt Was.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">This is now the third time that Jesus shewed himself to his disciples, after that he was risen from the dead.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌從死裏復活以後，向門徒顯現，這是第三次。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse15">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka mi-kaha ta neni mi-ran-ga-ranga mavok, ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus ti Simon Petrus-an, Simon [alak] ti Jona, ma-saoun kow kauwa mavæ'angö jau-an neini-æn katta? Ni-kma tyni-æn, Ha hei, Meirang, kavanna-en-hou ta ka-væ'ango-en-au ymhou-am Ni-k'ma tyni-æn, [Kading-au rou] pa-kan-au ta patak ki joekko-au.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka mi-kaha ta neni mi-ran-ga-ranga mavok, ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus ti Simon Petrus-an, Simon [alak] ti Jona, ma-saoun kow kauwa mavæ'angö jau-an neini-æn katta? Ni-kma tyni-æn, Ha hei, Meirang, kavanna-en-hou ta ka-væ'ango-en-au ymhou-am Ni-k'ma tyni-æn, [Kading-au rou] pa-kan-au ta patak ki joekko-au.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Doe sy Dan het middaghmael gehouden hadden seyde Jek tot Simon Detrus Simon sus [soon], hebt ghy my lieber dan dese Hy seyde tot hem Ja Heere ghy weet dat ick u lief hebbe. Hy seyde tot hem Weyt mijne lanuneren.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">So when they had dined, Jesus saith to Simon Peter, Simon, son of Jonas, lovest thou me more than these? He saith unto him, Yea, Lord; thou knowest that I love thee. He saith unto him, Feed my lambs.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們吃完了早飯，耶穌對西門‧彼得說：「約翰的兒子西門，你愛我比這些更深嗎？」彼得說：「主啊，是的，你知道我愛你。」耶穌對他說：「你餵養我的小羊。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse16">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-mattæ'i-la-tyni-æn tou ka-rarouha, Simon alak ti Jona, mavæ'ango kow kauwa jau-an? Ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Ha-hei, Meirang, kavanna-en hou ta ka-væ'angö-en-au ymhou-an. Ni k'ma tyni-æn, K'ading-au rou pa-k'an-au ta-joekko-au.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-mattæ'i-la-tyni-æn tou kararouha, Simon alak ti Jona, mavæ'ango kow kauwa jau-an? Ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Ha-hei, Meirang, kavanna-en hou ta ka-væ'angö-en-au ymhou-an. Ni k'ma tyni-æn, K'ading-au rou pa-k'an-au ta-joekko-au.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Hy seyde wederom tot hem ten tweeden mael : Simon Jona [soon], hebt ghy my lief : Hy seyde tot hem Jae Heere ghy weet dat ick u lief hebbe. Hy seyde tot hem Nocht mijne schapen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">He saith to him again the second time, Simon, son of Jonas, lovest thou me? He saith unto him, Yea, Lord; thou knowest that I love thee. He saith unto him, Feed my sheep.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌第二次又對他說：「約翰的兒子西門，你愛我嗎？」彼得說：「主啊，是的，你知道我愛你。」耶穌說：「你牧養我的羊。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse17">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'ma tyni-æn tou katatou-rou, Simon alak ti Jona, mavæ'ango-kow kauwa jau-an? Ka mavoulas ta ti Petrus, ka pa-sousou-en tyn tyni-æn tou kata-tourou; Mavæ'angö kow kauwa jau-an? ka ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Meirang, mou-ätigh' kow mau-mhga ki mamang, kavanna-en-hou ka kavæ'angö-en-au ymhou-an. Ni kma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Kading-au rou pakan-au ta joekko-au.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-k'ma tyni-æn tou katatou-rou, Simon alak ti Jona, mavæ'ango-kow kauwa jau-an? Ka mavoulas ta ti Petrus, ka pa-sousou-en tyn tyni-æn tou kata-tourou; Mavæ'angö kow kauwa jau-an? ka ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Meirang, mou-ätigh' kow mau-mhga ki mamang, kavanna-en-hou ka kavæ'angö-en-au ymhou-an. Ni kma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Kading-au rou pakan-au ta joekko-au.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Hy seyde tot hem zean derden-mael Simon Jona [soon], hebt ghy my lief : Petrus wierdt bedroft om dat hy ten derdenmael tot Hem seyde Hebt ghy my Lief : ende seyde tot hem Heere ghy weet alle dingen ghy weet Dat ick u lief hebbe. Jesus seyde tot hem Weydt mijne schapen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">He saith unto him the third time, Simon, son of Jonas, lovest thou me? Peter was grieved because he said unto him the third time, Lovest thou me? And he said unto him, Lord, thou knowest all things; thou knowest that I love thee. Jesus saith unto him, Feed my sheep.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">第三次對他說：「約翰的兒子西門，你愛我嗎？」彼得因為耶穌第三次對他說「你愛我嗎」，就憂愁，對耶穌說：「主啊，你是無所不知的；你知道我愛你。」耶穌說：「你餵養我的羊。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse18">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Missing, missing koun-au-kow, doe masaoun-appa kow rauwei, ni-ma-li-mado kow mæit ymhou-an, ka ni-mou-naunang tou mamang ka kamoei-en-hou: Irou-ra kæuh-mamou-âl-ato kow, sik-sik-ei-mhou ta rima-oho, ka-mait-ah ta pani ymhou-an mad tou assi-'mouhou kamoei-in.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Missing, missing koun-au-kow, doe masaoun-appa kow rauwei, ni-ma-li-mado kow mæit ymhou-an, ka ni-mou-naunang tou mamang ka kamoei-en-hou: Irou-ra kæuh-mamou-âl-ato kow, sik-sik-ei-mhou ta rima-oho, ka-mait-ah ta pani ymhou-an mad tou assi-'mouhou kamoei-in.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Doorwaer boorwaer segge ick u doe ghy jonger waert gorddet ghy selben ende wan: deldet waer ghy wildet : Maer wanneer ghy zult oudt geworden zijn soo sult ghy uwe handen uytstretstrecken ende een ander salu gorden ende brengen waer ghy niet en wilt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Verily, verily, I say unto thee, When thou wast young, thou girdest thyself, and walkedst whither thou wouldest: but when thou shalt be old, thou shalt stretch forth thy hands, and another shall gird thee, and carry thee whither thou wouldest not.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我實實在在地告訴你，你年少的時候，自己束上帶子，隨意往來；但年老的時候，你要伸出手來，別人要把你束上，帶你到不願意去的地方。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse19">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka pa-sousou-en tyn taatta, pou-kidi kisou kapatei-an ka mamei mang ka pouvavau-eih tyn ki kidi ta Alid. Irou ka mattæ'i-kaha ki atta, ni-k'ma tyni-æn, mææuug-a jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka pa-sousou-en tyn taatta, pou-kidi kisou kapatei-an ka mamei mang ka pouvavau-eih tyn ki kidi ta Alid. Irou ka mattæ'i-kaha ki atta, ni-k'ma tyni-æn, mææuug-a jau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende dit seyde Hy deteeckenende met Hoedanigen doodt hy Godt berheerlijcken soude. Ende dit ghelsproken hebbende seyde Hy tot hem bolght my.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">This spake he, signifying by what death he should glorify God. And when he had spoken this, he saith unto him, Follow me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">（耶穌說這話是指着彼得要怎樣死，榮耀上帝。）說了這話，就對他說：「你跟從我吧！」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse20">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka mæ'æu-doumma ta ti Petrus, ni-kytt'-an tyn ka mæ-'æuugh ta Pahtatæutæu-han kanna ka kavæ'-an-go-en, ka ni-mou-ohgo-appa rou hi-addou-doung-in tou aveu ti Jesus, kma, Meirang ti mang ta fsi-vanna-vanna-ah ymhou-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka mæ'æu-doumma ta ti Petrus, ni-kytt'-an tyn ka mæ-'æuugh ta Pahtatæutæu-han kanna ka kavæ'-an-go-en, ka ni-mou-ohgo-appa rou hi-addou-doung-in tou aveu ti Jesus, kma, Meirang ti mang ta fsi-vanna-vanna-ah ymhou-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende Petrus hem omkeerende sagh den Discipel bolgen welckhnu Jesus lief hadde Die oock in Het Abondtmael op sijne borst geballen was ende gesegt hadde Heere wie is't die u berraden sal.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then Peter, turning about, seeth the disciple whom Jesus loved following; which also leaned on his breast at supper, and said, Lord, which is he that betrayeth thee?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">彼得轉過來，看見耶穌所愛的那門徒跟着，（就是在晚飯的時候，靠着耶穌胸膛說：「主啊，賣你的是誰？」的那門徒。）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse21">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou kak'ytt-an ti Petrus ta timatta, ni-k'ma Jesus-an,M eirang-oumang-ah ta teni katta?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou kak'ytt-an ti Petrus ta timatta, ni-k'ma Jesus-an,M eirang-oumang-ah ta teni katta?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Als Petrus desen sagh seyde hy tot Jesum Heere maer wat [sal] dese ?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Peter seeing him saith to Jesus, Lord, and what shall this man do?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">彼得看見他，就問耶穌說：「主啊，這人將來如何？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse22">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Hei-rou mamoei koh ka maylli ta teni tou ki-di ki ierrarourou-an-au, mang-a mhou? Mæ æug-a ta ymhou jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Hei-rou mamoei koh ka maylli ta teni tou ki-di ki ierrarourou-an-au, mang-a mhou? Mæ æug-a ta ymhou jau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus seyde tot hem Indien ick wil dat Hy blijbe tot dat ick kome wat gaer het u aen? Dolght ghy my.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus saith unto him, If I will that he tarry till I come, what is that to thee? follow thou me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌對他說：「我若要他等到我來的時候，與你何干？你跟從我吧！」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse23">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-mæu-pnh ta sou katta tou tæ'i-appa-para, ka assi mapatei-ah ta Pahtatæutu-han kanna. Ka assi ni-pasousou-en ti Jesus, kiassi tyn kapatei-eih: ra att'-appa, heirou mamoei-koh ka maylli ta teni tou kidi ki ierrarou-row'-en-au, manga' mhou?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-mæu-pnh ta sou katta tou tæ'i-appa-para, ka assi mapatei-ah ta Pahtatæutu-han kanna. Ka assi ni-pasousou-en ti Jesus, kiassi tyn kapatei-eih: ra att'-appa, heirou mamoei-koh ka maylli ta teni tou kidi ki ierrarou-row'-en-au, manga' mhou?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Dit woort dan ginugh uyt onder de broederen Dat dese Discipel niet en soude sterben. Ende Jesus en hadde tot hem niet geseght Dat Hy niet sterben en soude : maer indien ick Wil Dat hy blijbe tot dat ick home wat gehaet het u aen?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then went this saying abroad among the brethren, that that disciple should not die: yet Jesus said not unto him, He shall not die; but, If I will that he tarry till I come, what is that to thee?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">於是這話傳在弟兄中間，說那門徒不死。其實，耶穌不是說他不死，乃是說：「我若要他等到我來的時候，與你何干？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse24">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Teni ta Pahtatæutu-han ka hmail, ka ni-smoulat-appa ki mamang katta: ka kavanna-n-niæn ka matiktik ki sou ta hail-lan tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Teni ta Pahtatæutu-han ka hmail, ka ni-smoulat-appa ki mamang katta: ka kavanna-n-niæn ka matiktik ki sou ta hail-lan tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Dese is De Discipel Die ban dese dinhen getuygt ende Dese dingen geschreben heeft : ende wy weten dat sijn ghetuygenisse waerachtigh is.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">This is the disciple which testifieth of these things, and wrote these things: and we know that his testimony is true.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">為這些事作見證，並且記載這些事的就是這門徒；我們也知道他的見證是真的。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse25">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Madagh-appa ta panini ki ma-mang, ka ni-pam''t-ten ti Jesus, hei-rou æ'ætylloug-an-nei meæ-fasat lava smoulat ta mamang kanna, pou kidi-en-au asli mamsing-ah ta ymid ki ni mara ki na sasoulat kanna. Amen.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Madagh-appa ta panini ki ma-mang, ka ni-pam''t-ten ti Jesus, hei-rou æ'ætylloug-an-nei meæ-fasat lava smoulat ta mamang kanna, pou kidi-en-au asli mamsing-ah ta ymid ki ni mara ki na sasoulat kanna. Amen.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende daer zijn noch bele andere dingen die Jesus gedaen heeft welcke soo'se elk bysonder beschreben wierden ick achte dat oock de werelt selbe de geschrebene boecken niet en zoude batten. Amen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And there are also many other things which Jesus did, the which, if they should be written every one, I suppose that even the world itself could not contain the books that should be written. Amen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌所行的事還有許多，若是一一地都寫出來，我想，所寫的書就是世界也容不下了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
</TEXT>