<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEXT id="Siraya_Dutch_John_Chapter9" xml:lang="fos" source="Siraya Bible, John gospel" copyright="public domain" citation="Gravius, Daniël. 1661. Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa. Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang. Amsterdam: Michiel Hartogh." BibTeX_citation="@book{Gravius1661,&#10;  author    = {Gravius, Daniël},&#10;  year      = {1661},&#10;  title     = {Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa},&#10;  note      = {Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang},&#10;  address   = {Amsterdam},&#10;  publisher = {Michiel Hartogh}&#10;}">
    <S id="verse1">
        <FORM kindOf="original">. Irou ka mali-æuragh, ni-kmytta ki saat ki vouel ka mavoutta ki na tan-næi tou pei-rauwei-en.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">. Irou ka mali-æuragh, ni-kmytta ki saat ki vouel ka mavoutta ki na tan-næi tou pei-rauwei-en.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Ende boor-by gaende sagh hy eenen mensche blint bande geboorte af.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And as Jesus passed by, he saw a man which was blind from his birth.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">耶穌過去的時候，看見一個人生來是瞎眼的。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse2">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-tmaligh tyni-æn ta Pæhta-tæutæu-han tyn, kma, Rabbi, ti-mang ta pou-varau, ti atta kauwa, ki tæ'i-alak kauwa tyni-æn, ka ni-pei-voutta-an mei-alak ta teni?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-tmaligh tyni-æn ta Pæhtatæutæu-han tyn, kma, Rabbi, ti-mang ta pou-varau, ti atta kauwa, ki tæ'i-alak kauwa tyni-æn, ka ni-pei-voutta-an mei-alak ta teni?</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Ende sijne Discipulen braeghden hem seggende Rabbi wie heeft'er gesondight Dese ofte sijne onders dat hy blindt soude gebooren worden :</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And his disciples asked him, saying, Master, who did sin, this man, or his parents, that he was born blind?</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">門徒問耶穌說：「拉比，這人生來是瞎眼的，是誰犯了罪？是這人呢？是他父母呢？」</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse3">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta ti Jesus, Assi ni-pouvarau ta ti atta, assi ki tæ'i-alak tyni-æn: râ [ni-pam't-ten-ato ta atta] ka pa-ka-æmæ'-auh paka-koua 'tyni-æn tapei-ryngei eih ki Alid.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta ti Jesus, Assi ni-pouvarau ta ti atta, assi ki tæ'i-alak tyni-æn: râ [ni-pam't-ten-ato ta atta] ka pa-ka-æmæ'-auh paka-koua 'tyni-æn tapei-ryngei eih ki Alid.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Jesus antwoordde Noch dese en Heeft ghesonDight noch sijne ouders: maer [dits is gefchiet] op Dat De wercken. Godts in hem sou-souden geopenbatrt worden.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Jesus answered, Neither hath this man sinned, nor his parents: but that the works of God should be made manifest in him.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">耶穌回答說：「也不是這人犯了罪，也不是他父母犯了罪，是要在他身上顯出上帝的作為來。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse4">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Kidi-ato ka kapoungas-au mau ta ryngei tyn ka nimadingi jau-an, rou a-koume-'appa ta wæi: ierroua-ah ta-euvan, ka assi ma-lpoug-a' mapoungas ta ti mamang.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Kidi-ato ka kapoungas-au mau ta ryngei tyn ka nimadingi jau-an, rou a-koume-'appa ta wæi: ierroua-ah ta-euvan, ka assi ma-lpoug-a' mapoungas ta ti mamang.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Ick moet wercken De wercken Des genen die my gesonden Heeft soo langh het dagh is : De nacht komt wanneer niemandt wercken En kana.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">I must work the works of him that sent me, while it is day: the night cometh, when no man can work.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">趁着白日，我們必須做那差我來者的工；黑夜將到，就沒有人能做工了。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse5">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Rou ia-koua app'-'oh touni, ræmh-koh ki ni.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Rou ia-koua app'-'oh touni, ræmh-koh ki ni.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> So lange ick in De wereldt ben soo ben ick Het licht der wereldt.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">As long as I am in the world, I am the light of the world.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">我在世上的時候，是世上的光。」</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse6">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka ni-matti-kaha ki atta, ni-pangarei-en tyn tou næi, si-loutta louttak ki na ngarei , ka ni-hmeik ki louttak k''anna tou matta ki mavoutta.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka ni-matti-kaha ki atta, ni-pangarei-en tyn tou næi, si-loutta louttak ki na ngarei , ka ni-hmeik ki louttak k''anna tou matta ki mavoutta.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Dit geseght hebbende spoogh hy op de aerde ende maeckte siick uyt Dat speecksel ende streeck dat siick op De oogen des blinden.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">When he had thus spoken, he spat on the ground, and made clay of the spittle, and he anointed the eyes of the blind man with the clay,</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">耶穌說了這話，就吐唾沫在地上，用唾沫和泥抹在瞎子的眼睛上，</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse7">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-koun tyn tyni-æn, 'Ou-kou-koua madioep-pa [ym-houan] tou æizug-han ki Siloe (ka pattæ'i-toun noun-nun ki sou, ni-padingi-en.) Ka ni-'ouk-oun tyn madi oep[tyni-æn,] ka ieroua-ato ka kmyt'-ato.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-koun tyn tyni-æn, 'Ou-kou-koua madioep-pa [ym-houan] tou æizug-han ki Siloe (ka pattæ'i-toun noun-nun ki sou, ni-padingi-en.) Ka ni-'ouk-oun tyn madi oep[tyni-æn,] ka ieroua-ato ka kmyt'-ato.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Ende seyde tot hem Gaet Henen wascht u in het badt-water Siloam (het welk obergeset wordt uytgesonden.) Hy Dan gingh henen ende wiesch hem ende quam siende.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And said unto him, Go, wash in the pool of Siloam, (which is by interpretation, Sent.) He went his way therefore, and washed, and came seeing.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">對他說：「你往西羅亞池子裏去洗。」（西羅亞翻出來就是「奉差遣」。） 他去一洗，回頭就看見了。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse8">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata kahalahalau-an, ne-ni-appa ka ni-kmytta tyni-n ka-lahei ka mavoutta-appa, ta ni-k'ma, Assi kauwa teni ta ni-mier-raoung kanna tmoumymmia ki tæ'-esh ki harum?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata kahalahalau-an, ne-ni-appa ka ni-kmytta tyni-n ka-lahei ka mavoutta-appa, ta ni-k'ma, Assi kauwa teni ta ni-mier-raoung kanna tmoumymmia ki tæ'-esh ki harum?</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> De gebueren dan ende Die hem te boren gesien hadden dat hy blint was seyden Is Dese niet Die sat ende beDelde :</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">The neighbours therefore, and they which before had seen him that he was blind, said, Is not this he that sat and begged?</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">他的鄰舍和那素常見他是討飯的，就說：「這不是那從前坐着討飯的人嗎？」</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse9">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k''ma tararouma, Teni k'anna: rarouma-appa, Mahau-wei tyni-æn. Ni-k'ma ta teni, Ti jau k'atta.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-k''ma tararouma, Teni k'anna: rarouma-appa, Mahau-wei tyni-æn. Ni-k'ma ta teni, Ti jau k'atta.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Andere seyden Hy is 't : ende andere Hy is hem gelijck. Hy seyde Ick ben't.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Some said, This is he: others said, He is like him: but he said, I am he.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">有人說：「是他」；又有人說：「不是，卻是像他。」他自己說：「是我。」</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse10">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annatanik'ma ta neni ty-ni, Ni-pa-r'kyllat-ten ke wmama ki mang ki matta ?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annatanik'ma ta neni tyni, Ni-pa-r'kyllat-ten ke wmama ki mang ki matta ?</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Sy Dan seyden tot hem Hoe zijn u De oogen geopent:</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Therefore said they unto him, How were thine eyes opened?</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">他們對他說：「你的眼睛是怎麼開的呢？」</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse11">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta teni kma, Vouel k'anna ka pa-nanang-en Jesus ta ni-si-loutta louttak ki na gnarei hmeik ki matta-au, ka koun-tyn jau-an, 'Ou kou-a tou 'æi-æug-han ki Siloë, madioep ym-hou-an. Ka ni-mou-koua-koh madioep jau-an, kakmytt'-âto koh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta teni kma, Vouel k'anna ka pa-nanang-en Jesus ta ni-si-loutta louttak ki na gnarei hmeik ki matta-au, ka koun-tyn jau-an, 'Ou koua tou 'æi-æug-han ki Siloë, madioep ym-hou-an. Ka ni-mou-koua-koh madioep jau-an, kakmytt'-âto koh.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Hy Hy antoordde ende seyde De mensche genaemt Jesus maeckte siick ende be= streeck mijne oogen en seyde tot my Gaet Henen aen Het badt-water Siloam ende wascht u. Ende ick gingh wnen ende wiesch my ende ick wierdt siende.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">He answered and said, A man that is called Jesus made clay, and anointed mine eyes, and said unto me, Go to the pool of Siloam, and wash: and I went and washed, and I received sight.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">他回答說：「有一個人，名叫耶穌，他和泥抹我的眼睛，對我說：『你往西羅亞池子去洗。』我去一洗，就看見了。」</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse12">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-k'ma ta neni ty-ni-æn, tou-mang ta teni kanna? Ni-k'ma [ta teni,] Assi-mau ou-mh-'an-ato.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-k'ma ta neni ty-ni-æn, tou-mang ta teni kanna? Ni-k'ma [ta teni,] Assi-mau ou-mh-'an-ato.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Sy Dan seyden tot hem waer is die: Hy seyde Ick en weet Het niet.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Then said they unto him, Where is he? He said, I know not.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">他們說：「那個人在哪裏？」他說：「我不知道。」</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse13">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-'æd nein pa-'ou-koua tyni-æn ki Fariseen, tyni-æn k'anna ka ni-mavoutta kala-hey.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-'æd nein pa-'ou-koua tyni-æn ki Fariseen, tyni-æn k'anna ka ni-mavoutta kala-hey.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Sy brochten hem tot de Phariseen Hem [namelick] die te boren blindt [geweest was].</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">They brought to the Pharisees him that aforetime was blind.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">他們把從前瞎眼的人帶到法利賽人那裏。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse14">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka na wæ'i-ato ki pæ'i-habab-an, rou ni-si-loutta lout-tak ta ti Jesus ki na ngarey pa-rkyllat ki matta tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka na wæ'i-ato ki pæ'i-habab-an, rou ni-si-loutta lout-tak ta ti Jesus ki na ngarey pa-rkyllat ki matta tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Ende het was Sabbath als Jesus Het sliick maeckte ende sijne oogen opende.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And it was the sabbath day when Jesus made the clay, and opened his eyes.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">耶穌和泥開他眼睛的日子是安息日。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse15">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni tmauka-la-appa tmaligh tyni-æn ta Fariseen, ma-ma ki mang ka kytt'an-nato tyn? Ni-k'ma ta teni neini-æn, Ni-heik-kin tyn ta louttak tou mat-ta-au, ka ni-madioep-koh jau-an, kakmytt'-âto-koh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni tmauka-la-appa tmaligh tyni-æn ta Fariseen, ma-ma ki mang ka kytt'an-nato tyn? Ni-k'ma ta teni neini-æn, Ni-heik-kin tyn ta louttak tou mat-ta-au, ka ni-madioep-koh jau-an, kakmytt'-âto-koh.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> De Phariseen Dan braeghden Hem oock wederom hoe hy siende geworden Was: Ende hy seyde tat haer Hy leyde sliick Op mijne oogen ende ick wiesch my enDe ick sie </TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Then again the Pharisees also asked him how he had received his sight. He said unto them, He put clay upon mine eyes, and I washed, and do see.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">法利賽人也問他是怎麼得看見的。瞎子對他們說：「他把泥抹在我的眼睛上，我去一洗，就看見了。」</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse16">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-k'mata rarou-ma ki Fariseen, Assi ni-makka-koua ki Alid ta vouel k'annâ: alei ka assi tyn 'illig-hen ta wæ'i ki Pæ'i-hababan. Ni-kma ta rarou-ma, Pa-lpough mama ki mang ta ta'u ka tama-kavarau pamut ki pou-kidi-en ka kma-hynna? Ka mæ-mæu-dou ha-'tota sou nein.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-k'mata rarou-ma ki Fariseen, Assi ni-makka-koua ki Alid ta vouel k'annâ: alei ka assi tyn 'illig-hen ta wæ'i ki Pæ'i-hababan. Ni-kma ta rarou-ma, Pa-lpough mama ki mang ta ta'u ka tama-kavarau pamut ki pou-kidi-en ka kma-hynna? Ka mæ-mæu-dou ha-'tota sou nein.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Somminge dan uyt de Phariseen seyden- Dese menche en is ban Godt niet: want hy en Houdt den Sabbath niet. Andere seyden Hoe kan een mensche [die] een sondaer is sulcke teeckenen nen doen : Ende daer was tweedracht onderhaer.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Therefore said some of the Pharisees, This man is not of God, because he keepeth not the sabbath day. Others said, How can a man that is a sinner do such miracles? And there was a division among them.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">法利賽人中有的說：「這個人不是從上帝來的，因為他不守安息日。」又有人說：「一個罪人怎能行這樣的神蹟呢？」他們就起了紛爭。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse17">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-mattæ'i-la ta neni ki ni-mavouta, Ymhou, matt'i-mang kow alei tyni-æn, ka ni-pa-rkyllat-ten tyn ta matta oho? Ni kma ta teni, Tama-Matt æi-tan ta ti anna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-mattæ'i-la ta neni ki ni-mavouta, Ymhou, matt'i-mang kow alei tyni-æn, ka ni-pa-rkyllat-ten tyn ta matta oho? Ni kma ta teni, Tama-Matt æi-tan ta ti anna.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Sy seyden wederom tot den blinden Ghy wat seght ghy ban hem bewijle hy uwe oogen geopent heeft ? Ende hy seyde Hy is een Propheet.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">They say unto the blind man again, What sayest thou of him, that he hath opened thine eyes? He said, He is a prophet.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">他們又對瞎子說：「他既然開了你的眼睛，你說他是怎樣的人呢？」他說：「是個先知。」</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse18">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata asfi ni-tna-'msing ta Joden tyni-æn, ka ni-mavoutta ta teni kalahei, ka kmytta-ito hnyn , tou kidi-appa kanna ki ni-tætææm ne-in ta tæ'i-alak tyni-n, ka kmytta-ato.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata asfi ni-tna-'msing ta Joden tyni-æn, ka ni-mavoutta ta teni kalahei, ka kmytta-ito hnyn , tou kidi-appa kanna ki ni-tætææm nein ta tæ'i-alak tyni-n, ka kmytta-ato.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld">. De Joden dan en geloofden ban hem niet dat Hy bindt gemeest was ende siende was geworden tot Dat sy geroepen Hadden De ouders des ghenen Die siemDe geworden was.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">But the Jews did not believe concerning him, that he had been blind, and received his sight, until they called the parents of him that had received his sight.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">猶太人不信他從前是瞎眼，後來能看見的，等到叫了他的父母來，</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse19">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-tmaligh ta neni k''ma neini-æn, Alak-oumi kauwa ta ti atta ka ni-pei-voutta-an mei-alak koun-noumi?Mama ki mang ka kmytt'-Ato hayn?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-tmaligh ta neni k''ma neini-æn, Alak-oumi kauwa ta ti atta ka ni-pei-voutta-an mei-alak koun-noumi?Mama ki mang ka kmytt'-Ato hayn?</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Ende sy braeghden haer seggende Is dese uwe sone welcke ghy seght Dat blindt gebooren is : Doe siet hy dan nu :</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And they asked them, saying, Is this your son, who ye say was born blind? how then doth he now see?</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">問他們說：「這是你們的兒子嗎？你們說他生來是瞎眼的，如今怎麼能看見了呢？」</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse20">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-mattæ'i-v'si ta tæ'i-alalak tyni-æn, k'ma neini-æn, Kava-na'-n-niæn ka alak-jan ta ti atta, ka ni-pei-voutta-an appa mei-alak:</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-mattæ'i-v'si ta tæ'i-alalak tyni-æn, k'ma neini-æn, Kava-na'-n-niæn ka alak-jan ta ti atta, ka ni-pei-voutta-an appa mei-alak:</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Syne ouders antwoordden haer ende seyden Wy weten Dat dese onse sone is ende dat hy blindt geboren is :</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">His parents answered them and said, We know that this is our son, and that he was born blind:</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">他父母回答說：「他是我們的兒子，生來就瞎眼，這是我們知道的。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse21">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ra mama ki mang ka kmyt-ta-ato hnyn, assi-min kavan-'an: ti-mang lava ta ni-pa-rkyllat ki matta tyn,assi-miæna 'ou-mhgan: kuh-kaha-ato ta teni keu-mha, tmauki-madoua tmaligh tyni-æn: sykkoun noung-ah ta teni pou-pænæh kisou.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ra mama ki mang ka kmyt-ta-ato hnyn, assi-min kavan-'an: ti-mang lava ta ni-pa-rkyllat ki matta tyn,assi-miæna 'ou-mhgan: kuh-kaha-ato ta teni keu-mha, tmauki-madoua tmaligh tyni-æn: sykkoun noung-ah ta teni pou-pænæh kisou.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Maer hoe hy nu siet en weten wy niet: of wie sijne oogen geopent heeft en weten wy niet: hy heeft [sijnen] ouderdom braget Hem selbe : hy sal ban hem-selben spreken.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">But by what means he now seeth, we know not; or who hath opened his eyes, we know not: he is of age; ask him: he shall speak for himself.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">至於他如今怎麼能看見，我們卻不知道；是誰開了他的眼睛，我們也不知道。他已經成了人，你們問他吧，他自己必能說。」</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse22">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-mattæ'i-komma-hyn-na ta t'i-alak tyni-æn, alei ki kahttakout-ten nein ki Joden. Nda ni-mattæ'i-kaha mattæ'i-sal mattæ'i-pouk ki sou ta Joden, hei-rou ka mattæ-'i-æmæ'-âl-ato ta ti-mamang ka ti Christus ta ti anna, ka pa-d'arang-eih ta teni tou Pæui-sasal-lan.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-mattæ'i-komma-hyn-na ta t'i-alak tyni-æn, alei ki kahttakout-ten nein ki Joden. Nda ni-mattæ'i-kaha mattæ'i-sal mattæ'i-pouk ki sou ta Joden, hei-rou ka mattæ-'i-æmæ'-âl-ato ta ti-mamang ka ti Christus ta ti anna, ka pa-d'arang-eih ta teni tou Pæui-sasal-lan.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Dit seyden sijne ouders om Dat sy De Joden breesden. Want de Joden hadhadden alreede te samen een besluyt gemaeckt soo yemandt hem belede Christum te zijn Dat Die uyt De Synagoge soude gewordpen Worden.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">These words spake his parents, because they feared the Jews: for the Jews had agreed already, that if any man did confess that he was Christ, he should be put out of the synagogue.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">他父母說這話，是怕猶太人；因為猶太人已經商議定了，若有認耶穌是基督的，要把他趕出會堂。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse23">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Alei kianna ni-k'ma ta tæ'i-alak tyni-æn, Kæuh-kaha-ato ta teni keu'-mha, tmauki-madou-a tyni-æn tmaligh</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Alei kianna ni-k'ma ta tæ'i-alak tyni-æn, Kæuh-kaha-ato ta teni keu'-mha, tmauki-madou-a tyni-æn tmaligh</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Daerom seyden sijne ouders Hy heeft [sijnen] ouderdom braget gem selbe.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Therefore said his parents, He is of age; ask him.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">因此他父母說：「他已經成了人，你們問他吧。」</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse24">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-mako kara-rouha ta neni tmætææm ki vouel k'anna ka ni-mavoutta kalahei, ka k'ma tyni-æn, Phei-to ki Alid ta louloug-han: kava na-'n-niæn ka tama-kavarau ta vouel k'anna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-mako kara-rouha ta neni tmætææm ki vouel k'anna ka ni-mavoutta kalahei, ka k'ma tyni-æn, Phei-to ki Alid ta louloug-han: kava na-'n-niæn ka tama-kavarau ta vouel k'anna.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Sy dan riepen boor De twee demael den mensche die blindt geweeft was ende seyden tot hem Geeft Godt De eere : wy weten Dat dese menche een sondaer is.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Then again called they the man that was blind, and said unto him, Give God the praise: we know that this man is a sinner.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">所以法利賽人第二次叫了那從前瞎眼的人來，對他說：「你該將榮耀歸給上帝，我們知道這人是個罪人。」</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse25">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Kani-mattæ'i-v'lli ta te-ni k'ma, Ma lava ka tama-kava-rau ta teni assi-mau kavan-'an: saäsat ta ka va'na-en-nau, ka na mavoutta koh kalahei, ka kmytt'-ato-koh hnyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Kani-mattæ'i-v'lli ta te-ni k'ma, Ma lava ka tama-kava-rau ta teni assi-mau kavan-'an: saäsat ta ka va'na-en-nau, ka na mavoutta koh kalahei, ka kmytt'-ato-koh hnyn.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Hy Dan antwoorde ende seyde Of hy een sondaer is en weet ick niet : een dinck weet ick dat ick blint was en nu zie.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">He answered and said, Whether he be a sinner or no, I know not: one thing I know, that, whereas I was blind, now I see.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">他說：「他是個罪人不是，我不知道；有一件事我知道，從前我是眼瞎的，如今能看見了。」</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse26">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-mattæ'i-la ta neni tyni-æn, Ni-oumamang ta teni ymhou-an? ni-pa-rkyllat-ten tyn mama ki mang ta matta oho?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-mattæ'i-la ta neni tyni-æn, Ni-oumamang ta teni ymhou-an? ni-pa-rkyllat-ten tyn mama ki mang ta matta oho?</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Ende sy seyden weDerom tot hem Wat heeft hy u gedaen : hoe Heeft hy uwe oogen geopdent ?</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Then said they to him again, What did he to thee? how opened he thine eyes?</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">他們就問他說：「他向你做甚麼？是怎麼開了你的眼睛呢？」</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse27">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-mattæ'i-vlli ta teni, Pattæ'i-kahan-ato-mau-kamou masousou, ka assi-kamou ni-mil-lingigh: mang ta kamoei-noumi tnalala millingigh? Mamoei-ka-mou kauwa kuh-rarauwei ka Pahtatæutæu-eih tyn ta ymou-mi-appa?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-mattæ'i-vlli ta teni, Pattæ'i-kahan-ato-mau-kamou masousou, ka assi-kamou ni-millingigh: mang ta kamoei-noumi tnalala millingigh? Mamoei-ka-mou kauwa kuh-rarauwei ka Pahtatæutæu-eih tyn ta ymou-mi-appa?</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Hy antwoorde haer Ick Hebt u alreede geseght ende ghy en Hebt Het niet geHoort: wat wilt ghy : wederom hooren : Wilt ghy lieden oock zijne Discipelen worden :</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">He answered them, I have told you already, and ye did not hear: wherefore would ye hear it again? will ye also be his disciples?</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">他回答說：「我方才告訴你們，你們不聽，為甚麼又要聽呢？莫非你們也要作他的門徒嗎？」</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse28">
        <FORM kindOf="original">'Annata ni-mattæ'i-sam-muk ta neni ki sou tyni-æn, k'ma, Ymhou ta Pahtatæutæu-han tyn: ra ymi-æn ta na Pæhtatæutæuugh ti Mofses.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">'Annata ni-mattæ'i-sam-muk ta neni ki sou tyni-æn, k'ma, Ymhou ta Pahtatæutæu-han tyn: ra ymi-æn ta na Pæhtatæutæuugh ti Mofses.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Sy Sy gaben hem Dan scheld woorDen ende seyden Ghy zijt sijn Discipel : maer wy zijn Mosis Discipelen.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Then they reviled him, and said, Thou art his disciple; but we are Moses' disciples.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">他們就罵他說：「你是他的門徒；我們是摩西的門徒。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse29">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Kavana-ni-æn ka ni-pa-susou-en ki Alid ti Moses-an: ta ti atta assi-miæn kavan'-an tou-mang ka ni-pakka-kouan tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Kavana-ni-æn ka ni-pa-susou-en ki Alid ti Moses-an: ta ti atta assi-miæn kavan'-an tou-mang ka ni-pakka-kouan tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Wy weten Dat Godt tot Mosem gesproken Heeft: maerr desen en weten wy niet ban waer hy is.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">We know that God spake unto Moses: as for this fellow, we know not from whence he is.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">上帝對摩西說話是我們知道的；只是這個人，我們不知道他從哪裏來！」</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse30">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta vouel kanna k'ma neini-æn, Atta ta 'ou-rynhgau-en, ka assi-moumi kavan-an ka tou-mang ta ni-pak-ka-koua'-n tyn, ietrou appa kan-na ka ni-pa-rkyllat tyn ta matta-au.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta vouel kanna k'ma neini-æn, Atta ta 'ou-rynhgau-en, ka assi-moumi kavan-an ka tou-mang ta ni-pak-ka-koua'-n tyn, ietrou appa kanna ka ni-pa-rkyllat tyn ta matta-au.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> De mensche antwoorde ende seyde tot haer Hier in immers [wat] wonders Dat ghy niet en weet ban waer hy is ende [nochtans] heeft Hy mijne ooghen gheopent.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">The man answered and said unto them, Why herein is a marvellous thing, that ye know not from whence he is, and yet he hath opened mine eyes.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">那人回答說：「他開了我的眼睛，你們竟不知道他從哪裏來，這真是奇怪！</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse31">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka kavan'-an-neta ka assi sha-valei ta Alid ki tama-kava-rau: ra ti mamang ta tama-t'amud ki Aid, ahkoua appa ki kamoei-in tyn, teni ta tna-valei-en tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka kavan'-an-neta ka assi sha-valei ta Alid ki tama-kava-rau: ra ti mamang ta tama-t'amud ki Aid, ahkoua appa ki kamoei-in tyn, teni ta tna-valei-en tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Ende wy weten Dat Godt De sondaers niet en Hoort : maer soo yemandt Godt bruchtigh is ende sijnen wille doet Dien hoort hy.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Now we know that God heareth not sinners: but if any man be a worshipper of God, and doeth his will, him he heareth.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">我們知道上帝不聽罪人，惟有敬奉上帝、遵行他旨意的，上帝才聽他。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse32">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Tou [ymmid ki] ydda-rynnoug-han assi ni-illinhg-en, Ka ni-pa-tkyllat ta ti mamang ki matta ki ni-pei-voutta-an mei-alak.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Tou [ymmid ki] ydda-rynnoug-han assi ni-illinhg-en, Ka ni-pa-tkyllat ta ti mamang ki matta ki ni-pei-voutta-an mei-alak.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Dan [alle] eeuwe en is het niet ghehoort Dat yemandt eens blindtgeboorenen oogen geopent Heeft.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Since the world began was it not heard that any man opened the eyes of one that was born blind.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">從創世以來，未曾聽見有人把生來是瞎子的眼睛開了。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse33">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Heirou assi ni-makka-koua ki Alid tatianna, assi pa-il poug-ah pamut ki mamang.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Heirou assi ni-makka-koua ki Alid tatianna, assi pa-il poug-ah pamut ki mamang.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Indien dese ban Godt niet en ware hy en soude niets konnen doen.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">If this man were not of God, he could do nothing.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">這人若不是從上帝來的，甚麼也不能做。」</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse34">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni mattæ'i-vlli ta neni k'ma tyni-æn, Ni-pei-tmouk kow mei-alak tou varau ta ym-hou, ka mæhtæutæuugh-kow y-mian-æn? Ka ni-padarang tane-ni pa-'ou-mala ty ni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni mattæ'i-vlli ta neni k'ma tyni-æn, Ni-pei-tmouk kow mei-alak tou varau ta ymhou, ka mæhtæutæuugh-kow y-mian-æn? Ka ni-padarang tane-ni pa-'ou-mala ty ni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Sy antwoorden ende seyden tot hem Ghy zijt geheel in sonden gebooren enDe leert ghy ons : Ende sy wierden hadem uyt.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">They answered and said unto him, Thou wast altogether born in sins, and dost thou teach us? And they cast him out.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">他們回答說：「你全然生在罪孽中，還要教訓我們嗎？」於是把他趕出去了。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse35">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-millingigh ta ti Jesus ka ni-pa-d'arang nein pa-'ou-ma-la tyni-æn, ierou ka kabalei-en tyn ta teni ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Tna-msing kow kauwa Ki Alak ki Alid?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-millingigh ta ti Jesus ka ni-pa-d'arang nein pa-'ou-ma-la tyni-æn, ierou ka kabalei-en tyn ta teni ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Tna-msing kow kauwa Ki Alak ki Alid?</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> JeJesus hoorde dat sy hem uytgeworbpen Hadden ende Hem bindende seyde hy tot hem Gelooft ghy in den Sone Godts:</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Jesus heard that they had cast him out; and when he had found him, he said unto him, Dost thou believe on the Son of God?</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">耶穌聽說他們把他趕出去，後來遇見他，就說：「你信上帝的兒子嗎？」</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse36">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-mattæ'i-vlli ta teni k'ma, Ti mang ta teni, Meirang, alei ka tna-msing-au-mau tyni-æn?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-mattæ'i-vlli ta teni k'ma, Ti mang ta teni, Meirang, alei ka tna-msing-au-mau tyni-æn?</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Hy antwoorde ende seyde Wie is hy Heere op Dat ick in hem mach ghelooben? </TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">He answered and said, Who is he, Lord, that I might believe on him?</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">他回答說：「主啊，誰是上帝的兒子，叫我信他呢？」</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse37">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-kma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Ka ni-k'ytta-en-hou ta teni, ka teni ka magh-tavagh ymhou-an, teni ta ti atta.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-kma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Ka ni-k'ytta-en-hou ta teni, ka teni ka magh-tavagh ymhou-an, teni ta ti atta.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Ende Jesus seyde tot hem Ende ghy Hebt hem gesein ende Die met u spreekt deselde is't.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And Jesus said unto him, Thou hast both seen him, and it is he that talketh with thee.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">耶穌說：「你已經看見他，現在和你說話的就是他。」</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse38">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'ma ta teni, Tna-'msing-koh, Meirang: ka ni-reip ta teni tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-k'ma ta teni, Tna-'msing-koh, Meirang: ka ni-reip ta teni tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Ende hy seyde Ick geloobe Neere : ende hy aenbadt hem.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And he said, Lord, I believe. And he worshipped him.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">他說：「主啊，我信！」就拜耶穌。</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse39">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus, Ierrou'-âto-koh tou næi katta alei ki dungdung-en, ka kmytta-ah ta neni ka assi-appa kmytta, ka ma-voutta-âl-ato ta neni ka kmyt-ta.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus, Ierrou'-âto-koh tou næi katta alei ki dungdung-en, ka kmytta-ah ta neni ka assi-appa kmytta, ka ma-voutta-âl-ato ta neni ka kmytta.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Ende Jesus seyde Ick ben tot een oordeel in Dese werelt gekomen op Dat De gene Die niet en sien sien mogen ende die sien blindt worDen.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And Jesus said, For judgment I am come into this world, that they which see not might see; and that they which see might be made blind.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">耶穌說：「我為審判到這世上來，叫不能看見的，可以看見；能看見的，反瞎了眼。」</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse40">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-millingigh ki atta ta [rarouma ki] Fariseen, ka ǣ'iæ-koua tyni-æn, ka ni-k'ma ta neni tyni-æn, Mavoutta-appa-kame kauwa ta ymi-æn?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-millingigh ki atta ta [rarouma ki] Fariseen, ka ǣ'iæ-koua tyni-æn, ka ni-k'ma ta neni tyni-æn, Mavoutta-appa-kame kauwa ta ymi-æn?</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Ende dit Hoorden [eenige] uyt De Phariseen Die hy hem waren ende seyden tot hem Zijn wy [dan] oock blindt.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">And some of the Pharisees which were with him heard these words, and said unto him, Are we blind also?</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">同他在那裏的法利賽人聽見這話，就說：「難道我們也瞎了眼嗎？」</TRANS>
    </S>
    <S id="verse41">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-kma ta ti Jesus neini-æn, Heirou mavoutta-kamou, ynna-kamou ä'ousi ki varau: ra hnyn kmytta-kame koun-nou-mi: alei ki anna mæylli ta varau-oumi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-kma ta ti Jesus neini-æn, Heirou mavoutta-kamou, ynna-kamou ä'ousi ki varau: ra hnyn kmytta-kame koun-nou-mi: alei ki anna mæylli ta varau-oumi.</FORM>
        <TRANS LANG="nld"> Jefus seyde tot haer Indien ghy blindt waert soo en soudt ghy gheen sonde hebben: maer segget ghyWy sien : soo blijft Dan uWe sonde.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="eng">Jesus said unto them, If ye were blind, ye should have no sin: but now ye say, We see; therefore your sin remaineth.</TRANS>
        <TRANS LANG="cmn">耶穌對他們說：「你們若瞎了眼，就沒有罪了；但如今你們說『我們能看見』，所以你們的罪還在。」</TRANS>
    </S>
</TEXT>