<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEXT id="Siraya_Dutch_John_Chapter8" xml:lang="fos" source="Siraya Bible, John gospel" copyright="public domain" citation="Gravius, Daniël. 1661. Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa. Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang. Amsterdam: Michiel Hartogh." BibTeX_citation="@book{Gravius1661,&#10;  author    = {Gravius, Daniël},&#10;  year      = {1661},&#10;  title     = {Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa},&#10;  note      = {Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang},&#10;  address   = {Amsterdam},&#10;  publisher = {Michiel Hartogh}&#10;}" dialect="Siraya">
    <S id="verse1">
        <FORM kindOf="original">. Râ ni-d'marang ta ti Jesus mou-voukkyn ka makka-vavouaki [voua ka mæ] ymmagh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">. Râ ni-d'marang ta ti Jesus mou-voukkyn ka makka-vavouaki [voua ka mæ] ymmagh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Mader Jesus gingh na den Olif-bergh.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus went unto the mount of Olives.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">於是各人都回家去了；耶穌卻往橄欖山去，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse2">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-sah-takkugh dou ma-damma sa-lyk-kough ta teni tou Kouva ki tatamm'dden ki Alid, ka ma ymmud ki ta'u ta ni-ierro-ua tyni-æn, irou ka mierroung-a-to ni-mæhtæutæu-ugh neini-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-sah-takkugh dou ma-damma sa-lyk-kough ta teni tou Kouva ki tatamm'dden ki Alid, ka ma ymmud ki ta'u ta ni-ierroua tyni-æn, irou ka mierroung-a-to ni-mæhtæutæu-ugh neini-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> EnEnde des morghens broegh quam hy Wederom in den Tempel ende alle Het bolck quam tot hem ende neder-geseten zijnde leerde hy haer.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And early in the morning he came again into the temple, and all the people came unto him; and he sat down, and taught them.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">清早又回到殿裏。眾百姓都到他那裏去，他就坐下，教訓他們。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse3">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-mad pa-'ou-koua ty-ni-æn ta Mahkou sasoulat ki Fariseen-appa saat ki ina ka ni-t'ou-roung tou pa-rbourbou-en :</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-mad pa-'ou-koua ty-ni-æn ta Mahkou sasoulat ki Fariseen-appa saat ki ina ka ni-t'ou-roung tou pa-rbourbou-en :</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende De Schrift-geleerde ende De Phariseen brachten tot hemen brouwe in ober spel gegrepen:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And the scribes and Pharisees brought unto him a woman taken in adultery; and when they had set her in the midst,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">文士和法利賽人帶着一個行淫時被拿的婦人來，叫她站在當中，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse4">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka ni-pa-i-toutou-kad-dun nein-i ta teni, ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Tama-Mæhtæutæuugh, ni-touroung tou ringei mamadou ta ina k'atta ka pa-rbour bou-ato.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka ni-pa-i-toutou-kad-dun neini ta teni, ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Tama-Mæhtæutæuugh, ni-touroung tou ringei mamadou ta ina k'atta ka pa-rbour bou-ato.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende haer gestelt hebbende in Het midden seyden sy tot hem Meester dese brouwe is op daedt selbe gegrepen operspel degaende.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">They say unto him, Master, this woman was taken in adultery, in the very act.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">就對耶穌說：「夫子，這婦人是正行淫之時被拿的。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse5">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-pahkou-sou-en-kame ta Mofses tou Tato-uhko, ka cyt-tauh ki na vahtou ta komma-hyn-na: Ra imhou mang k'ma kow?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-pahkou-sou-en-kame ta Mofses tou Tatouhko, ka cyt-tauh ki na vahtou ta komma-hyn-na: Ra imhou mang k'ma kow?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende Mofes heeft ons in De Wet geboden Dat De sulke gesteenight sullen worDen: Ghy dan wat seyden ghy.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Now Moses in the law commanded us, that such should be stoned: but what sayest thou?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">摩西在律法上吩咐我們把這樣的婦人用石頭打死。你說該把她怎麼樣呢？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse6">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-pa-sousou-en nein ta atta rihpung tyni-n, alei ka akou-me'-ah ki pat-barau-an-ei nein tyni-æn. Ra ni mæ'-æu-sousou ta ti Jesus sinoulat ki ke'æmus tou næi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-pa-sousou-en nein ta atta rihpung tyni-n, alei ka akou-me'-ah ki pat-barau-an-ei nein tyni-æn. Ra ni mæ'-æu-sousou ta ti Jesus sinoulat ki ke'æmus tou næi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende dit seyden sy hem bersoeckende op Dat sy [yet] hadden om hem te bescijuldigen Maer Jesus neder-buckende schreef met den binger in de aerde.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">This they said, tempting him, that they might have to accuse him. But Jesus stooped down, and with his finger wrote on the ground, as though he heard them not.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們說這話，乃試探耶穌，要得着告他的把柄。耶穌卻彎着腰，用指頭在地上畫字。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse7">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irouka itou-koua appa ta ne-nitmaligh tyni-æn, ni-mæ'æu tik-tik ta teni k'ma neini-æn, Ti-ma-mang ymoumi-n ta sou-siki va-rau pia-aurou-A smyt ki na vahtou tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irouka itou-koua appa ta ne-nitmaligh tyni-æn, ni-mæ'æu tik-tik ta teni k'ma neini-æn, Ti-ma-mang ymoumi-n ta sou-siki varau pia-aurou-A smyt ki na vahtou tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende alt sy hem bleben bragen rechtede hy hem op ende seyde tot haer Die ban u lieden sonder sonde is werpe eerst Den steen op Haer.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">So when they continued asking him, he lifted up himself, and said unto them, He that is without sin among you, let him first cast a stone at her.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們還是不住地問他，耶穌就直起腰來，對他們說：「你們中間誰是沒有罪的，誰就可以先拿石頭打她。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse8">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka mi-'la ni-mæ'æu-sou-sou ta teni smoulat tou næi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka mi-'la ni-mæ'æu-sou-sou ta teni smoulat tou næi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende wederom nederbuckende schreef Hy in De aerde.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And again he stooped down, and wrote on the ground.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">於是又彎着腰，用指頭在地上畫字。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse9">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Iroura millingigh ta neni [ki atta] ka rou ni-t'ounnoun-nun ki vana nein ki ryh, ni-sa-mamala ta saät sa-dilloug ki pani, sa-nau-namou ki na Mamoumou sa-lym-mou-lymmou ki na rarauwei: ka ni-pa-i-tou-saat tin tati Jesus, ki ina-appa k'anna ka i-tou tou kad-dato myttouh ko.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Iroura millingigh ta neni [ki atta] ka rou ni-t'ounnoun-nun ki vana nein ki ryh, ni-sa-mamala ta saät sa-dilloug ki pani, sa-nau-namou ki na Mamoumou sa-lym-mou-lymmou ki na rarauwei: ka ni-pa-i-tou-saat tin tati Jesus, ki ina-appa k'anna ka i-tou tou kad-dato myttouh ko.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Maer sy [dit] hoorende de ban [hare] conscientie obertuyght zijnde gingen uyt De een na De ander beginnende ban De oudtste tot De laetste : ende Jesus wiert aleen gelaten ende De Dronwe in het midden staende.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And they which heard it, being convicted by their own conscience, went out one by one, beginning at the eldest, even unto the last: and Jesus was left alone, and the woman standing in the midst.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們聽見這話，就從老到少，一個一個地都出去了，只剩下耶穌一人，還有那婦人仍然站在當中。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse10">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka papa æu-tiktik ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, ka rou assi tyn k'yttan ta saäat ki voual dijk ki ina, ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Ina, tou-mang ta neni ka akou varau k'ma ymhou-an? assi ni-dmungdung ta ti-mamang imhou-an?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka papa æu-tiktik ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, ka rou assi tyn k'yttan ta saäat ki voual dijk ki ina, ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Ina, tou-mang ta neni ka akou varau k'ma ymhou-an? assi ni-dmungdung ta ti-mamang imhou-an?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende Jesus hem op rechtende ende niemandt siende Dan brouwe seyde tot Haer Droande waer zijn dese uwe beschuldigers : en Heeft u niemntand beroordeelt :</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">When Jesus had lifted up himself, and saw none but the woman, he said unto her, Woman, where are those thine accusers? hath no man condemned thee?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌就直起腰來，對她說：「婦人，那些人在哪裏呢？沒有人定你的罪嗎？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse11">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'ma ta teni, Äousi Mei-rang. Ka ni-kouma ta ti Jesus ty-ni-æn, Tijau-appa ta assi dmung-dung ymhou-an: 'ou-koua-au, yn-na mi-la mavarau.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-k'ma ta teni, Äousi Mei-rang. Ka ni-kouma ta ti Jesus ty-ni-æn, Tijau-appa ta assi dmung-dung ymhou-an: 'ou-koua-au, ynna mi-la mavarau.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende sy seyde Niemandt Neere. Ende Jesus seyde tot haer So en beroordeele ick u oock niet : gaet henen ende en sondight niet meer.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">She said, No man, Lord. And Jesus said unto her, Neither do I condemn thee: go, and sin no more.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">她說：「主啊，沒有。」耶穌說：「我也不定你的罪。去吧，從此不要再犯罪了！」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse12">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni mattæ'i-la ta ti Jesus ki sou neini-æn, koun, Ti jau ta ræmæh ki næi: ti-mamang ta mææuugh jau-an assi mounau-nang-ah tou karimdim-man, ra akoume-ah ki ræmæh ki kæuag-han.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni mattæ'i-la ta ti Jesus ki sou neini-æn, koun, Ti jau ta ræmæh ki næi: ti-mamang ta mææuugh jau-an assi mounau-nang-ah tou karimdim-man, ra akoume-ah ki ræmæh ki kæuag-han.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">. Jesus dan sprack weDerom tot haerieden seggenDe Ich ben Het licht der wereldt: die my bolght en sal in De duysternisse niet wande: len megr sal het licht des lebens hebben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then spake Jesus again unto them, saying, I am the light of the world: he that followeth me shall not walk in darkness, but shall have the light of life.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌又對眾人說：「我是世界的光。跟從我的，就不在黑暗裏走，必要得着生命的光。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse13">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-k'ma ta Fariseen tyni-æn, Mattæ'i-hail Kow mattæ'i-nadou ymhou-an: assi matiktik ta pattæ'i-hail-en-hou.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-k'ma ta Fariseen tyni-æn, Mattæ'i-hail Kow mattæ'i-nadou ymhou-an: assi matiktik ta pattæ'i-hail-en-hou.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> De Phariseen Dan seyhden tot Hem Ghy ghetuyght ban u selden : uw'gtuygenisse en is Niet waer achtigh.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">The Pharisees therefore said unto him, Thou bearest record of thyself; thy record is not true.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">法利賽人對他說：「你是為自己作見證，你的見證不真。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse14">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta ti Jesus kouma neini æn, Mei ta-ka pat-tæ'i-hail-en-nau matti-nado jau-an, ramatuktukta patt'i-hail-en-nau: ka kavana-en-nau ka tou-mang ta ni-pakka-koua-en-nau, tou-mang-appa ta sah-ka koua-ei-mau: ra assi mavana ta ymou mi ka tou-mang ta pakka-koua-en-nau, tou-mang-appa ta sah-ka koua-en-nau.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta ti Jesus kouma neini æn, Mei ta-ka pat-tæ'i-hail-en-nau matti-nado jau-an, ramatuktukta patt'i-hail-en-nau: ka kavana-en-nau ka tou-mang ta ni-pakka-koua-en-nau, tou-mang-appa ta sah-ka koua-ei-mau: ra assi mavana ta ymou mi ka tou-mang ta pakka-koua-en-nau, tou-mang-appa ta sah-ka koua-en-nau.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus antwoordde ende seyde tot Haer Hoewel ick ick ban my selben getuyge so is [nochtans] mijn getuygenisse waerachtigh: want ick weet ban waer ick gekomen. ben ende waer ick henen gae: maer ghy lieden en weet niet ban waer ick kome ende Waer ick henen gae.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus answered and said unto them, Though I bear record of myself, yet my record is true: for I know whence I came, and whither I go; but ye cannot tell whence I come, and whither I go.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：「我雖然為自己作見證，我的見證還是真的；因我知道我從哪裏來，往哪裏去；你們卻不知道我從哪裏來，往哪裏去。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse15">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ymoumi ta dmungdung makka-i-bavat, ti jau assi-koh dmungdung ti mamang.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ymoumi ta dmungdung makka-i-bavat, ti jau assi-koh dmungdung ti mamang.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ghy oordeelt nae den bleesche ick en oordeele niemandt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Ye judge after the flesh; I judge no man.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們是以外貌判斷人，我卻不判斷人。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse16">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Heirou ka dmungdung-appa ti jau, matiktik ta dung-dung-en-nauka assi koh tou-saat, ratijau, ki Rama appa ka ni-ma-dingijau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Heirou ka dmungdung-appa ti jau, matiktik ta dung-dung-en-nauka assi koh tou-saat, ratijau, ki Rama appa ka ni-ma-dingijau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende indien ick ooch oordeele Mijn oordeel is wearachtigh : Want ick en ben niet alleen maer ick ende De Dader die my gesonden heeft.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And yet if I judge, my judgment is true: for I am not alone, but I and the Father that sent me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">就是判斷人，我的判斷也是真的；因為不是我獨自在這裏，還有差我來的父與我同在。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse17">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-s'oulat-ten appa tou Tatouhko-oumi, ka mashut ta pattæ'i-hail-len ki sou ki rareuha ki youal.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-s'oulat-ten appa tou Tatouhko-oumi, ka mashut ta pattæ'i-hail-len ki sou ki rareuha ki youal.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende Daer is oock in uwe Det geschreben dat het getungeniffe ban tee menschen waer achtigh is.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">It is also written in your law, that the testimony of two men is true.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們的律法上也記着說：『兩個人的見證是真的。』</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse18">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ti-jau ta mattæ'i-hail mat-ta'i-nado jau-an, ka mattæ'i-hail-appajau-an ta Rama ka ni-madingi jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ti-jau ta mattæ'i-hail mat-ta'i-nado jau-an, ka mattæ'i-hail-appajau-an ta Rama ka ni-madingi jau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ick ben het Die ban my selben getuyge ende De Dader Dit my gesonden heeft getuyght ban my.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">I am one that bear witness of myself, and the Father that sent me beareth witness of me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我是為自己作見證，還有差我來的父也是為我作見證。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse19">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni k'ma ta neni ty-ni-æn, Tou mang ta Raraman ohou 'Ni-mattæ'i-v'li ta tiJesus, Assi-kamou kmalang jau-an , ki R araman-appa: Heirou ka kma-lang-kamou jau-an, ynna-kamou k''alang-appa ki R araman-nau.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni k'ma ta neni ty-ni-æn, Tou mang ta Raraman ohou 'Ni-mattæ'i-v'li ta tiJesus, Assi-kamou kmalang jau-an , ki R araman-appa: Heirou ka kma-lang-kamou jau-an, ynna-kamou k''alang-appa ki R araman-nau.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">. Sy Dan seyden tot hem Waer is uwe Dader: Jesus antwoordde Ghy en kennet noch my noch mijnen dader : Indien ghy My kendet soo soudt ghy oock mijnen Dader kennen</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then said they unto him, Where is thy Father? Jesus answered, Ye neither know me, nor my Father: if ye had known me, ye should have known my Father also.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們就問他說：「你的父在哪裏？」耶穌回答說：「你們不認識我，也不認識我的父；若是認識我，也就認識我的父。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse20">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-masousou ta ti Jesus ki sou k'atta tou hili ki vastoularg ka atta-haha-an ki vangei, ka mah-tæutæuugh ta teni tou Kouva ki t'at'am'd-den ki Alid: ka assi-ni-tmouroung tyni-æn ta ti mamang Alei ka assi-appa ierrou'âto ta ki-di ki tæ'lei tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-masousou ta ti Jesus ki sou k'atta tou hili ki vastoularg ka atta-haha-an ki vangei, ka mah-tæutæuugh ta teni tou Kouva ki t'at'am'd-den ki Alid: ka assi-ni-tmouroung tyni-æn ta ti mamang Alei ka assi-appa ierrou'âto ta ki-di ki tæ'lei tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Dese woorden sprack Jesus by De Schat-kiste leeleerende in Den Tempel: ende niemant en greep hem Want sijne uyre en was noch niet gekomen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">These words spake Jesus in the treasury, as he taught in the temple: and no man laid hands on him; for his hour was not yet come.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">這些話是耶穌在殿裏的庫房、教訓人時所說的，也沒有人拿他，因為他的時候還沒有到。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse21">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-mattæ'i-la ta ti Jesus ki sou neini-æn, D'marang-ato koh ti jau, ka kmi'ym-ah-ka-mou jau-an, ka mapatei-ah-kamou tou varau-oumi: ka tou-mang ta sah-ka-koua-ei-mau, assi-kamou ma-lpough ierroua.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-mattæ'i-la ta ti Jesus ki sou neini-æn, D'marang-ato koh ti jau, ka kmi'ym-ah-ka-mou jau-an, ka mapatei-ah-kamou tou varau-oumi: ka tou-mang ta sah-ka-koua-ei-mau, assi-kamou ma-lpough ierroua.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus Dan seyde wederom tot haer Ick gae hemen ende ghy sult uy soecken ende in uwe sonde sult ghy scerden : daer ick henen gae en kondt ghy lieden niet komen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then said Jesus again unto them, I go my way, and ye shall seek me, and shall die in your sins: whither I go, ye cannot come.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌又對他們說：「我要去了，你們要找我，並且你們要死在罪中。我所去的地方，你們不能到。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse22">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-k'ma ta Joden, Papis-ma-dô ah-kauwa pa-ka-pa-tei tyni-æn? alei ka kou-n tyn, Tou-mang ta sah-kakou'-ei-mau, assi-kamou gma-lpough ierroua.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-k'ma ta Joden, Papis-ma-dô ah-kauwa pa-ka-pa-tei tyni-æn? alei ka koun tyn, Tou-mang ta sah-kakou'-ei-mau, assi-kamou gma-lpough ierroua.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> De Joden Dan seyden Sal hy oock hem selben doden: om Dat hy seght Daer ick henen gae en kondt ghy lieden niet komen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then said the Jews, Will he kill himself? because he saith, Whither I go, ye cannot come.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">猶太人說：「他說『我所去的地方，你們不能到』，難道他要自盡嗎？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse23">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-k'ma ta teni neini-æn, Makka-rarim-kamou ta y-moumi, makka-vavau-koh ti jau: makka-næi-kamou ta ymoumi, ti jau assi-koh makka-næi katta.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-k'ma ta teni neini-æn, Makka-rarim-kamou ta ymoumi, makka-vavau-koh ti jau: makka-næi-kamou ta ymoumi, ti jau assi-koh makka-næi katta.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende hy seyde tot haer Ghy-lieden zijt ban beneden, ick ben ban boben : ghy zijt uyt dese wereldt ick en ben niet uyt dese werelt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And he said unto them, Ye are from beneath; I am from above: ye are of this world; I am not of this world.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌對他們說：「你們是從下頭來的，我是從上頭來的；你們是屬這世界的，我不是屬這世界的。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse24">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Alei ki anna ni-pasousou-en-nau-kamou, ka mapatei-ah-kamou tou varau-oumi. Heirou assi-kamou tna-msing ka ti jau k'atta, mapatei-ah-kamou tou varau-oumi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Alei ki anna ni-pasousou-en-nau-kamou, ka mapatei-ah-kamou tou varau-oumi. Heirou assi-kamou tna-msing ka ti jau k'atta, mapatei-ah-kamou tou varau-oumi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ick hebbe u Dan gheseght Dat ghy in uwe sonden sult sterben. Want indien ghy niet en gelooft dat ick [die] ben ghy sult in uwe sonden sterben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">I said therefore unto you, that ye shall die in your sins: for if ye believe not that I am he, ye shall die in your sins.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">所以我對你們說，你們要死在罪中。你們若不信我是基督，必要死在罪中。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse25">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-k'ma ta neni tyni-æn, Ymhou ti-mang-kow? Ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus neini-æn, [Te-ni] ka na pattæ'i-na naunamou-au ymoumi-ǣæn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-k'ma ta neni tyni-æn, Ymhou ti-mang-kow? Ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus neini-æn, [Te-ni] ka na pattæ'i-na naunamou-au ymoumi-ǣæn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Sy seyden Dan tot hem Wie zijt ghy : Ende Jesus seyde tot haer Dat ick ban Den beginne u-lieden oock segge |</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then said they unto him, Who art thou? And Jesus saith unto them, Even the same that I said unto you from the beginning.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們就問他說：「你是誰？」耶穌對他們說：「就是我從起初所告訴你們的。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse26">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Madagh-appa ta ynna-mau pasousou-an-ei alei ymon-mi-æn dmungdung: ra matiktik ta teni ki sou ka ni-madingi jau-an: ka kamamangka ni-illing-hau ty ni-æn, atta ta patousou-en-nau ki næi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Madagh-appa ta ynna-mau pasousou-an-ei alei ymon-mi-æn dmungdung: ra matiktik ta teni ki sou ka ni-madingi jau-an: ka kamamangka ni-illing-hau ty ni-æn, atta ta patousou-en-nau ki næi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ick hebbe dele dingen ban.ban u te seggen ende te oorDeelen: maer Die my ghesonDen heeft is waerachtigh ende De dinghen Die ick ban hem gehoort hebbe deselbe spreke ick tot De werelt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">I have many things to say and to judge of you: but he that sent me is true; and I speak to the world those things which I have heard of him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我有許多事講論你們，判斷你們；但那差我來的是真的，我在他那裏所聽見的，我就傳給世人。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse27">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Assi hnyn 'ou-mhgan ka pa-sousou-en tyn ki Rama nei-ni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Assi hnyn 'ou-mhgan ka pa-sousou-en tyn ki Rama nei-ni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Sy en ber stonden niet Dat hy haer ban Den Dader sprack.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">They understood not that he spake to them of the Father.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們不明白耶穌是指着父說的。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse28">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus neini-n, Irou ka pou-va-vau-al-ato-kamou ki Alak ki ka'-euloung, annata 'ou-mhgei-mou-mi ka ti jau k'atta, ka assi-koh si-kounnoung pamut ki mamang, ra pa-fousou-en-nau ta atta mama ki ni-pahtæutæu-hen jau-an ki Ra-raman-au.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus neini-n, Irou ka pou-va-vau-al-ato-kamou ki Alak ki ka'-euloung, annata 'ou-mhgei-mou-mi ka ti jau k'atta, ka assi-koh si-kounnoung pamut ki mamang, ra pa-fousou-en-nau ta atta mama ki ni-pahtæutæu-hen jau-an ki Raraman-au.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus Dan seyde tot haer wanneer ghy den Sone des menschen sult berHooght hebben Dan sult ghy berstaen Dat ick [die] ben ende [dat] ick ban my selben niets en de maer dese Dingen spreke geliick mijn Dader my geleert heeft.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then said Jesus unto them, When ye have lifted up the Son of man, then shall ye know that I am he, and that I do nothing of myself; but as my Father hath taught me, I speak these things.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">所以耶穌說：「你們舉起人子以後，必知道我是基督，並且知道我沒有一件事是憑着自己做的。我說這些話乃是照着父所教訓我的。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse29">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka teni ka madingi jau-an ta i-tou-lam jau-an, assi-koh ni-pa-i-tou-saat-tun ki Rama, alei ka pam't-'nnau myhka koua ta ma-mang ka kam'au-en tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka teni ka madingi jau-an ta i-tou-lam jau-an, assi-koh ni-pa-i-tou-saat-tun ki Rama, alei ka pam't-'nnau myhka koua ta ma-mang ka kam'au-en tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende die my gesonden heeft is met my. De Dader en heeft my niet alleen gelaten want ick altndt doe dat hem behagelickis.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And he that sent me is with me: the Father hath not left me alone; for I do always those things that please him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那差我來的是與我同在；他沒有撇下我獨自在這裏，因為我常做他所喜悅的事。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse30">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ha masousou ta teni ki mamang k'atta, mabatoung ta ni-tna-msing tyni-n.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ha masousou ta teni ki mamang k'atta, mabatoung ta ni-tna-msing tyni-n.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Als Hy Dese Dingen sprack gheloorden beele Ã­n hem.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">As he spake these words, many believed on him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說這話的時候，就有許多人信他。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse31">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annatani-k'ma ta ti Jesus ki Joden ka tna-mfsing tyni-æn,  Heirou mæylli-kamou ki sou-au, d'lligh-kamou ki Pahta tæutæu-ug-han-nau.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annatani-k'ma ta ti Jesus ki Joden ka tna-mfsing tyni-æn,  Heirou mæylli-kamou ki sou-au, d'lligh-kamou ki Pahta tæutæu-ug-han-nau.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus Dan seyde tot de Joden Die [in] hem geloofden Indien ghy lieden in mijn Woord blijbet so zijt ghy waerlick mijne Discipu len.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then said Jesus to those Jews which believed on him, If ye continue in my word, then are ye my disciples indeed;</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌對信他的猶太人說：「你們若常常遵守我的道，就真是我的門徒；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse32">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka mou-mhga-ah-kamou ki katiktik-kan ki sou, ka pa-syk kounnoung-eih-kamou ki katik-tik-kan ki fou.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka mou-mhga-ah-kamou ki katiktik-kan ki sou, ka pa-syk kounnoung-eih-kamou ki katik-tik-kan ki fou.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende sult De waerheyt berstaen ende de waerheyt sal bry maken.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And ye shall know the truth, and the truth shall make you free.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們必曉得真理，真理必叫你們得以自由。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse33">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta neni tyni-æn, Na æp-kame ti Abraham, ka myhkakoua assi-kame ni-pou-koungcia-anti-mamang: mattæ'i-mama kow ki mang, Pa-sijk koun-noung-eih-kamou?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta neni tyni-æn, Na æp-kame ti Abraham, ka myhkakoua assi-kame ni-pou-koungcia-anti-mamang: mattæ'i-mama kow ki mang, Pa-sijk koun-noung-eih-kamou?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Sy antwoordden hem Wy zijn Abrahams zaet ende en Hebben noyt yemant gedient : Hoe seght ghy[dan] Ghy sult bry worden :</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">They answered him, We be Abraham's seed, and were never in bondage to any man: how sayest thou, Ye shall be made free?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們回答說：「我們是亞伯拉罕的後裔，從來沒有作過誰的奴僕。你怎麼說『你們必得以自由』呢？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse34">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta ti Jesus neini-æn, Missing, missing koun-nau-kamou-ra, Veiæh ka pamut ki varau koungcia ta teni ki varau.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta ti Jesus neini-æn, Missing, missing koun-nau-kamou-ra, Veiæh ka pamut ki varau koungcia ta teni ki varau.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus anwoordde haer Doorwaer boorwaer segge ick u Een yegelick die De sonde Doet is een dienstknecht der sonden</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus answered them, Verily, verily, I say unto you, Whosoever committeth sin is the servant of sin.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌回答說：「我實實在在地告訴你們，所有犯罪的就是罪的奴僕。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse35">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka assi mæylli i-tou ryn-nough tou tallagh ta koungcia: ra mǣylli-appai-tou-rynnough ta Alak.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka assi mæylli i-tou ryn-nough tou tallagh ta koungcia: ra mǣylli-appai-tou-rynnough ta Alak.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende de bienscknecht en blijt niet eeuwighlick in Het Huys: de sone blijft'er eeuwighlick.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And the servant abideth not in the house for ever: but the Son abideth ever.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">奴僕不能永遠住在家裏；兒子是永遠住在家裏。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse36">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Heirou ka pa-sykkou-noung-eil-lato-kamou ki Alak, pa-sy-d'lligh-ei-lato-kamou pa-sykkoun noung.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Heirou ka pa-sykkou-noung-eil-lato-kamou ki Alak, pa-sy-d'lligh-ei-lato-kamou pa-sykkoun noung.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Indien dan De Sone U sal dry gem aeckt hebben soo zult ghy waerlick bry zijn.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">If the Son therefore shall make you free, ye shall be free indeed.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">所以天父的兒子若叫你們自由，你們就真自由了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse37">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Kavana-en-nau ka na æp-kamou ti Abraham, ra kmi'ym-kamou ki paka patei-an-eih jau-an, alei ka äou-si ki i-tou kou'an emou-miæn ta sou-au.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Kavana-en-nau ka na æp-kamou ti Abraham, ra kmi'ym-kamou ki paka patei-an-eih jau-an, alei ka äou-si ki i-tou kou'an emou-miæn ta sou-au.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ick weet dat ghy Abrahams zaet zijt maer ghy soeckt my te Dooden want mijn woordt en heeft in u geen plaetse.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">I know that ye are Abraham's seed; but ye seek to kill me, because my word hath no place in you.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我知道你們是亞伯拉罕的子孫，你們卻想要殺我，因為你們心裏容不下我的道。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse38">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Masousou-koh ki ni-k'yt-ta-en-nau ki Raraman-au: ymou-mi appa ta pamut ki ni-k'ytta-'n-noumi ki raraman-oumi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Masousou-koh ki ni-k'yt-ta-en-nau ki Raraman-au: ymoumi appa ta pamut ki ni-k'ytta-'n-noumi ki raraman-oumi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ick spreke dat ick by mijnen Dader gesien hebbe : ghy doet dan oock Dat ghy hy uwen Dader gesien hebt,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">I speak that which I have seen with my Father: and ye do that which ye have seen with your father.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我所說的是在我父那裏看見的；你們所行的是在你們的父那裏聽見的。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse39">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta neni kouma tyni-æn, Ti Abraham ta naramou-jang. Ni-kouma ta ti Jesus neini-æn, Heirou na Alalak-kamou ti Abraham, ynna-kamou ahkoua [pamut] ki na ringei ti Abraham.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta neni kouma tyni-æn, Ti Abraham ta naramou-jang. Ni-kouma ta ti Jesus neini-æn, Heirou na Alalak-kamou ti Abraham, ynna-kamou ahkoua [pamut] ki na ringei ti Abraham.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Sy antwoorden ende seyden tot hem Ahraham is onse Dader. Jesus seyde tot haer Indien ghy Abrahams kinderen waert soo soudt ghy De wercken Abrahams doen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">They answered and said unto him, Abraham is our father. Jesus saith unto them, If ye were Abraham's children, ye would do the works of Abraham.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們說：「我們的父就是亞伯拉罕。」耶穌說：「你們若是亞伯拉罕的兒子，就必行亞伯拉罕所行的事。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse40">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Hnyn-da kmi'ym-kamou ki pakapatei-eih jau-an, ka vouet ka ni-massousfou ymoumi-æn ki katiktik-kan kifou, ka ni'illing'-hg'-au ki Alid. Assi ni-pamut ki attatati Abraham. .</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Hnyn-da kmi'ym-kamou ki pakapatei-eih jau-an, ka vouet ka ni-massousfou ymoumi-æn ki katiktik-kan kifou, ka ni'illing'-hg'-au ki Alid. Assi ni-pamut ki attatati Abraham. .</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Maer . Maer nu soeckt ghy my te dooden een mensche Die u De waerheyt gesproken Hebbe welcke ick ban Godt gehoort hebbe. Dat en dede Abraham niet.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But now ye seek to kill me, a man that hath told you the truth, which I have heard of God: this did not Abraham.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我將在上帝那裏所聽見的真理告訴了你們，現在你們卻想要殺我，這不是亞伯拉罕所行的事。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse41">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Emoumi-ra-ta pamut ki na ryngei ki raraman-oumi. Annata ni-k'ma ta neni tyni-æn; Assi-ka-me ni-pei-allak-ken tou kavei-joung-an: akoumea-kame saasat ki Rama ka Alid.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Emoumi-ra-ta pamut ki na ryngei ki raraman-oumi. Annata ni-k'ma ta neni tyni-æn; Assi-kame ni-pei-allak-ken tou kavei-joung-an: akoumea-kame saasat ki Rama ka Alid.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ghy Doet De wercken uwes baders. Sy seyden Dan tot hem Wy en zijn niet gebooren uyt hoererije : wy hebben eenen bader [namelick] Godt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Ye do the deeds of your father. Then said they to him, We be not born of fornication; we have one Father, even God.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們是行你們父所行的事。」他們說：「我們不是從淫亂生的；我們只有一位父，就是上帝。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse42">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus neini-æn, Heirou Rarama'noumi ta Alid, ynna-kamou ka-væ'ængs jau-an: ka ni-pa'-kka-rbou-en-nau ki Alid mou-pæ-nah. Ka assi-koh sykkounoun-ato ierroua, ra tenita ni-madingi jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus neini-æn, Heirou Rarama'noumi ta Alid, ynna-kamou ka-væ'ængs jau-an: ka ni-pa'-kka-rbou-en-nau ki Alid mou-pæ-nah. Ka assi-koh sykkounoun-ato ierroua, ra tenita ni-madingi jau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus Dan fseyde tot haer Indien Godt uwe DaDer ware soo soudet ghy My lief hebben : want ich ben ban Godt uytgegaen ende kome [van hem]. Want ick en ben ock ban my selben niet gekomen maer hy heeft my gesonden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus said unto them, If God were your Father, ye would love me: for I proceeded forth and came from God; neither came I of myself, but he sent me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：「倘若上帝是你們的父，你們就必愛我；因為我本是出於上帝，也是從上帝而來，並不是由着自己來，乃是他差我來。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse43">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka-oumang ka assi-ka-mou kmalang ki yngau-au ? Alei-[ato] ka assi-kamou tna-lpough millingigh ki fou-au.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka-oumang ka assi-ka-mou kmalang ki yngau-au ? Alei-[ato] ka assi-kamou tna-lpough millingigh ki fou-au.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Waeron en kent ghy mijne sprake niet: [Het is] om Dat ghy mijn woort niet en kondt hooren.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Why do ye not understand my speech? even because ye cannot hear my word.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們為甚麼不明白我的話呢？無非是因你們不能聽我的道。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse44">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Emoumi-ra, ni-makka-koua ki rama ki Littou, ka ma-moei-kamou pamut ki kamoei-in ki raraman-oumi. Na tama-Ipough ki ka-æuloung makka naunamou tateni, ka assi ni-i-tou-ka koua tou katiktik-kan ki sou : alei ka 3ou-si tyni-æn ki katiktik-kan ki fou. Irou mattæ'i-harang ta teni, masousou ki tæ'i-koua tyni-æn: alei ka tama-si-haharang ta teni, ki rama-appa ki [si-haharang-en] k'anna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Emoumi-ra, ni-makka-koua ki rama ki Littou, ka ma-moei-kamou pamut ki kamoei-in ki raraman-oumi. Na tama-Ipough ki ka-æuloung makka naunamou tateni, ka assi ni-i-tou-ka koua tou katiktik-kan ki sou : alei ka 3ou-si tyni-æn ki katiktik-kan ki fou. Irou mattæ'i-harang ta teni, masousou ki tæ'i-koua tyni-æn: alei ka tama-si-haharang ta teni, ki rama-appa ki [si-haharang-en] k'anna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ghy zijt uyt Den bader Den Duybel ende wilt De begeerten uwes baders doen. Die wae een menschenmoorder bal Den beginne ende en is in De waerheydt niet staende gebleben: want geen waerheydt en is in gem. Wanneer hy De leughen spreekt soo spreeckt hy uyt sijnsijn eygen : want hy is een leugenaer ende De bader der selbe [leugen].</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Ye are of your father the devil, and the lusts of your father ye will do. He was a murderer from the beginning, and abode not in the truth, because there is no truth in him. When he speaketh a lie, he speaketh of his own: for he is a liar, and the father of it.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們是出於你們的父魔鬼，你們父的私慾你們偏要行。他從起初是殺人的，不守真理，因他心裏沒有真理。他說謊是出於自己；因他本來是說謊的，也是說謊之人的父。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse45">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ra ti jau, alei ka pasou-ea-nau ta katiktik-kan ki sou, assi-môumi tna-msing-en.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ra ti jau, alei ka pasou-ea-nau ta katiktik-kan ki sou, assi-môumi tna-msing-en.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Maer my om Dat ick [u] De waerheyt segge en gelooft ghy niet.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And because I tell you the truth, ye believe me not.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我將真理告訴你們，你們就因此不信我。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse46">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ti-mang ymoumi-æn ta tmunub jau-an ki varau? heirou ka pasousou-en-nau ta katiktik-kan ki sou, ka'umang ka assi-ka-mou tna-msing jau-an?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ti-mang ymoumi-æn ta tmunub jau-an ki varau? heirou ka pasousou-en-nau ta katiktik-kan ki sou, ka'umang ka assi-ka-mou tna-msing jau-an?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Wie ban u obertuyght my ban sonde ? ende indien ick De waerheydt segge waerom en gelooft ghy my niet?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Which of you convinceth me of sin? And if I say the truth, why do ye not believe me?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們中間誰能指證我有罪呢？我既然將真理告訴你們，為甚麼不信我呢？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse47">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ti-mamang ta makka-koua ki Alid, millingigh ki na sou ki Alid: alei ki anna assi-moumi 'illing-hgen, alei ka assi-kamou makka-koua-ato ki Alid.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ti-mamang ta makka-koua ki Alid, millingigh ki na sou ki Alid: alei ki anna assi-moumi 'illing-hgen, alei ka assi-kamou makka-koua-ato ki Alid.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Die uyt Godt is Hoort De woorden Godts : Daerom en Hoort ghy-lieden niet om Dat ghy uyt Godt niet en zijj.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">He that is of God heareth God's words: ye therefore hear them not, because ye are not of God.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">出於上帝的，必聽上帝的話；你們不聽，因為你們不是出於上帝。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse48">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-mattæ'i v'lli ta Joden k'ma tyni-æn, Assi-kame kau wa mariang ki fou ka Samaritaen kow ka a kou Lyttou kow?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-mattæ'i v'lli ta Joden k'ma tyni-æn, Assi-kame kau wa mariang ki fou ka Samaritaen kow ka a kou Lyttou kow?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> De Joden Dan antwoordden ende seyden tot hem En seggen wy niet wel Dat ghy een Samaritaen zijt ende den Duybel hebt ?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then answered the Jews, and said unto him, Say we not well that thou art a Samaritan, and hast a devil?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">猶太人回答說：「我們說你是撒馬利亞人，並且是鬼附着的，這話豈不正對嗎？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse49">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta ti Jesus, Äou-si ki Littou jau-an, râ loumoulough-koh ki Raraman-nau, ymoumita moupagh ki lou-loug-an [mouroung] jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta ti Jesus, Äou-si ki Littou jau-an, râ loumoulough-koh ki Raraman-nau, ymoumita moupagh ki lou-loug-an [mouroung] jau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus antwoordden Ick en hebbe Den Dyubel niet maer ick eere mijnen Dader ende ghy onteert my.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus answered, I have not a devil; but I honour my Father, and ye do dishonour me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：「我不是鬼附着的；我尊敬我的父，你們倒輕慢我。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse50">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ra assi-koh kmi'ym ki louloug-an jau-an: akoumea ki kmi'ym ka dmungdunng-a'.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ra assi-koh kmi'ym ki louloug-an jau-an: akoumea ki kmi'ym ka dmungdunng-a'.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> [@Doch] ick en soeke mijne eere niet : Daer is een diese soeckt ende oordeelt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And I seek not mine own glory: there is one that seeketh and judgeth.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我不求自己的榮耀，有一位為我求榮耀、定是非的。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse51">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Missing, missing koun-nau-kamou, Heirou hma-âl-ato ta ti-mamang ki sou-au, assi kmytt-'ah ki kapatei-an tou yhka-kouan myddaryn-nough.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Missing, missing koun-nau-kamou, Heirou hma-âl-ato ta ti-mamang ki sou-au, assi kmytt-'ah ki kapatei-an tou yhka-kouan myddaryn-nough.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Doorwaer boorwaer segge ick u So yemandt mijn woordt sal bewaert hebben die en sal den doodt niet sien in Der eeuwigheyt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Verily, verily, I say unto you, If a man keep my saying, he shall never see death.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我實實在在地告訴你們，人若遵守我的道，就永遠不見死。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse52">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annatani-k'mata Joden tyni-æn, Hnyn kavana-'n-niæn ka akou Littou kow. Ni-mapa-tei ta ti Abraham, ki na Tama-Mat: tæ'i-tan-appa: ka mattæ'i-k'ma-ah kauwa-hynna ki sou, Hei-rou hma-il-ato ta ti-mamang ki sou-au, assi k-dymman-ah ki ka-patei-an touyhkakou-an mydda-rynnough?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annatani-k'mata Joden tyni-æn, Hnyn kavana-'n-niæn ka akou Littou kow. Ni-mapa-tei ta ti Abraham, ki na Tama-Mat: tæ'i-tan-appa: ka mattæ'i-k'ma-ah kauwa-hynna ki sou, Hei-rou hma-il-ato ta ti-mamang ki sou-au, assi k-dymman-ah ki kapatei-an touyhkakou-an mydda-rynnough?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> De Joden dan seyden tottot hem Nu bekennen wy dat ghy Den Duybel Hebt. Abraham is gestorden ende De Propheten: ende Seght gy Soo yemandt mijn woort bewaert sal hebben Die en sal den doodt niet smaken in Der eeuwigheyt :</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then said the Jews unto him, Now we know that thou hast a devil. Abraham is dead, and the prophets; and thou sayest, If a man keep my saying, he shall never taste of death.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">猶太人對他說：「現在我們知道你是鬼附着的。亞伯拉罕死了，眾先知也死了，你還說：『人若遵守我的道，就永遠不嘗死味。』</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse53">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Si-ourou kow kauwa tou vavau ki kidi ki na' Ramou-jan Ka ti Abraham ka ni-mapatei-ato? ka nimapatei-appa ta na Mattæ'i-tan: pæh-koua-en-hou timang-an: pæh-madou ymhouan ?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Si-ourou kow kauwa tou vavau ki kidi ki na' Ramou-jan Ka ti Abraham ka ni-mapatei-ato? ka nimapatei-appa ta na Mattæ'i-tan: pæh-koua-en-hou timang-an: pæh-madou ymhouan ?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Zijt ghy meer der Dan onse bader Abraham welcke gestorben is: ende De Propheten zijn gestorben : Wien maeckt ghy u selben :</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Art thou greater than our father Abraham, which is dead? and the prophets are dead: whom makest thou thyself?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">難道你比我們的祖宗亞伯拉罕還大嗎？他死了，眾先知也死了，你將自己當作甚麼人呢？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse54">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-mattæ'i-v'lita ti Jesus, Heirou pou-madou-koh pou-vavau ki kidi jau-an, sauki-na-nynno ta keirang-en ki kidi-au: ri ti Ama-appa-mau ta pou-va-vauki kidi jau-an, teni Ka Alid-jang koun-neumi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-mattæ'i-v'lita ti Jesus, Heirou pou-madou-koh pou-vavau ki kidi jau-an, sauki-na-nynno ta keirang-en ki kidi-au: ri ti Ama-appa-mau ta pou-va-vauki kidi jau-an, teni Ka Alid-jang koun-neumi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus anwooorddde Indien ick my selben eere soo en is mijje eere niets : mijn Dader is Het Die my eert welcken ghy seght Dat uwe Godt is.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus answered, If I honour myself, my honour is nothing: it is my Father that honoureth me; of whom ye say, that he is your God:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌回答說：「我若榮耀自己，我的榮耀就算不得甚麼；榮耀我的乃是我的父，就是你們所說是你們的上帝。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse55">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka assi-kamou kmalang tyni-æn, rd kalang-en-nau ta te-ni: heirou K'ma-koh, assi-mau: k'alang-en ta teni, mam'sl-ato-koh ymoumi-n ka tama-si-haha-rang: ra k'alang-en-nau ta teni, ka hma-koh ki sou tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka assi-kamou kmalang tyni-æn, rd kalang-en-nau ta te-ni: heirou K'ma-koh, assi-mau: k'alang-en ta teni, mam'sl-ato-koh ymoumi-n ka tama-si-haha-rang: ra k'alang-en-nau ta teni, ka hma-koh ki sou tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende ghy en kent hem niet maer ick kenne hem: ende indlen ick segge Dat ick hem niet en kenne so Zal ick ulieden geliick zijn [dat is] een leugenaer : maer Ick kenne hem ende beware sijn woord.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Yet ye have not known him; but I know him: and if I should say, I know him not, I shall be a liar like unto you: but I know him, and keep his saying.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們未曾認識他；我卻認識他。我若說不認識他，我就是說謊的，像你們一樣；但我認識他，也遵守他的道。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse56">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ti Abraham ka na rama-mou-n-oumi ni-mapangau ki tat-batban ki moei ka k'ytts-eih tyn ta wa'i-au: ka ni-k'ytt'an tyn [ta atta,] ka ni-marai-atou-ra.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ti Abraham ka na rama-mou-n-oumi ni-mapangau ki tat-batban ki moei ka k'ytts-eih tyn ta wa'i-au: ka ni-k'ytt'an tyn [ta atta,] ka ni-marai-atou-ra.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Abraham uwe Dader heeft met berheunginghe berlanght op Dat Hy mijnen dagh sien soude : ende Hy heeft [hem] gesien ende ig berblijt geweest.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Your father Abraham rejoiced to see my day: and he saw it, and was glad.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們的祖宗亞伯拉罕歡歡喜喜地仰望我的日子，既看見了就快樂。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse57">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-k'ma ta Joden tyni-æn, Ä'ou-si-appa kow ki rymma kytti-æn ki tauwil, ka ni-k'ytta-en-hou kauwa ta ti Abraham?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-k'ma ta Joden tyni-æn, Ä'ou-si-appa kow ki rymma kytti-æn ki tauwil, ka ni-k'ytta-en-hou kauwa ta ti Abraham?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> De De Joden dan seyden tot hem Ghy en Hebt noch geen bijftigh jaren ende hebt ghy Abraham gesien:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then said the Jews unto him, Thou art not yet fifty years old, and hast thou seen Abraham?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">猶太人說：「你還沒有五十歲，豈見過亞伯拉罕呢？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse58">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus neini-æn, Missing, missing koun-nau-kamou-ra, Si-ourou ka akoumea tati Abraham, akoumea-koh ti jau </FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus neini-æn, Missing, missing koun-nau-kamou-ra, Si-ourou ka akoumea tati Abraham, akoumea-koh ti jau </FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus seyde tot haer Doordwaer boorwaer segge ick u Eer Abraham was ben ick.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus said unto them, Verily, verily, I say unto you, Before Abraham was, I am.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：「我實實在在地告訴你們，還沒有亞伯拉罕就有了我。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse59">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-'ara nein ta vahtou ki cyt-an-eih' tyni-æn: Ra ni-sou-i-vung ta ti Jesus sa-mamala tou K'ouva ki tatam'd-den ki Alid, ka ni-tmou-kad nei-ni-æn, mali-æuragh komma-hyn-na.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-'ara nein ta vahtou ki cyt-an-eih' tyni-æn: Ra ni-sou-i-vung ta ti Jesus sa-mamala tou K'ouva ki tatam'd-den ki Alid, ka ni-tmou-kad nei-ni-æn, mali-æuragh komma-hyn-na.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Sy namen Dan steenen op Dat sy'se op hem. wierpen. Maer Jesus berberghde hem ende gingh uyt den Tempel gaende Door Het midden ban haer : ende gingh alsoo boorby.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then took they up stones to cast at him: but Jesus hid himself, and went out of the temple, going through the midst of them, and so passed by.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">於是他們拿石頭要打他；耶穌卻躲藏，從殿裏出去了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
</TEXT>