<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEXT id="Siraya_Dutch_John_Chapter19" xml:lang="fos" source="Siraya Bible, John gospel" copyright="public domain" citation="Gravius, Daniël. 1661. Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa. Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang. Amsterdam: Michiel Hartogh." BibTeX_citation="@book{Gravius1661,&#10;  author    = {Gravius, Daniël},&#10;  year      = {1661},&#10;  title     = {Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa},&#10;  note      = {Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang},&#10;  address   = {Amsterdam},&#10;  publisher = {Michiel Hartogh}&#10;}">
    <S id="verse1">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Tou kidi kanna ni-mara ka ti Pilatus ti Jesus-an, ka ni-patæu-burigh smaplat [tyni-n.]</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Tou kidi kanna ni-mara ka ti Pilatus ti Jesus-an, ka ni-patæu-burigh smaplat [tyni-n.]</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Doe name Pilatus Dan Jesum ende geessclde [hem].</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then Pilate therefore took Jesus, and scourged him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">當下彼拉多將耶穌鞭打了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse2">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka 't-kaha tmynnoun ta masacyt ki sakierrou kina adim, ni-poukoua paka-halap tou voun-go tyn, ka ni-pa-pah-koulamough-appa tyni-n ki kouvar ka na pa-tagh ka mamei ki apoei.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka 't-kaha tmynnoun ta masacyt ki sakierrou kina adim, ni-poukoua paka-halap tou voun-go tyn, ka ni-pa-pah-koulamough-appa tyni-n ki kouvar ka na pa-tagh ka mamei ki apoei.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende de krijghs-kenichten een kroone ban Doornen gemblochten hebbende setteden Die op sijn hooft ende Wierpen hem een purpuren kleedt om.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And the soldiers platted a crown of thorns, and put it on his head, and they put on him a purple robe,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">兵丁用荊棘編做冠冕戴在他頭上，給他穿上紫袍，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse3">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-k'ma, Tabe, Mei-sa-sou 'ka Si-bavau ki Joden. Kani-tmaplagh tou tymmi tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-k'ma, Tabe, Mei-sasou 'ka Si-bavau ki Joden. Kani-tmaplagh tou tymmi tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende seyen Weest gegroet ghy koningh Der Joden. Ende sy gaben hem kinneback-slagen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And said, Hail, King of the Jews! and they smote him with their hands.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">又挨近他，說：「恭喜，猶太人的王啊！」他們就用手掌打他。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse4">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-mi-la tati Pilatus sa-ma-mala, kma neini-æn, K'yt-tei,pa-'ou-pænæh-en-nau ta teni ymoumi-n, alei ka kavan'-ei-moumi, kaassi-mau pa-ki-valei-en ta varau tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-mi-la tati Pilatus sa-ma-mala, kma neini-æn, K'yttei,pa-'ou-pænæh-en-nau ta teni ymoumi-n, alei ka kavan'-ei-moumi, kaassi-mau pa-ki-valei-en ta varau tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Pilatus dan quam wederomt uyt ende seyde tot haer Siet ick brenge hem tot u-lieden uyt op Dat ghy wetet Dat ick in Hem geen schult en binde.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Pilate therefore went forth again, and saith unto them, Behold, I bring him forth to you, that ye may know that I find no fault in him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">彼拉多又出來對眾人說：「我帶他出來見你們，叫你們知道我查不出他有甚麼罪來。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse5">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-sa-mamala ta ti Jesus, ka ni-paka-sakierrou ki na adim mah-keulamough ki na pa-tagh ka mama ki apoei. Ka ni-k'ma [ta ti Pilatus]neini-æn,Kyt-tei, ta ka'euloung.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-sa-mamala ta ti Jesus, ka ni-paka-sakierrou ki na adim mah-keulamough ki na pa-tagh ka mama ki apoei. Ka ni-k'ma [ta ti Pilatus]neini-æn,Kyt-tei, ta ka'euloung.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus dan quam uyt dragende De doornen kroone ende het purpuren kleedt. Ende [Pilatus] seyde tot haer Siet De mensche.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then came Jesus forth, wearing the crown of thorns, and the purple robe. And Pilate saith unto them, Behold the man!</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌出來，戴着荊棘冠冕，穿着紫袍。\+pn 彼拉多\+pn*對他們說：「你們看這個人！」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse6">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka kmytta tyni-æn ta Tama-P'hgik ka Si-bavau ki ma-koua -appa fi-darim.[ neini-æn, ]ni-makou-ligh ta neni, k'ma, Pou-na-yæværæ-æ, pou-na-væværæ-æ tyni-æn. Ni-k'ma ta ti Pilatus neini-æn, Ar-'au-to tyni-æn ta ymoumi, ka pou-na-væværæ-æ tyni-æn. Nda assi-en-nau maki-valei ta varau tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka kmytta tyni-æn ta Tama-P'hgik ka Si-bavau ki ma-koua -appa fi-darim.[ neini-æn, ]ni-makou-ligh ta neni, k'ma, Pou-na-yæværæ-æ, pou-na-væværæ-æ tyni-æn. Ni-k'ma ta ti Pilatus neini-æn, Ar-'au-to tyni-æn ta ymoumi, ka pou-na-væværæ-æ tyni-æn. Nda assi-en-nau maki-valei ta varau tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Als hem dan de Oberpriesters ende De dienaers sagen riepen sy seggende kruyst [hem,] kruyst [hem]. Pilatus seyde tot Haer Neemt Neemt ghy-lieden hem ende kruyst [hem]. Want ick en binde in Gem geen schuld.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">When the chief priests therefore and officers saw him, they cried out, saying, Crucify him, crucify him. Pilate saith unto them, Take ye him, and crucify him: for I find no fault in him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">祭司長和差役看見他，就喊着說：「釘他十字架！釘他十字架！」彼拉多說：「你們自己把他釘十字架吧！我查不出他有甚麼罪來。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse7">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-mattæ'i-vlli ta Joden tyni-æn, Akou Tatouhko-kame, ka mapatei-ah ta teni ki Tatouh-ko-jan, alei ka ni-pou-madou-en tyn pou-Alak ki Alid tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-mattæ'i-vlli ta Joden tyni-æn, Akou Tatouhko-kame, ka mapatei-ah ta teni ki Tatouh-ko-jan, alei ka ni-pou-madou-en tyn pou-Alak ki Alid tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> De Joden antwoorden hem Wy hebben een Wet en na onse Wet moet hy sterbenwant hy heeft hem-selben tot Godts Sone gemaeckt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">The Jews answered him, We have a law, and by our law he ought to die, because he made himself the Son of God.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">猶太人回答說：「我們有律法，按那律法，他是該死的，因他以自己為上帝的兒子。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse8">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka millingigh ki sou k'atta ta ti Pilatus, ni-kasaoun-nen tyn mahtakout.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka millingigh ki sou k'atta ta ti Pilatus, ni-kasaoun-nen tyn mahtakout.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Doe Pilatus Dan Dit woordt hoorde wierdt hy meer bebreeft </TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">When Pilate therefore heard that saying, he was the more afraid;</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">彼拉多聽見這話，越發害怕，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse9">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-mou-rbo mi-la tou ta-lach ka keirang-en ki papæmæmæ-æn, ka ni-k'ma ti Jesus-an, Mang kow ki euma? Râ assi ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta ti Jesus ki sou tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-mou-rbo mi-la tou ta-lach ka keirang-en ki papæmæmæ-æn, ka ni-k'ma ti Jesus-an, Mang kow ki euma? Râ assi ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta ti Jesus ki sou tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende gingh wederom in het Rechthuys seyde tot Jesum Dan maer zijt gh? Maer Jesus en gaf hem geen antwoordt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And went again into the judgment hall, and saith unto Jesus, Whence art thou? But Jesus gave him no answer.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">又進衙門，對耶穌說：「你是哪裏來的？」耶穌卻不回答。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse10">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Anna ta ni-kma ta ti Pilatus tyni-æn, Assi ymhou-kauwa ka yngau-eihjau-an? Assi kow kauwa mou-mhga ka akou-ligh-koh tou pou-na-vævære-hæn ymhou-an, ka akou-ligh-app'-oh tou 'æumi'-en ymhou-an?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Anna ta ni-kma ta ti Pilatus tyni-æn, Assi ymhou-kauwa ka yngau-eihjau-an? Assi kow kauwa mou-mhga ka akou-ligh-koh tou pou-na-vævære-hæn ymhou-an, ka akou-ligh-app'-oh tou 'æumi'-en ymhou-an?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Pilatus dan seyde tot hem En spreeckt ghy tot my niet : Weet ghy niet Dat ick macht hebbe u te kruycigen ende macht hebbe u los te laten :</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then saith Pilate unto him, Speakest thou not unto me? knowest thou not that I have power to crucify thee, and have power to release thee?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">彼拉多說：「你不對我說話嗎？你豈不知我有權柄釋放你，也有權柄把你釘十字架嗎？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse11">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta ti Jesus, A'ou-si-ah-kow ki ligh jau-an, heirou ni-ynna pæp'æn ta atta makka vavau ymhou-an: alei ki anna teni ka ni-pæ'æ-tounnoun jau-an ymhou-an, akou varau ka. si-ourou irang.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta ti Jesus, A'ou-si-ah-kow ki ligh jau-an, heirou ni-ynna pæp'æn ta atta makka vavau ymhou-an: alei ki anna teni ka ni-pæ'æ-tounnoun jau-an ymhou-an, akou varau ka. si-ourou irang.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus antwoordde Gny en soudt geen macht hebben tegen my indien het u niet ban boden gegeben en ware : daerom Die my aen u heeft odergelebert heeft grooter sonde.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus answered, Thou couldest have no power at all against me, except it were given thee from above: therefore he that delivered me unto thee hath the greater sin.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌回答說：「若不是從上頭賜給你的，你就毫無權柄辦我。所以，把我交給你的那人罪更重了。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse12">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Tou kidi kanna ni-kmi-'ym ta ti Pilatus ki'æumi-'eih tyn tyni-æn: râ ni-makou-toun ta Joden, k'ma, Heirou mæumia kow ti att'-an, assi-ato kow rieu ki Si-atighSi-bavau: vejagh ka papei-nade pa-Pei-sasou tyni-e n, makou-douma ta teni ki sou ki Si-atigh Si-bavau.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Tou kidi kanna ni-kmi-'ym ta ti Pilatus ki'æumi-'eih tyn tyni-æn: râ ni-makou-toun ta Joden, k'ma, Heirou mæumia kow ti att'-an, assi-ato kow rieu ki Si-atighSi-bavau: vejagh ka papei-nade pa-Pei-sasou tyni-e n, makou-douma ta teni ki sou ki Si-atigh Si-bavau.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Dan doen af socht Pilatus hem los te laten : maer De Joden riepen seggende InIndien ghy desen los laet soo en zijt ghy des keypsers briend niet : een yegelick die hem-selben koning maeckt weder spreeckt Den keyser </TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And from thenceforth Pilate sought to release him: but the Jews cried out, saying, If thou let this man go, thou art not Caesar's friend: whosoever maketh himself a king speaketh against Caesar.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">從此，彼拉多想要釋放耶穌，無奈猶太人喊着說：「你若釋放這個人，就不是凱撒的忠臣。凡以自己為王的，就是背叛凱撒了。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse13">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka ni-millingigh ta ti Pilatus ki sou katta, ni-ad-tyn tati Jesus pa-sa-mamala, ka ni-mier-roung tou ierraroung-an pa-pa-mæmæh tou i-tou-kou-'an ka pa-nanang-en Lithostrotos, ra tou sou ki Hebreen Gabbatha.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka ni-millingigh ta ti Pilatus ki sou katta, ni-ad-tyn tati Jesus pa-sa-mamala, ka ni-mier-roung tou ierraroung-an pa-pa-mæmæh tou i-tou-kou-'an ka pa-nanang-en Lithostrotos, ra tou sou ki Hebreen Gabbatha.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Als Pilatus Dan Dit woordt hoorde bracht hy Jeum uyt emde sat neder op den Rechter hdelf de plaetse genaemt Lithostrotos ende in het Hebreensch Gabbatha.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">When Pilate therefore heard that saying, he brought Jesus forth, and sat down in the judgment seat in a place that is called the Pavement, but in the Hebrew, Gabbatha.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">彼拉多聽見這話，就帶耶穌出來，到了一個地方，名叫「鋪華石處」，希伯來話叫厄巴大，就在那裏坐堂。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse14">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka si-ttata-nan-en-ato ta 'Ou-vavatoug-han ki Halida-eu-en, tou hivat lavaki ka innim ki tæ'lei: ka ni-k'ma ki Joden, K 'yt-tei, ta Mei-sasou ka Si-bavau ymoumi-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka si-ttata-nan-en-ato ta 'Ou-vavatoug-han ki Halida-eu-en, tou hivat lavaki ka innim ki tæ'lei: ka ni-k'ma ki Joden, K 'yt-tei, ta Mei-sasou ka Si-bavau ymoumi-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Eude het was de boorbereydinghe Des Pascha enDe ontrent De seste uyre : enDe hy seyde tot De Joden Siet uwe Koningh.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And it was the preparation of the passover, and about the sixth hour: and he saith unto the Jews, Behold your King!</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那日是預備逾越節的日子，約有午正。彼拉多對猶太人說：「看哪，這是你們的王！」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse15">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Râni-makou-toun ta neni, Ar'au, ar'au, pou-navava ræ-'ato tyni-æn. Ni-k'ma ta ti Pilatusneini-æn, Pou-ra-væy-ræh-ei-mau kauwa ta Mei-sasou ka Si-bavau ymoumi-æn ? Ni-mattæ'i-vlli ta Tama-P'hgik ka Si-bavau, Aou-si-kame ki Meisa-sou, dyk ki Si-atigh Si-bavau.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Râni-makou-toun ta neni, Ar'au, ar'au, pou-navava ræ-'ato tyni-æn. Ni-k'ma ta ti Pilatusneini-æn, Pou-ra-væy-ræh-ei-mau kauwa ta Mei-sasou ka Si-bavau ymoumi-æn ? Ni-mattæ'i-vlli ta Tama-P'hgik ka Si-bavau, Aou-si-kame ki Meisasou, dyk ki Si-atigh Si-bavau.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Maer sy riepen Neemt wech neemt wech kruyst hem. Pilatus seyde tot haer Sal ick uwen koningh kruycigen : De Oberpriesters antwoordden Wyn en Hebben geenen Koningh Dan den Keyser.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But they cried out, Away with him, away with him, crucify him. Pilate saith unto them, Shall I crucify your King? The chief priests answered, We have no king but Caesar.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們喊着說：「除掉他！除掉他！釘他在十字架上！」彼拉多說：「我可以把你們的王釘十字架嗎？」祭司長回答說：「除了凱撒，我們沒有王。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse16">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-pæ'æ-toun noun tyni-æn pæ'æ-koua neini-æn, alei ka pou-nævæværæh-ei-Jato tateni. Ka ni-mara ta neniti Jesus-an patæu-pænæh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-pæ'æ-toun noun tyni-æn pæ'æ-koua neini-æn, alei ka pou-nævæværæh-ei-Jato tateni. Ka ni-mara ta neniti Jesus-an patæu-pænæh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Doe gaf hy hem dan Haer ober op Dat hy ghekruyst soude worden. Ende sy namen Jesum ende leydden [hem] wech.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then delivered he him therefore unto them to be crucified. And they took Jesus, and led him away.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">於是彼拉多將耶穌交給他們去釘十字架。 （太27‧32－44；可15‧21－32；路23‧26－43）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse17">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka aval-len tyn ta na væværæh tyn, ni-tpæpænæhmou-koua [tou i-tou-kou-'an] ka pa-nanang-en i-tou-kou'-an ki tok-touk ki voungo, râ tou sou ki Hebreen Golgatha:</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka aval-len tyn ta na væværæh tyn, ni-tpæpænæhmou-koua [tou i-tou-kou-'an] ka pa-nanang-en i-tou-kou'-an ki tok-touk ki voungo, râ tou sou ki Hebreen Golgatha:</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende hy dragende sijn kruys gingh uyt na de [plaetse] ghenaemt Hooftscheelscheel-plaetse welcke in het Hebreeusch genaemt wordt Golgatha :</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And he bearing his cross went forth into a place called the place of a skull, which is called in the Hebrew Golgotha:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們就把耶穌帶了去。耶穌背着自己的十字架出來，到了一個地方，名叫「髑髏地」，希伯來話叫各各他。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse18">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Tou hynna ni-pou-navæ-væræh tyni-æn, ka pou-lam appa tyni-æn rarouha ki pani, tou idi-idi ki sasasat, ka ni-pou-toukad-den nein ta ti Jesus.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Tou hynna ni-pou-navæ-væræh tyni-æn, ka pou-lam appa tyni-æn rarouha ki pani, tou idi-idi ki sasasat, ka ni-pou-toukad-den nein ta ti Jesus.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Alwaer sy hem kruysten ende Met hem twee andere aen elcke zijde eenen ende Jesum in't midden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Where they crucified him, and two other with him, on either side one, and Jesus in the midst.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們就在那裏釘他在十字架上，還有兩個人和他一同釘着，一邊一個，耶穌在中間。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse19">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-smoulad-appa ta ti Pilatus ki na æ'ǣ-halap, ka atta-halap-pen tyn tou na væværæh: ka ni-soulat-tyn kma-hynna, JESUS KA MAKKA NAZARETH MEISASOU KA SI-BAVAU KI JODEN.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-smoulad-appa ta ti Pilatus ki na æ'ǣ-halap, ka atta-halap-pen tyn tou na væværæh: ka ni-soulat-tyn kma-hynna, JESUS KA MAKKA NAZARETH MEISASOU KA SI-BAVAU KI JODEN.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende Pilatus schreef oock een opscrift ende sette: de [dat] op het kruys : ende Daer was geschreben Jesus de Nazarener, de Koningh der Joden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And Pilate wrote a title, and put it on the cross. And the writing was JESUS OF NAZARETH THE KING OF THE JEWS.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">彼拉多又用牌子寫了一個名號，安在十字架上，寫的是：「猶太人的王，拿撒勒人耶穌。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse20">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Na æǣ-halap kanna ta ni-kitting ki mabatoung ki Joden: alei ka tou tamang ki Euma ta i-tou-kou-'an ki ni-pou-na-væ-væræh-in ta ti Jesus: ka ni-soulat-tin ta anna tou sou ki Hebreen, ki Griekken; ki Romeynen.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Na æǣ-halap kanna ta ni-kitting ki mabatoung ki Joden: alei ka tou tamang ki Euma ta i-tou-kou-'an ki ni-pou-na-væ-væræh-in ta ti Jesus: ka ni-soulat-tin ta anna tou sou ki Hebreen, ki Griekken; ki Romeynen.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Dit opschrift Dan lasen bele ban de Joden : wand de plaetse daer Jesus gekruyt wiert was na by De stadt : ende Het was geschreben in 't Hebreeusch in 't Griecks [ende] in't Latijn.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">This title then read many of the Jews: for the place where Jesus was crucified was nigh to the city: and it was written in Hebrew, and Greek, and Latin.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">有許多猶太人念這名號；因為耶穌被釘十字架的地方與城相近，並且是用希伯來、羅馬、希臘三樣文字寫的。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse21">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-k'ma ta Ta-ma-P'hgik ka Si-bavau ki Joden ti Pilatus-an, Ynn'-ei-to smoulat, Ta Mei-sasou ka Si-bavau ki Joden: Râ att-'appa, ka ni-pa-sou-sou-en tyn, Mei-sasou-koh ka Si-bavau ki Joden.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-k'ma ta Ta-ma-P'hgik ka Si-bavau ki Joden ti Pilatus-an, Ynn'-ei-to smoulat, Ta Mei-sasou ka Si-bavau ki Joden: Râ att-'appa, ka ni-pa-sousou-en tyn, Mei-sasou-koh ka Si-bavau ki Joden.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> De Ober priesters Dan der Joden seyden tot Pilatum En schrijft niet De koningh der Joden : maer dat hy geseght heeft Ick ben be Koningh Der Joden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then said the chief priests of the Jews to Pilate, Write not, The King of the Jews; but that he said, I am King of the Jews.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">猶太人的祭司長就對彼拉多說：「不要寫『猶太人的王』，要寫『他自己說：我是猶太人的王』。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse22">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-mattæ'i v'lli ta ti Pilatus, Ka ni-soulat-en-nau, ta ni-soulat-en-nau.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-mattæ'i v'lli ta ti Pilatus, Ka ni-soulat-en-nau, ta ni-soulat-en-nau.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Pilatus antwoordde Dat ick geschreben hebbe [dat] hebbe ick geschreben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Pilate answered, What I have written I have written.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">彼拉多說：「我所寫的，我已經寫上了。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse23">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Masacyt k'anna rou ni-pou-na-væværæh ti Jesus-an, ni-mara ki ni-pammi-en tyn, (ka hi-pat-tan nyn, mætætæh ki masacijt ka sasasat ta sasat ki ætæh) ki sou-loei-appa. Ka roul-lin ka souloei kanna ta sou-si ki ni-paddo-do-m'-an, ra makka-vavau ni-t'mouk tmynoun.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Masacyt k'anna rou ni-pou-na-væværæh ti Jesus-an, ni-mara ki ni-pammi-en tyn, (ka hi-pat-tan nyn, mætætæh ki masacijt ka sasasat ta sasat ki ætæh) ki sou-loei-appa. Ka roul-lin ka souloei kanna ta sou-si ki ni-paddo-do-m'-an, ra makka-vavau ni-t'mouk tmynoun.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">. De krijgs-knechten Dan als sy Jesum gekruyst Hadden namen sijne kleederen ren (ende maeckten bier deelen boor elcken krijghsknecht een Deel :) ende DEN rock. De rock nu was sonder naet ban boben af geheelick geweben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then the soldiers, when they had crucified Jesus, took his garments, and made four parts, to every soldier a part; and also his coat: now the coat was without seam, woven from the top throughout.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">兵丁既然將耶穌釘在十字架上，就拿他的衣服分為四分，每兵一分；又拿他的裏衣，這件裏衣原來沒有縫兒，是上下一片織成的。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse24">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Anna ta ni-mættævæte-væh ta neni ki sou, Ynn'-eta ki'it ki atta, rd pakiau-eta rou-a-ti-mang-ah: alei ka paveut-auh ta na Sa-Soulat, kak'ma, Ni-matatag-ato ki ni-pamia-en-nau, ni-pa-kiau-appa alei ki koulamough-au. Attatani-pamt-ten ki masa-cyt.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Anna ta ni-mættævæte-væh ta neni ki sou, Ynn'-eta ki'it ki atta, rd pakiau-eta rou-a-ti-mang-ah: alei ka paveut-auh ta na Sa-Soulat, kak'ma, Ni-matatag-ato ki ni-pamia-en-nau, ni-pa-kiau-appa alei ki koulamough-au. Attatani-pamt-ten ki masa-cyt.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Sy dan seyden tot malnanderen Laet ons dien niet scheuren maer laet ons daer ober loten Wiens [die] zijn zal: op Dat de Schrift ber: bult worde Die seght Sy Hebben mijne kleederen onDer haer berdeelt ende Ober mijne kleedinge hebben sy het lot geworpen. Dit hehben Dan De krijghs-knechten geDaen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">They said therefore among themselves, Let us not rend it, but cast lots for it, whose it shall be: that the scripture might be fulfilled, which saith, They parted my raiment among them, and for my vesture they did cast lots. These things therefore the soldiers did.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們就彼此說：「我們不要撕開，只要拈鬮，看誰得着。」這要應驗經上的話說：</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse25">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-mi-touk ki na va-varæh ti Jesus mitouhko ta rare-nantyn, kitæ'i-appara-appa ki rarenan tyn, ti Maria ka [ni-kei-ja]ti Klope, ti Maria-appa Magdalena.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-mi-touk ki na va-varæh ti Jesus mitouhko ta rare-nantyn, kitæ'i-appara-appa ki rarenan tyn, ti Maria ka [ni-kei-ja]ti Klope, ti Maria-appa Magdalena.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende by Het kruyce Jesu stonden sijne Moeder ende sijns moeders suster Maria Clope [wijf], ende Maria Magdalene.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Now there stood by the cross of Jesus his mother, and his mother's sister, Mary the wife of Cleophas, and Mary Magdalene.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">站在耶穌十字架旁邊的，有他母親與他母親的姊妹，並革羅罷的妻子馬利亞，和抹大拉的馬利亞。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse26">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka kmytta ta ti Jesus ki Raren-'an [tyn,] ki Pahtatæutæu-'en appa ka kava'angs-en tyn ka i-tou-lam mi-'ttouko, ni-k'ma ki raren-'an tyn, I-na, kyt-tei ta Alak-oho.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka kmytta ta ti Jesus ki Raren-'an [tyn,] ki Pahtatæutæu-'en appa ka kava'angs-en tyn ka i-tou-lam mi-'ttouko, ni-k'ma ki raren-'an tyn, Ina, kyt-tei ta Alak-oho.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus nu siende [sijne] moeder ende Den Discipel dien hy lief hadde daer by staende seyde tot sijne moeder Drouwe siet uw' Sone.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">When Jesus therefore saw his mother, and the disciple standing by, whom he loved, he saith unto his mother, Woman, behold thy son!</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌見母親和他所愛的那門徒站在旁邊，就對他母親說：「母親，看，你的兒子！」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse27">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Si-æ-'ugh ki annani-k'ma ki Pahtatutu-hen, K'yttei, ta ti 'na oho. Ka tou kidi ki tæ'lei kanna ni-patou-lam tyni-æn ta Pæhtatæutæu-han pa-tæ-koua tou talagh tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Si-æ-'ugh ki annani-k'ma ki Pahtatutu-hen, K'yttei, ta ti 'na oho. Ka tou kidi ki tæ'lei kanna ni-patou-lam tyni-æn ta Pæhtatæutæu-han pa-tæ-koua tou talagh tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Daer nar seyde hy tot den Discipel Siet uw' Moeder. Ende ban Die uyre aen nam haer de Discipel in sijn [ huys ].</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then saith he to the disciple, Behold thy mother! And from that hour that disciple took her unto his own home.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">又對那門徒說：「看，你的母親！」從此，那門徒就接她到自己家裏去了。 （太27‧45－56；可15‧33－41；路23‧44－49）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse28">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Si-ǣ-ugh ki anna rou ka-van-an ti Jesus ka pafte-ato ta ymmid ki mamang, alei ka pa-veut-tauh ta na Sa-Soulat, ni-k'ma ta teni, Meit-ö-koh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Si-ǣ-ugh ki anna rou ka-van-an ti Jesus ka pafte-ato ta ymmid ki mamang, alei ka pa-veut-tauh ta na Sa-Soulat, ni-k'ma ta teni, Meit-ö-koh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Hier Hier nae Jesus wetende Dat nu alles bolbracht was op Dat De Schrift soude berbult worden seyde My dorst.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">After this, Jesus knowing that all things were now accomplished, that the scripture might be fulfilled, saith, I thirst.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">這事以後，耶穌知道各樣的事已經成了，為要使經上的話應驗，就說：「我渴了。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse29">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-atta-kou'an hynna ta sato ka matmoei ki mapyn-git, ka ni-pou-tmoei-en nein ki mapyngit ta na vadiou ka mama ki pourut, maryttoung malyfvit ki isope, ka ni-patou touh-kil ki anna tou moutous tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-atta-kou'an hynna ta sato ka matmoei ki mapyn-git, ka ni-pou-tmoei-en nein ki mapyngit ta na vadiou ka mama ki pourut, maryttoung malyfvit ki isope, ka ni-patou touh-kil ki anna tou moutous tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Daer stond Dan een bat bol edier ende sy bulden een spongie met edick ende omleydense met hysope ende brachtense aen sijnen mondt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Now there was set a vessel full of vinegar: and they filled a spunge with vinegar, and put it upon hyssop, and put it to his mouth.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">有一個器皿盛滿了醋，放在那裏；他們就拿海絨蘸滿了醋，綁在牛膝草上，送到他口。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse30">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka ni-k-dymman ta ti Jesus ki mapyngit, ni-k'ma, Pei-kah-'an-nato mei-amut: ka rou mǣ-'u-sousou ki voungo ni-myh-taraæuh kihynnaua.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka ni-k-dymman ta ti Jesus ki mapyngit, ni-k'ma, Pei-kah-'an-nato mei-amut: ka rou mǣ-'u-sousou ki voungo ni-myh-taraæuh kihynnaua.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Doe Jesus dan Den edick genomen hadde seyde hy Het is bolbracht : ende het Hooft buygende gaf den Geest.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">When Jesus therefore had received the vinegar, he said, It is finished: and he bowed his head, and gave up the ghost.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌嘗了那醋，就說：「成了！」便低下頭，將靈魂交付上帝了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse31">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ta Joden alei ka assi pa-i-tou-koua-eih tou na væ-væræh ta vouävoual rou wæ'i ki pæ'i-habab-'an, alei ka kidi-ato ki sï-ä-tatanang-en (nda tou kei-rang-en ta wæ'i kanna ki pæ-'i-ha-bab'-an) ni-tmou-mymmia ti Pilatus-an, ki vla-ei ki toural nein, ka'æumi-eil-lappa ta neni.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ta Joden alei ka assi pa-i-tou-koua-eih tou na væ-væræh ta vouävoual rou wæ'i ki pæ'i-habab-'an, alei ka kidi-ato ki sï-ä-tatanang-en (nda tou kei-rang-en ta wæ'i kanna ki pæ-'i-ha-bab'-an) ni-tmou-mymmia ti Pilatus-an, ki vla-ei ki toural nein, ka'æumi-eil-lappa ta neni.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> De Joden dan op dat de lichamen niet aen Het kruys en souden blijben op den Sabbath dewijle het De Door-bereybinge was (want Die dagh des Sabbaths mag groot ) baden Pilatum Dat hare beenen souden gebroken ende sy wech genomen worden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">The Jews therefore, because it was the preparation, that the bodies should not remain upon the cross on the sabbath day, (for that sabbath day was an high day,) besought Pilate that their legs might be broken, and that they might be taken away.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">猶太人因這日是預備日，又因那安息日是個大日，就求彼拉多叫人打斷他們的腿，把他們拿去，免得屍首當安息日留在十字架上。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse32">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-ierroua ta ma-sa-cyt, ka ni-v'lan nein ta toural ki naunamou, ki ka rarouha, ka ni-pou-lam tyni-æn pou-na-va-væræh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-ierroua ta ma-sa-cyt, ka ni-v'lan nein ta toural ki naunamou, ki ka rarouha, ka ni-pou-lam tyni-æn pou-na-va-væræh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> De krijghs-knechten ban quamen ende brakelt De beenen DES eerfien ende des anderen Die Met Hem gekruyst was.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then came the soldiers, and brake the legs of the first, and of the other which was crucified with him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">於是兵丁來，把頭一個人的腿，並與耶穌同釘第二個人的腿，都打斷了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse33">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou-ra mou-koua ti Jesus-an, rou k'ytt'an nein ka pis-kaha-ato mapatei, anna ta assi nein ni-vlan-ta toural tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou-ra mou-koua ti Jesus-an, rou k'ytt'an nein ka pis-kaha-ato mapatei, anna ta assi nein ni-vlan-ta toural tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Maer komende tot Jesum als sy sagen Dat hy nu gestorben was so en brakenken sy sijne beenen niet.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But when they came to Jesus, and saw that he was dead already, they brake not his legs:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">只是來到耶穌那裏，見他已經死了，就不打斷他的腿。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse34">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Rasaat ki masa-cyt ta ni-tmivous tou kating tyn ki rarou-rough, ka madis ni-mou-pænæh hynna ta æmagh ki raloum-ap-pa.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Rasaat ki masa-cyt ta ni-tmivous tou kating tyn ki rarou-rough, ka madis ni-mou-pænæh hynna ta æmagh ki raloum-ap-pa.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Maer een krijgsknechten boor stack sijne zijde met een speere ende terstont quam daer bloedt ende Water uyt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But one of the soldiers with a spear pierced his side, and forthwith came there out blood and water.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">惟有一個兵拿槍扎他的肋旁，隨即有血和水流出來。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse35">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka teni ka ni-kmytta, gmail ki atta, ka matikeik ta hail-len tyn: ka kavan'-an tyn ka mashut ta fou tyn, alei ka tna-'msing-al-appa-kamou ta ymou-mi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka teni ka ni-kmytta, gmail ki atta, ka matikeik ta hail-len tyn: ka kavan'-an tyn ka mashut ta fou tyn, alei ka tna-'msing-al-appa-kamou ta ymoumi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende die Get gesien heeft Die heeft het getuyght ende sijn ghetuygenisse is waerachtigh : ende Hy weet dat hy segt het gene Dat waer is op dat oock ghy gelooben meught.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And he that saw it bare record, and his record is true: and he knoweth that he saith true, that ye might believe.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">看見這事的那人就作見證－他的見證也是真的，並且他知道自己所說的是真的－叫你們也可以信。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse36">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-pam't-tin ta ma: mangkatta, alei ka pevut-tauh ta na Sa-Soulat, Assi v'lla-an-nei ta sasasat ki toural tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-pam't-tin ta ma: mangkatta, alei ka pevut-tauh ta na Sa-Soulat, Assi v'lla-an-nei ta sasasat ki toural tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Want Dese dinghen zijn geschiedt Op Dat de Schrift berbult worde Geen been ban hem en sal berbdroken wonrden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">For these things were done, that the scripture should be fulfilled, A bone of him shall not be broken.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">這些事成了，為要應驗經上的話說：「他的骨頭一根也不可折斷。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse37">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka matt'i-la ta'pani ki na Sa-Soulat, Kmytt'-ah ta neni ki ni-t'ivous-sen nein.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka matt'i-la ta'pani ki na Sa-Soulat, Kmytt'-ah ta neni ki ni-t'ivous-sen nein.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende wederom seght een ander Schrift Sy sullen sien in welcken sy gesteken hebben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And again another scripture saith, They shall look on him whom they pierced.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">經上又有一句說：「他們要仰望自己所扎的人。」 （太27‧57－61；可15‧42－47；路23‧50－56）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse38">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Si-æ'-ughkianna tiJoses kamakka Arimathea, (kana Pah-ta tautæu-uh tiJesus,ra tou dung alei ki tahkout tyn ki Joden) ta ni-tmoumymmiati Pilatus-an, ki pa-ara-'n-nei tyni-æn ta vouel ti Jesus: ka hahei-en ta atta ti Pilatus. Annata ni-ou-koua tyn mæ'umiaki vouel ti Jesus.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Si-æ'-ughkianna tiJoses kamakka Arimathea, (kana Pahta tautæu-uh tiJesus,ra tou dung alei ki tahkout tyn ki Joden) ta ni-tmoumymmiati Pilatus-an, ki pa-ara-'n-nei tyni-æn ta vouel ti Jesus: ka hahei-en ta atta ti Pilatus. Annata ni-ou-koua tyn mæ'umiaki vouel ti Jesus.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende daer na Joseph ban Arimathea (Die een Discipel Jesu was maer bebeckt om de breese der Joden) badt Pilatum dat hy mochte het lichaem Jesu weck nemen : ende Pilatus liet Het toe. Hy dan gingh ende nam het lichaem Jesu wech.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And after this Joseph of Arimathaea, being a disciple of Jesus, but secretly for fear of the Jews, besought Pilate that he might take away the body of Jesus: and Pilate gave him leave. He came therefore, and took the body of Jesus.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">這些事以後，有亞利馬太人約瑟，是耶穌的門徒，只因怕猶太人，就暗暗地作門徒。他來求彼拉多，要把耶穌的身體領去。彼拉多允准，他就把耶穌的身體領去了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse39">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-mou-koua-appa ta ti Nikodemus, (tenita ni-ierroua tou naunamou ka euvanan ti Jesus-an) ka ahkakes'ul tyn ki ni-hourat ka pa-atho-in ki Myrrhe ki Aloë, sat kæ'ætoug-han lava ki tingting.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-mou-koua-appa ta ti Nikodemus, (tenita ni-ierroua tou naunamou ka euvanan ti Jesus-an) ka ahkakes'ul tyn ki ni-hourat ka pa-atho-in ki Myrrhe ki Aloë, sat kæ'ætoug-han lava ki tingting.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende Nicodemus quam oock (Die Des Nachts eerst tot Jesum ghekomen was) brengende een mengsel ban ban Myrrhe ende Aloe ontrent Hondert ponden [ ge wichts. ]</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And there came also Nicodemus, which at the first came to Jesus by night, and brought a mixture of myrrh and aloes, about an hundred pound weight.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">又有尼哥德慕，就是先前夜裏去見耶穌的，帶着沒藥和沉香約有一百斤前來。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse40">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-ara' nein ta vouel ti Jesus, ka ni-tmoupou ki atta tou æ'it lam ki ourou ka mævang'ugh, mama ka na kidi ki Joden rou r'avak-kin.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-ara' nein ta vouel ti Jesus, ka ni-tmoupou ki atta tou æ'it lam ki ourou ka mævang'ugh, mama ka na kidi ki Joden rou r'avak-kin.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Sy namen dan Het lichaem Jesu ende bonden Dat in lijnen Doecken met de speceryen geliick De Joden De gewoonte Hebben han beGraben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then took they the body of Jesus, and wound it in linen clothes with the spices, as the manner of the Jews is to bury.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們就照猶太人殯葬的規矩，把耶穌的身體用細麻布加上香料裹好了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse41">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka akou raoul hynna tou i-tou-kou'an, ki ni-pou-na-væ-væræh-'æn tyni-æn, ka tou raoul kanna ta r'avak ka va'æu, ka assi-appa ni-atta-kou-'an ta ti maman.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka akou raoul hynna tou i-tou-kou'an, ki ni-pou-na-væ-væræh-'æn tyni-æn, ka tou raoul kanna ta r'avak ka va'æu, ka assi-appa ni-atta-kou-'an ta ti maman.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende daer was in De peaetse Daer hy gekruyst was een Hof ende in Den Hof een nieuw' graf in het Welck noch noyt yemandt geleght en was geweest.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Now in the place where he was crucified there was a garden; and in the garden a new sepulchre, wherein was never man yet laid.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">在耶穌釘十字架的地方有一個園子，園子裏有一座新墳墓，是從來沒有葬過人的。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse42">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Tou hynna ni-atta-kou'-an nein ta ti Jesus, alei ki Si-tata-nang-en ki Joden, nda i-tou-ta-mang ta r'avak kanna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Tou hynna ni-atta-kou'-an nein ta ti Jesus, alei ki Si-tata-nang-en ki Joden, nda i-tou-ta-mang ta r'avak kanna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Aldaer dan leyden sy Jesum om de Door bereydinge Der Joden obermits het graf na by was. Het twintigste Capittel.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">There laid they Jesus therefore because of the Jews' preparation day; for the sepulchre was nigh at hand.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">只因是猶太人的預備日，又因那墳墓近，他們就把耶穌安放在那裏。</TRANSL>
    </S>
</TEXT>