<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEXT id="Siraya_Dutch_John_Chapter17" xml:lang="fos" source="Siraya Bible, John gospel" copyright="public domain" citation="Gravius, Daniël. 1661. Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa. Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang. Amsterdam: Michiel Hartogh." BibTeX_citation="@book{Gravius1661,&#10;  author    = {Gravius, Daniël},&#10;  year      = {1661},&#10;  title     = {Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa},&#10;  note      = {Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang},&#10;  address   = {Amsterdam},&#10;  publisher = {Michiel Hartogh}&#10;}" dialect="Siraya">
    <S id="verse1">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Atta ta ni-pa-sousou-en ti Jesus,ka ni-pa-passou-va-vau-en tyn pa-passouvavullum ta mattatyn, k'ma, Rama ierrou'-ato takidi ki tæ'lei, pou vavau-au ki kidi ta Alak oho', alei ka pou-vavau-al-appa ki kidi ta Alak oho ymhou-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Atta ta nipasousouen ti Jesus,ka nipapassouvavauen tyn papassouvavullum ta mattatyn, k'ma, Rama ierrou'ato takidi ki tæ'lei, pou vavauau ki kidi ta Alak oho', alei ka pouvavaualappa ki kidi ta Alak oho ymhouan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Dit heeft Jesus ghesproken ende hy hief sijne oogen op na den Hemel ende seyde Dader De uyre ig gekomen berheerlickt uwen Sone op Dat oock uw Sone a berheerlicke.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">These words spake Jesus, and lifted up his eyes to heaven, and said, Father, the hour is come; glorify thy Son, that thy Son also may glorify thee:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說了這話，就舉目望天，說：＂父啊，時候到了，願你榮耀你的兒子，使兒子也榮耀你；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse2">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Mama ki ni-phæ-en-hou tyni-æn taligh tou ymmud ki vaat, alei ka kamamang ka ni-phæ-en-hou tyni-æn, phæ-eih tyn neini-æn ta ku ag-han ka myhka-koua myddarynnough.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Mama ki niphæenhou tyniæn taligh tou ymmud ki vaat, alei ka kamamang ka niphæenhou tyniæn, phæeih tyn neiniæn ta ku aghan ka myhkakoua myddarynnough.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Gelijckerwijs ghy hem macht gegeben Hebt ober alle bleesch op dat al wat ghy hem gegeben hebt hy haer het eeuwighe leben gebe.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">As thou hast given him power over all flesh, that he should give eternal life to as many as thou hast given him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">正如你曾賜給他權柄管理凡有血氣的，叫他將永生賜給你所賜給他的人。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse3">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Att'appata kæuag-han ka myhkakoua myddarynnough, ka kmalang-ah ta neni ymhou-an dyksaasat ki Alid ka d'Llighti Jesus-an-appa ka ti Chrisius ka ni-padingi-en-hou.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Att'appata kæuaghan ka myhkakoua myddarynnough, ka kmalangah ta neni ymhouan dyksaasat ki Alid ka d'Llighti Jesusanappa ka ti Chrisius ka nipadingienhou.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende Dit is Het eenwighe leben Dat sy u kennen Den eenigen waerachtigen Godt ende Jesum Christum dien ghy gesonden hebt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And this is life eternal, that they might know thee the only true God, and Jesus Christ, whom thou hast sent.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">認識你－獨一的真神，並且認識你所差來的耶穌基督，這就是永生。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse4">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-pou-vavau-en-nau-kow ki kidi tou næi: ni-ma lymmou lymmou-koh ki poungas ka ni-phæ-en-nau paka-poungas jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Nipouvavauennaukow ki kidi tou næi: nima lymmou lymmoukoh ki poungas ka niphæennau pakapoungas jauan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ick Ick hebbe u berheerlickt op Der aerden: iCk hebbe boleyndight het werck Dat ghy my gegeben Hebt om te doen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">I have glorified thee on the earth: I have finished the work which thou gavest me to do.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我在地上已經榮耀你，你所託付我的事，我已成全了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse5">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ra hnyn pou-vavau-a ki kidi jau-an ymhou Rama ki kidi ka akoume'-en-nau ym hou-an, rou ä'ou-ssi appa ta næi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ra hnyn pouvavaua ki kidi jauan ymhou Rama ki kidi ka akoume'ennau ym houan, rou ä'oussi appa ta næi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">. Ende nu berheerlijckt my ghy Dader by u selben met De heerlickeyt die ick by u hadde eer De wereldt was.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And now, O Father, glorify thou me with thine own self with the glory which I had with thee before the world was.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">父啊，現在求你使我同你享榮耀，就是未有世界以先，我同你所有的榮耀。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse6">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-pou-pænæh-koh ki Na-nang-hou tou kæ'uloung-an ka ni-phæ-en-hou jau-an tou næi. A-mhou ta neni, ka ni-phæ-en-hou ta neni jau-an, ka ni-hma ta neni ki sou-oho.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Nipoupænæhkoh ki Nananghou tou kæ'uloungan ka niphæenhou jauan tou næi. Amhou ta neni, ka niphæenhou ta neni jauan, ka nihma ta neni ki souoho.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ick hebbe uwen Naem gheopenbaert Den menschen die ghy my uyt de wereldt ghegeden Hebt. Sy waren uwe ende ghy hebt my De selbe gegeben ende sy hebben uw'woort bewaert.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">I have manifested thy name unto the men which thou gavest me out of the world: thine they were, and thou gavest them me; and they have kept thy word.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">＂你從世上賜給我的人，我已將你的名顯明與他們。他們本是你的，你將他們賜給我，他們也遵守了你的道。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse7">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Hnyn kmalang-ato ta neni ka mamang, ka ni-phæ-en-hou jau-an, ka na â-mhou ta anna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Hnyn kmalangato ta neni ka mamang, ka niphæenhou jauan, ka na âmhou ta anna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Nu hebben zy bekent Dat alles wat ghy my gegeben hebt ban u is.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Now they have known that all things whatsoever thou hast given me are of thee.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">如今他們知道，凡你所賜給我的，都是從你那裏來的；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse8">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka sou k'anna ka ni-phæ-en-hou jau-an, na pæ p'ǣ-au nei-ni-æn, ka ni-atta-ryh-en nein ta anna, ka d'lligh-âto kmalang ka ni-tæ'i-koua-en-nau makka-rbo ymhou-an, ka tna-'msing-ato ta neni ka ni-padingi-en-hou jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka sou k'anna ka niphæenhou jauan, na pæ p'ǣau neiniæn, ka niattaryhen nein ta anna, ka d'llighâto kmalang ka nitæ'ikouaennau makkarbo ymhouan, ka tna'msingato ta neni ka nipadingienhou jauan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Want de woorden Die ghy my gegeben Hebt hebe ick haer gogeben ende sy hebbense ontsangen ende sy hebben waerlick bekent Dat ick ban u uytgegaen ben ende hebben gelooft dat ghy my gesonden hebt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">For I have given unto them the words which thou gavest me; and they have received them, and have known surely that I came out from thee, and they have believed that thou didst send me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">因為你所賜給我的道，我已經賜給他們，他們也領受了，又確實知道，我是從你出來的，並且信你差了我來。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse9">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Tmoumymmya-koh alei neini-æn: Assi-koh tmoumym-mia alei ki næi, râ alei-appa neini-æn ka ni-phæ-en-hou jau-an, alei ka â-'mhou ta neni.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Tmoumymmyakoh alei neiniæn: Assikoh tmoumymmia alei ki næi, râ aleiappa neiniæn ka niphæenhou jauan, alei ka â'mhou ta neni.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ick bidde boor Haer: ick en bidde niet boor De werelt maer boor de gene die ghy my gegeben hebt want zy zijn uwe.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">I pray for them: I pray not for the world, but for them which thou hast given me; for they are thine.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我為他們祈求，不為世人祈求，卻為你所賜給我的人祈求，因他們本是你的。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse10">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ymmud ki â-jau, â-'mhou-appa, ka â-mhou a-jau-ap-pa: ka ni-pou-vavau-en-koh ki ki-di neini-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ymmud ki âjau, â'mhouappa, ka âmhou ajauappa: ka nipouvavauenkoh ki kidi neiniæn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende al het mijne is uwe ende het uwe is mijne : ende ende ick ben in haer berheer lickt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And all mine are thine, and thine are mine; and I am glorified in them.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">凡是我的，都是你的；你的也是我的，並且我因他們得了榮耀。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse11">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka äouloug-koh hnyn tou næi, ra'æ-i-a-ni-appa ta ne-ni kK'atta, ka mou-koua-ah-koh ymhou-an. Ramaka d'lligh ma-tiktik, k'ading-au ta neni tou Nanang-ohou,ka ni-ph-en-hou jau-an, alei ka sasat-ah ta neni mama ymytt-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka äoulougkoh hnyn tou næi, ra'æianiappa ta neni kK'atta, ka moukouaahkoh ymhouan. Ramaka d'lligh matiktik, k'adingau ta neni tou Nanangohou,ka niphenhou jauan, alei ka sasatah ta neni mama ymyttæn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende ick en ben niet meer in de werelt maer dese zijn in De wereldt ende ick kome tot u. Heylige Dader bewaertse in uwen Name Die ghy my gegeben Hebt op dat sy een zijn geliick als wy.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And now I am no more in the world, but these are in the world, and I come to thee. Holy Father, keep through thine own name those whom thou hast given me, that they may be one, as we are.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">從今以後，我不在世上，他們卻在世上；我往你那裏去。聖父啊，求你因你所賜給我的名保守他們，叫他們合而為一像我們一樣。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse12">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Dou æ-'i-a-lam-app'-ohneini-æn tou næi, ni-kading-au ta neni tou Nanang-ohou. Neni ka' ni-ph-en-hou jau-an ni-ka-ding-en-nau, ka assi ni-tau-rum-ma ta ti mamang neini-æn, dyk ki Alak ki si-dad-'an;alei ka paveut-auh ta na Sa-soulat.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Dou æ'ialamapp'ohneiniæn tou næi, nikadingau ta neni tou Nanangohou. Neni ka' niphenhou jauan nikadingennau, ka assi nitaurumma ta ti mamang neiniæn, dyk ki Alak ki sidad'an;alei ka paveutauh ta na Sasoulat.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Doe ick Met haer in de wereldt was bewaerde ickse in uwen name. Die ghy my gegeben hebt hebbe ick be waerdt ende niemandt uyt Haer en is berloren gegaen Dan De sone der berderffenisse op Dat De Schrift berbult worde.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">While I was with them in the world, I kept them in thy name: those that thou gavest me I have kept, and none of them is lost, but the son of perdition; that the scripture might be fulfilled.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我與他們同在的時候，因你所賜給我的名保守了他們，我也護衛了他們；其中除了那滅亡之子，沒有一個滅亡的，好叫經上的話得應驗。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse13">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ra hnyn mou-koua-koh ymhou-an, ka pa-sousou-en-nau ta atta tou næi, alei ka paka-tmoei-auh neini-n ta karai-en-nau.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ra hnyn moukouakoh ymhouan, ka pasousouennau ta atta tou næi, alei ka pakatmoeiauh neinin ta karaiennau.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Maer nu komt ick tot u ende spreke Dit in De werelt op Dat sy mijne blijdtschap berbult mogen hebben in Haer selben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And now come I to thee; and these things I speak in the world, that they might have my joy fulfilled in themselves.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">現在我往你那裏去，我還在世上說這話，是叫他們心裏充滿我的喜樂。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse14">
        <FORM kindOf="original">. Ni-phæ-en-nau neini-æn ta sou-ohio, ka næi ta ni-mavahier neini-æn, alei ka assi makka ni ta neni, mamaka asfi-koh makka ni ti jau.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">. Niphæennau neiniæn ta souohio, ka næi ta nimavahier neiniæn, alei ka assi makka ni ta neni, mamaka asfikoh makka ni ti jau.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ick hebbe haer uw' woordt gegeben ende de wereldt heeftse gehaet om dat sy ban De wereldt niet en zijn geliick als ick ban De wereldt niet in ben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">I have given them thy word; and the world hath hated them, because they are not of the world, even as I am not of the world.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我已將你的道賜給他們。世界又恨他們；因為他們不屬世界，正如我不屬世界一樣。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse15">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Assi-koh tmou-mymmia ki æ'æumi-'ei-'mhou ta neni tou næi, ri k'ading-aul-appa-'mhou ta neni ki Tama-pakat'ee.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Assikoh tmoumymmia ki æ'æumi'ei'mhou ta neni tou næi, ri k'adingaulappa'mhou ta neni ki Tamapakat'ee.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ick en bidde niet Dat ghy haer uyt de wereldt wech neemt maer Dat ghy haer bewaert ban Den boosen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">I pray not that thou shouldest take them out of the world, but that thou shouldest keep them from the evil.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我不求你叫他們離開世界，只求你保守他們脫離那惡者。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse16">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Assi makka næi ta neni mama jau an ka assi-koh makka næi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Assi makka næi ta neni mama jau an ka assikoh makka næi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Sy en zijn niet ban de de wereldt gelijckerwijs ick ban De wereldt niet en ben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">They are not of the world, even as I am not of the world.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們不屬世界，正如我不屬世界一樣。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse17">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Paka-d'lligh-au paka-tiktik ta neni tou katiktik-kan ki sou-oho: nda sou-oho ta katik-tik-kan ki sou.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Pakad'llighau pakatiktik ta neni tou katiktikkan ki souoho: nda souoho ta katiktikkan ki sou.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Heyligh'se in uwe wereheyt : uw' woordt is de waerheyt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Sanctify them through thy truth: thy word is truth.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">求你用真理使他們成聖；你的道就是真理。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse18">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Mama ki ni-padadingi-en-hou jau-an pa-'ou-koua tou ni, ni-padingi-au komma-hyn-na pa-'ou-koua ta neni tou næi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Mama ki nipadadingienhou jauan pa'oukoua tou ni, nipadingiau kommahynna pa'oukoua ta neni tou næi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Gelijckerwijs ghy my gesonden Hebt in De wereldt(alsoo) hebbe ick haer oock in De wereldt gesonden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">As thou hast sent me into the world, even so have I also sent them into the world.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你怎樣差我到世上，我也照樣差他們到世上。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse19">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka paka-mado-en-nau paka-d'lligh paka-tiktik jau-an alei neini-æn, ki paka-d'lligh-eil-appa ta neni pakatiktik tou ka-tiktik-kan ki sou.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka pakamadoennau pakad'lligh pakatiktik jauan alei neiniæn, ki pakad'lligheilappa ta neni pakatiktik tou katiktikkan ki sou.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende ick heylige my selben boor Haer op Dat oock sy geheylight mogen zijn in waer heydt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And for their sakes I sanctify myself, that they also might be sanctified through the truth.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我為他們的緣故，自己分別為聖，叫他們也因真理成聖。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse20">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Assi-koh tmou-dyk tmou-mymmia alei neini-æn k'atta, ra alei appa neini-æn ka tna-'msing-ah jau-an ki na sou nein.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Assikoh tmoudyk tmoumymmia alei neiniæn k'atta, ra alei appa neiniæn ka tna'msingah jauan ki na sou nein.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende ick en bidde niet alleen boot dese maer oock boor De gene Die door Haer woordt in my gelooben sullen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Neither pray I for these alone, but for them also which shall believe on me through their word;</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">＂我不但為這些人祈求，也為那些因他們的話信我的人祈求，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse21">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Alei ka mako-i-ä ym'd-dâh mako'i sat ta neni, mama ymhou Rama jau-an, ti jau-appa ymhou-an, ka mako-i-saat-al-ap-pa ta neni ymytt'-æn: alei ka tna-'msing ah ta næi ki ni-padingi-en-hou jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Alei ka makoiä ym'ddâh mako'i sat ta neni, mama ymhou Rama jauan, ti jauappa ymhouan, ka makoisaatalappa ta neni ymytt'æn: alei ka tna'msing ah ta næi ki nipadingienhou jauan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Op Dat sy alle een zijn gelijckerwijs ghy Da: der in my ende ick in u Dat oock sy in ons een zijt: op dat de wereldt geloobe Dat ghy my gesonden hebt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">That they all may be one; as thou, Father, art in me, and I in thee, that they also may be one in us: that the world may believe that thou hast sent me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">使他們都合而為一。正如你父在我裏面，我在你裏面，使他們也在我們裏面，叫世人可以信你差了我來。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse22">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-phæ-en-nau neini-æn ta keirang-an ki kidi ka na pæp'æ-oho jau-an: alei ka saäsat-ah ta neni mama ka saäsat-kytta ta ymyt-ta.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka niphæennau neiniæn ta keirangan ki kidi ka na pæp'æoho jauan: alei ka saäsatah ta neni mama ka saäsatkytta ta ymytta.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende ick hebbe Haer de heerlickuyt gegeben Die ghy my gededen hebt : op Dat sy een zijn geliick als wy een zijn.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And the glory which thou gavest me I have given them; that they may be one, even as we are one:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你所賜給我的榮耀，我已賜給他們，使他們合而為一，像我們合而為一。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse23">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Tijau neini-æn, imhou-appa jau-an: alei ka makoi ta-raæug-â 'ta neni makoi-sat, ka kmalang-al-appa ta næi, ki ni-pa-dingi-en hou jau-an, ka ni-kavæ-'angö-en appa'-'mhou neini-æn : mama ki ni-kavæ'angö-en-hou jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Tijau neiniæn, imhouappa jauan: alei ka makoi taraæugâ 'ta neni makoisat, ka kmalangalappa ta næi, ki nipadingien hou jauan, ka nikavæ'angöen appa''mhou neiniæn : mama ki nikavæ'angöenhou jauan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ick in haer ende ghy in my : op Dat sy bolmaeckt zijn in een ende op dat dat de wereldt bekenne Dat ghy my gesonden Hebt enDe haer lief gehadt Hebt : geliick ghy my lief gehadt Hebt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">I in them, and thou in me, that they may be made perfect in one; and that the world may know that thou hast sent me, and hast loved them, as thou hast loved me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我在他們裏面，你在我裏面，使他們完完全全地合而為一，叫世人知道你差了我來，也知道你愛他們如同愛我一樣。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse24">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Rama, mamoei-koh tou æ-i-a-koua ei-mau, i-tou-lam-appa jau-an ka ni-phæ-en-hou jau-an : alei ka mararau-ah ta neni ki keirang-en ki kidi-au, ka ni-phæ-en hou jau-an, nda ni-mavæ'angö kow jau-an, rou assi-appa ni-pa-i-tou samding-in ta raroun ki næi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Rama, mamoeikoh tou æiakoua eimau, itoulamappa jauan ka niphæenhou jauan : alei ka mararauah ta neni ki keirangen ki kidiau, ka niphæen hou jauan, nda nimavæ'angö kow jauan, rou assiappa nipaitou samdingin ta raroun ki næi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Dader ick wil Dat daer ick en oock die by mt zijn Die ghy my gegeben hebt : op Dat sy mijne Heer: lickeyt moghen aenschouwen Die ghy my gegeben hebt want ghy Hebt my lief gehadt boor De grond-legginge der wereldt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Father, I will that they also, whom thou hast given me, be with me where I am; that they may behold my glory, which thou hast given me: for thou lovedst me before the foundation of the world.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">父啊，我在哪裏，願你所賜給我的人也同我在那裏，叫他們看見你所賜給我的榮耀；因為創立世界以前，你已經愛我了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse25">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Rama ka matiktik, assi ni-kmalang ymhou-anta næi : râ ti jau ta ni-kmalang ymhou-an, ka ni-kmalang-appa ta neni k'atta ki ni-padingi-en hou jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Rama ka matiktik, assi nikmalang ymhouanta næi : râ ti jau ta nikmalang ymhouan, ka nikmalangappa ta neni k'atta ki nipadingien hou jauan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Rechtbeerdighe DaDer De wereldt en Heeft u niet gekent: maer ick hebbe u gekent ende dese Hebben bekendt Dat opp my gesonden hebt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">O righteous Father, the world hath not known thee: but I have known thee, and these have known that thou hast sent me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">公義的父啊，世人未曾認識你，我卻認識你；這些人也知道你差了我來。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse26">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-pak'alang-en-nau neini-æn ta Nanang oho, ka pa-l'alang-eil-appa-mau : alei ka kavæ-angö-en-hou jau-an i-tou-koua-âl-ato neini-æn, ti jau-appa nei-ni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka nipak'alangennau neiniæn ta Nanang oho, ka pal'alangeilappamau : alei ka kavæangöenhou jauan itoukouaâlato neiniæn, ti jauappa neiniæn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">Ende ick hebbe haer uwen name bekent gemaekt ende sal (hem) bekent maken : op Dat De Lief De Daer meDe ghy my lief gehadt Hebt in Haer zy ende ick in haer.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And I have declared unto them thy name, and will declare it: that the love wherewith thou hast loved me may be in them, and I in them.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我已將你的名指示他們，還要指示他們，使你所愛我的愛在他們裏面，我也在他們裏面。＂</TRANSL>
    </S>
</TEXT>
