<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEXT id="Siraya_Dutch_John_Chapter11" xml:lang="fos" source="Siraya Bible, John gospel" copyright="public domain" citation="Gravius, Daniël. 1661. Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa. Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang. Amsterdam: Michiel Hartogh." BibTeX_citation="@book{Gravius1661,&#10;  author    = {Gravius, Daniël},&#10;  year      = {1661},&#10;  title     = {Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa},&#10;  note      = {Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang},&#10;  address   = {Amsterdam},&#10;  publisher = {Michiel Hartogh}&#10;}">
    <S id="verse1">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka akou voual ka saasat ka-maslam ka ti Lazarus[ta nanang tyn,] ka makka Bethania, ka na euma ti Maria ki tæ'i-qpar'-appa tyn ka ti Martha.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka akou voual ka saasat ka-maslam ka ti Lazarus[ta nanang tyn,] ka makka Bethania, ka na euma ti Maria ki tæ'i-qpar'-appa tyn ka ti Martha.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende daer was een seker [man] krananck [genaemt] Lazarus ban Bethanien uyt het bleck Marie ende susters Marthe.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Now a certain man was sick, named Lazarus, of Bethany, the town of Mary and her sister Martha.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">有一個患病的人，名叫拉撒路，住在伯大尼，就是馬利亞和她姊姊馬大的村莊。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse2">
        <FORM kindOf="original">(Ti Maria teni ta ti anna ka nismala'-ymmagh ki ymmagh ki Meirirang, ka ni-rigkagh ki rahpal tyn ki vouk-kugh tyn : ka niæha tyn ka ti Lazarus ta mailam.)</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">(Ti Maria teni ta ti anna ka nismala'-ymmagh ki ymmagh ki Meirirang, ka ni-rigkagh ki rahpal tyn ki vouk-kugh tyn : ka niæha tyn ka ti Lazarus ta mailam.)</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> (Maris nu was de ghene Die Den Heere ghesalft Heeft met salbe ende sijne boeten afgedrooght heeft met Haren Hayre : welcker broeber Lazarus kranck was. )</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">(It was that Mary which anointed the Lord with ointment, and wiped his feet with her hair, whose brother Lazarus was sick.)</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">這馬利亞就是那用香膏抹主，又用頭髮擦他腳的；患病的拉撒路是她的兄弟。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse3">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-madingi ta niæ-ha tyn pa-'ou-koua tyni-n, kma, Meirang, teni ka kavæ'ango-en-hou ta mailam.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-madingi ta niæ-ha tyn pa-'ou-koua tyni-n, kma, Meirang, teni ka kavæ'ango-en-hou ta mailam.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Sijne susters Dan sonden tot hem seggende Heere siet dien ghy lief hebt is Krant.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Therefore his sisters sent unto him, saying, Lord, behold, he whom thou lovest is sick.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">她姊妹兩個就打發人去見耶穌，說：「主啊，你所愛的人病了。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse4">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka millingigh [ ki at-ta] tatiJesus ni-kma, Assi tou kapatei-eih tyn ta maalam k'atta, ra tou pou-vavau-eih ki kidi ki Alid: alei ka' pou-vavau-eih ki atta ki kidi ta Alak ki Alid.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka millingigh [ ki at-ta] tatiJesus ni-kma, Assi tou kapatei-eih tyn ta maalam k'atta, ra tou pou-vavau-eih ki kidi ki Alid: alei ka' pou-vavau-eih ki atta ki kidi ta Alak ki Alid.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende Jesus [dat] hoorende seyde Dese kranckheyt en is niet tot der doodt maer ter heerlickhept Godt : op Dat De Sone Gods door deselbe berheerlickt worde.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">When Jesus heard that, he said, This sickness is not unto death, but for the glory of God, that the Son of God might be glorified thereby.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌聽見，就說：「這病不至於死，乃是為上帝的榮耀，叫上帝的兒子因此得榮耀。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse5">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Nda kavæ'angs-en ti Jesus ta-ti Marta:, ki ti-apara-appa tyn, ta ti Lazarus ki rou-ma.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Nda kavæ'angs-en ti Jesus tati Marta:, ki ti-apara-appa tyn, ta ti Lazarus ki rou-ma.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus nu hadde Martham ende hare sustter ende Lazarum lief.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Now Jesus loved Martha, and her sister, and Lazarus.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌素來愛馬大和她妹子並拉撒路。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse6">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou-rani-millingigh ta teni ka mailam ta teni, ni-mæyl li-[ appa ] makka-rouha ki wæi tou i-tou kou an ka ǣia-kou'-an tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou-rani-millingigh ta teni ka mailam ta teni, ni-mæyl li-[ appa ] makka-rouha ki wæi tou i-tou kou an ka ǣia-kou'-an tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">When he had heard therefore that he was sick, he abode two days still in the same place where he was.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">聽見拉撒路病了，就在所居之地仍住了兩天。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse7">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Si-ǣæugh ki anna ni-ma-sousou ki Pahta tæutæu-han tyn, Sa-lyk koug-eita mou-koua tou Judea.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Si-ǣæugh ki anna ni-ma-sousou ki Pahta tæutæu-han tyn, Sa-lyk koug-eita mou-koua tou Judea.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Als hy Dan ghehoort hadde Dat hy kranck was doe bleef hy [ noch ] twee dagen.dagen in Die plaetse Daer hy was. Daer na seyde hy boorder tot Den Discipelen Laet ons wederom na Judeam gaen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then after that saith he to his disciples, Let us go into Judaea again.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">然後對門徒說：「我們再往猶太去吧。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse8">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'ma ta Pahtatæutæu-'han tyni-æn, Rabbi, assi-appa madailia ka ni-kmi'ym ta Joden ki cyt-an-ei ki vahtou ymhou-an, ka sa-lyk koug-ah-kow mou-koua hynna?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-k'ma ta Pahtatæutæu-'han tyni-æn, Rabbi, assi-appa madailia ka ni-kmi'ym ta Joden ki cyt-an-ei ki vahtou ymhou-an, ka sa-lyk koug-ah-kow mou-koua hynna?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> De discipelen seyden tot hem Rabbi De Joden hebben u nu [ onlanghs ] gesoch te steenigen ende gaet ghy wederom der waerts?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">His disciples say unto him, Master, the Jews of late sought to stone thee; and goest thou thither again?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">門徒說：「拉比，猶太人近來要拿石頭打你，你還往那裏去嗎？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse9">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta ti Jesus, Assi kauwa sat kyttiæn 'æb'ki rouha ta tæ'lei ki sasat ki wæi? Heirou mou-naunang ta ti ma-mang dou akou wæ'i, assi hmalih dæuræu ta teni: alei ka k'ytt-'an tyn ta ræmæh ki næi katta:</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta ti Jesus, Assi kauwa sat kyttiæn 'æb'ki rouha ta tæ'lei ki sasat ki wæi? Heirou mou-naunang ta ti ma-mang dou akou wæ'i, assi hmalih dæuræu ta teni: alei ka k'ytt-'an tyn ta ræmæh ki næi katta:</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus antwoordde Zijnder niet twaelf uyren in ben dagh : Indien yemandt in Den dagh wandelt soo en stoot hy Hem niet : obermits hy't licht De fer wereelt siet:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Jesus answered, Are there not twelve hours in the day? If any man walk in the day, he stumbleth not, because he seeth the light of this world.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌回答說：「白日不是有十二小時嗎？人在白日走路，就不致跌倒，因為看見這世上的光。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse10">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou-ra mou-naunang ta ti mamang dou euvannan, hmali-dæuræu ta teni: alei ka ä'-ou-si ki ræmæh tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou-ra mou-naunang ta ti mamang dou euvannan, hmali-dæuræu ta teni: alei ka ä'-ou-si ki ræmæh tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Maer inden yedant In Der nacht wandelt so stoot hy hem: obermits het licht m hem niet en is.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But if a man walk in the night, he stumbleth, because there is no light in him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">若在黑夜走路，就必跌倒，因為他沒有光。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse11">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Atta ta ni-pa-sousou-en tyn: si-ææugh ki anna ni-k'ma ta teni neini-æn, mi-eirup ta ti Lazarus ka riou-eta: ra mou-koua koh tyni-æn ki papattimæu agh-ei-mautou-'ieir 'p-pan tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Atta ta ni-pa-sousou-en tyn: si-ææugh ki anna ni-k'ma ta teni neini-æn, mi-eirup ta ti Lazarus ka riou-eta: ra mou-koua koh tyni-æn ki papattimæu agh-ei-mautou-'ieir 'p-pan tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Dit sprack Hy : ende daer nae seyde hy tot Haer Lazarus onse briendt slaept: maer ick gae henen om hem uyt den slaep op te wecken.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">These things said he: and after that he saith unto them, Our friend Lazarus sleepeth; but I go, that I may awake him out of sleep.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說了這話，隨後對他們說：「我們的朋友拉撒路睡了，我去叫醒他。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse12">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni kma ta Pahta tæutæu'-hantyn, Meirang, hei-rou mieirip ta teni kauh-dæryk-ka'g-âl-ato.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni kma ta Pahta tæutæu'-hantyn, Meirang, hei-rou mieirip ta teni kauh-dæryk-ka'g-âl-ato.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Sijne Discipulen dan seyden Heere Indien hy slaept soo sal hy gesont worden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then said his disciples, Lord, if he sleep, he shall do well.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">門徒說：「主啊，他若睡了，就必好了。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse13">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Râ ti Jesus ta ni-masou-sou ki ni-kapatei-an tyn: râ ni-pæhdimdim-men nein ka pasou-sou-en tyn ki i-eirup ka i-erp-pin.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Râ ti Jesus ta ni-masou-sou ki ni-kapatei-an tyn: râ ni-pæhdimdim-men nein ka pasou-sou-en tyn ki i-eirup ka i-erp-pin.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Doch Jesus hadde gesproocken ban sijne doodt: maermaer sy meynden Dat hy sprack ban De ruste Des slaeps.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Howbeit Jesus spake of his death: but they thought that he had spoken of taking of rest in sleep.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌這話是指着他死說的，他們卻以為是說照常睡了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse14">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-mattæ'i-tum-tum ta ti Jesus neini-æn, Ni-map-patei-ato ta ti Lazarus.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-mattæ'i-tum-tum ta ti Jesus neini-æn, Ni-map-patei-ato ta ti Lazarus.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Doe seyde dan Jesus tot haer bry uyt Lazarus is gestorben</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then said Jesus unto them plainly, Lazarus is dead.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌就明明地告訴他們說：「拉撒路死了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse15">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka marai-koh alei y-moumi-æn, ka assi-koh ni-æ'ia-koua hynna, alei ka tna-'msing-ei-moumi: nda mou-koua-eitta tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka marai-koh alei y-moumi-æn, ka assi-koh ni-æ'ia-koua hynna, alei ka tna-'msing-ei-moumi: nda mou-koua-eitta tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende ick ben blijde om uwent wille Dat ick Daer niet geweest en ben op Dat ghy gelooben meught : doch laet ons tot hem gaen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And I am glad for your sakes that I was not there, to the intent ye may believe; nevertheless let us go unto him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我沒有在那裏就歡喜，這是為你們的緣故，好叫你們相信。如今我們可以往他那裏去吧。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse16">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ti Thomas ka Didymus ta fioua tyn, ni-k'ma ki Pahtatæutæu-han ka lam tyn, Mou-koua-appa ta ymytta alei ka pis-para-kytta tyni-æn mapatei.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ti Thomas ka Didymus ta fioua tyn, ni-k'ma ki Pahtatæutæu-han ka lam tyn, Mou-koua-appa ta ymytta alei ka pis-para-kytta tyni-æn mapatei.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende Thomas, genaamd Didymus, zeide tot de medediscipelen: Laten wy mede gaen, opdat wy met hem sterven.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then said Thomas, which is called Didymus, unto his fellowdisciples, Let us also go, that we may die with him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">多馬，又稱為低土馬，就對那同作門徒的說：「我們也去和他同死吧。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse17">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou kaietrou'-ato ta ti Jesus ni-kabalei tyn ka makk'-ahpat ki wæ'i ka'æia ravak-ato ta teni.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou kaietrou'-ato ta ti Jesus ni-kabalei tyn ka makk'-ahpat ki wæ'i ka'æia ravak-ato ta teni.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus dan gekomen zijnde : bondt Dat hy nu bier daghen in het graf gheweest Was.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then when Jesus came, he found that he had lain in the grave four days already.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌到了，就知道拉撒路在墳墓裏已經四天了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse18">
        <FORM kindOf="original">( Ka Bethania ta i-tou-ta-mang ki Jerusalem, satkytti=n lava æb ki rymma ki stadien ki na ka dadallia hynna.)</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">( Ka Bethania ta i-tou-ta-mang ki Jerusalem, satkytti=n lava æb ki rymma ki stadien ki na ka dadallia hynna.)</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> ( Bethania nu was na hy Jerusalem ontrent bijfthien stadien ban [daer.] )</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Now Bethany was nigh unto Jerusalem, about fifteen furlongs off:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">伯大尼離耶路撒冷不遠，約有六里路。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse19">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka mabatoung ki Joden ta ierrou-'ato ti Martha-an ti Maria-an, tou paka-haniap-pei nei-ni-æn alei ki niæha nein.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka mabatoung ki Joden ta ierrou-'ato ti Martha-an ti Maria-an, tou paka-haniap-pei nei-ni-æn alei ki niæha nein.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende bele uyt Den Joden waren ghekomen tot Martham ende Mariam op Dat sy haer bertroosten souden ober Haren broeder.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And many of the Jews came to Martha and Mary, to comfort them concerning their brother.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">有好些猶太人來看馬大和馬利亞，要為她們的兄弟安慰她們。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse20">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ti Martha, irou ka millingigh ki ierrou-an ti Jesus, ni-dmoummadoummata teni tyni-æn: ra ti Maria ta ni-tæ'æ-ra roungtou talagh-da.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ti Martha, irou ka millingigh ki ierrou-an ti Jesus, ni-dmoummadoummata teni tyni-æn: ra ti Maria ta ni-tæ'æ-ra roungtou talagh-da.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Martha dan als sy hoorde Dat Jesus quam qingh hem te gemoete : doch Maria bleef in huys fitten.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then Martha, as soon as she heard that Jesus was coming, went and met him: but Mary sat still in the house.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">馬大聽見耶穌來了，就出去迎接他；馬利亞卻仍然坐在家裏。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse21">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annatani-kmatati Martha ti Jesus-an, Meirang, heirou na anna-un kow hia, ynna assi ka-patei ta niǣ ha-au.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annatani-kmatati Martha ti Jesus-an, Meirang, heirou na anna-un kow hia, ynna assi ka-patei ta niǣ ha-au.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Soo seyde Martha ban dan tot Jesum Heere waert ghy hier geweest soo en ware mijn broeder NIet gestorben:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then said Martha unto Jesus, Lord, if thou hadst been here, my brother had not died.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">馬大對耶穌說：「主啊，你若早在這裏，我兄弟必不死。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse22">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Râ kavana-en-nau hnyn', kamamang ka t'ou mimi-au-mou-hou ki Alid, ka piǣ-ah ki atta ta Alid imhou-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Râ kavana-en-nau hnyn', kamamang ka t'ou mimi-au-mou-hou ki Alid, ka piǣ-ah ki atta ta Alid imhou-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Maer oock nu weet ick Dat alles mat ghy ban Godt begeeren sult Godt u Het geben sal.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But I know, that even now, whatsoever thou wilt ask of God, God will give it thee.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">就是現在，我也知道，你無論向上帝求甚麼，上帝也必賜給你。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse23">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-kma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Lykkoug-ah æhpit ta niǣ-ha-u-ouhou.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-kma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Lykkoug-ah æhpit ta niǣ-ha-u-ouhou.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus seyde tot haer Dw' broeder sal weder opstaen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Jesus saith unto her, Thy brother shall rise again.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：「你兄弟必然復活。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse24">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-kma ta ti Martha tyni-æn, Kavana-en-nau ka lykkoug-ahta teni tou lykkoug-an æhpit tou wæi ka tou ǣæugh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-kma ta ti Martha tyni-æn, Kavana-en-nau ka lykkoug-ahta teni tou lykkoug-an æhpit tou wæi ka tou ǣæugh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Martha seyde tot hem Ick weet dat hy opstaen sal in de opstandinge ten laetsten dage.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Martha saith unto him, I know that he shall rise again in the resurrection at the last day.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">馬大說：「我知道在末日復活的時候，他必復活。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse25">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Ti jau ta lykkoug-an æhpit, ki kæuag-gan appa: ti mamang ta tna-msing jau-an, meuag-ah ta teni meita-rou pis-kaha-ato.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Ti jau ta lykkoug-an æhpit, ki kæuag-gan appa: ti mamang ta tna-msing jau-an, meuag-ah ta teni meita-rou pis-kaha-ato.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus seyde tot haer Ick ben De opstandinge ende Het leben: Die in my gelooft salleben alwaer hy oock gestorben :</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Jesus said unto her, I am the resurrection, and the life: he that believeth in me, though he were dead, yet shall he live:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌對她說：「復活在我，生命也在我。信我的人雖然死了，也必復活；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse26">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Veiagh-appa ka mæuagh ka tna-msing jau-an, assi mapa-tei-ah tou 'yhkakouan mydda-rynnough. Tna-msing kow kau-wa ki atta.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Veiagh-appa ka mæuagh ka tna-msing jau-an, assi mapa-tei-ah tou 'yhkakouan mydda-rynnough. Tna-msing kow kau-wa ki atta.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende een yegelick die leeft ende in my gelooft sal niet sterben in Der eeuwigheyt. Gelooft ghy dat?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And whosoever liveth and believeth in me shall never die. Believest thou this?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">凡活着信我的人必永遠不死。你信這話嗎？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse27">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'ma ta teni tyni-æn, Hahei Meirang: tna-'msing koh ka ti Christus kow ka Alak ki Alid, ka ierrou'-âl-ato tou næi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-k'ma ta teni tyni-æn, Hahei Meirang: tna-'msing koh ka ti Christus kow ka Alak ki Alid, ka ierrou'-âl-ato tou næi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Sy seyde tot hem Ja Heere: ich hebbe gelooft Dat ghy zijt de Christus De Sone Godts Die in De werelt komen soude.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">She saith unto him, Yea, Lord: I believe that thou art the Christ, the Son of God, which should come into the world.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">馬大說：「主啊，是的，我信你是基督，是上帝的兒子，就是那要臨到世界的。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse28">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka pattæ'i-kahan tyn ta atta ni-d'marangta teni, ka ni-makou-ouzoung tmætææm ti Maria-an ka tæi-äpara tyn, kma, Annaun ta Tama-Mahtæutæu-ugh, tmætææm ta teni ymhou-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka pattæ'i-kahan tyn ta atta ni-d'marangta teni, ka ni-makou-ouzoung tmætææm ti Maria-an ka tæi-äpara tyn, kma, Annaun ta Tama-Mahtæutæu-ugh, tmætææm ta teni ymhou-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende dit geseght hebbende gingh sy henen ende riep Mariam Hare suster heymelick seggende De Mee-Meester is Daer ende hy roept u.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And when she had so said, she went her way, and called Mary her sister secretly, saying, The Master is come, and calleth for thee.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">馬大說了這話，就回去暗暗地叫她妹子馬利亞，說：「夫子來了，叫你。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse29">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Tenirou millingigh [ki atta,] Jmadijs æhpit:ka ni-dmoum-madoumma tyai-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Tenirou millingigh [ki atta,] Jmadijs æhpit:ka ni-dmoum-madoumma tyai-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Dese als sy [dat] hoor de stont haestelick op ende ging tot hem.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">As soon as she heard that, she arose quickly, and came unto him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">馬利亞聽見了，就急忙起來，到耶穌那裏去。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse30">
        <FORM kindOf="original">(Kaassi-appa mæu-um-'ato ta ti Jesus : r æ-ia-koua-appa tou ni-pæua-kI'-an ti Martha tyni-æn.)</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">(Kaassi-appa mæu-um-'ato ta ti Jesus : r æ-ia-koua-appa tou ni-pæua-kI'-an ti Martha tyni-æn.)</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> ( Jesus nu en Was noch in het bieck niet ghekomen : maer was in De plaetse Daer kem Martha te gemoet gekomen was. )</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Now Jesus was not yet come into the town, but was in that place where Martha met him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那時，耶穌還沒有進村子，仍在馬大迎接他的地方。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse31">
        <FORM kindOf="original">KaJoden k'anna ka æ-i-a-lam tyn tou talagh pakahaniap tyni-æn, irouka kmytta ta neni ti Matia-an ka dys-sen tyn hpit sa-mamala, ni-mæu-ugh ta neni tyni-æn.k'ma, Sah-kakoua ta teni tou ravak, alei ka tmangi tangi-ah hynna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">KaJoden k'anna ka æ-i-a-lam tyn tou talagh pakahaniap tyni-æn, irouka kmytta ta neni ti Matia-an ka dys-sen tyn hpit sa-mamala, ni-mæu-ugh ta neni tyni-æn.k'ma, Sah-kakoua ta teni tou ravak, alei ka tmangi tangi-ah hynna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> De Joden Dan Die Met haer in het huys waren ende haer bertroosteden siende Mariam Dat sy haestelick opstont ende uyt gingh bolghden haer seggende Sy gaet na het graf op dat sy aldaer weene.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The Jews then which were with her in the house, and comforted her, when they saw Mary, that she rose up hastily and went out, followed her, saying, She goeth unto the grave to weep there.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那些同馬利亞在家裏安慰她的猶太人，見她急忙起來出去，就跟着她，以為她要往墳墓那裏去哭。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse32">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annatati Maria, irou ka mou-kou ato ti Jesuss an, ka rou K'ytt-'an tyn tyni-æn, ni-sai-hakub tou rahpal tyn k'ma tyni-æn, Meirang, heirou na anna-un kow hia, ynna assi kapatei ta nis-ha-au.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annatati Maria, irou ka mou-kou ato ti Jesuss an, ka rou K'ytt-'an tyn tyni-æn, ni-sai-hakub tou rahpal tyn k'ma tyni-æn, Meirang, heirou na anna-un kow hia, ynna assi kapatei ta nis-ha-au.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Maria Dan als sy quam Daer Jesus was ende hem sagh biel aen sijne boeten seggende tot hem Heere indien ghy hier geweeft waert so en ware mijn broeDer niet gestorben</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then when Mary was come where Jesus was, and saw him, she fell down at his feet, saying unto him, Lord, if thou hadst been here, my brother had not died.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">馬利亞到了耶穌那裏，看見他，就俯伏在他腳前，說：「主啊，你若早在這裏，我兄弟必不死。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse33">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka kmytta ta ti Jesus tyni-æn ka tmangitangi ta te-ni, ka tmangi tangi [appa] ta Jo-den ka tou Jam tyni-æn, ni-bak-kan ki ryh ka ni-um-madou mou-tkau.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka kmytta ta ti Jesus tyni-æn ka tmangitangi ta te-ni, ka tmangi tangi [appa] ta Joden ka tou Jam tyni-æn, ni-bak-kan ki ryh ka ni-um-madou mou-tkau.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus Dan als hy haer sagh weenen ende de JoDen Die met Haer quamen [oock] weenen Wiert hy seer beeweeght in Den geest ende onteoerde Hem selben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">When Jesus therefore saw her weeping, and the Jews also weeping which came with her, he groaned in the spirit, and was troubled.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌看見她哭，並看見與她同來的猶太人也哭，就心裏悲歎，又甚憂愁，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse34">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'ma-appa Ni-matta-kounna-kamqu tyni-æn?Ni-k'ma ta neni tyni-æn, Meijrang mou-koua k'ytt-ei-to.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-k'ma-appa Ni-matta-kounna-kamqu tyni-æn?Ni-k'ma ta neni tyni-æn, Meijrang mou-koua k'ytt-ei-to.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende seyde Waer hebt ghy hem geleght: Sy seyden tot hem Heert Komt ende siet het.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And said, Where have ye laid him? They said unto him, Lord, come and see.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">便說：「你們把他安放在哪裏？」他們回答說：「請主來看。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse35">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-tmangi tangi ta ti Jesus.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-tmangi tangi ta ti Jesus.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus weende.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Jesus wept.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌哭了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse36">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-k'ma ta Joden, K'ytt'-ei mama kimang ka kavæ'-angö-en tyn tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-k'ma ta Joden, K'ytt'ei mama kimang ka kavæ'-angö-en tyn tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> De Joden Dan seyden Siet Hoe lief hy hem hadde.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then said the Jews, Behold how he loved him!</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">猶太人就說：「你看他愛這人是何等懇切。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse37">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-k'ma ta rarouma neini-æn, assi ni-pa-il pough kau-wa pamut ta teni, ka ni-pa rkyl-lat ki matta ki mavoutta, ka assi pei-mæmæræmmæh-in ta ti atta?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-k'ma ta rarouma neini-æn, assi ni-pa-il pough kau-wa pamut ta teni, ka ni-pa rkyl-lat ki matta ki mavoutta, ka assi pei-mæmæræmmæh-in ta ti atta?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende somminghe uyt haer seyden en konde hy Die de oogen des blinden geopent heeft niet maken Dat oock dese niet gestorben en ware?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And some of them said, Could not this man, which opened the eyes of the blind, have caused that even this man should not have died?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">其中有人說：「他既然開了瞎子的眼睛，豈不能叫這人不死嗎？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse38">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka ni-illan i-bbak ki tyh ta ti Jesus, ni-sah-ka koua tou ravak: ka karyfvykkifta anna, ka ni-atta-halap-pen ki vahtou.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka ni-illan i-bbak ki tyh ta ti Jesus, ni-sah-ka koua tou ravak: ka karyfvykkifta anna, ka ni-atta-halap-pen ki vahtou.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus Dan wederom in hem-selben seer beweeght zijnde quam tot het graf: enDe Het was een speloneke enDe eenen steen was daer opgeleght.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Jesus therefore again groaning in himself cometh to the grave. It was a cave, and a stone lay upon it.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌又心裏悲歎，來到墳墓前；那墳墓是個洞，有一塊石頭擋着。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse39">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'mata ti Jesus, Ha-mi-'au ta vahtou. Ti Martha ka niæha ki ni-mapatei, ta ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Meirang, mi-lalangso-ato hnyn, alei ka makk'' ahpat ki wæ'i [ki ni-k-ihkou-an tyn tou hynna].</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-k'mata ti Jesus, Ha-mi-'au ta vahtou. Ti Martha ka niæha ki ni-mapatei, ta ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Meirang, mi-lalangso-ato hnyn, alei ka makk'' ahpat ki wæ'i [ki ni-k-ihkou-an tyn tou hynna].</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus seyde Neemt Den steen wegh. Martha De suster Des gestorbenen seyde tot hem Heere Hy rieckt ny al want hy heeft bier dagen [aldaer gelegen.]</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Jesus said, Take ye away the stone. Martha, the sister of him that was dead, saith unto him, Lord, by this time he stinketh: for he hath been dead four days.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：「你們把石頭挪開。」那死人的姊姊馬大對他說：「主啊，他現在必是臭了，因為他死了已經四天了。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse40">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Assi-mau kow kauwa ni-pa-sousou-en, Rou tna-msing-kow, ka kmytt'ah-kow ki keirang-an ki kidi ki Alid?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Assi-mau kow kauwa ni-pa-sousou-en, Rou tna-msing-kow, ka kmytt'ah-kow ki keirang-an ki kidi ki Alid?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus seyde tot haar Hebbe ick u niet geseght Dat Soo ghy gelooft ghy De heerlickheyt Godts sien sult ?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Jesus saith unto her, Said I not unto thee, that, if thou wouldest believe, thou shouldest see the glory of God?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：「我不是對你說過，你若信，就必看見上帝的榮耀嗎？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse41">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-hami-'an nein ta vahtou 'k-ihkou-an ki patei. Ka ni-pa-passou-vavau ta ti Jesus ki matta, kma, Rama, lou-loug-'nau-kow, ki ni-tna-valei hou jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-hami-'an nein ta vahtou 'k-ihkou-an ki patei. Ka ni-pa-passou-vavau ta ti Jesus ki matta, kma, Rama, lou-loug-'nau-kow, ki ni-tna-valei hou jau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Sy namen ban Den steen wegh Daer De gestorbene lagh. Ende Jesus hief de oogen opwaerts ende seyde Dader ick dancke u Dat ghy my gehoort Hebt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then they took away the stone from the place where the dead was laid. And Jesus lifted up his eyes, and said, Father, I thank thee that thou hast heard me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們就把石頭挪開。耶穌舉目望天，說：「父啊，我感謝你，因為你已經聽我。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse42">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka kavana-en-nau ka myh ka koua kow millingigh jau-an: ra alei ki makoilalaulau, ka i-tou ryttoung myttoukko ni-pa-sou-sou-en-nau [ki atta,] alei ka tna-mfsing-ahta neni, ka ni-pa-dingi-en-hou jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka kavana-en-nau ka myh ka koua kow millingigh jau-an: ra alei ki makoilalaulau, ka i-tou ryttoung myttoukko ni-pa-sousou-en-nau [ki atta,] alei ka tna-mfsing-ahta neni, ka ni-pa-dingi-en-hou jau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Doch ick wit Dat ghy: my altijdt hoort : Maer om der Der schare wille Die rontom staet hebbe ick [dit] geseghtop Dat sy souden ghelooben Dat ghy my gesonden Hebt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And I knew that thou hearest me always: but because of the people which stand by I said it, that they may believe that thou hast sent me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我也知道你常聽我，但我說這話是為周圍站着的眾人，叫他們信是你差了我來。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse43">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka mattæ'i-kaha ki atta ni-makolangæh ta teni ki yngau ka ierang, Lazarus mou-pænæ-'æ.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka mattæ'i-kaha ki atta ni-makolangæh ta teni ki yngau ka ierang, Lazarus mou-pænæ-'æ.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende als hy Dit geseght hadde riep hy met grooter stemme Lazare komt uyt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And when he thus had spoken, he cried with a loud voice, Lazarus, come forth.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">說了這話，就大聲呼叫說：「拉撒路出來！」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse44">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-mou-pænæh ta ni-mapatei, ka ni-'avut tou rima tou rahpal ki na avut, ka ni-toup-pou tavlung tyn ki na tatouppo ki moula. Ni-kma ta tiJesuss nei-ni-æn, 'Ææu-na ast-tei tyni-æn ka padarang-a tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-mou-pænæh ta ni-mapatei, ka ni-'avut tou rima tou rahpal ki na avut, ka ni-toup-pou tavlung tyn ki na tatouppo ki moula. Ni-kma ta tiJesuss nei-ni-æn, 'Ææu-na ast-tei tyni-æn ka padarang-a tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende de ghestorbene quam uyt ghebonden aen handen ende boeten Met grafdoecken ende sijn aengesicht Was omwonden Met eenem sweet-doeck. Jesus seyde tot jaer Ontbindt hem ende laet hem hemen gaen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And he that was dead came forth, bound hand and foot with graveclothes: and his face was bound about with a napkin. Jesus saith unto them, Loose him, and let him go.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那死人就出來了，手腳裹着布，臉上包着手巾。耶穌對他們說：「解開，叫他走！」 （太26‧1－5；可14‧1－2；路22‧1－2）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse45">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata mabatoung ki Joden ka ierou'-ato ti Maria-an, ka ni-mararau ki pei-rynga ryngei ti Jesus, ni-tna-'msing tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata mabatoung ki Joden ka ierou'-ato ti Maria-an, ka ni-mararau ki pei-rynga ryngei ti Jesus, ni-tna-'msing tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende Jesus [dat] hoorende seyde Dese kranckheyt en is niet tot der doodt maer ter heerlickhept Godt : op Dat De Sone Gods door deselbe berheerlickt worde.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then many of the Jews which came to Mary, and had seen the things which Jesus did, believed on him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那些來看馬利亞的猶太人見了耶穌所做的事，就多有信他的；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse46">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ra ni d'marang ta rarou-ma neini-æn moukoua ki Fariseen, banna neini-æn ki na ryn-gei ti Jesus.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ra ni d'marang ta rarou-ma neini-æn moukoua ki Fariseen, banna neini-æn ki na ryn-gei ti Jesus.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Maer sommighe ban haer gingen tot De Pariseen ende seyden tot Haer't gene Jesus gedaen hadde.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But some of them went their ways to the Pharisees, and told them what things Jesus had done.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">但其中也有去見法利賽人的，將耶穌所做的事告訴他們。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse47">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-pa-pæu-a-kyp-pou kyppou ta Tama-P'hik ka Si-bavau ki Farifeen-appa ki pai-sasaal-lan, ka koun nein, 'Ou-mang-ah-kytta? Ka madagh ki pou-kidi-en ka pam't-tin ki vouel k'atta.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-pa-pæu-a-kyp-pou kyppou ta Tama-P'hik ka Si-bavau ki Farifeen-appa ki pai-sasaal-lan, ka koun nein, 'Ou-mang-ah-kytta? Ka madagh ki pou-kidi-en ka pam't-tin ki vouel k'atta.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> De Oberpriesters Dan ende de Phariseen bergaderDe den Raedt ende seyben Wat sullen wy Doen? Want dese mensche Doet bele teeckemen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then gathered the chief priests and the Pharisees a council, and said, What do we? for this man doeth many miracles.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">祭司長和法利賽人聚集公會，說：「這人行好些神蹟，我們怎麼辦呢？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse48">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Heirou pa-yhka koua-kyt-ta komma-hynna tyni-æn, tna-ymd-dah ta neni tna-'msing ty-ni-æn, ka ierrou-ah ta Romey-nen maril ki itoukou-an-eta ki ta'u-appa.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Heirou pa-yhka koua-kyt-ta komma-hynna tyni-æn, tna-ymd-dah ta neni tna-'msing ty-ni-æn, ka ierrou-ah ta Romey-nen maril ki itoukou-an-eta ki ta'u-appa.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Indien wy hem alsoo laten laten [geworden], sy sullen alle in hem gelooben ende de Romenynen sullen komen ende weck nemen beyde onse plaetse ende bolck.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">If we let him thus alone, all men will believe on him: and the Romans shall come and take away both our place and nation.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">若這樣由着他，人人都要信他，羅馬人也要來奪我們的地土和我們的百姓。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse49">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka saät neini-æn ti Kajafas ka Dadyllo ka Si-bavau tou tauwil kanna, ta ni-kma neini-æn, Assi-kamou mou-mhga ki mamang:</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka saät neini-æn ti Kajafas ka Dadyllo ka Si-bavau tou tauwil kanna, ta ni-kma neini-æn, Assi-kamou mou-mhga ki mamang:</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende een uyt haer [namelijck] Cajaphas Die Des selben jaers Hooge priester wag seyde tot haer Ghy en berstaet niets :</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And one of them, named Caiaphas, being the high priest that same year, said unto them, Ye know nothing at all,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">內中有一個人，名叫該亞法，本年作大祭司，對他們說：「你們不知道甚麼。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse50">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka assi-kamou pæh-ba-lei ka mariang-ah ymitt'-'æn ka mapatei-ah ta saäsat ki voual mi-vli ki ta'u, alei ka assi tau-tmouk-ah tau-rumma ta taou.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka assi-kamou pæh-ba-lei ka mariang-ah ymitt'-'æn ka mapatei-ah ta saäsat ki voual mi-vli ki ta'u, alei ka assi tau-tmouk-ah tau-rumma ta taou.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Noch ghy en [bedenckt] niet Dat Het ons nut is Dat een mensche sterde boor Het bolck ende Het geheele bolck niet berloren en gae.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Nor consider that it is expedient for us, that one man should die for the people, and that the whole nation perish not.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">獨不想一個人替百姓死，免得通國滅亡，就是你們的益處。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse51">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka assi tyn katta ni-pat-tæ'i-madou: ra alei ka Dadyllo ka Si-bavau tou tauwil k'anna, ni-pattæ'i-tan tyn, ka mapatei-ah ta ti Jesus mi-v'li kita'u:</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka assi tyn katta ni-pat-tæ'i-madou: ra alei ka Dadyllo ka Si-bavau tou tauwil k'anna, ni-pattæ'i-tan tyn, ka mapatei-ah ta ti Jesus mi-v'li kita'u:</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende dit seyde hy niet uyt hem selben : maer zijnde Hooge-priester Des selben jaers propheteerde hy Dat Jesus sterben soude boor het bolck:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And this spake he not of himself: but being high priest that year, he prophesied that Jesus should die for that nation;</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他這話不是出於自己，是因他本年作大祭司，所以預言耶穌將要替這一國死；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse52">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka assi dyk mi-v'lliki ta'u kanna, ra alei-appa ka ull'd-auh tyn ta ni-papaiä voak ka alalak ki Alid.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka assi dyk mi-v'lliki ta'u kanna, ra alei-appa ka ull'd-auh tyn ta ni-papaiä voak ka alalak ki Alid.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende niet alleen boor Dat bolck maer op Dat hy oock De kinderen Gods Die berfroyt waren tot een souDe bergaderen </TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And not for that nation only, but that also he should gather together in one the children of God that were scattered abroad.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">也不但替這一國死，並要將上帝四散的子民都聚集歸一。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse53">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata na kidi ki wæ'i kanna ni-papah kyppou ta ne ni ki sou ki pakapatei-an-nei tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata na kidi ki wæ'i kanna ni-papah kyppou ta ne ni ki sou ki pakapatei-an-nei tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Dan Dien dach dan af raedflaghden sy te samen dat sy hem dooden souden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then from that day forth they took counsel together for to put him to death.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">從那日起，他們就商議要殺耶穌。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse54">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata assi ni-mou-nau-nang ta ti Jesus hmi-tamæuh tou pænæh ki Joden: ra ni-d'marang-appa hynna mou-koua tou pou-rough ka tou hylli ki pæu-læh tou euma ka pananang-ing Esra-im : ka ni-hmi-koua tou hyn-na hmi-lam ki Pahta tæutæu-han tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata assi ni-mou-nau-nang ta ti Jesus hmi-tamæuh tou pænæh ki Joden: ra ni-d'marang-appa hynna mou-koua tou pou-rough ka tou hylli ki pæu-læh tou euma ka pananang-ing Esra-im : ka ni-hmi-koua tou hyn-na hmi-lam ki Pahta tæutæu-han tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus Dan en wanDelde niet meer bryelick onder De Joden : maer ginck ban Daer nae het landt by De woe stijne stijne nae De stadt genaemt Ephraim : ende ber keerde alDaer met sijne Discipelen</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Jesus therefore walked no more openly among the Jews; but went thence unto a country near to the wilderness, into a city called Ephraim, and there continued with his disciples.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">所以，耶穌不再顯然行在猶太人中間，就離開那裏往靠近曠野的地方去，到了一座城，名叫以法蓮，就在那裏和門徒同住。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse55">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka æia-ta mang ta 'Ou-vavatoug-han ki Hali-da æu'-en ki Joden, Ka mabatoung ta vo-ual tou pourough k'anna ka ni-sa-bavau mou-Jerusalem, t-ou-rou ki 'Ou-vavatoug-han ki Ha-li-daæu-en, alei ki paka-koup-tigh-ei neini-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka æia-ta mang ta 'Ou-vavatoug-han ki Hali-da æu'-en ki Joden, Ka mabatoung ta voual tou pourough k'anna ka ni-sa-bavau mou-Jerusalem, t-ou-rou ki 'Ou-vavatoug-han ki Ha-li-daæu-en, alei ki paka-koup-tigh-ei neini-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">. Ende het Pascha der Jodent was na by ende beele uyt das Landt gingen op nae Jerusalem boor het Pascha op Dat sy Haer selben reynighden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And the Jews' passover was nigh at hand: and many went out of the country up to Jerusalem before the passover, to purify themselves.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">猶太人的逾越節近了，有許多人從鄉下上耶路撒冷去，要在節前潔淨自己。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse56">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-k'i'ym nein ta ti Jesus, ka ni-mattæ'i-tavætæ-væh ta neni mitouhko tou Kou-va ki t'a tam'd-den ki Alid, Pæh-mang-noumi pægdimdim? Assi kauwa ierrou-ah ta teni tou 'Ou-vavatoug-han?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-k'i'ym nein ta ti Jesus, ka ni-mattæ'i-tavætæ-væh ta neni mitouhko tou Kou-va ki t'a tam'd-den ki Alid, Pæh-mang-noumi pægdimdim? Assi kauwa ierrou-ah ta teni tou 'Ou-vavatoug-han?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">. Sy sochten Dan Jesum ende seyden onder malkanderen staende in Den Tempel Wat Dunckt u ? [dunckt u] dat hy niet komen en sal tot het Feest ?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then sought they for Jesus, and spake among themselves, as they stood in the temple, What think ye, that he will not come to the feast?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他們就尋找耶穌，站在殿裏彼此說：「你們的意思如何，他不來過節嗎？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse57">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-mahkou-sou ta Ta-'p'hik ka Si-bavau ki Fariseen-appa, heirou mou-mha lava ta ti mamang ka æ-i-a-kouna ta teni, ka pakavana-auh tyn ta an-na, alei ka touroung-au nein tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-mahkou-sou ta Ta-'p'hik ka Si-bavau ki Fariseen-appa, heirou mou-mha lava ta ti mamang ka æ-i-a-kouna ta teni, ka pakavana-auh tyn ta an-na, alei ka touroung-au nein tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> De Ober-priesters nu ende De Phariseen hadden een ghebodt gegeben Dat soo yemant wiste waer hy was, hy soude Het te kennen geben op dat hy Hem mochten bangen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Now both the chief priests and the Pharisees had given a commandment, that, if any man knew where he were, he should shew it, that they might take him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那時，祭司長和法利賽人早已吩咐說，若有人知道耶穌在哪裏，就要報明，好去拿他。</TRANSL>
    </S>
</TEXT>