<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEXT id="Siraya_Dutch_John_Chapter14" xml:lang="fos" source="Siraya Bible, John gospel" copyright="public domain" citation="Gravius, Daniël. 1661. Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa. Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang. Amsterdam: Michiel Hartogh." BibTeX_citation="@book{Gravius1661,&#10;  author    = {Gravius, Daniël},&#10;  year      = {1661},&#10;  title     = {Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa},&#10;  note      = {Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang},&#10;  address   = {Amsterdam},&#10;  publisher = {Michiel Hartogh}&#10;}" dialect="Siraya">
    <S id="verse1">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ynna m-eringau ki voulas tou tintin-oumi: tna-'msing-kamou ki Alid, tna-'msin-ga-appa jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ynna m-eringau ki voulas tou tintin-oumi: tna-'msing-kamou ki Alid, tna-'msin-ga-appa jau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Vw' herte en worde niet ontroert : ghylieden gelooft in Godt gelooft oock in my.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Let not your heart be troubled: ye believe in God, believe also in me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">「你們心裏不要憂愁；你們信上帝，也當信我。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse2">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Tou talagh ki Rama-au ta madagh ki i-tou-kakouan: rou assi komma-hynna ynna-koh bannavanna ymoumi-æn: mou-koua-koh tmanang ki i-touko-ua-an ka i-toukou-'ei-moumi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Tou talagh ki Rama-au ta madagh ki i-tou-kakouan: rou assi komma-hynna ynna-koh bannavanna ymoumi-æn: mou-koua-koh tmanang ki i-touko-ua-an ka i-toukou-'ei-moumi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> in Het huys mijns Daders zijn bele woningen andersins soo soude ick het u geseght hebben: ick gae henen om u plaetse te bereyden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">In my Father's house are many mansions: if it were not so, I would have told you. I go to prepare a place for you.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">在我父的家裏有許多住處；若是沒有，我就早已告訴你們了。我去原是為你們預備地方去。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse3">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka d'marang-âl-ato mou-koua tmanang ymoumi-æn kii-toukoua-an, sa-lyk koug-ah-koh mara ymoumi-æn pa-ou-koua ymoumi-æn, alei ka ǣ-i-a-koua-âl-appa-kamou ta ymoumi tou ǣ-i-a-koua-ei-mau.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka d'marang-âl-ato mou-koua tmanang ymoumi-æn kii-toukoua-an, sa-lyk koug-ah-koh mara ymoumi-æn pa-ou-koua ymoumi-æn, alei ka ǣ-i-a-koua-âl-appa-kamou ta ymoumi tou ǣ-i-a-koua-ei-mau.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende soo wanneer ick henen sal gegaen zijn ende u plaetse sat bereyt hebben soo kome ick weder ende sal u tot my nemen op Dat ghy oock zijn meught Daer ick ben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And if I go and prepare a place for you, I will come again, and receive you unto myself; that where I am, there ye may be also.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我若去為你們預備了地方，就必再來接你們到我那裏去，我在哪裏，叫你們也在那裏。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse4">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka tou mang ka sahka kou'-ei-mau mavana-kamou, ka mou-mhga-kamou ki darang.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka tou mang ka sahka kou'-ei-mau mavana-kamou, ka mou-mhga-kamou ki darang.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende maer ick henen gae Weet ghy: ende den wegh weet ghy.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And whither I go ye know, and the way ye know.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我往哪裏去，你們知道；那條路，你們也知道。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse5">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'mata ti Thomas ty-ni-æn, Meirang, assi-kame mava-na tou mang ta sah-kakoua-ei-mhou: ka mou-lpough-kame ma-ma ki mang mou-mhga ki darang?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-k'mata ti Thomas ty-ni-æn, Meirang, assi-kame mava-na tou mang ta sah-kakoua-ei-mhou: ka mou-lpough-kame ma-ma ki mang mou-mhga ki darang?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Thomas seyde tot hem Heere wy en weten niet maer ghy henen gaet : Ende hoe konnen wy ben wegh we-</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Thomas saith unto him, Lord, we know not whither thou goest; and how can we know the way?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">多馬對他說：「主啊，我們不知道你往哪裏去，怎麼知道那條路呢？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse6">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Nik'ma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Ti jauta darang, ki ka-d'ilig-an, ki kauag-han-appa. Asfi mou-koua ta ti mamang ki Rama-an, dijk alei jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Nik'ma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Ti jauta darang, ki ka-d'ilig-an, ki kauag-han-appa. Asfi mou-koua ta ti mamang ki Rama-an, dijk alei jau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> JeJesus seyde tot hem Ick ben De wegh ende de waerheyt ende het leben. Niemandt en Komt tot Den Dader Dan door my.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus saith unto him, I am the way, the truth, and the life: no man cometh unto the Father, but by me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：「我就是道路、真理、生命；若不藉着我，沒有人能到父那裏去。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse7">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Heirou kmalang-kamou jau-an, ynna-kamou kalang-ate ki Rama'au: ka hnyn kmalang-kamou tyni-n, ka ni-kmytta-ka-mou tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Heirou kmalang-kamou jau-an, ynna-kamou kalang-ate ki Rama'au: ka hnyn kmalang-kamou tyni-n, ka ni-kmytta-ka-mou tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Indien ghy-lieden my ghekent haddet soo soudet ghy oock mijnen Dader ghekent Hebben : ende ban nu kennet ghy hem ende hebbet hem gesien.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">If ye had known me, ye should have known my Father also: and from henceforth ye know him, and have seen him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們若認識我，也就認識我的父。從今以後，你們認識他，並且已經看見他。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse8">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'ma tati Filippus tyni-æn, Meirang, pak'ytta-au-ka-me ki Rama, ka mamfsing-al-ato-ymiæn-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-k'ma tati Filippus tyni-æn, Meirang, pak'ytta-au-ka-me ki Rama, ka mamfsing-al-ato-ymiæn-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Philippus seyde tot hem Neere toont ons Den Dader ende Het is ons genoegh.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Philip saith unto him, Lord, shew us the Father, and it sufficeth us.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">腓力對他說：「求主將父顯給我們看，我們就知足了。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse9">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Makka komma-hynna ki dallia ka æ-i-a-lam koh ymoumi-æn, kaassi-kow kmalang jau-an Filippus? Ti mamang ta ni-kmyt-ta jau-an, ni-kmyttappaki R a-ma: ka matta'i mang kow, pa-k'ytta-au-kame ki Rama ?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Makka komma-hynna ki dallia ka æ-i-a-lam koh ymoumi-æn, kaassi-kow kmalang jau-an Filippus? Ti mamang ta ni-kmytta jau-an, ni-kmyttappaki R a-ma: ka matta'i mang kow, pa-k'ytta-au-kame ki Rama ?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">. Jesus seyde tot hem Ben ick so langen tijdt met u lieden ende en hebt ghy my niet gekent Philippe : Die my gesien heeft die Heeft Den DaDer gesien : ende hoe seght ghy Toont ons den Dader :</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus saith unto him, Have I been so long time with you, and yet hast thou not known me, Philip? he that hath seen me hath seen the Father; and how sayest thou then, Shew us the Father?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌對他說：「腓力，我與你們同在這樣長久，你還不認識我嗎？人看見了我，就是看見了父；你怎麼說『將父顯給我們看』呢？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse10">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Assi-kow kauwa tna-mfing ka i-tou-koua-en nau ki Rama, ka i-tou-koua-appa ta R ama jau-an?Sou katta ka pasou-sou-en-nau ymoumi-n, assi-koh sykkounnoung masousou, ra Ra-ma appa ka mylli jau-an, teni ta pamut ki ryngei.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Assi-kow kauwa tna-mfing ka i-tou-koua-en nau ki Rama, ka i-tou-koua-appa ta R ama jau-an?Sou katta ka pasou-sou-en-nau ymoumi-n, assi-koh sykkounnoung masousou, ra Rama appa ka mylli jau-an, teni ta pamut ki ryngei.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">. Ghelooft ghy niet Dat ick In den Dader [ben], ende de Dader in my is : De woorden Die ik tot u-lieden spreke en spreke ick ban my selben niet maer de Dader die in my blijft de selbe Doet De wercken.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Believest thou not that I am in the Father, and the Father in me? the words that I speak unto you I speak not of myself: but the Father that dwelleth in me, he doeth the works.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我在父裏面，父在我裏面，你不信嗎？我對你們所說的話，不是憑着自己說的，乃是住在我裏面的父做他自己的事。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse11">
        <FORM kindOf="original">. Tna-'msing-ajau-an, kai-tou-koua koh ki Rama, ka i-tou-koua appata Rama jau-an,ka hei-rou assi, annata tha-'msing-a jau-an alei ki ryngei mamadou.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">. Tna-'msing-ajau-an, kai-tou-koua koh ki Rama, ka i-tou-koua appata Rama jau-an,ka hei-rou assi, annata tha-'msing-a jau-an alei ki ryngei mamadou.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">. Geloobet my Dat ick in den Dader[ben], ende de Dader in my is ende indien niet soo soo gheloobet my om De wercken selbe.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Believe me that I am in the Father, and the Father in me: or else believe me for the very works' sake.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們當信我，我在父裏面，父在我裏面；即或不信，也當因我所做的事信我。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse12">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Missing, missing koun-nau-kamou-ra, ti mamang ta tna-'msing jau-an, ryngei k'anna ka pamt-ten-nau, pam't-aul-appa tyn, ka mei-saoun-al-appa ki an-na. Ka d'marang-koh mou-koua ki Rama-an:</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Missing, missing koun-nau-kamou-ra, ti mamang ta tna-'msing jau-an, ryngei k'anna ka pamt-ten-nau, pam't-aul-appa tyn, ka mei-saoun-al-appa ki an-na. Ka d'marang-koh mou-koua ki Rama-an:</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Doorwaer boorwaer segge ick u-lieden die in my gelooft De wercken Die ick Doe sal hy oock doen ende sal meerder doen Dan dese. Want ick gae Henen tot mijnen Dader :</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Verily, verily, I say unto you, He that believeth on me, the works that I do shall he do also; and greater works than these shall he do; because I go unto my Father.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我實實在在地告訴你們，我所做的事，信我的人也要做，並且要做比這更大的事，因為我往父那裏去。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse13">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka mamang ka t'oumi-mia-ei-moumi tou Nanang-au, pam't-au-mau k'anna: alei ka pou-vavau-eih ki kidi ta Rama tou Alak.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka mamang ka t'oumi-mia-ei-moumi tou Nanang-au, pam't-au-mau k'anna: alei ka pou-vavau-eih ki kidi ta Rama tou Alak.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende soo wat ghy begeerej sult in mijnen Name Dat sal ick doen: op Dat de Da: Der In De Sone berheerlickt worde.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And whatsoever ye shall ask in my name, that will I do, that the Father may be glorified in the Son.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們奉我的名無論求甚麼，我必成就，叫父因兒子得榮耀。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse14">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Heirou tmoumimi-ah-kam ou ki mamang tou Nanang-au, pam't-au-mau k'anna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Heirou tmoumimi-ah-kam ou ki mamang tou Nanang-au, pam't-au-mau k'anna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Soo ghy yet begeeren sult in mijnen Name ick sal't doen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">If ye shall ask any thing in my name, I will do it.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們若奉我的名求甚麼，我必成就。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse15">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Heirou mavæ'angö-ka-mou jau-an, hmaäto ki pakou-sou-en-nau.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Heirou mavæ'angö-ka-mou jau-an, hmaäto ki pakou-sou-en-nau.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Indien ghy my lief hebt so bewaert mijne geboDen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">If ye love me, keep my commandments.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">「你們若愛我，就必遵守我的命令。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse16">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Katmoumimi-ah-koh ki Rama, ka pi-'æh ki Tama-Paka-haniap ka pani ymoumi-æn, alei ka mæylli-ah ymoumi-æn-tou yhkakouan myddarynnough.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Katmoumimi-ah-koh ki Rama, ka pi-'æh ki Tama-Paka-haniap ka pani ymoumi-æn, alei ka mæylli-ah ymoumi-æn-tou yhkakouan myddarynnough.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende Ick sal den Dader bidden ende hy sal u eenen anderen Trooster geben op Dat hy by u blijbe in Der eeuwigheyt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And I will pray the Father, and he shall give you another Comforter, that he may abide with you for ever;</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我要求父，父就另外賜給你們一位保惠師，叫他永遠與你們同在，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse17">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Teni-an ka Joep-pan ki katiktik-an ki sou, ka assi at-ta-lpoug-in matta-ryh ki næi, alei ka assi kmytta tyni-æn, ka assi kmalang tyni-æn: ri kma-lang-kamou tyni-æn ta ymou-mi, ka mæylli ta teni ymoumi-æn, ka i-tou-koua-âl appa ymou-mi-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Teni-an ka Joep-pan ki katiktik-an ki sou, ka assi at-ta-lpoug-in matta-ryh ki næi, alei ka assi kmytta tyni-æn, ka assi kmalang tyni-æn: ri kma-lang-kamou tyni-æn ta ymoumi, ka mæylli ta teni ymoumi-æn, ka i-tou-koua-âl appa ymou-mi-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> [Namelick] den Geest Der waerheydt welcken br wereldt niet en Kan ontfangen want sy en siet hem niet noch en kent hem niet : maer ghy kent hem want hy blijft by u-lieden ende sal in u zijn.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Even the Spirit of truth; whom the world cannot receive, because it seeth him not, neither knoweth him: but ye know him; for he dwelleth with you, and shall be in you.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">就是真理的聖靈，乃世人不能接受的；因為不見他，也不認識他。你們卻認識他，因他常與你們同在，也要在你們裏面。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse18">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Assi-koh patou snæh-a'ymoumi-næ: sa-lykkough-ah-koh mou-koua ymoumi-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Assi-koh patou snæh-a'ymoumi-næ: sa-lykkough-ah-koh mou-koua ymoumi-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ick en sal u geen wesen. sen laten : ick kome [weder] tot u.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">I will not leave you comfortless: I will come to you.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我不撇下你們為孤兒，我必到你們這裏來。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse19">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Assi madallia ka assi kmytta-ah jau-an tanæi: ri kmyt-ta-ah-kamou jau-an ta emoumi: Alei kamæuag-koh, ka mæuag-ah-kamou ta ymoumi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Assi madallia ka assi kmytta-ah jau-an tanæi: ri kmyt-ta-ah-kamou jau-an ta emoumi: Alei kamæuag-koh, ka mæuag-ah-kamou ta ymoumi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Noch eenen kleynen [tijdt] ende De wereldt en sal my niet meer sien : maer ghy sult my sien : Want ick lebe ende ghy sult leben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Yet a little while, and the world seeth me no more; but ye see me: because I live, ye shall live also.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">還有不多的時候，世人不再看見我，你們卻看見我；因為我活着，你們也要活着。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse20">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Tou wæ'ik'anna kmalang-ah-kamou, ka[i-tou-koua]-koh ki Rama, ka [i-tou-koua]-kamou jau-an, ka [i-tou-koua-app]-'oh ymou-mi-n.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Tou wæ'ik'anna kmalang-ah-kamou, ka[i-tou-koua]-koh ki Rama, ka [i-tou-koua]-kamou jau-an, ka [i-tou-koua-app]-'oh ymoumi-n.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> In dien Dagh sult ghy bekennen Dat ick in mijnen. Dader [ben,] ende ghy in My ende ick in u.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">At that day ye shall know that I am in my Father, and ye in me, and I in you.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">到那日，你們就知道我在父裏面，你們在我裏面，我也在你們裏面。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse21">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ti-mamang ta akoumea ki pahkou-sou-en-nau, ka hmas-appakianna, teni tamavæ'angs jau-an: ka ti-mamang ta mav'an-go jau-an, teni ta kavæ'ings-eih ki Raraman-au: ka mavæ'ango-ah-koh tyni-æn, ka paka-madou-ei-mau jau-an paka-æmæh tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ti-mamang ta akoumea ki pahkou-sou-en-nau, ka hmas-appakianna, teni tamavæ'angs jau-an: ka ti-mamang ta mav'an-go jau-an, teni ta kavæ'ings-eih ki Raraman-au: ka mavæ'ango-ah-koh tyni-æn, ka paka-madou-ei-mau jau-an paka-æmæh tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Die Mijne geboden Heeft ende Deselbe bewaert die is't die my lief heeft: ende Die my lief Heeft sal ban mijnen Dader geliebet worden : ende ick sal hem lief hebben ende ick sal my selben aen hem openbaren.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">He that hath my commandments, and keepeth them, he it is that loveth me: and he that loveth me shall be loved of my Father, and I will love him, and will manifest myself to him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">有了我的命令又遵守的，這人就是愛我的；愛我的必蒙我父愛他，我也要愛他，並且要向他顯現。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse22">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'matyni-ænta ti Judas, assi ti Iskariot, Meirang, ka-mang kanna, ka paka-madou-ei-mhou ymhou-an paka-æmh y-mian-an, assi paka-æmh ki næi?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-k'matyni-ænta ti Judas, assi ti Iskariot, Meirang, ka-mang kanna, ka paka-madou-ei-mhou ymhou-an paka-æmh y-mian-an, assi paka-æmh ki næi?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Judas niet De Isca riot seyde tot hem Herre wat is het Dat ghy selben aen ons sult openbaren ende niet aen De Wereldt :</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Judas saith unto him, not Iscariot, Lord, how is it that thou wilt manifest thyself unto us, and not unto the world?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">猶大（不是加略人猶大）問耶穌說：「主啊，為甚麼要向我們顯現，不向世人顯現呢？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse23">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni mattæ'i-v'slita ti Jesus K'ma tyni-æn, Ti-mamang ta mavæ'angs jau-an,hmai-ah ki sou au: kKa Rama-au ta mavæ'ango-ahtyni-æn, ka mou-koua-ah-kame tyni-æn, ka i-tou-kakou-ah-kame tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni mattæ'i-v'slita ti Jesus K'ma tyni-æn, Ti-mamang ta mavæ'angs jau-an,hmai-ah ki sou au: kKa Rama-au ta mavæ'ango-ahtyni-æn, ka mou-koua-ah-kame tyni-æn, ka i-tou-kakou-ah-kame tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus antwoordde ende seyde tot Hem Soo yemandt my lief heeft Die sal mijn woordt bewaren : ende mijn Dader sal hem lief hebben ende wy sullen tot hem komen ende sullen wooninge by hem maken.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus answered and said unto him, If a man love me, he will keep my words: and my Father will love him, and we will come unto him, and make our abode with him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌回答說：「人若愛我，就必遵守我的道；我父也必愛他，並且我們要到他那裏去，與他同住。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse24">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ti-mamang ta assi mavæa'ango jau-an, assi hmaä ki sou-au. Ka sou k'atta ka 'illing'h-noumi, assi a jau, râ a tou Rama-appa,ka ni-madingi jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ti-mamang ta assi mavæa'ango jau-an, assi hmaä ki sou-au. Ka sou k'atta ka 'illing'h-noumi, assi a jau, râ a tou Rama-appa,ka ni-madingi jau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Dit My niet lief en heeft Die en bewaert mijne woorwoorden niet. Ende Het Wordt dat ghy-lieden hoort en is Het mijne niet maer Des Daders Die my gesonden heeft.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">He that loveth me not keepeth not my sayings: and the word which ye hear is not mine, but the Father's which sent me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">不愛我的人就不遵守我的道。你們所聽見的道不是我的，乃是差我來之父的道。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse25">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Pa-sousou-en-ato-mau-kamou ki mamang k'atta dou mæylli-app'-oh ymoumi-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Pa-sousou-en-ato-mau-kamou ki mamang k'atta dou mæylli-app'-oh ymoumi-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Dese dinghen hebbe ick tot u gesproken by u blijbende.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">These things have I spoken unto you, being yet present with you.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">「我還與你們同住的時候，已將這些話對你們說了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse26">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ra Tama-Paka-haniap ka Joep-pan ka d'lligh matiktik, ka padingi-eih ki Rama tou Na-nang-au, teni ta makou-atigh-ah mahkou-æmis ymoumi-æn, ka pa-hibalei-âl-appa ki mamang ka na sou-au ymoumi-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ra Tama-Paka-haniap ka Joep-pan ka d'lligh matiktik, ka padingi-eih ki Rama tou Na-nang-au, teni ta makou-atigh-ah mahkou-æmis ymoumi-æn, ka pa-hibalei-âl-appa ki mamang ka na sou-au ymoumi-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Maer de Trooster De heylige Geest welcken De DaDer seyden sal in mijnen Name Die sal u alles leeren ende sal u indachtigh maken alles wan ick u geseght hebbe.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But the Comforter, which is the Holy Ghost, whom the Father will send in my name, he shall teach you all things, and bring all things to your remembrance, whatsoever I have said unto you.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">但保惠師，就是父因我的名所要差來的聖靈，他要將一切的事指教你們，並且要叫你們想起我對你們所說的一切話。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse27">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Reia ta atta-koua-en-nau ymoumi-æn, reia-au ta pæp'æ-au ymoumi-æn: assi mama ka pæ-p'æn ki næi, tapæpæpǣ-au k'an-na ymoumi-æn; Ynna mieringau ki voulas tou tintin-oumi, ynna mahtakout.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Reia ta atta-koua-en-nau ymoumi-æn, reia-au ta pæp'æ-au ymoumi-æn: assi mama ka pæ-p'æn ki næi, tapæpæpǣ-au k'an-na ymoumi-æn; Ynna mieringau ki voulas tou tintin-oumi, ynna mahtakout.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Drede late ick u mijnen brede gebe ick u : Niet gelicker wijns De werelt [hem] geeft gebe ick [hem]u. Dw' herte en worde niet ontroert noch en zijt niet bert'saeght.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Peace I leave with you, my peace I give unto you: not as the world giveth, give I unto you. Let not your heart be troubled, neither let it be afraid.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我留下平安給你們；我將我的平安賜給你們。我所賜的，不像世人所賜的。你們心裏不要憂愁，也不要膽怯。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse28">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-millingigh-kamou ka ni-pa-sousou-en-nau ymoumi-æn, D'marang-koh, ka sa-lyk-kough-ah-koh mou-koua ymou-mi-æn. Heirou-ra mavæ'angö-ato-ka mou jau-an, ynna-kamou karai alei ka na sou-au, D'ma-rang-koh mou-koua ki Rama-an: ka Rama-au ta si-ourou i-tou-va-vau ki kidi jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-millingigh-kamou ka ni-pa-sousou-en-nau ymoumi-æn, D'marang-koh, ka sa-lyk-kough-ah-koh mou-koua ymou-mi-æn. Heirou-ra mavæ'angö-ato-ka mou jau-an, ynna-kamou karai alei ka na sou-au, D'ma-rang-koh mou-koua ki Rama-an: ka Rama-au ta si-ourou i-tou-va-vau ki kidi jau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ghy hebt gehoort dat ick tat u geseght hebbe Ick gae henen ende kome [weder] tot u. Indien ghy my lief haddet soo soudet ghy U berlijden om Dat ick geseght hebbe Ick gae henen tot Den Dader : want mijn Dader is meerder dan ick.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Ye have heard how I said unto you, I go away, and come again unto you. If ye loved me, ye would rejoice, because I said, I go unto the Father: for my Father is greater than I.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們聽見我對你們說了，我去還要到你們這裏來。你們若愛我，因我到父那裏去，就必喜樂，因為父是比我大的。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse29">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-vannavanna-en-au-kamou hnyn rou assi-appa pa-væut-tin, alei ka rou pavut-ato, ka tna-msing-ah-kamou-ra.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-vannavanna-en-au-kamou hnyn rou assi-appa pa-væut-tin, alei ka rou pavut-ato, ka tna-msing-ah-kamou-ra.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende nu hebbe ick Het u geseght eer het geschiet is op dat wanneer het geschiedt sal zijn. zijn ghy gelooben menght.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And now I have told you before it come to pass, that, when it is come to pass, ye might believe.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">現在事情還沒有成就，我預先告訴你們，叫你們到事情成就的時候就可以信。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse30">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Assi-koh mattæ'i-ta pang-ah hnyn ki sou ymou-mi-æn : alei ka ierrarouroua ta Meisasou ki næi katta, râ ä'ou-si ta teni ki ma-mang jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Assi-koh mattæ'i-ta pang-ah hnyn ki sou ymou-mi-æn : alei ka ierrarouroua ta Meisasou ki næi katta, râ ä'ou-si ta teni ki ma-mang jau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ick en sal niet beel meer met u spreken : want De Oberste deser Wereldt komt ende en heeft aen my niets.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Hereafter I will not talk much with you: for the prince of this world cometh, and hath nothing in me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">以後我不再和你們多說話，因為這世界的王將到。他在我裏面是毫無所有；</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse31">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Alei-appa ka mou-mhga-ah ta næi ka kavæ'angö-en-nau ta Rama, ka pamut-koh kma-hyn-na mama ki ni-pahkou-sou-en ki Rama jau-an. Æhpit-tâ, d'ma-rang-eta hia.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Alei-appa ka mou-mhga-ah ta næi ka kavæ'angö-en-nau ta Rama, ka pamut-koh kma-hynna mama ki ni-pahkou-sou-en ki Rama jau-an. Æhpit-tâ, d'ma-rang-eta hia.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Maer op dat de wereldt wete Dat ick Den Dader lief hebbe ende alsoo Doe gelijckerwijs my De Dader geboden heeft. Staet op laet ons ban Hier gaen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">But that the world may know that I love the Father; and as the Father gave me commandment, even so I do. Arise, let us go hence.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">但要叫世人知道我愛父，並且父怎樣吩咐我，我就怎樣行。起來，我們走吧！」</TRANSL>
    </S>
</TEXT>