<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEXT id="Siraya_Dutch_John_Chapter20" xml:lang="fos" source="Siraya Bible, John gospel" copyright="public domain" citation="Gravius, Daniël. 1661. Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa. Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang. Amsterdam: Michiel Hartogh." BibTeX_citation="@book{Gravius1661,&#10;  author    = {Gravius, Daniël},&#10;  year      = {1661},&#10;  title     = {Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa},&#10;  note      = {Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang},&#10;  address   = {Amsterdam},&#10;  publisher = {Michiel Hartogh}&#10;}">
    <S id="verse1">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka tou wæ'i ka naunnamou ki pta ki pæ'i-habab-'an ni-sah-takkugh ta ti Maria Magda-lena, rou marimdim-appa, mou-koua tou ravak: ka ni-kyt-ta-'n tyn ta vahttou ka eu-mi-'en-nato tou ravak.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka tou wæ'i ka naunnamou ki pta ki pæ'i-habab-'an ni-sah-takkugh ta ti Maria Magda-lena, rou marimdim-appa, mou-koua tou ravak: ka ni-kyt-ta-'n tyn ta vahttou ka eu-mi-'en-nato tou ravak.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende op den eersten dagh der weke ginck Maria Madgalene broegh als het noch duyster was na het graf : ende sagh den steen ban Het graf wech genomen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The first day of the week cometh Mary Magdalene early, when it was yet dark, unto the sepulchre, and seeth the stone taken away from the sepulchre.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">七日的第一日清早，天還黑的時候，抹大拉的馬利亞來到墳墓那裏，看見石頭從墳墓挪開了，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse2">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-si houm mou-koua ti Simon Petrus-an, ki Pahtateutæu'-enappa ka sa'sat ka kavæangö-en ti Jesus, ka ni-kma neini-æn, Ara'n-nato ta Meirang, mæeumia tou ravak k a assi-mian kavan'an ni-makka-kounna ta neni tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-si houm mou-koua ti Simon Petrus-an, ki Pahtateutæu'-enappa ka sa'sat ka kavæangö-en ti Jesus, ka ni-kma neini-æn, Ara'n-nato ta Meirang, mæeumia tou ravak k a assi-mian kavan'an ni-makka-kounna ta neni tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Sy liep dan ende quam tot Simon Petrus ende tot Den anderen Discipel welcelien Jesus lief hadde ende seyde tot haer Sy hebben den den Heere wech ghenomen uyt het graf ende wy en weten niet waer sy hem geleght hebben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then she runneth, and cometh to Simon Peter, and to the other disciple, whom Jesus loved, and saith unto them, They have taken away the LORD out of the sepulchre, and we know not where they have laid him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">就跑來見西門‧彼得和耶穌所愛的那個門徒，對他們說：「有人把主從墳墓裏挪了去，我們不知道放在哪裏。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse3">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-tpapænh ta ti Petrus, ki Pahtatæutæu'-hanap-pa ka saaisat, ka ni-ierrouatou ra-vak.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-tpapænh ta ti Petrus, ki Pahtatæutæu'-hanap-pa ka saaisat, ka ni-ierrouatou ravak.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Petrus Dan gingh uytende De ander Discipel ende sy quamen tot het graf.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Peter therefore went forth, and that other disciple, and came to the sepulchre.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">彼得和那門徒就出來，往墳墓那裏去。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse4">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ra darouha kanna ta ni-ma hkaulla si-houm: ra Pahtatæu'han-appa ka sasisat ta ni-si-houm fsi-ourou mt'ægh ti Petrus-an, ka si-ouro'-en tyn mou-koua tou ravak.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ra darouha kanna ta ni-ma hkaulla si-houm: ra Pahtatæu'han-appa ka sasisat ta ni-si-houm fsi-ourou mt'ægh ti Petrus-an, ka si-ouro'-en tyn mou-koua tou ravak.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende dese twee liepen te geliick : ende De ander Discipel liep boor uyt suelder Dan Petrus ende quam eerst tot het graf.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">So they ran both together: and the other disciple did outrun Peter, and came first to the sepulchre.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">兩個人同跑，那門徒比彼得跑得更快，先到了墳墓，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse5">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka mæ'æu-sousou, ni-kyt-t'an tyn ta atta-kou-an ka æ-it, ra assi ni-mou-rbo' hynna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka mæ'æu-sousou, ni-kyt-t'an tyn ta atta-kou-an ka æ-it, ra assi ni-mou-rbo' hynna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende als hy neder buckte sagh hy De doecken liggen nochtans en gingh hy [daer] niet in.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And he stooping down, and looking in, saw the linen clothes lying; yet went he not in.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">低頭往裏看，就見細麻布還放在那裏，只是沒有進去。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse6">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-ierroua-appa ta ti Simon Petrus mæ-æ-ugh tyni-n, ka ni-mou-rbou ta teni tou ravak, kmytta ki atta-kou'an ka a-it.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-ierroua-appa ta ti Simon Petrus mæ-æ-ugh tyni-n, ka ni-mou-rbou ta teni tou ravak, kmytta ki atta-kou'an ka a-it.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Simon Petrus Dan quam ende bolghde hem enDe gingh in Het graf ende sag de doecken liggen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then cometh Simon Peter following him, and went into the sepulchre, and seeth the linen clothes lie,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">西門‧彼得隨後也到了，進墳墓裏去，就看見細麻布還放在那裏，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse7">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka na ta t'oupou ki moul-la ka ni-atta-halap-pen tou voun-go tyn assi ni-atta-sal-lan ki æ-it, ra ni-atta''-1bæh -enappa matta-'kkurik tou pani ki i-tou-kou'-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka na ta t'oupou ki moul-la ka ni-atta-halap-pen tou voun-go tyn assi ni-atta-sal-lan ki æ-it, ra ni-atta''-1bæh -enappa matta-'kkurik tou pani ki i-tou-kou'-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende den sweet-doeck die op sijn Hooft gheweest was [en sagh hy] niet by de doecken liggen maer in't bysonder in een [ander] plaetse t'sanen gerolt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And the napkin, that was about his head, not lying with the linen clothes, but wrapped together in a place by itself.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">又看見耶穌的裹頭巾沒有和細麻布放在一處，是另在一處捲着。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse8">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-mou-rbo-appa ta Pahtatæutæu-'han ka saasat ka ni-si-ourou mou-kouatou r'avak, ka ni-k'yt-tan tyn, ka ni-tna'-'mfsing-appa.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-mou-rbo-appa ta Pahtatæutæu-'han ka saasat ka ni-si-ourou mou-kouatou r'avak, ka ni-k'yt-tan tyn, ka ni-tna'-'mfsing-appa.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Doe gingh Dan oock De ander Discipel daer in Die eerst tot Het graf gekomen was en sagh het ende gheloosde.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then went in also that other disciple, which came first to the sepulchre, and he saw, and believed.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">先到墳墓的那門徒也進去，看見就信了。（</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse9">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Nda asfi-appa-nein 'ou-mhg'an ta na Sa-Soulat, ka lyk-kough-eih tyn æhpit ki ni-ka pa-tei-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Nda asfi-appa-nein 'ou-mhg'an ta na Sa-Soulat, ka lyk-kough-eih tyn æhpit ki ni-ka pa-tei-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Want sy en wiscen noch De Schrift niet Dat hy ban den dooden moest opstaen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">For as yet they knew not the scripture, that he must rise again from the dead.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">因為他們還不明白聖經的意思，就是耶穌必要從死裏復活。）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse10">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Anna-ta ni d'marang ta Pahtatæutæu-'han sa-lykkough mou-talagh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Anna-ta ni d'marang ta Pahtatæutæu-'han sa-lykkough mou-talagh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> De De Discipelen Dan gingen wederom na huys.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then the disciples went away again unto their own home.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">於是兩個門徒回自己的住處去了。 （太28‧9－10；可16‧9－11）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse11">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-myttouhkko ta ti Maria i-tou mala tou ravak, ka tmangi-tangi. Irou ka tmangi-tangi ni-mæ'æu-sousou ta teni tou r'avak. </FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-myttouhkko ta ti Maria i-tou mala tou ravak, ka tmangi-tangi. Irou ka tmangi-tangi ni-mæ'æu-sousou ta teni tou r'avak. </FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende Maria stont buyten by Het graf weenende Als sy Dan weende buekte sy in Het graf.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But Mary stood without at the sepulchre weeping: and as she wept, she stooped down, and looked into the sepulchre,</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">馬利亞卻站在墳墓外面哭。哭的時候，低頭往墳墓裏看，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse12">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Kani-k'yt-t-'an tyn ta ra-rouhaki Tama-Gnau tou [pa-'mmi-an ka] mapoulle, ka mier-roung ta saäsat tou voungö, sa'sat-appa tou rahpal, ki ni-atta-kou'-an ta vouel ti Jesus.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Kani-k'yt-t-'an tyn ta ra-rouhaki Tama-Gnau tou [pa-'mmi-an ka] mapoulle, ka mier-roung ta saäsat tou voungö, sa'sat-appa tou rahpal, ki ni-atta-kou'-an ta vouel ti Jesus.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende sagh twee Engelen in witte [kleederen] sitten eenen aen Het hooft en De echen den De boeten daer het lichiaem Jesu gelegen hadde.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And seeth two angels in white sitting, the one at the head, and the other at the feet, where the body of Jesus had lain.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">就見兩個天使，穿着白衣，在安放耶穌身體的地方坐着，一個在頭，一個在腳。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse13">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-k'ma ta neni tyni-æn, Ina, mang ka ta t'angit'angi-en'nhou? Ni-k'ma neini-æn: Alei ka ni-ara ta Meirang-au, ka assi-mau 'ou-mhg'an ni-matta-kounna ta neni tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-k'ma ta neni tyni-æn, Ina, mang ka ta t'angit'angi-en'nhou? Ni-k'ma neini-æn: Alei ka ni-ara ta Meirang-au, ka assi-mau 'ou-mhg'an ni-matta-kounna ta neni tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende Die seyden tot haer Drouwe wat weent ghy? Sy seyde tot haer: Om Dat sy mijnen Heere wech genomen hebben ende ick en weet Niet waer sy hem geleght hebben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And they say unto her, Woman, why weepest thou? She saith unto them, Because they have taken away my LORD, and I know not where they have laid him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">天使對她說：「婦人，你為甚麼哭？」她說：「因為有人把我主挪了去，我不知道放在哪裏。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse14">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka mattæ'i-kaha ki atta, ni-rmyd-douk ta teni mæ-'æuvering, ka ni-k'yt-t-'an tyn ta ti Jesus ka myttouhko, râ assi tyn 'ou-mh'gan ka ti Jesus ta ti anna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka mattæ'i-kaha ki atta, ni-rmyd-douk ta teni mæ-'æuvering, ka ni-k'yt-t-'an tyn ta ti Jesus ka myttouhko, râ assi tyn 'ou-mh'gan ka ti Jesus ta ti anna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende als sy dit geseght hadde keerde sy haer achterwaerts ende sagh Jesum staen ende sy en wist niet dat het Jesus was.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And when she had thus said, she turned herself back, and saw Jesus standing, and knew not that it was Jesus.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">說了這話，就轉過身來，看見耶穌站在那裏，卻不知道是耶穌。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse15">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-kma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Ina, mang tat'angit'angi-en-hou? timang ta ki'ym-men-hou? Tama-Si-rarahoul lava ni-koua tyn, ka ni-k'mata teni-tyni-æn, Meirang, hei-rou ni-mara-kow tyni-æn pou-tauwagh, vann'-ei-koh ni-matta-kounna kow tyni-æn, ka ara-au-mau ta</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-kma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Ina, mang tat'angit'angi-en-hou? timang ta ki'ym-men-hou? Tama-Si-rarahoul lava ni-koua tyn, ka ni-k'mata teni-tyni-æn, Meirang, hei-rou ni-mara-kow tyni-æn pou-tauwagh, vann'-ei-koh ni-matta-kounna kow tyni-æn, ka ara-au-mau ta</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus seyde tot haer Drouwe wat wernt ghy : Wien soeckt ghy : Sy meynende Dat Het De hobernier was seyde tot hem Heere soo ghy hem [wech] gedragen hebt seght my waer ghy hem geleght Hebt ende ick sal hem wegh nemen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Jesus saith unto her, Woman, why weepest thou? whom seekest thou? She, supposing him to be the gardener, saith unto him, Sir, if thou have borne him hence, tell me where thou hast laid him, and I will take him away.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌問她說：「婦人，為甚麼哭？你找誰呢？」馬利亞以為是看園的，就對他說：「先生，若是你把他移了去，請告訴我，你把他放在哪裏，我便去取他。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse16">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'mata ti Jesus tyni-æn, Maria. Irou ka mæ'æu-doum-ma ta teni ni-kma tyni-n, Rabbouni: ynna akoua-nnei ki fou, Tama-Mahtæutæuugh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-k'mata ti Jesus tyni-æn, Maria. Irou ka mæ'æu-doum-ma ta teni ni-kma tyni-n, Rabbouni: ynna akoua-nnei ki fou, Tama-Mahtæutæuugh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> JeJesus seyde tot haer Maria. Sy haer om keerende seyde tot hem Rabbouni het welck is geseght Meester.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Jesus saith unto her, Mary. She turned herself, and saith unto him, Rabboni; which is to say, Master.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：「馬利亞。」馬利亞就轉過來，用希伯來話對他說：「拉波尼！」（拉波尼就是夫子的意思。）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse17">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Ynn'-ei-koh smeukkla, assi-appa mau ni-sa-bavau-en tou Raram-'an-au: rȧ 'ou-koua-au ki tæ'i-appapara-au, vanna vanna neini-æn, Sa-bavau-koh tou Raram-an-au tou Raram-'an-ap-pa moumi, tou Alid-au, tou Alid-appa-moumi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Ynn'-ei-koh smeukkla, assi-appa mau ni-sa-bavau-en tou Raram-'an-au: rȧ 'ou-koua-au ki tæ'i-appapara-au, vanna vanna neini-æn, Sa-bavau-koh tou Raraman-au tou Raram-'an-ap-pa moumi, tou Alid-au, tou Alid-appa-moumi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus seyde tot Haer En raetkt my niet aen want ick en ben noch niet opgebaren tot mijnen Dader: maen gaet henen tot mijne broeders ende secht haer Ick bare op tot mijnen Dader ende uwen Dader ende [tot] mijnen Godt ende uwen Godt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Jesus saith unto her, Touch me not; for I am not yet ascended to my Father: but go to my brethren, and say unto them, I ascend unto my Father, and your Father; and to my God, and your God.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：「不要摸我，因我還沒有升上去見我的父。你往我弟兄那裏去，告訴他們說，我要升上去見我的父，也是你們的父，見我的上帝，也是你們的上帝。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse18">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Kani-mou-koua ta ti Maria Mahdalena ma-hnau ki Ph-tatæutu-han, ka ni-k'yt-t'an tyn ta Meirang, ka ni-pa-sousou-en-appa tyn ta atta tyni-n.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Kani-mou-koua ta ti Maria Mahdalena ma-hnau ki Ph-tatæutu-han, ka ni-k'yt-t'an tyn ta Meirang, ka ni-pa-sousou-en-appa tyn ta atta tyni-n.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Maria Magdalene gingh ende boodtschapte Den Discipelen Dat sy den Heere gesien hadde ende [ dat ] hy haer Dit geseght hadde.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Mary Magdalene came and told the disciples that she had seen the LORD, and that he had spoken these things unto her.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">抹大拉的馬利亞就去告訴門徒說：「我已經看見了主。」她又將主對她說的這話告訴他們。 （太28‧16－20；可16‧14－18；路24‧36－49）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse19">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka madoung-ato tou saasat ki wæ'i kanna ka naunamou ki pta ki pæ'i-habab'-an, rou ni-'illigh ta ngataf, tou ni-p-'-u-i-kla-kla'n ki Phtatæutæu-han alei ki tahkout-'n-nein ki Joden, ni-ierrouata ti Jesus myttouhko i-tou-touk kad, ka ni-k'ma neini-æn, A kou-reia ymoumi-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka madoung-ato tou saasat ki wæ'i kanna ka naunamou ki pta ki pæ'i-habab'-an, rou ni-'illigh ta ngataf, tou ni-p-'-u-i-kla-kla'n ki Phtatæutæu-han alei ki tahkout-'n-nein ki Joden, ni-ierrouata ti Jesus myttouhko i-tou-touk kad, ka ni-k'ma neini-æn, A kou-reia ymoumi-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Als Het Dan abondt was op Den selben eersten dagh der weke ende als de deuren gesloten waren daer De Discipelen bergadert waren om De breese Der Joden quam Jesus ende stondt in het midden ende seyde tot haer Drede zy u-lieden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then the same day at evening, being the first day of the week, when the doors were shut where the disciples were assembled for fear of the Jews, came Jesus and stood in the midst, and saith unto them, Peace be unto you.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那日（就是七日的第一日）晚上，門徒所在的地方，因怕猶太人，門都關了。耶穌來，站在當中，對他們說：「願你們平安！」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse20">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka mattæ'i-kaha ki atta ni-pa-k'yt-t-'an tyn neini-æn ta rimatyn ki kating-appa[tyn]. Annata ni-marei ta Pahtatæutæu-han dou k'yt-t-'an nein ta Meirang.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka mattæ'i-kaha ki atta ni-pa-k'yt-t-'an tyn neini-æn ta rimatyn ki kating-appa[tyn]. Annata ni-marei ta Pahtatæutæu-han dou k'yt-t-'an nein ta Meirang.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende Dit geseght hebbende toonde hy haer sijne handen ende [sijne] zijde. De Discipelen Dan wierden berblijdt als sy Den Heere sagen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And when he had so said, he shewed unto them his hands and his side. Then were the disciples glad, when they saw the LORD.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">說了這話，就把手和肋旁指給他們看。門徒看見主，就喜樂了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse21">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-mattæ'i-lata ti Jesus neini-æn, Akou-reia ymou-mi-æn: mama ki ni-padingi-en ki Rama jau-an, madingi-app-'oh ymoumi-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-mattæ'i-lata ti Jesus neini-æn, Akou-reia ymou-mi-æn: mama ki ni-padingi-en ki Rama jau-an, madingi-app-'oh ymoumi-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus dan seyde wederderom tot haer Drede zy ulieden : ghelijckerwijs my De Dader gesonden heeft sende ick oock u-lieden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then said Jesus to them again, Peace be unto you: as my Father hath sent me, even so send I you.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌又對他們說：「願你們平安！父怎樣差遣了我，我也照樣差遣你們。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse22">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka ni-mattæ'i-kaha ki atta ni-mi-joep ta teni, k'ma neini-æn, 'Ara-au-to ta Joep-pan ka D'lligh Matiktik.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka ni-mattæ'i-kaha ki atta ni-mi-joep ta teni, k'ma neini-æn, 'Ara-au-to ta Joep-pan ka D'lligh Matiktik.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende als hy Dit geseght hadde blies hy [op haer], ende seyde tot haer Ontfanght den heyligen Geest.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And when he had said this, he breathed on them, and saith unto them, Receive ye the Holy Ghost:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">說了這話，就向他們吹一口氣，說：「你們受聖靈！</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse23">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Namamang ka 'atta-ral-ei-moumi ta varau, 'atta-ral-eil-la-to k'anna neinï-æn: na mamang-appa ka pa-i-kakoua-ei-moumi, pa-i-koua-eil-lato kanna neini-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Namamang ka 'atta-ral-ei-moumi ta varau, 'atta-ral-eil-la-to k'anna neinï-æn: na mamang-appa ka pa-i-kakoua-ei-moumi, pa-i-koua-eil-lato kanna neini-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Soo ghy yemandts sonden bergeeft Dien worden'se bergeben : soo ghy yemandts [sonden] hondt [dien] zijn'se gehouden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Whose soever sins ye remit, they are remitted unto them; and whose soever sins ye retain, they are retained.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們赦免誰的罪，誰的罪就赦免了；你們留下誰的罪，誰的罪就留下了。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse24">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ti Thomas ka saät ki sat kyttiæn 'æb ki rouha, ka si-houa Didymus, assi i-tou-lam nei-ni-æn dou ierrou-'ato ta ti Jesus.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ti Thomas ka saät ki sat kyttiæn 'æb ki rouha, ka si-houa Didymus, assi i-tou-lam nei-ni-æn dou ierrou-'ato ta ti Jesus.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende Thomas een ban de twaelbe geseght Didymus en was met haer niet Doe Jesus [ daer ] quam.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But Thomas, one of the twelve, called Didymus, was not with them when Jesus came.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那十二個門徒中，有稱為低土馬的多馬；耶穌來的時候，他沒有和他們同在。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse25">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-k'ma tyni-æn ta Pahtatæutæu-han ka rarouma, Ni-k'yt-ta ni-en ta Meirang. Râ ni-k'ma ta teni, Hei-rou assi-koh kmytta ki na loukka ki pahou tou rima tyn, rou assi-koh toummou ki kæ'æ-mous-au tou na loukka ki pahou, t'mmou-appa ki rima-au tou kating tyn, assi-koh tna-'msing-ah.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-k'ma tyni-æn ta Pahtatæutæu-han ka rarouma, Ni-k'yt-ta ni-en ta Meirang. Râ ni-k'ma ta teni, Hei-rou assi-koh kmytta ki na loukka ki pahou tou rima tyn, rou assi-koh toummou ki kæ'æ-mous-au tou na loukka ki pahou, t'mmou-appa ki rima-au tou kating tyn, assi-koh tna-'msing-ah.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> De andere Discipelen Dan seyden tot hem Wy Hebben Den Heere ghesien Doch hy seyde tot haer Indien ick in sijne handen niet en sie Het teecken der nagelen ende mijne bingeren steke in Het teecken Der magelen ende steke mijne handt in sijne zijDe ick en sal geensins gelooben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The other disciples therefore said unto him, We have seen the LORD. But he said unto them, Except I shall see in his hands the print of the nails, and put my finger into the print of the nails, and thrust my hand into his side, I will not believe.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那些門徒就對他說：「我們已經看見主了。」多馬卻說：「我非看見他手上的釘痕，用指頭探入那釘痕，又用手探入他的肋旁，我總不信。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse26">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka si-ǣ'æugh ki kouh. yhpa ki wæ'i ǣ-i-a-rbou mi-la ta Pahtatæutæu-han, ka i-tou-lam neini-æn ta ti Thomas: ka ni-ier-roua tati Jesus rou ni-illif ta nga-taf, myttoukko i-tou toukkad, ka ni-k'ma, Akou-reia ymoumi-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka si-ǣ'æugh ki kouh. yhpa ki wæ'i ǣ-i-a-rbou mi-la ta Pahtatæutæu-han, ka i-tou-lam neini-æn ta ti Thomas: ka ni-ier-roua tati Jesus rou ni-illif ta ngataf, myttoukko i-tou toukkad, ka ni-k'ma, Akou-reia ymoumi-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende na acht dagen qaren sijne Discipelen wederom binnen ende Thomas met haer: [ende] Jesus quam als De Deuren gesloten waren ende stont in het midden. ende seyde Drede zy u-lieden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And after eight days again his disciples were within, and Thomas with them: then came Jesus, the doors being shut, and stood in the midst, and said, Peace be unto you.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">過了八日，門徒又在屋裏，多馬也和他們同在，門都關了。耶穌來，站在當中說：「願你們平安！」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse27">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Si-æ'æugh ki anna ni-k'ma ti Thomas-an, Ad-dau-'to hia ki kæ'æmous-oho, k'yt-t-'ei ta rima-au, ka ad-dau-'to ta rima oho, t'ou ou-au tou kating-au, Ka ynnâ assi tna-'msing, râ tama-tna-'msing-appa.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Si-æ'æugh ki anna ni-k'ma ti Thomas-an, Ad-dau-'to hia ki kæ'æmous-oho, k'yt-t-'ei ta rima-au, ka ad-dau-'to ta rima oho, t'ou ou-au tou kating-au, Ka ynnâ assi tna-'msing, râ tama-tna-'msing-appa.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Daer Daer nae seyde hy tot Thomam Brenght uwen binger hier ende siet Mijne banden ende blenght ue handt ende steecktse in mijne zijde Ende en zijt niet ongeloobigh maer geloobigh.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Then saith he to Thomas, Reach hither thy finger, and behold my hands; and reach hither thy hand, and thrust it into my side: and be not faithless, but believing.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">就對多馬說：「伸過你的指頭來，摸我的手；伸出你的手來，探入我的肋旁。不要疑惑，總要信！」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse28">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni mattæ'i-v'lli ta ti Thomas k'ma tyni-æn, Meirang-au, Alid-dappa-mau.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni mattæ'i-v'lli ta ti Thomas k'ma tyni-æn, Meirang-au, Alid-dappa-mau.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende Thomas antwoordde ende seyde tot hem Mijn Heere ende mijn Godt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And Thomas answered and said unto him, My LORD and my God.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">多馬說：「我的主！我的上帝！」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse29">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Alei ka ni-kmytta-kow jau-an Thomas, tna-'msing-ato kow: Tama tæ'i-riang ta assi ni kmytta, ka tna-'msing-al-ato.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Alei ka ni-kmytta-kow jau-an Thomas, tna-'msing-ato kow: Tama tæ'i-riang ta assi ni kmytta, ka tna-'msing-al-ato.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus seyde tot hem Om dat ghy my gesien Hebt Thoma so hebt ghy gelooft: Saligh [sijnse] die niet en sul= len gesien hebben ende [nochtans] sullen gelooft Hebben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Jesus saith unto him, Thomas, because thou hast seen me, thou hast believed: blessed are they that have not seen, and yet have believed.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌對他說：「你因看見了我才信；那沒有看見就信的有福了。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse30">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Madagh-appa ki na pou-kakidi ka pani ta ni pam't-ten ti Jesus tou æ-i-a-kou'-an ki Pahtatæutæu-han tyn, ka assi ni-s'oulat-tin tou soulat katta.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Madagh-appa ki na pou-kakidi ka pani ta ni pam't-ten ti Jesus tou æ-i-a-kou'-an ki Pahtatæutæu-han tyn, ka assi ni-s'oulat-tin tou soulat katta.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus Dan heeft noch wel beel andere teekenen in de tegenwoordigheyt sijner Discipelen gedaen die niet en zijn geschreben in Dit boeck.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">And many other signs truly did Jesus in the presence of his disciples, which are not written in this book:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌在門徒面前另外行了許多神蹟，沒有記在這書上。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse31">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Râ ni s'oulat-tin ta ma-mang k'atta, alei ka tna-'msing-ah-kamou ka ti Jesus ta ti Christus, Alak ki Alid, ka rou tna-'msing-kamou ka akoume'-ah-ka-mou ki kæu-æ-han tou Nanang tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Râ ni s'oulat-tin ta ma-mang k'atta, alei ka tna-'msing-ah-kamou ka ti Jesus ta ti Christus, Alak ki Alid, ka rou tna-'msing-kamou ka akoume'-ah-ka-mou ki kæu-æ-han tou Nanang tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Maer Dese zijn geschreben op Dat ghy geloobet dat Jesus is de Christus de Sone Gods ende op Dat ghy ge: loobende Het leben hebbet in sijnen Name. Het een-en-twintig ste Capittel.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But these are written, that ye might believe that Jesus is the Christ, the Son of God; and that believing ye might have life through his name.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">但記這些事要叫你們信耶穌是基督，是上帝的兒子，並且叫你們信了他，就可以因他的名得生命。</TRANSL>
    </S>
</TEXT>