<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEXT id="Siraya_Dutch_John_Chapter13" xml:lang="fos" source="Siraya Bible, John gospel" copyright="public domain" citation="Gravius, Daniël. 1661. Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa. Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang. Amsterdam: Michiel Hartogh." BibTeX_citation="@book{Gravius1661,&#10;  author    = {Gravius, Daniël},&#10;  year      = {1661},&#10;  title     = {Het Heylige Evangelium Matthei en Johannis ofte Hagnau Ka D'llig Matiktik. Ka na sasoulat ti Mattheus, ti Johannes appa},&#10;  note      = {Overgeset inde Formosaansche tale, voor de Inwoonders van Soulang, Mattau, Sinckan, Bacloan, Tavocan en Tevorang},&#10;  address   = {Amsterdam},&#10;  publisher = {Michiel Hartogh}&#10;}">
    <S id="verse1">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka tou ourou ki'Ou-vava-toug-han ki Hali-da eu-an, irou kavana-'an ti Jesus ka ierrou-âto ta kidi ki tæ'lei tyn, ki sah-tounnoun-eih tyn tou næi k'atta mou-koua ti Rama-an, ma-ma ki ni-kavæ'angö-en tyn ta a teni ka æ-i-a næy, komma-hynna ni-kavæ angö-en tyn neini-æn tou kidi ki lymmou lymmou.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka tou ourou ki'Ou-vava-toug-han ki Hali-da eu-an, irou kavana-'an ti Jesus ka ierrou-âto ta kidi ki tæ'lei tyn, ki sah-tounnoun-eih tyn tou næi k'atta mou-koua ti Rama-an, ma-ma ki ni-kavæ'angö-en tyn ta a teni ka æ-i-a næy, komma-hynna ni-kavæ angö-en tyn neini-æn tou kidi ki lymmou lymmou.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende boor het Feest ban Pascha Jesus wetende Dat sijne uyre gekomen was dat hy uyt dese wereldt soude obergaen tot den Dader alsoo hy De sijne Die in de wereldt waren lief gehadt hadde soo heeft hyse lief gehadt tot den eynde.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Now before the feast of the passover, when Jesus knew that his hour was come that he should depart out of this world unto the Father, having loved his own which were in the world, he loved them unto the end.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">逾越節以前，耶穌知道自己離世歸父的時候到了。他既然愛世間屬自己的人，就愛他們到底。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse2">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka'i-kah-'an ta Hiaddoudoung-en (dou ni-pou-raryh ta Littou tou tintin ti Judas ka ti Simon Iskariot ki si-vanna vann'-eih tyn tyni-æn)</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka'i-kah-'an ta Hiaddoudoung-en (dou ni-pou-raryh ta Littou tou tintin ti Judas ka ti Simon Iskariot ki si-vanna vann'-eih tyn tyni-æn)</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende als het Abondtmael gedaen Mas (Doe nu De Duybel in Het herte ban Judas Simonis A Istariot gegeben hadde Dat hy hem berraden soude)</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And supper being ended, the devil having now put into the heart of Judas Iscariot, Simon's son, to betray him;</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">吃晚飯的時候，魔鬼已將賣耶穌的意思放在西門的兒子加略人猶大心裏。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse3">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Dou kavana-an ti Jesus ka ni-pæ'ǣ-ymd-den ta mamang pi'ǣ ki Rama tou rima tyni-en, ka ni-pakka-kou-'an tyn ki Alid, ka mi-likough-âl-appa mou-koua ki Alid,</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Dou kavana-an ti Jesus ka ni-pæ'ǣ-ymd-den ta mamang pi'ǣ ki Rama tou rima tyni-en, ka ni-pakka-kou-'an tyn ki Alid, ka mi-likough-âl-appa mou-koua ki Alid,</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus wetende dat De Dader Hem alle dinghen in de han den gegeben hadde enDe Dat hy ban Godt uyt gegaen was ende tot Godt hemen gingh </TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus knowing that the Father had given all things into his hands, and that he was come from God, and went to God;</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌知道父已將萬有交在他手裏，且知道自己是從上帝出來的，又要歸到上帝那裏去，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse4">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-æhpit ki ni-Hiaddoudoung-en, ka ni-tmoura ki kou-lamogh [tyn,] ka dou ara tyn ta äit, ni-mäit tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-æhpit ki ni-Hiaddoudoung-en, ka ni-tmoura ki kou-lamogh [tyn,] ka dou ara tyn ta äit, ni-mäit tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Stont op ban het Abondtmael endeleyde [sijne] kleederen af ende nemende eenen lijnen Doeck omgordde Hem selben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">He riseth from supper, and laid aside his garments; and took a towel, and girded himself.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">就離席站起來，脫了衣服，拿一條手巾束腰，</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse5">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Si-ǣæug ki anna ni-roudou-en tyn ta raloum tou' padadiei-en; ka ni-madiei ki rahpal ki Pah-tatæu tæu-han, ka ni-rihkagh-appa ki ait ka ht-tæn tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Si-ǣæug ki anna ni-roudou-en tyn ta raloum tou' padadiei-en; ka ni-madiei ki rahpal ki Pah-tatæu tæu-han, ka ni-rihkagh-appa ki ait ka ht-tæn tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Daer nae goot hy water in het becken ende begon De boeten Der Discipelen te wasschen ende af te broogen met met den lijnen doeck daer mede hy omngordt Was.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">After that he poureth water into a bason, and began to wash the disciples' feet, and to wipe them with the towel wherewith he was girded.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">隨後把水倒在盆裏，就洗門徒的腳，並用自己所束的手巾擦乾。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse6">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Annata ni-mou-koua ti Simon Petrus-an, ka teni ta ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Meirang, padiei-ei-'mhou kauwa ta rahpal-au?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Annata ni-mou-koua ti Simon Petrus-an, ka teni ta ni-k'ma tyni-æn, Meirang, padiei-ei-'mhou kauwa ta rahpal-au?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Hy dan quam tot Simon Petrus ende die seyde tot hem heere sult Ghy my De boeten wasschen ?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then cometh he to Simon Peter: and Peter saith unto him, Lord, dost thou wash my feet?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">挨到西門‧彼得，彼得對他說：「主啊，你洗我的腳嗎？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse7">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-matuK'i-v'llita ti Jesus k'ma tyni-æn, Assi-kow mou-mhga hnyn ta ryngei-au, ri mou-mhga-ah-kow rourouman.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-matuK'i-v'llita ti Jesus k'ma tyni-æn, Assi-kow mou-mhga hnyn ta ryngei-au, ri mou-mhga-ah-kow rourouman.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus antwoordde en seyde tot hem Dat ick Doe en Weet ghy Nu niet Maer ghy sult het na de sen berstaen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus answered and said unto him, What I do thou knowest not now; but thou shalt know hereafter.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌回答說：「我所做的，你如今不知道，後來必明白。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse8">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'ma tati Petrus tyni-n, Assi kowmadi ei-a' ki rahpal-au-tou yhkakouan myddaryn nough. Ni-matt'i-v'lli ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Heirou assi-koh ma-diei ymhou-an, a'ou-si-ah kow ki ætæh lam jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-k'ma tati Petrus tyni-n, Assi kowmadi ei-a' ki rahpal-au-tou yhkakouan myddaryn nough. Ni-matt'i-v'lli ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Heirou assi-koh ma-diei ymhou-an, a'ou-si-ah kow ki ætæh lam jau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Petrus seyde tot hem Ghy en sult mijne boeten niet wasschen in Der eeuwigheyt Jesus antwoordde hem InDien ick u niet en wassche ghy en Hebt geen deel met my.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Peter saith unto him, Thou shalt never wash my feet. Jesus answered him, If I wash thee not, thou hast no part with me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">彼得說：「你永不可洗我的腳！」耶穌說：「我若不洗你，你就與我無分了。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse9">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'ma ta ti Simon Petrus tyni-æn, Meirang, assi dyk ki rahpal-au, ra ki rimaki voungo-appa.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-k'ma ta ti Simon Petrus tyni-æn, Meirang, assi dyk ki rahpal-au, ra ki rimaki voungo-appa.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Simon Petrus seyde tot hem Heere niet alleen mijne boeten maer oock De handen ende het Hooft.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Simon Peter saith unto him, Lord, not my feet only, but also my hands and my head.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">西門‧彼得說：「主啊，不但我的腳，連手和頭也要洗。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse10">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Ti mamang ta ni-i-æug assi mæ-i-ææpo dyk ki padiei-en ki-rahpal:rA ma-tmouk-ato makoup-tigh. Ka makouptig-kamou, rs assi ma-ymmid.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Ti mamang ta ni-i-æug assi mæ-i-ææpo dyk ki padiei-en ki-rahpal:rA ma-tmouk-ato makoup-tigh. Ka makouptig-kamou, rs assi ma-ymmid.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus seyde tot hem Die gewasschen is en Heeft niet ban noode Dan De boeten te wasschen maer is geheel reyn. Ende ghy-lieden zijt reyn doch niet alle.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus saith to him, He that is washed needeth not save to wash his feet, but is clean every whit: and ye are clean, but not all.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：「凡洗過澡的人，只要把腳一洗，全身就乾淨了。你們是乾淨的，然而不都是乾淨的。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse11">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Kakavana-an tyn ti-mang ta fsi-vanna vanna-ah tyni-æn: alei ki anna ka koun tyn, A ssi-ka-mou ma-ymmid makouptigh.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Kakavana-an tyn ti-mang ta fsi-vanna vanna-ah tyni-æn: alei ki anna ka koun tyn, A ssi-ka-mou ma-ymmid makouptigh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Want hy wist wie hem berraden soude : daerom seyde hy Ghy en zijt niet alle reyn.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">For he knew who should betray him; therefore said he, Ye are not all clean.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌原知道要賣他的是誰，所以說：「你們不都是乾淨的。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse12">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka ni-madiei-ato ki rahpal nein, ka rou ni-alykkoug ki pammammi-æn tyn, ni-mila mierroung tou avok-kan,' ka ni-k'ma neini-æn, Mou-mhga-ka-mou kauwa ki na ryngei-au ymoumi-æn?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka ni-madiei-ato ki rahpal nein, ka rou ni-alykkoug ki pammammi-æn tyn, ni-mila mierroung tou avok-kan,' ka ni-k'ma neini-æn, Mou-mhga-ka-mou kauwa ki na ryngei-au ymoumi-æn?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Als hy dan hare boeten gewasschen ende sijne klederen genomen hadde sat hy wederom aen ende seyde tottot haer Derstaet ghy wat ick u-lieden gedaen hebbe?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">So after he had washed their feet, and had taken his garments, and was set down again, he said unto them, Know ye what I have done to you?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌洗完了他們的腳，就穿上衣服，又坐下，對他們說：「我向你們所做的，你們明白嗎？</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse13">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Mananang-kamou jau-an Mahtæutæuugh ki Meirang-appa, ka mariang-kamou kisou: alei ka ti jau k'anna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Mananang-kamou jau-an Mahtæutæuugh ki Meirang-appa, ka mariang-kamou kisou: alei ka ti jau k'anna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ghy heet my Meester ende Heere ende ghy seght wel :want ick ben't</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Ye call me Master and Lord: and ye say well; for so I am.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們稱呼我夫子，稱呼我主，你們說的不錯，我本來是。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse14">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Heirou ka ni-madiei-koh ti jau ka Meirang ki Mahtatæu-tæuugh-appa ki rahpal oumi, an-nata kidi-ato ka pati-tavætavæh-ei-moumi madiei ta rahpahpal-oumi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Heirou ka ni-madiei-koh ti jau ka Meirang ki Mahtatæu-tæuugh-appa ki rahpal oumi, annata kidi-ato ka pati-tavætavæh-ei-moumi madiei ta rahpahpal-oumi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Indien dan ick De Heere ende De Meester uwe boeten gewasschen hebbe soo zijt ghy oock schuldigh malkanders boeten te wasschen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">If I then, your Lord and Master, have washed your feet; ye also ought to wash one another's feet.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我是你們的主，你們的夫子，尚且洗你們的腳，你們也當彼此洗腳。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse15">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-papei-kounnoung-en-nau-kamou-ra, mama ka ni-pam't-en-nau, ka mei-komma-ah-kamou hynna ta ymoumi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-papei-kounnoung-en-nau-kamou-ra, mama ka ni-pam't-en-nau, ka mei-komma-ah-kamou hynna ta ymoumi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Want ick hebbe u een erempel gegeben Op Dat gelijcker wijs ick u gedaen hebbe ghy-lieden oock Doet.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">For I have given you an example, that ye should do as I have done to you.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我給你們作了榜樣，叫你們照着我向你們所做的去做。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse16">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Missing, missing koun-nau-kamou, Assi masaoun tou va-vau ki kidi ta koungcia ki Mei-rang tyn, assi masaoun tou vavau-ki kidi ta ni-padadingi-en ki ni-madingi tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Missing, missing koun-nau-kamou, Assi masaoun tou vavau ki kidi ta koungcia ki Mei-rang tyn, assi masaoun tou vavau-ki kidi ta ni-padadingi-en ki ni-madingi tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Doorwaer boorwaer segge ick u Eendienst-knecht en is niet meerder Dan sijn geere noch een gesante meerder Dan Die Hem gesonden heeft.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ick en segghe niet ban u allen : ick weet welcke ick uytberkooren hebbe : maer [dit geschiedt] op Dat De Schrift berbult werde Die met my het broodt eet beeft tegen my sijn berssen opgeheben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Verily, verily, I say unto you, The servant is not greater than his lord; neither he that is sent greater than he that sent him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我實實在在地告訴你們，僕人不能大於主人，差人也不能大於差他的人。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse17">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Heirou mavana-kamou ki mamang katta, tama-tæ'i-riang-kamou rou pam't-ten-oumi ta atta.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Heirou mavana-kamou ki mamang katta, tama-tæ'i-riang-kamou rou pam't-ten-oumi ta atta.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Indien ghy dese dins ghen weet saligh zijt ghy soo ghy de selbe Doet.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">If ye know these things, happy are ye if ye do them.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們既知道這事，若是去行就有福了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse18">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Assi-koh mattæ'i-sal ymou-mi-æn: kavana-en-nau na ma-mang ta ni-peri-au: ra alei-appa ka pavæut-auh ta na Sasoulat, Teni ka mi-lam ki paoul jau-an, ni-p'lleiki ngouro tyn. mæ'æu-doumma jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Assi-koh mattæ'i-sal ymou-mi-æn: kavana-en-nau na ma-mang ta ni-peri-au: ra alei-appa ka pavæut-auh ta na Sasoulat, Teni ka mi-lam ki paoul jau-an, ni-p'lleiki ngouro tyn. mæ'æu-doumma jau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">I speak not of you all: I know whom I have chosen: but that the scripture may be fulfilled, He that eateth bread with me hath lifted up his heel against me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我這話不是指着你們眾人說的，我知道我所揀選的是誰。現在要應驗經上的話，說：『同我吃飯的人用腳踢我。』</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse19">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Vannavanna-en-nau-ka-mou hnyn, rou assi appa pa-væut tin, alei ka rou ni-pavut-ato, ka tna-'msing-ah-kamou ka ti jau kanna.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Vannavanna-en-nau-ka-mou hnyn, rou assi appa pa-væut tin, alei ka rou ni-pavut-ato, ka tna-'msing-ah-kamou ka ti jau kanna.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Dan Dan nu segghe ick het u-lieden eer het geschiet is op Dat wanneer het gefchiet sal zijn ghy gelooben meunght Dat ick het ben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Now I tell you before it come, that, when it is come to pass, ye may believe that I am he.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">如今事情還沒有成就，我要先告訴你們，叫你們到事情成就的時候可以信我是基督。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse20">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Missing, missing koun-nau-kamou-ra, Heirou pahyh tatalaghta ti mamangki padadin-gi-en-nau, tenita pa-yhtatalagh jau-an, ti mamamang-appa ta pa-yhtatalaghj jau-an, tenita pa-yh-tatalagh tyni-æn ka ni-madingi jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Missing, missing koun-nau-kamou-ra, Heirou pahyh tatalaghta ti mamangki padadin-gi-en-nau, tenita pa-yhtatalagh jau-an, ti mamamang-appa ta pa-yhtatalaghj jau-an, tenita pa-yh-tatalagh tyni-æn ka ni-madingi jau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Doorwaer boorwaer segge ick u Soo ick yemandt sende wie [dien] ontsanght Die onsanght my ende wie my ontsanght die obtsanght hem Die my gesonden Heeft.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Verily, verily, I say unto you, He that receiveth whomsoever I send receiveth me; and he that receiveth me receiveth him that sent me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我實實在在地告訴你們，有人接待我所差遣的，就是接待我；接待我，就是接待那差遣我的。」 （太26‧20－25；可14‧17－21；路22‧21－23）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse21">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka mattæ'i-kaha ta ti Jesus ki mamang k'atta, mierin-gau-ato ki voulas tou ryh tyn ,ka ni-gmail mattæ'i-æmah, ka ni koun tyn, Missing, missing koun-nau-kamou, sa'sat ymoumi-n ta si-vanna vanna-ah jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka mattæ'i-kaha ta ti Jesus ki mamang k'atta, mierin-gau-ato ki voulas tou ryh tyn ,ka ni-gmail mattæ'i-æmah, ka ni koun tyn, Missing, missing koun-nau-kamou, sa'sat ymoumi-n ta si-vanna vanna-ah jau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus dese dingen geseght hebbende wierdt ontroert in Den geest ende betuyghde ende seyde Doorwaer boorwaer segghe ick u dat een ban u-lieden my sal berraden.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">When Jesus had thus said, he was troubled in spirit, and testified, and said, Verily, verily, I say unto you, that one of you shall betray me.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說了這話，心裏憂愁，就明說：「我實實在在地告訴你們，你們中間有一個人要賣我了。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse22">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Anna ta ni-mæsæ'-tati-migh ta Pæhtatæutu-han, pæh-dælæh timang lava ta pattæ'i mymmymi'-'n tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Anna ta ni-mæsæ'-tati-migh ta Pæhtatæutu-han, pæh-dælæh timang lava ta pattæ'i mymmymi'-'n tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> De Discipulen Dan sagen op malkanderen twij= selede ban wien Hy [dat] seyde.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Then the disciples looked one on another, doubting of whom he spake.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">門徒彼此對看，猜不透所說的是誰。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse23">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka sasat ki Pæhtatæutæu-han tyn ta ni-ghunni ki voungo tou æ-'iava ti Jefuus ka kavæ'ango-enti Jesus.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka sasat ki Pæhtatæutæu-han tyn ta ni-ghunni ki voungo tou æ-'iava ti Jefuus ka kavæ'ango-enti Jesus.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende een ban sijne Discipulen Was aensittende in Den schoot Jesu welcken Jesus lief hadde.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Now there was leaning on Jesus' bosom one of his disciples, whom Jesus loved.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">有一個門徒，是耶穌所愛的，側身挨近耶穌的懷裏。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse24">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Tenitati-'k-patten ti Si-mon Petrus ka tetalyg-auh tyn, ti mang lava' ta ni-patt'æ'i-mym-mia tyn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Tenitati-'k-patten ti Simon Petrus ka tetalyg-auh tyn, ti mang lava' ta ni-patt'æ'i-mym-mia tyn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Simon Petrus Dan wenckte desen dat hy bragen soude wie hy Doch ware van welcken hy [dit] seyde.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Simon Peter therefore beckoned to him, that he should ask who it should be of whom he spake.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">西門‧彼得點頭對他說：「你告訴我們，主是指着誰說的。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse25">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Kateni kanna ta ni-ghun-ni tou av'u ti Jesus k'ma tyni-æn, Meirang, ti mang tateni k'anna?</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Kateni kanna ta ni-ghun-ni tou av'u ti Jesus k'ma tyni-æn, Meirang, ti mang tateni k'anna?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende dese ballende an De borst Jesu seyde tot hem Heere wie is't:</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">He then lying on Jesus' breast saith unto him, Lord, who is it?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">那門徒便就勢靠着耶穌的胸膛，問他說：「主啊，是誰呢？」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse26">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta ti Jesus, Teni ta ti anna ka phǣ-ei-mau ki na pi ka na d'adauk-k'au: Irou ka ni-dadauk tyn ta na pi, ni-phæn tyn ti Judas-an ka ti Simon Iskariot.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta ti Jesus, Teni ta ti anna ka phǣ-ei-mau ki na pi ka na d'adauk-k'au: Irou ka ni-dadauk tyn ta na pi, ni-phæn tyn ti Judas-an ka ti Simon Iskariot.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Je. Jesus antwoordde Dese is't dien ick De bete als ickse ingedoopt hebbe geben sal: Ende als hy De bete ingedoopt hadde gaf hyse Jude Simonis Iscariot.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus answered, He it is, to whom I shall give a sop, when I have dipped it. And when he had dipped the sop, he gave it to Judas Iscariot, the son of Simon.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌回答說：「我蘸一點餅給誰，就是誰。」耶穌就蘸了一點餅，遞給加略人西門的兒子猶大。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse27">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Karou ni-'ara tyn tana pi k'anna, ni-sa-ra rbou ta Littou ty-ni-æn. Annata ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Kamamang ka pam't-ei-mhou mei-dyss-â.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Karou ni-'ara tyn tana pi k'anna, ni-sa-ra rbou ta Littou ty-ni-æn. Annata ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Kamamang ka pam't-ei-mhou mei-dyss-â.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende na De bete Doe boer De Satan in hem. Jesus Dan seyde tot hem. Dat ghy Doet Doet Het haestelick</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">And after the sop Satan entered into him. Then said Jesus unto him, That thou doest, do quickly.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他吃了以後，撒但就入了他的心。耶穌便對他說：「你所做的，快做吧！」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse28">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka assi mou mhga ki atta ta ti mamang neini-æn ka mie-roung hynna, alei kimang ka pa-sousou-en tyn [ta atta] tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka assi mou mhga ki atta ta ti mamang neini-æn ka mie-roung hynna, alei kimang ka pa-sousou-en tyn [ta atta] tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Ende dit en berstandt miemandt der gene Die aen saten waer toe hy hem [dat] seyde.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Now no man at the table knew for what intent he spake this unto him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">同席的人沒有一個知道是為甚麼對他說這話。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse29">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ka ni-pæhdimdim ta ra-rouma, alei ka mei-pauti ta ti Judas, ka pa-sousou-en ti Jesus tyni-æn, Peila-auto ki mǣ-iææpo-kyt-ta tou 'Ou-vavatoug-han, ka pi'æ-âl-ato lava ta teni ki-ma-mang ki malymmouk.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ka ni-pæhdimdim ta ra-rouma, alei ka mei-pauti ta ti Judas, ka pa-sousou-en ti Jesus tyni-æn, Peila-auto ki mǣ-iææpo-kyt-ta tou 'Ou-vavatoug-han, ka pi'æ-âl-ato lava ta teni ki-ma-mang ki malymmouk.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Want sommige meynden Dewijle Judas De burse hadde dat hem Jesus seyde Koopt het ghene wy ban nooDe Hebben tot het Feest ofte dat hy Den armen wat geben soude.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">For some of them thought, because Judas had the bag, that Jesus had said unto him, Buy those things that we have need of against the feast; or, that he should give something to the poor.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">有人因猶大帶着錢囊，以為耶穌是對他說：「你去買我們過節所應用的東西」，或是叫他拿甚麼賙濟窮人。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse30">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka ni-'ara tyn ta na pi k'anna ni-madys sa-mamala. Ka euvænnæn ta kidi.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka ni-'ara tyn ta na pi k'anna ni-madys sa-mamala. Ka euvænnæn ta kidi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld">. Hy dan de bete genomen hebbende ging terstont uyt. Ende het was nacht.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">He then having received the sop went immediately out: and it was night.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">猶大受了那點餅，立刻就出去。那時候是夜間了。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse31">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Irou ka ni-sa-mamala ta te-ni, ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus, Pou-vavau-en-ato hnyn ki kidi ta Alak ki kæ-euloung, ka pou-vavau-in-nappa ki kidi ta Alid tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Irou ka ni-sa-mamala ta te-ni, ni-k'ma ta ti Jesus, Pou-vavau-en-ato hnyn ki kidi ta Alak ki kæ-euloung, ka pou-vavau-in-nappa ki kidi ta Alid tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Als hy Dan uytgegaen was seyde Jesus. Nu is De Sone des menschen berheerlickt ende Godt is in hem berheerlickt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Therefore, when he was gone out, Jesus said, Now is the Son of man glorified, and God is glorified in him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">他既出去，耶穌就說：「如今人子得了榮耀，上帝在人子身上也得了榮耀。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse32">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Heirou ni-pou-vavau-in ki kidi ta Alid tyni-æn pouvavau-âl-appa ki kidi tyni-æn, ta Alid ty-ni-æn mamadou, ka pou-dis-ah pouvavau ki kidi tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Heirou ni-pou-vavau-in ki kidi ta Alid tyni-æn pouvavau-âl-appa ki kidi tyni-æn, ta Alid ty-ni-æn mamadou, ka pou-dis-ah pouvavau ki kidi tyni-æn.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Indien Godt in hem berheerlickt is soo sal ook Godt Hem berheerlicken in hem selben ende hy sal hem terst ont berherlicken.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">If God be glorified in him, God shall also glorify him in himself, and shall straightway glorify him.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">上帝要因自己榮耀人子，並且要快快地榮耀他。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse33">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Kallalak, assi madallia ka æ-i-a-lam-app-'oh  ymoumiæn. Kmi'ym-ah-kamou jau-an ka ma-ma ki ni-pa-sousou-en-nau ki Joden, Tou sah-ka-koua-ei-mau assi-kamou malpougah ierroua, mat-ti[komma-hynna]-app'oh hnyn ymoumi-n.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Kallalak, assi madallia ka æ-i-a-lam-app-'oh  ymoumiæn. Kmi'ym-ah-kamou jau-an ka ma-ma ki ni-pa-sousou-en-nau ki Joden, Tou sah-ka-koua-ei-mau assi-kamou malpougah ierroua, mat-ti[komma-hynna]-app'oh hnyn ymoumi-n.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> KinKinderkens noch eenen kleynen [tijdt] ben ick by u. Ghy sult my soecken ende gheliick ick Den Joden geseght hebbe Daer ick henen gae en kondt ghy niet Komen [alsoo] segge ick u-lieden nu oock.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Little children, yet a little while I am with you. Ye shall seek me: and as I said unto the Jews, Whither I go, ye cannot come; so now I say to you.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">小子們，我還有不多的時候與你們同在；後來你們要找我，但我所去的地方你們不能到。這話我曾對猶太人說過，如今也照樣對你們說。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse34">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Væ'æu ki pahkou-sasou ta pæpæ-au ymoumi-æn, ka makka-nænædo-ah-kamou makka-va-væ'ings. Mama ki ni kavæ'æn-go-en-nau ymousmi-æn, ka mak-ka naneds-ah kamo komma-hynna makka-væve'angs.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Væ'æu ki pahkou-sasou ta pæpæ-au ymoumi-æn, ka makka-nænædo-ah-kamou makka-va-væ'ings. Mama ki ni kavæ'æn-go-en-nau ymousmi-æn, ka makka naneds-ah kamo komma-hynna makka-væve'angs.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Een nieuw gebodt gebe ick u dat ghy malkanderen lief hebt. Geliick ick u lief ghehadt hebbe Dat oock ghy malkanderen lief hebt.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">A new commandment I give unto you, That ye love one another; as I have loved you, that ye also love one another.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">我賜給你們一條新命令，乃是叫你們彼此相愛；我怎樣愛你們，你們也要怎樣相愛。</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse35">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Tou atta k-'ym'd-dah ta neni kmalang, ka Pahta tæutæu-en-nau-kamou ta ymoumi, dou makka-nænædo-kamou makka-vævæ'ango.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Tou atta k-'ym'd-dah ta neni kmalang, ka Pahta tæutæu-en-nau-kamou ta ymoumi, dou makka-nænædo-kamou makka-vævæ'ango.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Hier aen sullen sy alle bekennen dat ghy mijne Discipelen zijt soo ghy liefde hebt onder malkanderen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">By this shall all men know that ye are my disciples, if ye have love one to another.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">你們若有彼此相愛的心，眾人因此就認出你們是我的門徒了。」 （太26‧ 31 －35；可14‧27 －31；路22‧31－34）</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse36">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'mata ti Simon Petrus tyni-æn, Meirang, 'marang-ah-kow mou-koua tou-mang? Ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Tou sah-kakoua-ei-mau, assi-kow smala-lpough hnyn smala-dyllough jau-an: ra smala-dyl-lough-ah-kow dou rouman.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-k'mata ti Simon Petrus tyni-æn, Meirang, 'marang-ah-kow mou-koua tou-mang? Ni-mattæ'i-v'lli ta ti Jesus tyni-æn, Tou sah-kakoua-ei-mau, assi-kow smala-lpough hnyn smala-dyllough jau-an: ra smala-dyl-lough-ah-kow dou rouman.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Simon Petrus seyDe tot hem Heere waer gaet ghy henen : Jesus antwoordde hem Daer ick henen gae en kont ghy my nu niet bolghen : maer ghy sult my na= maels bolgen.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Simon Peter said unto him, Lord, whither goest thou? Jesus answered him, Whither I go, thou canst not follow me now; but thou shalt follow me afterwards.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">西門‧彼得問耶穌說：「主往哪裏去？」耶穌回答說：「我所去的地方，你現在不能跟我去，後來卻要跟我去。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse37">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-k'mata ti Petrus tyni-æn, Meirang, ka-oumang ka assi-koh smala-lpough hnyn ima-la 'dyllough ymhou-an? Pou-koua-ah-koh pou-v'lli ymhou-an ki k'uag-han-au.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-k'mata ti Petrus tyni-æn, Meirang, ka-oumang ka assi-koh smala-lpough hnyn ima-la 'dyllough ymhou-an? Pou-koua-ah-koh pou-v'lli ymhou-an ki k'uag-han-au.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Petrus seyde tot hem Heere waerom en kan ick u nu niet bolgen : Ick sal mijn leben boor u setten.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Peter said unto him, Lord, why cannot I follow thee now? I will lay down my life for thy sake.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">彼得說：「主啊，我為甚麼現在不能跟你去？我願意為你捨命！」</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="verse38">
        <FORM kindOf="original">Ni-mattæ'i-v'lli tati Jesus tyni-æn, Pou-koua-ei-mhou kau-wa pou-b'lli jauan ta kæuag-han hou? Missing, missing koun-nau-kow, assi mouni-ah ta taoukka kou assi kow't-touroul-ato rmau jau-an.</FORM>
        <FORM kindOf="standard">Ni-mattæ'i-v'lli tati Jesus tyni-æn, Pou-koua-ei-mhou kau-wa pou-b'lli jauan ta kæuag-han hou? Missing, missing koun-nau-kow, assi mouni-ah ta taoukka kou assi kow't-touroul-ato rmau jau-an.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="nld"> Jesus antwoordde hem hem Sult ghy u leben boor my setten : Doorwaer boorwaer segge ick u De haen en sal niet kraeyem tot Dat ghy my driemael berloochent sult hebben.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="eng">Jesus answered him, Wilt thou lay down thy life for my sake? Verily, verily, I say unto thee, The cock shall not crow, till thou hast denied me thrice.</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zho">耶穌說：「你願意為我捨命嗎？我實實在在地告訴你，雞叫以先，你要三次不認我。」</TRANSL>
    </S>
</TEXT>