<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="nipaluma-sumanahay_tana,_somanahay_tana" source="Wikipedia">
  <S> sumanahay tana, somanahay tana 

(:)

kagak kakunizasubal: Eukaryota
salaedan: Plantae
panan: Magnoliophyta
upiz: Magnoliopsida
mata:Sapindales
sapamat:Rutaceae
mikitinay:Zanthoxylum
hicahicaay:Z. ailanthoides

u siwkay nu nipaluma
u sanek nu nipaluma
malaheci tu imelang
pasubana i cacudadan a lacul
u zuma a cidekay a kamu, saungay misapayu' a cidekay
u sulit nu zuma a kamu-Hulam atu Amilika
&quot;&quot;30-80６-12&quot;&quot;0.5-0.6
Zanthoxylum ailanthoides, also called ailanthus-like prickly ash, (Chinese: ; pinyin: chun ye hua jiao, lit. &quot;Ailanthus-leaved pepper&quot;, Chinese: ; pinyin: yue-jiao; Wade-Giles: yüeh-chiao, lit. &quot;Yue pepper&quot;,  shi zhu yu, lit. &quot;edible shān zhū yú&quot;; Japanese: ,  karasu-zanshō, karasu-no-sanshō, lit. &quot;crow prickly ash&quot;) is an Asiatic plant of the prickly-ash genus Zanthoxylum, natively occurring in forest-covered parts of southeastern China, Taiwan, Southeast Asia, and Japan from Honshu southward. The piquant fruit serves as a local &quot;substitute for the ordinary red-pepper&quot; in China. In Taiwan, the young leaves are used in cuisines.
Though some refer to the species as &quot;Japanese prickly-ash&quot;, that name is confusing since it is sometimes applied to the sanshōwhich is Z. piperitum. Z. ailanthoides is not normally exploited for human consumption in Japan, unless you count the prehistoric people from the Jōmon period. It is foraged in the wild by the Japanese macaque.
A regional nickname is tara, and in fact, its young shoots are often mistaken for the true tara (Aralia elata) by gatherers of wild plants. The Latin name ailanthoides of the species comes from its leaves resembling those of the Ailanthus.
Like other genera of plants in the rue family, it serves as the host food plant for the larvae of several Asian swallowtail butterflyspecies, such as Papilio bianor, Papilio helenus, Papilio protenor, and Papilio xuthus.

</S>
</TEXT>
