<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT xml:lang="33_taroko." source="33_Taroko">
    <S id="0">
        <FORM>prajing ta matas do, mtmay ruwan ptasan ka mtgsa,rmngaw ka mdudul, “Hiyug! Thmuku!”</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">上課了，老師走進教室，班長說:「起立!敬禮!」</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">It’s time for class , the teacher walked into the classroom, and the monitor said: “Stand up! Salute!”</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="1">
        <FORM>Paru hnang nami rmngaw, “mtgsa, embiyax su hug.”</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我們大聲的說:「老師好。」</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">We said loudly, “Hi, teacher.”</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="2">
        <FORM>Matas siida o, tmgsa mnan sspug kari Truku ka mtgsa.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">上課的時候，老師教我們數字的族語。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">In class, the teacher taught us the Truku language of numbers.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="3">
        <FORM>Smnegul nami mtgsa smpug, muyas nami uyas sspug.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我們跟著老師唸，我們唱了數字歌。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">We followed the teacher to read, we sang the number song.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="4">
        <FORM>Smluhay ku lala bi ka kari ta Truku.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我學會好多族語。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I have learned many Truku languages.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="5">
        <FORM>Musa ku matas kdjiyax, smluhay ku kari ta Truku kdjiyax, rrngaw mu ni pqbhangun mu bubu.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我天天上學，我天天學族語，我要講給媽媽聽。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I go to school every day, I learn the Truku language every day, and I want to tell my mother.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="6">
        <FORM>Ubus ka hangan mu.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我的名字是Ubus。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">My name is Ubus.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="7">
        <FORM>Asing ka hangan tama mu.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我爸爸的名字是Asing。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">My dad’s name is Asing.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="8">
        <FORM>Ipay ka hangan bubu mu.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我媽媽的名字是Ipay。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">My mother’s name is Ipay.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="9">
        <FORM>Maxal hngkwasan ka hngkawas mu sayang.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我今年10歲。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I am 10 years old.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="10">
        <FORM>Niqan kingal qbsuran mu snaw, hangan na o Yudaw, maxal kingal hngkwasan ka hngkawas na sayang.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我有一個哥哥，他叫Yudaw，他今年11歲。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I have a brother, his name is Yudaw, he is 11 years old.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="11">
        <FORM>Seupu nami matas kingal tgbilaq ptasan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我們在同一間學校讀書。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">We study in the same school.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="12">
        <FORM>Smkuxul muyas ka dha nami qbsuran mu snaw.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我和哥哥都喜歡唱歌。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Both my brother and I like to sing.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="13">
        <FORM>Smkuxul ku tmapaq qsiya yayung, msangay siida o, mseupu nami musa tmapaq qsiya yayung ka kana ruwan sapah mu.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我喜歡游泳，放假的時候，我們全家會一起去游泳。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I like swimming. During the holidays, our whole family go swimming together.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="14">
        <FORM>Smkuxul ku mklaan bgurah lupung, saw kiya o, mtduwa nami mseupu muyas ni tmapaq qsiya yayung.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我喜歡認識新朋友，我們可以一起唱歌和游泳。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I love meeting new people, we can sing and swim together.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="15">
        <FORM>Laqi ku seejiq Truku ka yaku, ga mniq Bsngan ka sapah nami.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我是太魯閣族的小孩。我們家住在富世玻士岸。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I am an Truku child.Our family lives in Bsngan.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="16">
        <FORM>Rima hiyi ka ruwan sapah mu.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我們家共有五個人。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">There are five people in our family.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="17">
        <FORM>Niqan tru mnswayi ka sapah nami.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我們家有三個兄弟姊妹。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">There are three brothers and sisters in our family.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="18">
        <FORM>Niqan tama, bubu, qbsuran mu snaw ni qbsuran mu kuyuh.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我跟爸爸、媽媽、哥哥和姊姊住在一起。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I live with my father, mother, brother and sister.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="19">
        <FORM>Ttakar bi ka tama mu, knsat qpahun na ka tama mu.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我的爸爸很高，我的爸爸是警察。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">My father is tall and he is a policeman.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="20">
        <FORM>Hlawax bi ka bubu mu, msapuh qpahun na ka bubu mu.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我的媽媽很瘦，我的媽媽是醫生。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">My mother is thin and she is a doctor.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="21">
        <FORM>Tghuy mnan mniq sapah rmngaw kari bubu ka tama mu.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">爸爸在家會和我們說族語。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">My father speaks the Truku language with us at home.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="22">
        <FORM>Mseupu nami musa alang ka msangay rbagan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我們暑假都會回部落。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">We will all go back to the tribe during the summer vacation.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="23">
        <FORM>Tghuy ku mnswayi mu mseupu nami qrak qpatur.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我和兄姊會一起抓青蛙。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">My brother and sister and I will catch frogs together.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="24">
        <FORM>Smkuxul ku kingal ruwan sapah mu.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我很喜歡我們家的人。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I like our family very much.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="25">
        <FORM>Musa hmrapas ka bubu mu ni yaku sayang.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">今天我和媽媽出去玩。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I went out with my mother today.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="26">
        <FORM>Mgqliyang bi ka karat jiyan, ini ktalux ni ini mskuy ka karat, mtleetu bi ka bgihur.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">白天的天空很藍，天氣不冷也不熱，風很涼爽。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The sky is blue during the day, the weather is neither cold nor hot, and the wind is cool.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="27">
        <FORM>Meekan nami bawa mniq babaw spriq, sbu mniq qbubur mu ka hidaw ni muxul balay.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我們在草地上吃著麵包，陽光灑在身上，非常溫暖。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">We ate bread on the grass, the sun was shining on us, and it was very warm.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="28">
        <FORM>Babaw kdaaxan da, ppriyux ka karat da.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">下午，天空變紅了。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">In the afternoon, the sky turned red.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="29">
        <FORM>Smiling ku bubu mu, hmuya embanah ka karat hug.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我問媽媽，為甚麼天空是紅色的。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I asked my mother why the sky is red.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="30">
        <FORM>Rmngaw ka bubu mu, ida bi biyaw miyah ka bgihur paru da.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">媽媽說，可能是颱風要來了。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Mom said, maybe the typhoon is coming.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="31">
        <FORM>Nasi ungat rulung ka keeman do, sriyu ka ppngrah da.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">晚上天上沒有雲，星星出來了。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">There were no clouds in the sky at night, and the stars came out.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="32">
        <FORM>Mha nami sapah da.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我們也要回家了。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">We were going home too.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="33">
        <FORM>Musa elug sapah siida o, smulu ku tghuy ppngrah.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">在回家的路上，我跟星星許願。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">On the way home, I made a wish with the stars,</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="34">
        <FORM>Smulu iya iyah ka bgihur paru, lmnglung ku mlatat musa hmrapas.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">希望颱風不要來，我還想再出去玩。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I hope the typhoon doesn't come, I still want to go out to play again.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="35">
        <FORM>Kiyig bi sapah nami ka ptasan mu, mksa ku musa ptasan kdjiyax, mksa ku miyah sapah uri.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我的學校在我們家旁邊，我天天走路去學校，也走路回家。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">My school is next to our house, I walk to school every day, and I also walk home.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="36">
        <FORM>Aji paru ka ptasan mu, aji hbaraw ka laqi matas, pmkkla nami kana.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我們學校不大，沒有很多學生，大家互相認識。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Our school is not big, there are not many students, everyone knows each other.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="37">
        <FORM>Mseupu nami mssli ngangut ptasan, mseupu nami mrrawa qurug, mseupu nami empprngaw.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">所有小朋友會聚在操場，一起玩球、一起聊天。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">All the children will gather in the playground, play ball and chat together.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="38">
        <FORM>Mdka sapah paru ka ptasan, smksik nami kdjiyax, smksik nami mtbhgay ka ruwan ptasan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">老師們也會和我們一起玩，學校是個大家庭。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The teachers also play with us, the school is one big family.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="39">
        <FORM>Smksik nami kdjiyax, smksik nami mtbhgay ka ruwan ptasan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我們每天都要打掃，大家要把教室打掃乾淨。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">We have to clean every day, and everyone has to clean the classroom.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="40">
        <FORM>Duma seejiq o rmisuh smrus bling rhngun, duma o musa smeeksik.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">有些人去擦窗戶，有些人去掃地。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Some people clean the windows, some sweep the floor.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="41">
        <FORM>Musa nami smksik kana knkingal muhing ptasan. mseupu nami ppdayaw, mtbhgay balay kdjiyax ka ptasan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我們還會打掃學校的各個角落，大家分工合作，學校每天都很乾淨。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">We will also clean every corner of the school. Everyone works together, and the school is very clean every day.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="42">
        <FORM>Shiga, mnsa ku alang qmita baki.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">昨天，我去部落拜訪爺爺。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Yesterday, I went to visit my grandpa in the tribe.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="43">
        <FORM>Bsiyaq bi ini nami tqita da, kmdamat ku bi hyaan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我們很久沒有見面了，我很想念他。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">We haven't seen each other for a long time and I miss him a lot.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="44">
        <FORM>Qmita knan ka baki o asi ku na pqdali sagas. pmahan ku na qsiya rnabaw.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">爺爺一看到我，就請我吃西瓜，請我喝茶。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">As soon as grandpa saw me, he invited me to eat watermelon and drink tea.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="45">
        <FORM>Ssibus bi hnuma na sagas ka baki, balay bi malu uqun.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">爺爺種的西瓜很甜，真的很好吃。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The watermelon grown by grandpa is very sweet and really delicious.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="46">
        <FORM>Mkuxul ku qsiya rnabaw baki uri. malu bi mahan uri.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我也喜歡爺爺的茶，也很好喝。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I also like grandpa's tea, it's tasted good too.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="47">
        <FORM>Ska hidaw do, mseupu ku payi mhapuy kdeaxan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">中午的時候，我和奶奶一起煮午餐。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">At noon, I cooked lunch with my grandma.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="48">
        <FORM>Mhapuy suyang bi kdeaxan ka payi, niqan qsurux, rudux, baun, pngusul uri.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">奶奶煮了很豐盛的午餐，有魚、有雞、有南瓜、還有蝸牛。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Grandma cooked a big lunch, including fish, chicken, pumpkin, and snails.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="49">
        <FORM>Babaw mnhdu nami kmjiyax do musa nami qnpahan pajiq kmtuy pajiq.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">吃完午餐後，我們去菜園摘菜。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">After lunch, we went to the vegetable garden to pick vegetables.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="50">
        <FORM>Mangal lala bi bunga, sari ni qusul ka payi sbgay na knan adas sapah.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">奶奶拿了很多地瓜、芋頭和蕗蕎給我，要我帶回家。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Grandma brought me a lot of sweet potatoes, taro and buckwheat, and asked me to take them home.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="51">
        <FORM>Mswayay ku dhyaan ni meiyah ku mita dhyaan pxal duri sun mu.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我跟他們道別，說下次再去看他們。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I said goodbye to them and said I'd see them next time.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="52">
        <FORM>Sayang o meadas mnan musa rwaan mneudus ka mtgsa. Mniq nami rhngung embkug marig paya.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">今天老師帶我們去動物園，我們在門口排隊買票。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Today the teacher took us to the zoo, and we lined up at the gate to buy tickets.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="53">
        <FORM>Babaw mtmay nami rwaan mneudus do rmngaw ka mtgsa:“ Brah o qqbhni, bukuy o qquyu, lita nanak qmita.”</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh"> so you can visit them yourself.&quot;&quot;</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">After entering the zoo, the teacher said, There are birds in the front and snakes in the back</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="54">
        <FORM>Mngungu ku quyu kika ini ku usa qmita qyquyu.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我會怕蛇，所以我不看蛇類。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I'm afraid of snakes, so I don't look at snakes.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="55">
        <FORM>Qmita ku lala bi qbhni, ga skkiya babaw qhuni ka dhiya. qmita ku purung ga mtaqi ska rangah qhuni uri.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我看到了很多鳥，他們在樹上飛來飛去，還有看到貓頭鷹在樹洞裡睡覺。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I saw a lot of birds flying around in the trees and saw owls sleeping in tree hollows.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="56">
        <FORM>Rwaan mneudus o niqan kacing wiwil muhing, kacing mrata/ema ni rklit. Aji ku qmnita ka nnii mneudus. Qtaan sayang do balay bi qrasun wah.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">動物園裡有大象、馬和老虎，我從前沒有看過這些動物，今天看到了真的很開心。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">There are elephants, horses and tigers in the zoo. I have never seen these animals before. I was really happy to see them today.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="57">
        <FORM>Lala bi psingal mu ka sasing, Pqtai mu tama ni bubu.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我拍了很多照片，給爸爸媽媽看。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I took a lot of pictures and showed them to my parents.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="58">
        <FORM>Pseupu ku tama ni bubu miyah pxal duri.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">下次再跟爸爸媽媽一起來。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Next time I will come with my parents.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="59">
        <FORM>Jiyax sngayang nii, musa nami qmita swayi snaw tama mu ka qbsuran mu kuyuh ni yaku.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">這個假日，我和姊姊去台東拜訪叔叔。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">This holiday, my sister and I went to Taitung to visit my uncle.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="60">
        <FORM>Paah nami Taipei papa tdruy qrngul musa Taitung.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我們從台北搭火車去臺東。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">We took the train from Taipei to Taitung.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="61">
        <FORM>Dhuq Taitung do mgriq tdruy miyah smtrung pyaan tdruy mnan ka ririh tama.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">到了台東，叔叔開車來車站接我們。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">When we arrived in Taitung, my uncle drove to the station to pick us up.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="62">
        <FORM>Aji thiyaq bi ka knthyaqan sapah ririh tama ni pyaan tdruy, mgriq cicih tdruy do dhuq da.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">車站離叔叔家沒有很遠，開車一下子就到了。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The station is not far from my uncle's house, and it's just a short drive away.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="63">
        <FORM>Dalih sapah ririh tama hiya o niqan 1 paru bi tbgan. Mseupu nami peapa tdruy gakat dhuq tbgan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">叔叔家附近有個很大的牧場，我們一起騎腳踏車到牧場。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">There is a big ranch near my uncle's house, and we rode bicycles to the ranch together.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="64">
        <FORM>Mniq tbgan do madas mnan ka ririh tama tmabug mirit ni peapa ema.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">在牧場，叔叔帶我們餵羊和騎馬。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">In the ranch, my uncle took us to feed the sheep and ride horses.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="65">
        <FORM>Keeman do musa nami sbrigan paru alang mkan nhapuy.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">晚上，我們一起去市區吃飯。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">In the evening, we went to the city to have dinner together.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="66">
        <FORM>Ska paru alang o lala bi tdruy, kiya ni papa nami tdruy utubay/pupuk musa hiya.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">市區車子很多，所以我們騎摩托車去那裡。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">There are a lot of cars in the city, so we go there by motorcycle.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="67">
        <FORM>Mtealax bi siida do, duwa hlayan ka tdruy utubay wada guyun da. Asi nami papa tdruy bahu tealax.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">要離開的時候，發現摩托車被偷了，我們只好搭公車離開。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">When we were about to leave, we found that the motorcycle had been stolen, so we had to leave by bus.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="68">
        <FORM>Miyah nami dhuq Taipei ka sayang da. Ini klai ririh tama gaga na hlayan ka tdruy utubay na dhug.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">現在我們回到台北了，不知道叔叔的摩托車找到了沒有。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Now that we are back in Taipei, I don't know if my uncle's motorcycle has been found.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="69">
        <FORM>Bilaq ku siida o mniq Bsuring ka sapah nami. Babaw matas do musa thjil Teypaq da. Ida mniq meudus alang paru.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">小時候我們家住在秀林，上學以後，就搬到了台北，一直在都市裡生活。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">When we were young, our family lived in Bsuring. After I started school, we moved to Taipei and have been living in the city ever since.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="70">
        <FORM>Babaw matas paru ptasan do smluhay ku 1 iyax tuki quri ptasan knkla kndsan seejiq tnpusu, mkkla ku lala kngklgan seejiq tnpusu Taiwan knsyangan ka knkla kndsan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">上了大學以後，我修了一堂關於原住民文化的課程，瞭解到臺灣原住民族有各式各樣豐富的文化。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">After I went to college, I took a course on aboriginal culture and learned that the aboriginal people in Taiwan have various and rich cultures.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="71">
        <FORM>Kiya ni rbagan hngkawas sayang do musa alang qmita smiling rudan ka qbsuran mu snaw ni yaku. Kmklaun nami nanak ka knklgan seejiq knkla kndsan ta.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">因此，今年暑假時，我和哥哥回到部落訪問老人家，想要瞭解自己族群的文化。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">So this summer, my brother and I went back to our tribe to visit the elderly, hoping to understand the culture of our own ethnic group.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="72">
        <FORM>Wada maspat kmxalan hngkwasan na ka rudan da, kiya ni mdka saw mgska knrudan seejiq qtaan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">老人家已經八十歲了，但是看起來還像中年人。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The old man is already eighty years old, but he still looks like a middle-aged man.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="73">
        <FORM>Smiling ku hyaan mnmanu kari ka klaun na, mkla bi rmngaw kari Truku ka hiya. mkla kari Tayal, kari Ngayngay ni kari Nihung.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我問他會哪些語言，他的太魯閣族語說得很流利，也會說泰雅語、客家話和日本話。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I asked him which languages he knew, and he was fluent in Truku, as well as Atayal, Hakka and Japanese.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="74">
        <FORM>Smnilng ku hyaan do hana ku mkla, kla sa paah laqi do smluhay kari Nihung da. Kuyuh na o seejiq Tayal. Kiya ni qnpahan na o mgkla lala bi seejiq Ngangay, kika saw nii mkla rmngaw lala knlgan kari.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我問他才知道，原來他小時候就學日本話，太太是泰雅族人，而他工作上認識許多客家人，所以他會說這麼多語言。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I asked him to find out that he learned Japanese when he was a child, his wife is an Atayal, and he knows many Hakkas at work, so he can speak so many languages.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="75">
        <FORM>Empprngaw nami ssida do lala bi rnngaw na quri knkla knxalan maduk ka rudan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我們訪談的時候，老人家談論了許多關於狩獵的傳統知識。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">During our interview, the old man talked about a lot of traditional knowledge about hunting.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="76">
        <FORM>Ana nami ini qhdui mkla embahang, kiya ni spowda nami nngalan nami sasaw qnawal baga, mtduwa tgluus embahang duri.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">雖然我們沒有辦法完全聽懂，但是我們有用手機錄影，可以再仔細聆聽。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Although we could’t fully understand it, we could record it on our cell phones and listen to it more.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="77">
        <FORM>Bilaq ku siida ini ku kla knkla kndsan seejiq ta nanak, ita nanak ka saw seejiq tnpusu o niqan cicih saw smsiqa kida.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">小時候我不瞭解自己族群的文化，對於自己是原住民有點不好意思。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">When I was young, I didn’t understand the culture of my ethnic group, and I was a little embarrassed that I was an aborigine.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="78">
        <FORM>Rinah lala klaun ta do, rina tgkla ita nanak ka seejiq Truku o maa kingal bi nanak ni balay bi tdhuun uri.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">瞭解愈多以後，愈覺得自己身為太魯閣族人，是很獨特的，也很值得驕傲。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The more I know, the more I feel that being a Truku is unique and something to be proud of.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="79">
        <FORM>Gbiyan sayang, meiyah sapah ka swayi mu snaw da.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">今天傍晚，弟弟就要回家了。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">My younger brother is going home this evening.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="80">
        <FORM>Musa marig rudux sbrigan ka payi ni yaku, ppsramal mhapuy uuqun swayi mu snaw nhapuy gbiyan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我和奶奶去市場買雞，準備煮好吃的晚餐給弟弟。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">My grandma and I went to the market to buy chickens and prepared a delicious dinner for my younger brother.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="81">
        <FORM>Muda nami sbrigan damat, lala bi bgurah mgpajiq pajiq ka sbrigan damat.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我們經過了菜攤，菜攤有好多新鮮的青菜。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">We passed the vegetable stand, which had a lot of fresh green vegetables.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="82">
        <FORM>Marig nami wahir bunga, lnbay ni tbihi banah.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我們買了空心菜、山藥和胡蘿蔔。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">We bought water spinach, yams and carrots.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="83">
        <FORM>Rmngaw ka tnpusu sbrigan hiyi qhuni, “Ssibus bi ka kalat ni qlupas mu. brigi cicih wah!” msa.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">旁邊水果攤的老闆說:「我的鳳梨和桃子很甜。買一些吧!」</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The owner of the nearby fruit stand said: “My pineapples and peaches are very sweet. Buy some!”</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="84">
        <FORM>Mnarig nami kalat ni qlupas ka yami.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我們買了鳳梨和桃子。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">We bought pineapples and peaches.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="85">
        <FORM>Muda nami sbrigan hiyi, rmngaw ka tnpusu, embarig namu manu? Paru ni mtbnaw bi ka rudux sayang, kingal o 300 kbkuy pila.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我們經過了肉攤，老闆說:「你要買什麼?今天的雞又大又肥，一隻300元。」</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">We passed the meat stall, and the boss said, “What do you want to buy? Today's chickens are big and fat, and one is 300 NTD.”</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="86">
        <FORM>Suqi bi knkrayan da msa lmnglung ka payi. Slingan na ka tnpusu ini tduwa mhnuk cicih sun na.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">奶奶覺得太貴了，問老闆可不可以便宜一點。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Grandma thought it was too expensive and asked the boss if it could be cheaper.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="87">
        <FORM>Kiya ni rmngaw ka tnpusu mhnuk bi ka kida, ini tduwa mhnuk da.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">但老闆說已經很便宜，不能再減了。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The boss next door said, come and buy my fish, my fish is big and cheap.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="88">
        <FORM>Rmngaw ka kiyig tnpusu, iyah marig qsurux mu, paru ni mhnuk bi ka qsurux mu.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">隔壁的老闆說，來買我的魚，我的魚又大又便宜。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The boss next door said, come and buy my fish, my fish is big and cheap.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="89">
        <FORM>Tghici bi do marig nami rudux ni marig qsurux uri. Saan mhapuy sapah kingal tluan ka damat.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">最後我們買了雞也買了魚，回家煮了一桌子的菜。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">In the end we bought chicken and fish, and went home to cook a table of food.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="90">
        <FORM>Bsiyaq bi tnegaan, mkuung ka karat da.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">等了好久，天已經黑了。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">After waiting for a long time, it was already dark.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="91">
        <FORM>Miyah qnawal na ka swayi mu snaw rmngaw asi lu ini tduwa msangay ka qpuring mrata da ni empxal jiyax sngayan do kika mtduwa miyah da msa.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">弟弟打電話回來說，軍隊突然不能放假了，要下一個禮拜日才回來。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The younger brother called back and said that the army suddenly couldn't take a vacation and would not be back until the next Sunday.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="92">
        <FORM>Rmngaw ka payi mnhapuy saw nii knlala, plwaani kana iyah supu mkan wah!</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">奶奶說已經煮了這麼多，叫大家一起來吃吧!</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Grandma said that she has cooked so much, so let's eat together!</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="93">
        <FORM>Mlawa nami lplupung dlutut, mseupu tblaiq mkan knsyangan uqan gbiyan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我們邀請了親朋好友，一起來享用豐盛的晚餐。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">We invited friends and family to have a great dinner together.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="94">
        <FORM>Niqan kingal tnhiyan mu matas hangan na o Yakaw, smhungi bi madas qaya kdjiyax.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我有一個同學叫Yakaw，他常常忘記帶東西。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I have a classmate named Yakaw, he often forgets to bring things.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="95">
        <FORM>Matas bi siida, kmsiyuk ppatas, ssrus aji o ptasun patas tnhiyan na.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">上課的時候，他跟同學借鉛筆、橡皮擦或是筆記本。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">During class, he borrowed pencils, erasers or notebooks from his classmates.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="96">
        <FORM>Empxal, mndha, mntru, pksiyuk bi qaya hyaan kana.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">一次、兩次、三次，大家會借東西給他。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Once, twice, three times, everyone would lend him something.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="97">
        <FORM>Kiya ni niqan kingal naqih lnhayan na. Kmsiyuk qaya do ini bgay.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">但是他有個壞習慣，經常借了東西卻不還。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But he has a bad habit of often borrowing things but not returning them.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="98">
        <FORM>Hici bi do ini pksiyuk qaya hyaan kana da.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">最後大家都不想借他東西了。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">In the end, no one wanted to borrow anything from him.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="99">
        <FORM>Niqan kingal jiyax, musa nami msupu mrrawa ngangut.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">有一天，我們大家一起去郊遊。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">One day, we all went on an outing together.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="100">
        <FORM>muda elug kmusa bi ngangut ka Yakaw, kiya ni smhungi madas lblak ssrus.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">路途中，Yakaw想上廁所，但他忘記帶衛生紙。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">On the way, Yakaw wanted to go to the bathroom, but he forgot to bring toilet paper.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="101">
        <FORM>mksiyuk tnhiyan na lblak ssrus, kiya ni smiyuk hyaan kana ini ku adas yaku uri msa smiyuk rmngaw.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">他跟同學借衛生紙，可是大家都回他說，我也沒有帶耶。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">He borrowed toilet paper from his classmates, but everyone told him that I didn’t bring them either.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="102">
        <FORM>Mtbiyax bi ka Yakaw ni lmingis da. Msaang rmngaw, hmuya ma namu ini pksiyuk lblak ssrus knan!</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">Yakaw急的哭了出來。他生氣的說，為什麼大家都不借我衛生紙!</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Yakaw burst into tears. He said angrily, why don’t everyone lend me toilet paper!</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="103">
        <FORM>Smiyuk hyaan ka tnhiyan na. Yasa ini su bi adas nanak ka isu, duri ni knsyukan su ka qaya o ini su bqaani!</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">同學告訴他，因為你都不自己帶，而且借給你的東西，你都不會還!</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The classmate told him, because you didn’t bring it yourself, and you wouldn’t return the things lent to you!</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="104">
        <FORM>Saw saman musa ptasan, mgrbu bi dhuq ptasan ka Yakaw. Ngali na ka knsyukan na tnhiyan na ka qyqaya o bqaani na tnhiyan na kana.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">隔天上學，Yakaw很早就到學校了，Yakaw把跟同學借的東西都還給同學們。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The next day at school, Yakaw arrived at school early and returned everything he had borrowed from his classmates.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="105">
        <FORM>Psruwa tnhiyan na ka Yakaw ni rmngaw, babaw na do ida ku bi meadas qaya mu nanak, mhuway namu balay brah na o smruwa namu pksiyuk qaya hyaan uri.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">Yakaw向同學們道歉，並說他以後一定會自己帶東西，也謝謝同學們之前願意借他東西。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Yakaw apologized to the students and said that he would definitely bring his own things in the future, and thanked the classmates for their willingness to lend him things before.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="106">
        <FORM>Emptsamat alang ka tama mu.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我的爸爸是部落的獵人。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">My dad is a hunter of the tribe.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="107">
        <FORM>Bilaq ku siida, mlatat keeman ka nirih mu tama ni tama, madas pucing ni puniq.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我小的時候，爸爸和叔叔會在晚上出門，帶著獵刀和獵槍。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">When I was little, my dad and uncle would go out at night with hunting knives and guns.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="108">
        <FORM>Rmdax karat do madas nbuan dha samat miyah da.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">天亮時，他們就會帶著獵到的獵物回來。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">At daybreak, they returned with their prey.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="109">
        <FORM>Duma o bowyak, duma o rapit, msuwil niqan glaqung uri.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">有時候是山豬、有時候是飛鼠，偶爾也會有雉雞。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Sometimes it was a boar, sometimes a flying squirrel, and occasionally a pheasant.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="110">
        <FORM>Mniq rhngung alang sgun na ka samat ni seasug dha sjiqun.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">他們會在村口將獵物分好，分享給族人。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">They would divide the prey at the entrance of the village and share it with the tribe.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="111">
        <FORM>Stnxay skribug ku tama mu kdjiyax, mkmusa ku sneegul tama maduk.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我每次都會吵著爸爸，要跟著爸爸去打獵。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Every time I quarreled with my father, I wanted to go hunting with my father.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="112">
        <FORM>Rmngaw ka tama, paru su do dsun ku na supu maduk da.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">爸爸說等我長大了他再帶我一起去。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Dad said that he would take me with me when I grew up.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="113">
        <FORM>Mkla dmuuuy qlubung qmrak samat uri ka snaw alang, mkla smmalu waya qlubung ni dangar btunux.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">部落的男人也會用陷阱抓獵物，他們會製作套索陷阱和石壓式陷阱。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The men of the tribe also trap their prey, making lasso traps and rock traps.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="114">
        <FORM>Mkla bi qmlubung gasil ka tama mu, rmngaw ka tama, nii o qrak glaqung kiya, tgluus ta bi qmita ka dapil papak endaan samat. Psaan ta elug uuda samat ka qlubung.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我的爸爸很會製作套索陷阱，爸爸說，這是用來捕抓雉雞的，我們要仔細觀察獵物的腳印，陷阱要放在獵物走的路上。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">My dad is very good at making lasso traps. Dad said that this is used to catch pheasants. We have to carefully observe the footprints of the prey, and the traps should be placed on the path of the prey.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="115">
        <FORM>Iiyux ku nhari mseupu rudan musa maduk, smluhay ku qmlubung kdjiyax. Ini bi biyaw balay bi mtduwa qmrak samat ka qlubung mu da.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">為了可以趕快和大人一起去打獵，我每天練習製作陷阱，很快地我的陷阱就真的可以抓到獵物了。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">In order to go hunting with adults as soon as possible, I practiced making traps every day, and soon my traps can really catch prey.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="116">
        <FORM>Babaw qmnita ku tama rmngaw knan hici o ida su mha maa malu bi emptsamat.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">爸爸看到後對我說我以後一定會是很厲害的獵人。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Dad saw it and told me that I will be a very good hunter in the future.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="117">
        <FORM>Sayang paru ku da, mapa ku bhniq ni buji mu, mseupu ku tama musa maduk.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">現在我長大了，我背起我的弓和箭矢，跟著爸爸一起去打獵。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Now that I have grown up, I carry my bow and arrows and go hunting with my father.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="118">
        <FORM>Miyah alang do ngalun nami ka snbu nami samat sseasug nami seejiq ta.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">回村時將獵到的獵物和族人們分享。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">When returning to the village, share the hunted prey with the tribe.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="119">
        <FORM>Rmngaw ka tama, qrasan ta bi ka utux rudan smblaiq mgay saw nii lala bi nngalan ta samat.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">爸爸說，我們要感謝祖靈賜福，讓我們有很多獵物收穫。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Dad said, we want to thank the ancestors for their blessings, so that we have a lot of prey to harvest.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="120">
        <FORM>Mqsuqi ku musa ptasan ka mgrbu da .</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我早上上學遲到了。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I was late for school this morning.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="121">
        <FORM>Musa ptasan siida , smhungi ku madas aba patas .</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">去學校的時候，我忘了帶書包。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">When I was going to school, I forgot to bring my backpack.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="122">
        <FORM>Ini ku adas ana manu .</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我什麼東西都沒有帶。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I didn’t bring anything with me.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="123">
        <FORM>Matas siida , seupu ku tnhiyan mu matas qmita patas .</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">上課的時候，我和同學一起看課本。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">During class, I and my classmates read the textbook together.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="124">
        <FORM>Pspung matas siida , pksyukan kuna ppatas ni ssrus ka tnhiyan mu matas .</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">考試的時候，同學借我筆和橡皮擦。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">During the exam, a classmate lent me a pen and an eraser.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="125">
        <FORM>Rngagan kuna ka mtgsa , “ babaw na do tutuy nhari , iya pqsuqi da ! ”</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">老師跟我說：「下次早點起床，不要再遲到了!」</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The teacher told me, “Wake up earlier next time and don’t be late again!”</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="126">
        <FORM>Malu bi lupung mu o Watan , laqi Truku ka hiya uri .</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我的好朋友叫Watan，他也是太魯閣族的小孩。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">My good friend’s name is Watan, and he is also an Truku child.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="127">
        <FORM>Seupu nami matas mniq alang Kdusan .</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我們一起在Kdusan部落讀書。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">We study together in the Kdusan tribe.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="128">
        <FORM>Seupu nami embahang rudan rmngaw endaan sbiyaw kdjiyax , mkla nami bi rmngaw kari Truku .</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我們常常一起聽耆老說故事，我們都很會說太魯閣語。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">We often listen to the elders telling stories together, and we both can speak the Truku proficiently.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="129">
        <FORM>Takar ni mtbnaw ku bi , llbu ni hlawax bi ka Watan .</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我很高也很胖，Watan很矮也很瘦。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I am tall and overweight, while Watan is short and thin.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="130">
        <FORM>Mpplaq bi ka Watan , smkuxul bi hyaan kana .</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">Watan很有活力，大家都很喜歡他。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Watan is very energetic, and everyone likes him a lot.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="131">
        <FORM>Jiyax psslian tmalang ptasan ka sayang, muda lala bi psdka ka ptasan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">今天是學校的運動會，學校舉辦了許多競賽。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Today was the school's sports day, and the school organized many competitions.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="132">
        <FORM>Niqan brbil gasil, qurug btragan qaqay, tmalang, rmgrig ni pstalang buji.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">有拔河、足球、跑步、跳舞和射箭。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">There were tug of war, soccer, running, dancing, and archery.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="133">
        <FORM>Psdka ku tmalang ka yaku.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我比賽跑步。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I participated in the running competition.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="134">
        <FORM>Pklug ku tmalang siida, mtakur ku da, sdara bi ka bqlit.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">當我跑步的時候，我跌倒了，膝蓋流了很多血。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">When I was running, I fell down, and my knees were bleeding.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="135">
        <FORM>Kiya ni mhiyug ku, ida ku mquri brah tmalang.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">但我站起來，繼續向前跑。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">But I stood up and continued running forward.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="136">
        <FORM>Dhuq ku nhdaan siida, mqaras bi kana ka seejiq.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我到終點時所有人都很開心。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Everyone was happy when I reached the finish line.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="137">
        <FORM>Ana ku ini angal tgbrah hangan, ida ku mqaras balay, yaasa mnhdu ku psdka da.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">雖然沒有獲得第一名，但我很高興，因為我完成了比賽。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Although I didn't get first place, I'm glad because I completed the race.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="138">
        <FORM>Yaku ni tama mu o musa nami qmita nirih tama mu ka shiga.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">昨天我和爸爸去拜訪我的叔叔。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Yesterday, my father and I visited my uncle.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="139">
        <FORM>Mluqih ka qaqay nirih tama da.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">叔叔的腳受傷了。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">My uncle injured his foot.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="140">
        <FORM>Rngagan nami na, empruq kingal bling ka dnamux sapah.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">他告訴我們，房子的屋頂破了一個洞。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">He told us that there was a hole in the roof of his house.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="141">
        <FORM>Pklug smmalu dnamux ka hiya siida ga, mtucing pnaah dnamux da.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">他在修理屋頂時，從屋頂摔下來了。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">He fell off the roof while repairing it.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="142">
        <FORM>Madas hiyi kacing ni sbiki ka tama sbgay na nirih tama.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">爸爸帶了牛肉和檳榔給叔叔。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">My father brought beef and betel nuts for my uncle.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="143">
        <FORM>Empprngaw nami ruwan sapah ka yaku ni nirih tama, seasug kuna rmngaw lala bi endaan na.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我和叔叔在房間裡聊天，他分享了很多故事。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">My uncle and I chatted in the room, and he shared many stories.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="144">
        <FORM>Mmowsa ku siida, tmdahu knan ka nirih tama, wada ku maaparu ni mtradaw bi uri da.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我要離開前，叔叔誇我長高了，也變得更帥氣了。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Before I left, my uncle praised me for growing taller and becoming more handsome.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="145">
        <FORM>Rngagan mu, “Tgai saw malu ka qaqay su da o iyah tuhuy sapah nami uri.”</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我說：「等叔叔腳好了，下次也來我們家玩。」</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I said, “When your foot gets better, come to our house next time and visit us.”</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="146">
        <FORM>Hngkawas empusal kbkuy empusal dha siida, mnda emprngaw ka Klwaan tduwa powsa hangan kari ta nanak ka patas hnyigan Seejiq Tnpusu.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">在2022年，政府召開了原住民身分證可單列族名的會議。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">In 2022, the government announced that indigenous identification cards can include tribal names separately.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="147">
        <FORM>Smniling ku risaw alang Umin Peydang, hiya o bsiyaq balay gmspung patas hnyigan “powsa hangan kari ta nanak” mquri Klwaan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我訪問了長期向政府爭取身分證「單列族名」的部落青年Umin Peydang。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I interviewed Umin Peydang, a young tribal member who has long been advocating for the inclusion of tribal names on identification cards.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="148">
        <FORM>Mnhdu nami empprngaw, jiyax sngayan nii mowsa sapah na smiling hyaan.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我和他約定好這個假日到他家訪問他。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">We had arranged to visit his home this holiday for the interview.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="149">
        <FORM>Kska Sniling mu siida, pgkla knan pnyahan hangan na, dsun kuna pgkla kingal ruwan sapah na ni alang na uri.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">在訪問的過程中，他向我介紹了他的名字的由來，也帶我認識了他的家人、他的部落。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">During the interview, he introduced to me the origin of his name and also introduced me to his family and tribe.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="150">
        <FORM>Smiling ku hyaan, hmuya ma su saw ida gigit priyux hangan, uda powsa patas seuxal o naqih hug?</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我問他為什麼堅持要改名，舊的登記方式不好嗎?</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">I asked him why he insisted on changing his name. Wasn’t the old registration method sufficient?</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="151">
        <FORM>Rngagan kuna, yaasa dmuuy kari Cyukuku o ini psleexan balay pgkla hangan na, duma seejiq “烏先生” msa mlawa hyaan uri, kiya ni saw bi smhulis.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">\&quot; which resulted in many jokes being made.&quot;</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">He told me that using Chinese characters could not accurately convey his name, and others would still call him \Wu Xian Sheng</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="152">
        <FORM>Rmngaw ka Umin Peydang, “Hangan pnatas kari Seejiq Tnpusu o kika balay bi hangan ta. Hangan mu o pgkla klgan seejiq ta, pnswayan sapah ta, hnyigan ta, tai saw emphbaraw balay ka seejiq dhuq hmlay hangan dha nanak.”</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh"> our family</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Umin Peydang said, \The names written in indigenous languages are our true names. My name represents our ethnic group</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="153">
        <FORM>Shiga o musa sbrigan smbarig ka yaku ni payi, madas lala bi pajiq nhuma na nanak ka payi, smmalu uqun Seejiq Tnpusu uri biqan na ana ima.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">昨天我跟奶奶去市集擺攤，奶奶帶了許多自己種的蔬菜去，也製作了原住民美食給大家。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Yesterday, I went to the market with my grandmother to set up a stall. My grandmother brought a lot of vegetables that she grew herself and also prepared indigenous cuisine for everyone.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="154">
        <FORM>Smkuxul bi sbrigan payi ka kana seejiq, hbaraw bi seejiq marig usik ni sruhing, hbaraw seejiq miyah mkan nhapuy hnpuyan na.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">大家很喜歡奶奶的攤位，辣椒和山蘇很多人買，許多人來品嘗她煮的菜餚。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Everyone loved my grandmother’s stall. Many people bought the chilis and Nest fern, and many people came to taste the dishes she cooked.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="155">
        <FORM>Rmala ni butul hnpuyan na o malu balay uqan, niqan muduh hiyi bowyak uri, knshiya na hmgut hbaraw lupung mniyah, miyah embkug sbrigan nami kana.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">她煮的過貓和糯米飯非常好吃，還有烤山豬肉，味道吸引了很多客人，大家都來我們攤位排隊。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">The ferns and sticky rice she cooked were delicious, as well as the braised pork with maqaw pepper and wild boar meat. The flavors attracted many customers, and everyone lined up at our stall.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="156">
        <FORM>Mhapuy siida ka payi, kmeaguh ku lupung mniyah kiyig ka yaku, mlawa ku kiyig hiya, “Hmaan mu nanak kana ka pajiq, ini rusi sapuh, iyah marig nhari!”</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">奶奶煮東西的時候，我在旁邊招攬客人。我在一旁大喊著：「蔬菜都是自己種的，天然有機，趕快來買喔!」</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">While my grandmother was cooking, I was on the side attracting customers. I shouted, “The vegetables are self-grown, all-natural and organic! Come and buy now!”</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="157">
        <FORM>Aji biyaw qhduun smbarig kana ka qngqaya nami da. “Nuxay bi dnyagan su.” msa ka payi.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">我們的東西很快就賣完了。奶奶說：「都是因為有你的幫忙。」</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Our goods sold out quickly, and my grandmother said, “It’s all thanks to your help.”</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="158">
        <FORM>Euda nii, wada ku smluhay pnegluban quri knkla pnhmaan ni uqun Seejiq Tnpusu, duri ni knrbkan muda smbarig.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">這個活動，我學到了有關原住民植物和食品的知識，並且體驗到了擺攤的辛苦。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Through this event, I learned about indigenous plants and food and experienced the hard work of running a stall.</TRANSL>
    </S>
    <S id="159">
        <FORM>Qmita ku payi smkuxul bi uqun nrudan, smparu ni mqaras bi lnglungan mu.</FORM>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="zh">看到了奶奶對傳統食物的熱愛，我感到非常驕傲和榮幸。</TRANSL>
        <TRANSL xml:lang="en">Seeing my grandmother’s passion for traditional food, I feel very proud and honored.</TRANSL>
    </S>
</TEXT>
