<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEXT id="Jayanth_Reddy" source="Wikipedia">
  <S>Jayanth Reddy is a Martial Arts and Tae Kwon Do expert from Hyderabad, India. Early Life Jayanth was born in Hyderabad on 14 December 1962 to Vittal Reddy and Shivamma. He did his schooling from Vijaya School and later joined Mani Jeremiah High School. He completed his Intermediate from Aliya Junior College. Jayanth was a very good cricketer and used to also play soccer. It all started in 1976 when his brothers Krishna Reddy and Sridhar Reddy brought him a book on martial arts, which led him into the classes of traditional Karate. After four years of rigorous practice, he earned a Black Belt in karate but that did not stop him from exploring other material art forms as his fascination to deliver those high kicks in mid air paved the way for the beginning of an epic journey into the world of Taekwondo. At the age of 12, he was inspired by Bruce Lee's Enter the Dragon and one thing led to another. Initially, his parents were sceptical about it and thought he would end up as a gangster. But as he started to win awards in the martial arts circuit, their attitude changed completely. His brothers gave classes on traditional karate and he was coached by Narsimha and Srinivasan. The turning point in his career came when Manoj Tiwari motivated him to take up Taekwondo. Apart from being a coach and a contender, he also distinguished himself as an organiser by conducting a South Zone Championship in 1983. After staging numerous Taekwondo demonstrations across India and conducting several districts, state, zonal and National level Championships, he started exploring this art in greater depth and that is what took him to the United States, where he underwent a six month advanced training camp under the watchful eyes of two 9th Degree black belters Moo Yang Lee and Pong Ki Kim. He followed it up with an advanced course in speed training once again in the US. This enabled to earn the 4th to 6th Dan Black Belt titles from various world renowned Martial Arts Associations. He also availed the unique opportunity of training with several Grand Masters and athletes of over 50 countries across the globe which helped him to stay updated by gaining several modern techniques. Jayanth's main goal is to help Indians create world records in Martial arts. A total of 2,000 people have undergone training at his academy ever since its inception in 2010. He is now coming up with a first of its kind Martial Arts league in India. &quot;Martial Arts has given a lot to me and now I want to give the sport back in any way possible to increase its popularity in the next 10 years. I wish to help another 10,000 Indians achieve world records. This will improve India's reputation in the world of Martial Arts, which is currently dominated by countries like China, Japan, Korea and Thailand,&quot; he said. Professional Career Achieved 29 Guinness World Records Achieved 12 US Presidential Sports awards (1993, 1998, 2005, 2010 and 2020) from President of the USA Achieved 12 world records from Limca, RHR, Asian etc. from 2012 to 2015 Kukkiwon, Korea honored appreciation award 2013, 2016 and 2019 Awarded citation from World Taekwondo Federation, Korea Awarded with Hall of Fame USA in 1999 International Champion in 1999 2000 National and National games Champion in 1983, 84, 85, 86 and 1987 8th DAN Black Belt from Taekwondo Jidokwan, Korea 8th DAN Black Belt from World Taekwondo Masters Association As an Author A subset of books authored by Mr. Jayanth Reddy Secrets of Longevity Revealed The Hidden Secrets of Martial Arts Secrets of advanced Explosive Speed Kicking and Speed punching Dynamic power of mind Secrets of Advanced Speed fighting Humans destroying the god The Most Inspirational and Motivational quotes of success in Martial arts, Sports, Mind , Life and God Martial yoga 9 minutes Fitness workout The Ancient secret of preventive exercises for &quot;CORONA VIRUS&quot; Secrets of 3 minutes workout Secrets of 30 minutes workout Advanced World Taekwondo Training See Also Jayanth on YouTube Jayanth on Google Scholar External Links Instagram LinkedIn</S>
</TEXT>
